<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>india jammu on HERESY LEVAIN</title><link>/tags/india-jammu/</link><description>Latest experiments in india jammu from HERESY LEVAIN</description><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2023 HERESY LEVAIN 🍞 CC BY-NC-SA 4.0</copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 15 May 2023 02:02:44 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/india-jammu/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>levure de bière #5.2: Tropical Chico bomboloni</title><link>/posts/byb-5-2/</link><pubDate>Mon, 15 May 2023 02:02:44 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/byb-5-2/</guid><description>Experimental thiol-complimentary wholegrain &lt;em>bomboloni&lt;/em> (yeasted Italian donuts), via co-fermentation of 2 yeast strains: California ale yeast and thiolized London Tropics. An intentionally austere dough that highlights the yeast&amp;rsquo;s super power.</description><content>&lt;p>&lt;em>Beer = liquid bread. Want to stay updated on my &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/craft-beer-yeast">craft beer yeast bread-plays&lt;/a>? Subscribe to the &lt;a href="https://tinyletter.com/breadbuster">newsletter&lt;/a>!&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Since making that &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/byb-5-1/">POG bomb&lt;/a> with Berkeley&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href="https://berkeleyyeast.com/strains/london-tropics/">London Tropics&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://berkeleyyeast.com/boost/thiol/">Thiol Boost&lt;/a>, I&amp;rsquo;ve been thinking a lot about the goldmine of thiol precursors in malts &amp;ndash; and malts alone.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Given a lot more thiol precursors come from malts than hops, it probably makes more sense to play with different base malts and malt varieties than with new age hops.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>German scientists have devised &lt;a href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/full/10.1021/acs.jafc.0c06305">a solvent-free, automated method&lt;/a> for brewers to measure and track hop-derived thiols during the brewing process. How cool would it be, to be able to quantify the amount of thiol precursors in different malts, and find out which malt varieties pair the best with a particular thiolized yeast?&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-2/montana_barley_green.jpg"
alt="Montana barley into harvest"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Gorgeous barley heading into harvest, on Karl De Jonge&amp;rsquo;s farm in Gallatin Valley, Montana.&lt;/p>&lt;p>Source: &lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/gallatinvalleymaltco/photos/a.707201556296362/978615135821668/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">Gallatin Valley Malt Co.&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Most maltsters don&amp;rsquo;t list information about their grain varieties, only generic info like the malt type (pale, pilsner, crystal, etc). To find out the specific varietals of grains the malts are made from, I&amp;rsquo;ve had to ask the maltsters directly for COAs (certificates of analysis).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;ve worked with enough grains (of different varieties) to know that the varietal can make a big difference in the end-product, e.g. a bread made from 100% &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/turkey-red/">Turkey Red&lt;/a> is noticeably different from one made from 100% &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/joaquin-oro/">Joaquin Oro&lt;/a> or &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/white-sonora/">Sonora Blanca&lt;/a>. In pale ales, modern barley varieties like Metcalfe and Copeland from Montana or western Canada may be more suited to the American style than the others, while heirloom varieties like Golden Promise or Maris Otter add a bit of nutty character to British variations.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Many brewers proudly describe their base malts &amp;ndash; the vast majority of the grist in most beers &amp;ndash; simply as &amp;ldquo;2-row.&amp;rdquo; That label merely indicates it&amp;rsquo;s not the &amp;ldquo;inferior&amp;rdquo;, higher-protein 6-row barley variety. But those are broad categories &amp;ndash; just like &lt;a href="https://newenglandapples.org/2020/10/16/russets-small-size-big-flavor/">russet&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://www.chelseagreen.com/2022/surprisingly-sweet-crab-apples/">crab&lt;/a>, and club are categories of apples (so much for the Johnny Appleseed fairy tale) &amp;ndash; and imply nothing about the actual barley variety, even less about how the grain is malted. Most brewers just take whatever malt variety is available, maybe occasionally thinking about 2-row vs. 6-row, winter vs. summer, maltster vs. maltster, and US-Canada vs. Europe.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As with wheat, I&amp;rsquo;ve learned that if a malt is generic enough to be characterized by just its category, it&amp;rsquo;s not going to give the end-product much flavor or character. But what really made me appreciate malt as a craft, in and of itself, was 2 things:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Learning how to make traditional Baltic peasant rye bread from single-variety grain (rye) during 2020 COVID lockdown. In rural villages in Belarus and Latvia, for example, grandmas still make some of the world&amp;rsquo;s most flavorful (and underrated) breads today &amp;ndash; with only rye flour, water, salt, and natural yeast; they coax incredibly complex flavors out of the unassuming rye kernel through different stages of chemical reactions. That inspired me to malt my own rye for breadmaking: pale rye malt, Russian red fermented rye malt (&lt;em>solod&lt;/em>), chocolate rye malt, and even malt syrup, from different varieties of rye (Abruzzi, Gazelle, Hazlet, Ryman, &lt;em>Svedjerug&lt;/em>, Prima, etc). I was absolutely mesmerized by the different flavor profile and intensity each rye malt (and each rye variety) added to the final bread.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Studying European beer history. European beer styles evolved in tandem with local barley varieties and malt. Particularly in places like Bavaria, &lt;em>Helles&lt;/em> (pale lagers) &amp;ndash; despite being delicately hopped and regularly made with just a single malt &amp;ndash; taste different across breweries, because the malt, which is the whole ballgame, is different. Breweries have access to dozens of different malthouses, each making their pilsner malts slightly differently, from a range of different barley varieties. The same is true &amp;ndash; and even more pronounced &amp;ndash; in the UK, where ale brewers not only know which facility makes their malt, but also have passionate opinions about the barley variety. In cask ales, for example, the differences between different barley varieties and malts are magnified, creating distinct flavors.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-2/montana_barley.jpg"
alt="Montana barley"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Heritage barley near harvest time, on Karl De Jonge&amp;rsquo;s farm in Gallatin Valley, Montana.&lt;/p>&lt;p>Source: &lt;a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/ChQ6zVeLJDc/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">Gallatin Valley Malt Co.&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>One of the factors that contributed to the development of the brewing industry as a whole was the spread of pale malts. In the Late Middle Ages, England had been struggling with wood shortages and switched to using the cheaper coal. A major problem with coal was that it produces sulfurous fumes during burning, and the flavors imparted to malt dried in coal-fueled kilns &amp;ndash; and subsequently the beer &amp;ndash; were &lt;a href="https://www.beeretseq.com/where-theres-smoke-theres-pale-ale/">not acceptable&lt;/a>. Hence, in &lt;em>ye olden times&lt;/em> malt had to be dried over wood, peat, or straw &amp;ndash; all of which infused malt with the smoky character of the heat source and gave it a brown color &amp;ndash; or the best Welsh anthracite, the supply of which was quite limited.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In 1603, &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hugh_Plat">Sir Hugh Plat&lt;/a> suggested that coal might be charred in a manner analogous to the way charcoal is produced from wood. He heated some coal without burning it, which distilled the coal, removed its offensive sulfurous smell, and left a residue with a high carbon content and few impurities. This was coke, which proved to be a highly useful fuel for heating and industry.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The coke process remained unnoticed until 1642, when malt makers in Derbyshire began to employ coke for roasting malt. Coke demonstrated superior qualities over other fuels at the time: It generates a great deal of heat without the attendant soot and smoke, and it allows better thermal control. Coke-dried malt was considered an improvement in quality over wood-dried malt, and brought about an &amp;ldquo;alteration which all England admired.&amp;rdquo; Brewers were finally able to mass-produce a lighter roast of the malt that was not &amp;ldquo;smoked.&amp;rdquo; This malt was called &amp;ldquo;pale,&amp;rdquo; and it led to the creation of what by the end of the 17th century was called &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->&amp;quot;&lt;strong>pale ale&lt;/strong>.&amp;quot;&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --> Coke became the &lt;em>crème de la crème&lt;/em> of fuels in England. Coke-fired blast furnaces made the production of inexpensive cast iron possible, which was one of the factors that drove the Industrial Revolution.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The British Empire was in full sway, with merchants and traders traveling around the world. India was the &amp;ldquo;crown jewel&amp;rdquo; of the empire, hosting a large British military and civilian population with a thirst for beer. The tropical climate in India made local brewing of typical English pale ales impossible. Casks of porters and stouts shipped in from England fared poorly because of the long sea voyage and temperature fluctuations; bottled products produced mixed results as well.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In 1790, George Hogeson of the Bow Brewery in London developed a recipe for pale ale that included a huge increase in hops and a much higher alcohol content (both known to have preservative qualities). The export casks were primed with sugar and dry-hopped prior to shipping. The resulting beer arrived in India unspoiled, but much stronger and hoppier than the domestic version. This &amp;ldquo;India Pale Ale&amp;rdquo; (&lt;strong>IPA&lt;/strong>) quickly became hugely popular and profitable.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Pale malt has a huge advantage over darker malts: It contains more enzymes and more fermentable sugars, which allows for more efficient beer production; the taste of the finished beer is much cleaner, as yeasts are able to break down a higher percentage of the chemical compounds dissolved in wort. This fact was likely not explicitly known to brewers until the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hydrometer#Saccharometer">saccharometer&lt;/a> was invented in the late 18th century. Given that coke was too expensive for commercial brewing back then, pale ales remained mostly exclusive to the households of the wealthy gentry in northern England.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-2/barley-germinating.jpg"
alt="germinating barley"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Germinating barley&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>In the US, light lager was the focus of domestic breweries until ~2000. The specific needs of breweries for producing this style of beer trumped the beer&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;character&amp;rdquo; development. 2-row malt is good enough; the barley and malt industries became streamlined to efficiently produce this neutral, light-flavored product for the purpose of brewing domestic light lagers. This specialization, however, created a structural problem for craft breweries looking for malt flavors &amp;ndash; worse, it led to a zymurgic myopia.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As a result, American breweries don&amp;rsquo;t have nearly the selection of malts that Germans have. Weyermann, a common source, makes a high-quality pilsner malt from 2-row spring barley. Brewers love its strong, distinctive character, which really makes a lager pop. The problem is every lager tastes like Weyermann® pilsner malt, which is why so many breweries in Bavaria use different malthouses to differentiate their beers.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Craft brewing has gone through eras of hop enlightenment and yeast consciousness. Not too long ago, brewers were content with a handful of C-hops and some Chico yeast. Now hop breeders release dozens of new hops a year; yeast labs and yeast varieties are mushrooming. Brewers are constantly tinkering with ingredients to produce new flavors, and highly attuned to subtle differences.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;I ask my maltsters to include the barley variety mix in their analysis data. Having a malt analysis without varietal data is like describing a dog without knowing the breed.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Dan Carey, New Glarus Brewing&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>It seemed like a watershed moment when we first scratched the surface of &amp;ldquo;biotransformation&amp;rdquo; and, subsequently, the effect of ester-rich yeasts on IPAs. As this style has evolved by leaps and bounds, we have gained a better understanding of how hops interact with different processes &amp;ndash; and with yeast.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>How might different base malts affect beers?&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-2/gallatin_malts.jpg"
alt="Gallatin malts steeps"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Color &amp;amp; flavor analysis steeps at Gallatin Valley Malt&lt;/p>&lt;p>Source: &lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/gallatinvalleymaltco/photos/a.707201556296362/1198845917131921/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">Gallatin Valley Malt Co.&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>America does have a number of &lt;a href="https://craftmalting.com/">craft malthouses&lt;/a>. Although many aren&amp;rsquo;t yet able to supply breweries with a reliable source of base malts for a year of regular-production beer, things might change with growing interest that will allow them to increase production and lower prices to compete with mass-produced malts. Some of these craft malts are not only interesting and flavorful, but also benefit the local economy and environment. A world with dozens of small, viable malthouses has the potential to transform beer tremendously, like hops and yeasts did.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For example, the single-origin base malts crafted by &lt;a href="https://www.gallatinvalleymalt.com/">Gallatin Valley Malt&lt;/a> (a farmer-owned craft malthouse in Manhattan, Montana) are quite distinct from the same types I&amp;rsquo;ve tried from several other malthouses (including &lt;a href="https://montanacraftmalt.com/">Montana Craft Malt&lt;/a>, which is located only ~1 hour away from Gallatin Valley Malt).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Heather Sargent, Head Maltstress at Gallatin Valley Malt, articulates the variability to me:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;Malts will generally vary in flavor and analysis between malt houses for several reasons. Where the barley is grown and how it&amp;rsquo;s grown play a huge part in the quality that the Maltster has to work with. Whether or not the grain is blended is another factor. Dry farming vs. irrigated. The way in which the grain is malted. Therefore, brewers can make their determinations based on the outcomes and what they like.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>That means, there are thousands of variations in just the &amp;ldquo;pale malt&amp;rdquo;! And the malt that goes into the recipe matters.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Breweries' chalkboards and printed menus often boast hop varieties, hoping (often correctly) that words like Citra, Enigma, or Lemondrop will entice customers to order a pint.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It&amp;rsquo;s rare, literally unheard of, for a brewery to advertise the malt bill on a menu (although it does show up from time to time on labels). The most overlooked ingredient can mean the difference between an enjoyable pint and a drain pour, and even help a brewery stand out and differentiate itself from the pack.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In what appears to be a fairly mature industry, craft malts have a chance to inject a new wave of innovation into our glasses.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The varieties of the grains that go into the malt are just as important as the hops that go into the wort. And not only the variety, but also the growing region (terroir) affects the malt&amp;rsquo;s flavor, haze, and foam stability.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-2/20230509_175115.jpg"
alt="tropical bomboloni"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Wholegrain thiolized &lt;em>bomboloni&lt;/em> (co-fermentation: London Tropics + California ale yeast)&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>In this experiment, I wanted to change the grains in the malt and see how that would impact the thiols in the final product.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="saccharified-mash">Saccharified mash&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>I limited thiol precursor-loaded, diastatic barley malt to 30% of total grains in the mash; the rest was all adjuncts, as far as diastatic powers and thiol precursors are concerned.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The light-golden &lt;a href="https://www.gallatinvalleymalt.com/gallatin-pale">pale malt&lt;/a> by Gallatin Valley Malt, made from Genie barley (grown, harvested, and malted right on GVM&amp;rsquo;s own farm in Montana&amp;rsquo;s breadbasket, the fertile &lt;a href="https://bozemanmagazine.com/articles/2018/09/04/102964-gallatin-agricultural-history">Gallatin Valley&lt;/a>, in a true field-to-kiln fashion), has an endearing aroma of sweet biscuits out of the box. When freshly ground, the malt tastes like Honey Nut Cheerios with a yummy sunflower seed butter drizzle &amp;ndash; none of the grass/straw/hay notes I&amp;rsquo;ve noticed in pale malts from some other malthouses.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>%&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Oberkülmer spelt flour (unmalted, unsifted)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>40%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>68g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>pale barley malt (Genie - Gallatin Valley Malt)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>30%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>51g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sourdough breadcrumbs, toasted&lt;/td>
&lt;td>30%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>51g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>warm water (~100°F)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>135%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>230g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Total: 400g&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I milled the grains into a flour, and mixed everything with water. I intentionally kept the mash thick, because I wanted to create an Italian &lt;em>lievito madre&lt;/em>-style stiff barm.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The mash then went through&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>30 minutes at ~105°F&lt;/li>
&lt;li>30 minutes at ~114°F&lt;/li>
&lt;li>4 hours at 144-154°F&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>After saccharification, the mash tasted brightly sweet and malty &amp;ndash; it reminded me of &lt;em>cannelés bordelais&lt;/em> drizzled with a decadent caramel sauce. GVM&amp;rsquo;s flagship &lt;a href="https://www.gallatinvalleymalt.com/gallatin-pale">pale malt&lt;/a> well deserved the silver medal at the 2022 Craft Maltsters Guild.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="barm">Barm&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>People seem to love to hate on the &amp;ldquo;Chico&amp;rdquo; strain. I&amp;rsquo;m guessing the main reason is that it&amp;rsquo;s a &amp;ldquo;boring&amp;rdquo; strain that doesn&amp;rsquo;t get you &amp;ldquo;fun&amp;rdquo; flavors like some other yeasts.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Interestingly, Jeremy Myers, head of production for Bachs Biermanufaktur in Saarland, Germany, &lt;a href="https://beerandbrewing.com/cold-healthy-and-crowded-lager-fermentation-simplified/">suggests&lt;/a> using White Labs WLP001 for lagers. He says &amp;ldquo;fermenting cold with that yeast leaves behind a beer with just the kind of clean, crisp flavor we want in a lager.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>IMO, &amp;ldquo;boring&amp;rdquo; strains like WLP001 are clean, versatile, low-ester, and low-phenol. They can be super useful and valuable in the right context. For example, they are &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/wlp001/">terrific for breads&lt;/a> that are intended to highlight a grain&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em>terroir&lt;/em>. If you ferment a few doughs with WLP001, keeping everything the same except the flours (use different varieties of wheat, e.g. Joaquin Oro vs. Sonora Blanca vs. Turkey Red), I bet you&amp;rsquo;d taste different flavors and &amp;ldquo;grain-forwardness&amp;rdquo; in each baked product. At least I did. In the &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/byb-1-2/">whole wheat bread&lt;/a> I made with WLP001, the yeast elevated the character of Turkey Red to such a degree that I never thought it was possible (with sourdough or bread yeast), and produced a stunningly pure, robust wheat flavor without the slightest hint of acidity &amp;ndash; it was like eating a box of Triscuit Original or drinking an American wheat beer. Pure, authentic, natural wheatopia.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Like how the Chico strain drove IPA 2.0 due to its &amp;ldquo;cleanness&amp;rdquo; that emphasizes malt and allows hops to shine through, I think it has the potential to do the same thing for Pizza/Bread 3.0 (especially when coupled with the &amp;ldquo;local grain&amp;rdquo; movement). Clean strains highlight the humble grain and let the grain flavor shine through, much more so than sourdough or bread yeast.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In this case, I scooped out 140g of the cooled mash (260g remaining), and added a 50/50 blend of &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/london-tropics/">London Tropics&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/wlp001/">WLP001 California ale yeast&lt;/a>. I intended to temper the thiol levels and let other characteristics stand out, to create a multi-layered, balanced bouquet of tropical aromas/flavors. (ICYMI, London Tropics proved to be an incredibly powerful &amp;ldquo;weapon of mass thiolization&amp;rdquo; in my &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/byb-5-1/">last experiment&lt;/a>.)&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>%&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>saccharified mash&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>140g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>London Tropics liquid yeast (Berkeley Yeast)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>0.5%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>0.7g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>California ale yeast (WLP001 - White Labs)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>0.5%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>0.7g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Total: 141.4g&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I added both yeasts at the same time, since they have similar optimal temperature range. I let the barm ferment, loosely covered, at 68-72°F for ~18 hours. The barm doubled in volume by the end.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Like &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/byb-5-1/">last time&lt;/a>, POG-type tropical aromas started to manifest ~3 hours in, but never got as pungent, which was expected, since the amount of precursors in the mash was drastically reduced and the inoculation rate of thiolized yeast was halved.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="final-dough">Final dough&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>This time, I decided to make a batch of &lt;em>bomboloni&lt;/em> (yeasted Italian donuts), instead of a loaf of bread. And I intentionally made these &lt;em>bomboloni&lt;/em> much more austere than &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/california-dreamin-5/">the Sonora Blanca version&lt;/a>. I wanted the yeasts to shine, untempered by spices or other add-ins.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>%&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Turkey Red whole wheat flour&lt;/td>
&lt;td>50.0%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>150g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>India Jammu whole wheat flour&lt;/td>
&lt;td>50.0%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>150g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>barm&lt;/td>
&lt;td>47.1%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>141.4g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>saccharified mash&lt;/td>
&lt;td>86.7%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>260g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>tap water&lt;/td>
&lt;td>15.0%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>45g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sea salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1.0%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>3g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Total: 749.4g &amp;mdash;-&amp;gt; makes 12 donuts @ ~62g each&lt;/p>
&lt;p>No sugar in the dough, because I wanted the sweetness to come from the coating on the outside, which would make the layers complement each other as you bite through them. Heterogeneity and contrast!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Unadorned ingredients can make something greater than the sum of its parts.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-2/20230509_174455.jpg"
alt="tropical bomboloni"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Wholegrain thiolized &lt;em>bomboloni&lt;/em> (co-fermentation: London Tropics + California ale yeast)&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The process was straightforward, too.&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Mix everything together into a stiff dough. (The dough smelt gently sweet and fruity, like a floral forest after rain.)&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Bulk ferment at ~72°F for 6 hours. Fold once every 30 mins, 4 times in total.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Retard in the fermentation fridge (~45°F) for 12 hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Divide into 12 pieces (~62g each), and shape into taut balls.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Proof at ~72°F for ~6 hours until doubled in size.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Heat a pot of coconut oil to 350°F; fry for 5-7 minutes on each side until brown and crispy.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Remove from oil and let dry on a wire rack lined with paper towels.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Once cool (but still warm), coat in homemade powdered sugar enhanced with a dash of cinnamon.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-2/20230509_174710.jpg"
alt="tropical bomboloni"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Wholegrain thiolized &lt;em>bomboloni&lt;/em> (co-fermentation: London Tropics + California ale yeast)&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>These donuts had a super fluffy, airy texture, almost completely concealing the fact they were made from unsifted whole grains. They also had a substantial mouthfeel &amp;ndash; quite contrary to the emptiness I always experience when eating donuts from national donut chains, which tend to be so overloaded with sugar that they melt in your mouth like cotton candy (in a bad way).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The tropical aroma was hard to distinguish underneath the cinnamon sugar coating, but a ripe fruit flavor was noticeable in the crumb, alongside an unyielding wheat flavor. It mildly reminded me of Kellogg&amp;rsquo;s Tropical Froot Loops cereal. Definitely not POG bombs this time.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Overall, I think these thiol-complimentary &lt;em>bomboloni&lt;/em> turned out much more balanced and delectable than my &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/byb-5-1/">last thiol-dominant bake&lt;/a> &amp;ndash; once again, proving &amp;ldquo;more isn&amp;rsquo;t always better.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Still, I don&amp;rsquo;t think the flavor was quite right &amp;ndash; it didn&amp;rsquo;t have the multi-layered bouquet of aromas/flavors I was expecting. Something was still amiss.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-2/20230509_175742.jpg"
alt="tropical bomboloni"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Wholegrain thiolized &lt;em>bomboloni&lt;/em> (co-fermentation: London Tropics + California ale yeast)&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Never underestimate what a yeast can do.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>🍻🍻🍻🍻&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Special thanks to&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://berkeleyyeast.com/">Berkeley Yeast&lt;/a>, for generously offering me the opportunity to do these fun thiol experiments.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Heather Sargent (the awesome Head Maltstress at &lt;a href="https://www.gallatinvalleymalt.com/">Gallatin Valley Malt&lt;/a>), for indulging my curiosity in malts and giving me the opportunity to experiment with GVM&amp;rsquo;s high-quality, single-origin malts.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>Peckham, Stephen (1880). &lt;em>Special Reports on Petroleum, Coke, and Building Stones.&lt;/em> United States Census Office. 10th census. p. 53.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/section></content></item></channel></rss>