<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>früchtebrot on HERESY LEVAIN</title><link>/tags/fr%C3%BCchtebrot/</link><description>Latest experiments in früchtebrot from HERESY LEVAIN</description><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2023 HERESY LEVAIN 🍞 CC BY-NC-SA 4.0</copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 16 Jan 2023 23:17:50 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/fr%C3%BCchtebrot/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Shinsekai no Ambrosia</title><link>/posts/shinsekai-ambrosia/</link><pubDate>Mon, 16 Jan 2023 23:17:50 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/shinsekai-ambrosia/</guid><description>The OG fruit &amp;amp; nut energy bar.</description><content>&lt;p>Noma, the Copenhagen restaurant that helped define a genre of ultra high-end, locally foraged, and culinarily groundbreaking cuisine, is &lt;a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2023/01/09/dining/noma-closing-rene-redzepi.html">closing&lt;/a> in 2024. Over the last decade, being able to experience Noma has apparently become a status symbol. Funny how the culinary icon was &lt;em>forced&lt;/em> to shut down after it found itself facing financial difficulties.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In October 2021, Noma &amp;ndash; arguably the most prestigious kitchen in the world &amp;ndash; started paying its interns (known as &lt;em>stagiaires&lt;/em>) for the first time. And that has added $50,000 to the restaurant&amp;rsquo;s monthly operating expenses, according to the NYT.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Rene Redzepi, chef-owner of Noma, said Monday that it wasn&amp;rsquo;t possible to make the math of fine dining work for his almost 100 employees and himself. &amp;hellip; In 2021, the restaurant lost money, even with government support, while selling $700 lunches.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Kate Krader, &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href="https://archive.is/JTOuA">Noma, One of the World’s Best Restaurants, Is Closing Its Doors&lt;/a>&amp;rdquo;, Bloomberg&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>According to an &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/files/Noma-offentliggorelse.pdf">annual report&lt;/a>, Noma received 🇩🇰 kr10.9 million (USD ~$1.57m) in Covid-19 compensation from the Danish government in 2021 while booking a net &lt;em>loss&lt;/em> of 🇩🇰 kr1.69 million (USD ~$240k); the previous year, it received 🇩🇰 kr8.05 million (USD ~$1.16m) in government financial aid and recorded a tiny profit of 🇩🇰 kr39,816 (USD ~$5,748).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Currently, one pays USD ~$500/person to eat a weeknight dinner soberly at Noma. The restaurant can seat ~42 diners comfortably. Let&amp;rsquo;s say 20 people dine at Noma every night Tues-Fri and 20 at Saturday lunch. $500 x 20 ppl x 5 days = $50,000/week in gross revenue (not even counting beverages), or &amp;gt;=$200k per month. If Noma is fully booked every day, it would make at least $105k/week, &amp;gt;=$440k a month, or &amp;gt;= $5m a year. And that&amp;rsquo;s just a baseline projection. $50,000/month in labor cost for ~100 employees = $500/month for each worker!!! 😱😨😳😱😱 Can you survive on that anywhere in the developed world?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If &amp;ldquo;the world&amp;rsquo;s most influential restaurant&amp;rdquo; that brings in &lt;em>at least&lt;/em> a quarter million USD in gross revenue each freakin' month can&amp;rsquo;t keep its doors open while paying its workers a meager wage of $500/month, then this industry at large has some major restructuring and soul-searching to do. Numbers don&amp;rsquo;t lie.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>The Finnish chef Kim Mikkola, who worked at Noma for four years, said that fine dining, like diamonds, ballet and other elite pursuits, often has abuse built into it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>“Everything luxetarian is built on somebody’s back; somebody has to pay,” he said.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>I can&amp;rsquo;t bring myself to mourn Noma&amp;rsquo;s closure, because there is no part of me that feels something is being lost or taken away. And no, I&amp;rsquo;ve never dined at Noma, so I can&amp;rsquo;t tell you how life-changing a Noma meal was. I did read &lt;em>The Noma Guide to Fermentation&lt;/em> a few years ago and tried making the rye bread miso (&amp;ldquo;ryeso&amp;rdquo;).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;m glad Noma existed and René Redzepi realized a business that exploits unpaid labor is unsustainable, financially and morally. I hope the next restaurant that rises to influence global cuisine as much as Noma did will be a pioneer in some sort of real sustainability, not just propelled by fanaticism around a singular genius or its &lt;a href="https://theworld.org/stories/2012-04-08/fascist-food-fight">avant-garde fascism&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The truth is, however elaborately prepared or miraculously transformed, at the end of the day it&amp;rsquo;s just food &amp;ndash; something that you swallow and inevitably becomes shit. Maybe that&amp;rsquo;s what made Anthony Bourdain so depressed.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>A human being is primarily a bag for putting food into.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>George Orwell&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>A lot of things are upside-down in the brave new Po-Lo (post-lockdown) world. Expensive fine dining as we know it seems to be &lt;a href="https://robbreport.com/paid-issue/death-fine-dining/">on its way out&lt;/a>. In fact, another destination for fine dining (in Silicon Valley), &lt;a href="https://sf.eater.com/2022/11/7/23444965/manresa-closing-reservations">Manresa&lt;/a>, closed in late 2022.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I am reminded of &lt;a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt9764362/">&lt;em>The Menu&lt;/em>&lt;/a>. The movie takes place mostly inside Hawthorne, a fictional uber-luxurious restaurant on a small island that seats only a dozen customers a night at $1,250/person. Workers are stuck between the belief that what they are doing (i.e. passionately pursuing their dreams) is worth sacrificing everything for and the reality that they have surrendered their lives to grueling service work which the monied class treats as merely social status accessories.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>There is something strange about real life &amp;ndash; you can feel so plugged in and so distant at the same time. You want to be part of the action, but you find yourself on the outside. And then, if you get close enough, you realize that the main goal of so many on the inside is to keep you out, and to make you think they know something that you do not, which is patently untrue.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Towards the end of &lt;em>The Menu&lt;/em>, Chef Slowik pours his heart and soul into making Margot a good old-fashioned cheeseburger, because he sees it as an opportunity to redeem himself from his failure to stay true to his art and make up for all the passionless meals he prepared for the rich. When Margot takes a bite and appreciates the burger for what it is &amp;ndash; a filling meal that satiates her hunger &amp;ndash; the chef finally feels proud and content.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This burger reminds me of &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kz9z_Q7ced8">&lt;em>lablabi&lt;/em>&lt;/a>, a working-class staple in Tunisia. To make &lt;em>lablabi&lt;/em>, you basically pour a thin soup with boiled chickpeas over a pile of stale bread that&amp;rsquo;s torn up into tiny pieces. &lt;em>Lablabi&lt;/em> is cheap, quick, and filling; it fuels you for the rest of the day and keeps you warm during the winter.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>At the other end of the dining spectrum is &lt;a href="https://www.danperlman.net/1999/07/11/white-trash-dinner/">&amp;ldquo;trailer trash food&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a>, stuff that I imagine the main character in Barbara Kingsolver&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em>Demon Copperhead&lt;/em> grew up eating. I haven&amp;rsquo;t forgotten the shock I experienced when I first encountered the &lt;a href="https://www.thelunchbelle.com/recipes-1/2010/12/1/recipe-white-trash-ambrosia.html">ambrosia&lt;/a> at a working-class eatery in South Carolina: canned fruits were mixed with canned whipped cream, mayonnaise, sugar, and mini marshmallows, and topped with Cool Whip. It&amp;rsquo;s apparently a Southern holiday tradition. (The OG ambrosia made in the 1800s used only 3 ingredients: orange slices, grated coconut, and sugar.)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A friend of mine recently went to Italy on vacation and brought me a &lt;em>panforte di Siena&lt;/em> &amp;ndash; a traditional Italian confection that&amp;rsquo;s a cross between fruitcake, candy, and &lt;em>Lebkuchen&lt;/em>. Basically, a dense, sweet &amp;ldquo;cake&amp;rdquo; made from candied fruits, nuts, spices, a touch of flour, and a sugar/honey syrup, dusted in powdered sugar on all sides. It tastes absolutely delicious, but far too sweet for me. I wanted to make a less sweet version with pretty much the same ingredients.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I stumbled across &lt;a href="http://www.farine-mc.com/2012/02/hutzelbrot-with-dried-cherries-and.html">&lt;em>hutzelbrot&lt;/em>&lt;/a>, looked into it further, and fell down a &lt;a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fr%C3%BCchtebrot">rabbit hole&lt;/a>&amp;hellip; Eric Carle&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href="https://eric-carle.com/eric-carle-book-gallery/the-very-hungry-caterpillar-1969/">hungry caterpillar&lt;/a> ate &lt;em>das Früchtebrot&lt;/em>??&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Hutzelbrot&lt;/em> is a German fruit bread, originally made with dried pears (called &amp;ldquo;hutzeln&amp;rdquo; in Alemannisch), but it gained many regional names as well &amp;ndash; &amp;ldquo;zelten&amp;rdquo; (Bolzano), &amp;ldquo;schnitzbrot&amp;rdquo; (Schwaben), &amp;ldquo;birnebrot&amp;rdquo; (Das Allgäu), &amp;ldquo;kletzenbrot&amp;rdquo; (Bavaria-Austria) or simply the more generic &amp;ldquo;früchtebrot&amp;rdquo; as it can be filled any dried fruits other than pears.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In the old days, the stingy farmers' wives would dry the leftover pears to avoid food waste and make the &lt;em>hutzelbrot&lt;/em> on St. Thomas' day, December 21st (the winter solstice). The wives and maids would embrace their pear trees, with their hands and arms still covered in dough, to ensure a good harvest in the following year.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Nothing beats ye olde traditional recipe. From &lt;a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fr%C3%BCchtebrot">Wikipedia&lt;/a>:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Originally Früchtebrot was made without honey, brown sugar or white sugar, with the sweetness coming only from the dried pears. Equally uncommon is Früchtebrot made of wheat dough. Using wheat dough makes the bread look less rustic, but also hinders the combustion of the fruits baked into it.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>So, it&amp;rsquo;s the medieval OG energy bar &amp;ndash; just dried fruits, nuts and a touch of rye flour!!!&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>An 18th-century manuscript describes celteno, a predecessor of Zelten. The recipe reads: &amp;ldquo;Take some Candia grapes, raisins, pine nuts, peeled almonds cut long, minutely cut lemon peel, aniseed seeds, candied citron, cinnamon powder, a little sugar, and a little flour and mix everything together. Take a small piece of brewer&amp;rsquo;s yeast, the size of a walnut&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Sabina Montevergine, &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href="https://www.lacucinaitaliana.com/italian-food/italian-dishes/zelten-christmas-cake-italian-mountains">Zelten&lt;/a>&amp;rdquo;, La Cucina Italiana&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>The internet shows me many kinds of &lt;em>das Früchtebrot&lt;/em>, which roughly fall into two categories:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>yeast-leavened breads, such as &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qMtdyZAjq3U">this früchtebrot&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=rDgT6aqO9wc">Kletzenbrot aus der ländlichen Küche&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=2v5Rzz73qhY">Schnitzbrot&lt;/a>, and &lt;a href="https://heissehimbeeren.com/das-saftigste-original-fruechtebrot-rezept-von-oma/">grandma&amp;rsquo;s original Früchtebrot&lt;/a> (with rye flour). The yeasted dough usually goes through a first rise, before mixing with rehydrated dried fruits and nuts. The dough can barely enrobe the huge amount of add-ins, and acts more like a binder.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>quick breads with baking powder, such as &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0t0bCzNaBfA">saftiges Früchtebrot&lt;/a> and &lt;em>Apfelbrot&lt;/em>.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Marcel Paa&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href="https://www.marcelpaa.com/rezepte/fruechtebrot">Früchtebrot-Powerbrot&lt;/a> uses a yeasted wholegrain preferment and a sourdough levain, similar to Peter Reinhardt&amp;rsquo;s.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Taking a page from all of the above, I started my heretical experiment a few days ago.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/shinsekai-ambrosia/202301151820.jpg"
alt="Shinsekai no Ambrosia"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;h4 id="saccharified-scald">Saccharified scald&lt;/h4>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>coarse rye flour (&lt;em>svedjerug&lt;/em> - Vestre Aschim, Norway)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>hot water&lt;/td>
&lt;td>230%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>white rye malt (diastatic)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;a href="https://brotgost.blogspot.com/2019/06/red-rye-malt.html">red rye malt&lt;/a> (not diastatic)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Mix everything together into a gravy. Cover and keep warm (~150°F) for 3+ hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="thermophilic-levain">Thermophilic levain&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>Once the scald has saccharified and cooled off to ~120°F, add a dollop of &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=x7dgQgYLuUs">thermophilic starter&lt;/a> (~7% of the total scald weight) &amp;ndash; or plain yogurt with live and active cultures.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Mix them together and put a plastic cling wrap on the surface to remove as much air as possible. Leave it to sour anaerobically for 18 hours at 120-125°F.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="pre-dough">Pre-dough&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>After 18 hours, stir some stale bread crumbs (altus) into the thermophilic levain. My altus added up to 35% of the thermophilic levain&amp;rsquo;s weight.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Keep refrigerated until ready to use (you can also leave it overnight at room temperature).&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="rye-sour">Rye sour&lt;/h4>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>whole rye flour (&lt;em>svedjerug&lt;/em> - Vestre Aschim, Norway)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>rye sourdough starter&lt;/td>
&lt;td>30%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>h₂o&lt;/td>
&lt;td>80%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Mix all of the ingredients. Let it double at room temperature (which can take 8-12 hours depending on the temperature).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>When fully ripened, cover tightly and refrigerate overnight, if necessary, to coordinate timing with the other parts. As you can see, I&amp;rsquo;m in absolutely no rush when I&amp;rsquo;m baking.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="final-dough">Final dough&lt;/h4>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>whole rye flour (&lt;em>svedjerug&lt;/em> - Vestre Aschim, Norway)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>pre-dough&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1270%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>rye sour&lt;/td>
&lt;td>400%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>dried fruits&lt;/td>
&lt;td>800%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>fresh grated coconut&lt;/td>
&lt;td>200%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>walnuts, toasted and chopped&lt;/td>
&lt;td>200%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>gingerbread spice (homemade)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>20%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Havnsø flake salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Dried fruits included dates, figs, goji berries, raisins, prunes, pineapples, and mangoes. (I would add dried pears, apples, apricots, cranberries, cherries, etc. if I had them on hand.) I didn&amp;rsquo;t soak them, just chopped and mixed them directly into the final dough.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Combine everything in a large bowl. Mix for a few minutes until all the ingredients are evenly integrated and distributed into the dough.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Let the dough rest at room temperature for ~1 hour.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Transfer to a wet surface and shape.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Final proof: I let the dough rise for ~12 hours at 60°F, until it had risen by ~50%.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Bake at 350°F for 50 mins.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Cool on a rack and wait 24+ hours before slicing.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/shinsekai-ambrosia/202301141647.jpg"
alt="Shinsekai no Ambrosia"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>This bread turned out superbly moist and dense, like a liquidy Lärabar. I couldn&amp;rsquo;t believe the knife came out clean! The scald worked out marvelously as a binder.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>First bite reminded me of a cocoa banana bread, which is weird because there was absolutely no banana or cocoa in it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It&amp;rsquo;s definitely not as decadent as &lt;em>il panforte di Siena&lt;/em>, but plenty sweet enough for me (I could eat 2 small slices at most in one sitting). I would definitely put a lot more nuts into it next time, and maybe reduce the amount of fruits.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/shinsekai-ambrosia/202301141649.jpg"
alt="Shinsekai no Ambrosia"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>This ambrosial fruit bread should be relished in the depth of winter &amp;ndash; it will help you discover that there is an invincible summer in you. エクスタシーへのパスポートです。&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Stanley Ginsberg has a recipe for &lt;em>zelten&lt;/em> in &lt;em>The Rye Baker&lt;/em>. No mention that it&amp;rsquo;s just &lt;em>hutzelbrot&lt;/em> by a different name.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Today is MLK Day in the US &amp;ndash; a federal holiday. I was looking for grains on some Swedish &lt;em>net butiker&lt;/em> this morning, and popped into a farm store statically built with Hugo (like this site you are reading right now). That&amp;rsquo;s a first and a breath of fresh air, given the virtually unassailable dominance by Shopify and Squarespace in e-commerce. It made me feel hopeful.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;ve been thinking a lot about an anime I watched a long time ago &amp;ndash; &lt;em>Shinsekai yori&lt;/em> (新世界より / From the New World).&lt;/p>
&lt;div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
&lt;iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/IH3cUNl595I" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video">&lt;/iframe>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>Eating another slice of my &lt;em>Shinsekai no Ambrosia&lt;/em> (新世界のアンブロシア, &amp;ldquo;ambrosia of the new world&amp;rdquo;), before the world starts back up on Tuesday.&lt;/p></content></item></channel></rss>