<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>cookies on HERESY LEVAIN</title><link>/tags/cookies/</link><description>Latest experiments in cookies from HERESY LEVAIN</description><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2023 HERESY LEVAIN 🍞 CC BY-NC-SA 4.0</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 26 Feb 2023 02:12:55 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/cookies/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>California Dreamin' #3: Sonora Blanca</title><link>/posts/california-dreamin-3/</link><pubDate>Sun, 26 Feb 2023 02:12:55 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/california-dreamin-3/</guid><description>[California Grain Adventure #3] Sonora Blanca minima: 100% wholegrain chocolate chip &lt;em>cookies de masa madre&lt;/em>, from scratch.</description><content>&lt;p>&lt;em>This is part 3 of my &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/california-grain-adventure/">California Grain Adventure&lt;/a>.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>For beauty, California is like the fresh, glowing, golden crescent moon; it is waxing steadily to a noble fullness of development.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Inez Haynes Irwin, &lt;em>The Californiacs&lt;/em> (1919)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>The California coast always looks so sunny and breathtaking, completely concealing the fact that most of the state is too dry to allow for a lot of life to thrive.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/california-dreamin-1">part 1&lt;/a>, I mentioned how California is a great exception to the rest of the US. Here&amp;rsquo;s yet another example: California is one of the few places where 4 of the 5 global climate zones (and 10 different climate subdivisions) occur in close proximity. Perhaps the only other place on the planet similar to California is central Chile, where this convergence is made even more extreme by the dramatic Andean topography.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-3/california-koppen-climates.png"
alt="Koppen climates in California"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Much of the state boasts a Mediterranean-style climate, which is rare outside of the Mediterranean Sea region. The one in California actually has 3 variations:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>cool summers and mild winters along the coast and the western slope of the Sierra Nevada;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>cool summers and mild winters, also along the coast, but with frequent summer fog;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>mild wet winters followed by hot dry summers with little or no rain for months, in the interior valley.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>With all types, most of the rain falls in winter &amp;ndash; not summer &amp;ndash; which is unusual for most of the world, where the opposite happens.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Precipitation levels also vary from year to year. Droughts come and go; extreme, multi-year statewide droughts have occurred several times throughout the past century; regional droughts have also plagued different parts of the state over the years.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Furthermore, most of California&amp;rsquo;s rain and snow fall in the northern half of the state &amp;ndash; in the Sierra Nevada Mountains, along the North Coast, and in the Cascade Range. However, most of the state&amp;rsquo;s population lives in the tremendously drier southern half.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Due to the variability in precipitation and the imbalance in population, California depends on a large network of reservoirs, dams, and aqueducts to store and transport surface water where and when people need it. According to a &lt;a href="https://lao.ca.gov/publications/report/3571">2017 report&lt;/a> from the Legislative Analyst&amp;rsquo;s Office, California has &amp;gt;20,000 miles of levees and channels, and over 1,500 dams and reservoirs. Make no mistake, California&amp;rsquo;s various flood control projects have been funded by the federal government.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Yup, &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/california-books">a great deal&lt;/a> about California does not, on its own preferred terms, add up.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>This extreme reliance of California on federal money, so seemingly at odds with the emphasis on unfettered individualism that constitutes the local core belief, was a pattern set early on, and derived in part from the very individualism it would seem to belie.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Joan Didion, &lt;em>Where I Was From&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>In southern California, water travels a great distance to get to people&amp;rsquo;s faucets: ~25% of the water used in southern California comes from the Colorado River; another 30% from the northern Sierras via the State Water Project; and the remaining 45% comes from a mix of &amp;ldquo;local&amp;rdquo; supplies, including the City of Los Angeles' eastern Sierra deliveries as well as desalination, recycling, and groundwater.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-3/california-map.png"
alt="Map of California"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Real-life California water wars (implicating everyone from local philanthropists right up to then-President Theodore Roosevelt) inspired the 1974 film noir &lt;em>Chinatown&lt;/em>, which played down the extent of the corruption involved. Perhaps it&amp;rsquo;s no surprise that later dystopian movies like &lt;em>Blade Runner&lt;/em> (1982) imagined a future Los Angeles of 2019 as a rain-soaked wasteland, after all the havoc that city officials wrought on the area&amp;rsquo;s ecosystem for personal profit.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The digital world is a lot of fun and undeniably innovative; search engines are ad vehicles and AI-powered voice assistants suck. Still, technology hasn&amp;rsquo;t been able to abstract away reality, and people seem to forget that it&amp;rsquo;s changes in the physical world that drive a lot of living standard improvements. Given how many people struggle in low-end jobs and how quickly tech expenditures are going up, claiming the internet is great smacks of &amp;ldquo;let them eat iPhones!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Competition for water is only growing and intensifying throughout California, particularly in the Central Valley.&lt;/p>
&lt;div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
&lt;iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/fWRs5B7rWYw" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video">&lt;/iframe>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>The Central Valley is very easy to ignore &amp;ndash; not in any way as glamorous as Silicon Valley or Hollywood &amp;ndash; but it&amp;rsquo;s as important to eaters (aka. all of us) as Silicon Valley is to smartphone users or Hollywood is to moviegoers.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Bordered on either side by mountains, the Central Valley stretches ~450 miles long from Redding to Bakersfield and ~50 miles wide on average, and occupies a land mass of 18,000 square miles (11.5 million acres) &amp;ndash; roughly the size of Massachusetts and Vermont combined. This valley is predominantly used for agriculture; it occupies &amp;lt;1% of US farmland, but supplies ~25% of Americans' food and accounts for 20% of the nation&amp;rsquo;s groundwater demand.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This valley contains the world&amp;rsquo;s largest patch of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/San_Joaquin_(soil)">Class 1 soil&lt;/a>, the best there is. The ~25°F temperature swing from day to night is an ideal growing range for plants. The sun shines nearly 300 days a year. The eastern half of the valley (and the western, to some extent) uses snowpack melt from the Sierra as its water source, i.e. it doesn&amp;rsquo;t have the same drought and flood problems as the Midwest. The winters are extremely mild with no snow, which offers a whole different growing season for plants that don&amp;rsquo;t adore summer heat.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The mild temperatures and winter rain support some of the highest biodiversity in the state. A few hundred different crops are grown in the valley, including those indigenous to South Asia, Southeast Asia and Mexico. Interestingly, some of that is canceled out by California&amp;rsquo;s Desert climates.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The expansive Central Valley is really two valleys: the Sacramento Valley to the north and the San Joaquin Valley to the south. The Steppe climate of the San Joaquin Valley is oppressively hot and dry like a desert, but averages enough moisture to support grasslands and other vegetation that commonly loathe the desert.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The Central Valley became widely known in the 1920s and 1930s, when farmers arrived from the eastern US, Oklahoma, Italy or Armenia and wrote home about the clean air, bountiful water and cheap land. This massive swath is now among the world&amp;rsquo;s most productive agricultural region &amp;ndash; and has helped California transformed from an agricultural backwater to one of the crown jewels of the US food system. The valley now produces almost all of the almonds, pistachios, and walnuts consumed domestically; &amp;gt;=90% of the artichokes, broccolis, carrots, celeries, garlic, grapes, plums, and tangerines; &amp;gt;=75% of the apricots, cauliflowers, lemons, strawberries, and raspberries; and &amp;gt;=40% of the cabbages, lettuces, oranges, peaches, and peppers.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The Central Valley is patently &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->John Steinbeck&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --> country. There are many fascinating places there like the &lt;a href="https://dustbowlcamp.org/history/">Weedpatch Camp&lt;/a>, the &lt;a href="https://www.bodie.com/plan/">Bodie&lt;/a> ghost town, the Japanese Internment Camp (aka. &lt;a href="https://www.nps.gov/manz/index.htm">Manzanar War Relocation Center&lt;/a>), Death Valley, Mount Whitney (the highest peak in the lower 48 states).&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>During the dry years, the people forgot about the rich years, and when the wet years returned, they lost all memory of the dry years. It was always that way.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>John Steinbeck, &lt;em>East of Eden&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Nothing much has changed in California and the Salinas Valley since 1952 when Steinbeck wrote &lt;em>East of Eden&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Farming and food production in the Central Valley are extremely vulnerable to droughts and floods. In a normal year, ~50% of the water used in the Central Valley comes from groundwater. During drought, when less water is available from rivers and canals, agriculture in the Central Valley typically depends on groundwater for over 2/3 of its water supplies.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As California enters exceptional &lt;a href="https://cww.water.ca.gov/droughtindicator">drought&lt;/a>, groundwater supplies throughout the Central Valley are being withdrawn faster than nature can replenish.&lt;/p>
&lt;div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
&lt;iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/-mSBOseNiZg" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video">&lt;/iframe>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>This is nothing new. Declines in groundwater levels have plagued the Central Valley for decades. Groundwater, according to one study, is effectively nonrenewable, because it can take centuries for aquifers to replenish once they are depleted, particularly in arid areas without significant rainfall.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Another study found that the depletion has worsened significantly since 2019, in a race to the bottom. Farmers need as much water as they can take out of the aquifers to farm the land in the hot and dry San Joaquin Valley.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>When groundwater levels keep on dropping, land surface can begin to subside.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Indeed, the overdrafting of the aquifer is causing portions of the valley floor to sink. As diminishing water levels leave spaces underground in layers of gravel, sand and clay, the ground collapses and permanently reduces the aquifer&amp;rsquo;s water-bearing capacity. In parts of the valley, the land has been sinking about 1 ft a year, damaging canals and wells.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If the groundwater disappears, so too does the food production. That means food shortages and higher food prices. By 2040, the San Joaquin Valley is projected to lose over &lt;a href="https://www.ppic.org/wp-content/uploads/water-and-the-future-of-the-san-joaquin-valley-february-2019.pdf">535,000 acres&lt;/a> of agricultural production. That&amp;rsquo;s &amp;gt;10% of the area farmed!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Meanwhile, towns in the Central Valley are beginning to run out of municipal water. Across the state, electric grids are also at risk if hydroelectric dams don&amp;rsquo;t get enough water to produce power. How are 10% of California&amp;rsquo;s car owners going to operate their Teslas?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Over the next two decades, California could lose ~10% of its water supplies. A growing number of scientists say the Golden State&amp;rsquo;s great &amp;ldquo;aridification&amp;rdquo; could permanently and profoundly change the state&amp;rsquo;s landscape and social fabric.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>What would John Steinbeck have written about the ongoing drought in California?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>What&amp;rsquo;s the flip side to the megadrought? Megaflood?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>California&amp;rsquo;s climate, already chaotic under normal conditions, is only getting weirder and wilder. Even if California does get enough rain this year to end the drought, it doesn&amp;rsquo;t change the fact that the ongoing water crisis is worsening.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It amazes me even more that the scarcest economic resources &amp;ndash; entrepreneurial ability and technical talent &amp;ndash; are spent on automating a globally abundant resource (i.e. cheap labor) and creating new variants of digital cocaine that are arguably more addictive and more harmful than cigarettes, instead of solving real-world problems.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>In California, water is now the most precious crop of all. Some farmers have realized that it makes better economic sense to sell unused water than to grow water-intensive crops like rice and almonds.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A huge transformation is happening up and down California&amp;rsquo;s Central Valley, as the agricultural labor supply shrinks and water becomes scarcer. Vast stretches of land are now fallow because there&amp;rsquo;s no water. New calculations are being made about what specific crops to grow, how much, and where. Millions of dollars are being spent on replenishing the aquifer that has been depleted for so long.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In the era of greater weather volatility, when water can be unreliable, adaptability is an asset.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-3/sonora-cwc.jpg"
alt="Sonora wheat berries"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Sonora Blanca wheat berries, from the San Joaquin Valley of California.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Which is why landrace plant varieties like the &lt;strong>Sonora Blanca&lt;/strong> wheat are important. Wheat production still requires water, but a lot less than growing rice, nuts or fruits.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/desert-dynamo">ICYMI&lt;/a>, Sonora is a heritage soft white winter wheat brought to the Americas by Spanish missionaries in the 1600s. It&amp;rsquo;s one of the &lt;a href="https://slowfoodusa.org/white-sonora-wheat/">oldest&lt;/a> varieties cultivated in North America, predating &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/red-fife/">Red Fife&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/turkey-red/">Turkey Red&lt;/a>. It&amp;rsquo;s also sometimes called Father Kino&amp;rsquo;s wheat, after Father Eusebio Francisco Kino who established Catholic missions throughout the Pimera Alta (present-day Sonora and southern Arizona) in the late 1600s.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The earliest known cultivation records document the grain&amp;rsquo;s existence in the early 1700s in the mountains of Sonora, a region in northern Mexico. That&amp;rsquo;s probably where the variety earned its name; to this day, Sonoran tortillas are more often made from soft wheat flour than maize like in the rest of Mexico.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>By the 1800s, Sonora wheat was widely planted in California and other areas in the southwestern US; it was a predominant source of flour for the western population, until the rise of industrialization after World War I, when hybridized high-yield commodity wheat replaced it. By the 1980s, Sonora was commercially dead. Luckily &amp;ndash; for those of us who care &amp;ndash; Sonora has been revived in the southwest thanks to the local-grain movement that spread like wildfire across the US.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-3/sonora-vs-joaquin.jpg"
alt="Sonora Blanca vs. Joaquin Oro"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Sonora Blanca (left) vs. Joaquin Oro (right), both grown in the San Joaquin Valley of California.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Sonora&amp;rsquo;s heritage earns it some clout by default. More importantly, the wheat has been adapting to the drought conditions in California for &lt;em>hundreds of years&lt;/em> (shall we crown it &amp;ldquo;the OG California Wheat?&amp;quot;). This adaptability has made the landrace variety popular among California grain farmers. Drought-tolerance eliminates the need for expensive irrigation. Additionally, Sonora&amp;rsquo;s lower protein content requires less input from the farmer, and lower nitrogen requirement makes it perfectly suitable for organic farming (no need to worry about the nitrogen content of the soil).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I baked with &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/desert-dynamo">Arizona-grown Sonora&lt;/a> a while ago, and named it &amp;ldquo;desert dynamo.&amp;rdquo; I still think it&amp;rsquo;s aptly named and well deserved. Everyone was telling me it was impossible to bake a lofty bread out of soft wheat alone, so I made a 100% Sonora bread just to show them it &lt;em>can&lt;/em> be done. The bread turned out so bloody marvelous it blew my expectations out of the water.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Thanks to generous friends at the California Wheat Commission, I got a chance to delve deeper into Sonora &amp;ndash; with the San Joaquin Valley terroir (grown by Eck Farms, CA).&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>Sonora actually can be planted in either fall or spring. It&amp;rsquo;s an early spring variety that does equally well as a winter wheat in milder winter climates that don&amp;rsquo;t freeze hard.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-3/sonora-backyard.jpg"
alt="Sonora growing in a 4×4 garden bed"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Sonora growing in a 4ft × 4ft garden bed.&lt;/p>&lt;p>Source: &lt;a href="https://gardenerd.com/blog/growing-white-sonora-wheat/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">Gardenerd&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>In southern California, even if you plant Sonora in October as a winter wheat, the climate there doesn&amp;rsquo;t really allow for winter wheat to behave like a winter wheat, which ordinarily grows low and wide in late fall, goes dormant in winter, then emerges and branches out in spring to maturity.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Sonora has a relatively high protein content (~12.7%), but is typically characterized as a &amp;ldquo;soft&amp;rdquo; wheat &amp;ndash; which befuddles me. The often-cited reason is that Sonora has inadequate &lt;a href="https://modernistcuisine.com/mc/gluten-how-does-it-work/">gluten-forming proteins&lt;/a>. I&amp;rsquo;ve never done individual testing of the glutenin and gliadin fractions in any wheat, nor am I interested in such, so don&amp;rsquo;t ask me. What I do know is that &lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=i6oQNo4gpeE">protein content&lt;/a> of a flour tells you little about the flour&amp;rsquo;s strength or baking performance. Some amino acids that make up the protein are usually water-soluble and contribute little to the strength of the flour, so a high-protein flour can actually have weak gluten.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-3/sonora-wheat-berries.jpg"
alt="Sonora Blanca wheat berries"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Sonora Blanca wheat berries, from the San Joaquin Valley of California.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>My &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/desert-dynamo">last bake&lt;/a> with Sonora proved to me that the flour is indeed capable of making a stretchable dough &amp;ndash; far more stretchable than a dough made with other soft wheats like Frederick (7.5%-9% protein) or even some hard wheats like &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/orange-sunshine">Warthog&lt;/a>; and apparently stretchable enough that Sonorans developed large flour tortillas, burritos and chimichangas with it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Sonoran-style flour tortillas (&lt;em>tortillas de harina estilo Sonora&lt;/em>) are works of art; they are stretched paper thin and cooked on a hot griddle, producing small blisters that give them a smoky flavor. Check out &lt;a href="https://www.latimes.com/food/la-fo-patricia-escarcega-sonoratown-review-20190424-story.html">Sonoratown&lt;/a>&amp;rsquo;s glorious flour tortillas in downtown Los Angeles, if you haven&amp;rsquo;t. They are freshly made daily, with &lt;a href="https://cooking.nytimes.com/recipes/1019621-sonoran-style-flour-tortillas">5 ingredients&lt;/a>: salt, water, lard, baking powder and soft Sonoran wheat flour produced in San Luis Río Colorado, on the Mexico-US border. These $10 plates of Sonoran tacos are so spectacular that hundreds of Angelenos would rather spend their time lining up in front of Sonoratown than going to flashy dinners at the world-famous &lt;a href="https://la.eater.com/2019/12/18/21028471/tartine-manufactory-downtown-los-angeles-the-row-closed-why">Tartine&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
&lt;iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/js2mgjJkyGE" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video">&lt;/iframe>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>A side note: If you have ever spent some time in Arizona, you may have noticed that the most distinctive marker of Arizonan cuisine is Sonoran-style Mexican food, an approach to border cooking that differs from Tex-Mex, New Mexican, or Baja styles and is seldom found outside of Arizona. Unlike the rest of Mexico where maize is king, Sonora is a wheat-growing region where the flour tortilla gets special attention, although they still use corn tortillas for a variety of dishes. In California, you are asked if you want flour or corn tortillas with dinner. In the Sonoran-style restaurants of Arizona, it&amp;rsquo;s assumed that you want the flour version.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>Sonora wheat berries are moderately hard, and lend themselves to milling.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Similar to &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/joaquin-oro/">Joaquin Oro&lt;/a>, Sonora mills to a fine, soft wholegrain flour on the first run (on a countertop electric WonderMill set to Bread Flour).&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-3/sonora-milled.jpg"
alt="Sonora Blanca wheat berries"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Freshly milled Sonora Blanca: a smooth, velvety wholegrain flour on the first run.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Since Sonora is commercially classified as a &amp;ldquo;soft&amp;rdquo; wheat, a lot of bakers automatically pass it up in breadmaking and use it instead in scones, biscuits, pies, muffins, tortillas, cookies, and cakes.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In fact, Sonora has a hidden kick of strength (&amp;quot;&lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/desert-dynamo">desert dynamo&lt;/a>&amp;quot;) that makes it work for many purposes and many meals. You can feed your family all three meals relying on just Sonora: biscuits/scones/muffins/tortillas for breakfast, naans or breads for lunch/dinner, and cakes/cookies throughout the day.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you are new to Sonora and other heritage wheat flours, start with a familiar recipe such as chocolate chip cookies.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-3/20230224_230603.jpg"
alt="Sonora Blanca chocolate chip cookies"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Chocolate chip &lt;em>cookies de masa madre&lt;/em>, with freshly milled wholegrain Sonora Blanca flour.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>I made two batches of chocolate chip &lt;em>cookies de masa madre&lt;/em> (with sourdough) from unsifted Sonora flour. All of the flour is pre-fermented to boost the flavor and bioavailability.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="iteration-1">Iteration #1&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Formula:&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Sonora Blanca flour, 100% extraction&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>200g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->malted barley flour&lt;sup id="fnref:2">&lt;a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->, 100% extraction&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>20g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>water&lt;/td>
&lt;td>55%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>110g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sourdough discard&lt;/td>
&lt;td>20%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>40g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;em>beurre noisette&lt;/em> (brown &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->butter&lt;sup id="fnref:3">&lt;a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">3&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->), softened&lt;/td>
&lt;td>25%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>50g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>extra virgin coconut oil, softened&lt;/td>
&lt;td>25%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>50g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->&lt;em>piloncillo oscuro&lt;/em>&lt;sup id="fnref:4">&lt;a href="#fn:4" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">4&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->, softened &amp;amp; chopped&lt;/td>
&lt;td>40%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>80g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>honey&lt;/td>
&lt;td>40%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>80g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>vanilla extract&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>4g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>4g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>baking soda&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->&lt;em>chocolate caliente mexicano&lt;/em> (homemade)&lt;sup id="fnref:5">&lt;a href="#fn:5" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">5&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->&lt;/td>
&lt;td>20%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>40g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>chocolate chips (Ghirardelli bittersweet)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>90%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>180g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>&lt;code>Note&lt;/code>: I didn&amp;rsquo;t use any eggs in these cookies, because eggs have been scarce on store shelves; whatever eggs I manage to track down, they are selling at &lt;a href="https://eggspensive.net/">record high prices&lt;/a>. Government data showed US consumers were paying $4.25 on average for a dozen eggs as of last December, which was 138% more than the year before.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The process is super simple:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Make the super &lt;em>masa madre&lt;/em>: Mix together the whole wheat flour, malt, water, and sourdough into a stiff ball. Let it ferment in a warm place for 3-4 hours, or until doubled in volume. Keep an eye on it &amp;ndash; you don&amp;rsquo;t want it to overripen and get sour.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Break up the &lt;em>masa madre&lt;/em>. Add the rest of the ingredients except the chocolate chips; mix until homogeneous.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Stir in the chocolate chips; mix until evenly dispersed.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Scoop onto a baking tray, spaced about 2&amp;rdquo; apart. (Chill the dough and the scoop first for 15-20 minutes, if you prefer thicker cookies.)&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Bake for 15 minutes at 300F, or until spread out and light brown.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-3/20230224_225515.jpg"
alt="Sonora Blanca chocolate chip cookies"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Chocolate chip &lt;em>cookies de masa madre&lt;/em>, with freshly milled wholegrain Sonora Blanca flour.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Listen up!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Here are three tricks to the very best chocolate cookies:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Use fresh wholegrain flour!&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Add 10% malted barley flour.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Brown the butter to accentuate the maltiness of the flours. Do yourself a favor and get a block of high-quality butter: 83% from Wisconsin, Kerrygold, New Zealand butter, or Isigny Sainte-Mère.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>Voila!&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-3/20230224_231154.jpg"
alt="Sonora Blanca chocolate chip cookies"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Chocolate chip &lt;em>cookies de masa madre&lt;/em>, fresh from the oven. The soft chewy interior is oozing with warm chocolate.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>A thin, crispy crust enrobes a soft center oozing with melty chocolate. Heavens.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Every bite gets a rich hit of chocolate in all its creamy, nutty, and caramelized glory.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-3/20230224_230201.jpg"
alt="Sonora Blanca chocolate chip cookies"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h3 id="iteration-2">Iteration #2&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>These cookies were gone within a few hours of emerging from the oven, so I had to make a 2nd freakin' batch.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I happened to have a few gorgeous beetroots (probably from California&amp;rsquo;s San Joaquin Valley, too), so I roasted the cubed beets on a charcoal-fired BBQ grill until perfectly caramelized. Then I puréed the beets in a blender, and added some of the red gold into the cookie dough.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Sonora Blanca flour, 100% extraction&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>200g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>malted barley flour, 100% extraction&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>20g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>water&lt;/td>
&lt;td>55%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>110g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sourdough discard&lt;/td>
&lt;td>20%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>40g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>roasted beetroot purée&lt;/td>
&lt;td>50%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>extra virgin coconut oil, softened&lt;/td>
&lt;td>25%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>50g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;em>piloncillo oscuro&lt;/em>, softened &amp;amp; chopped&lt;/td>
&lt;td>40%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>80g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>honey&lt;/td>
&lt;td>40%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>80g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>vanilla extract&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>4g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>4g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>baking soda&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>chocolate chips (Ghirardelli bittersweet)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>90%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>180g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>If you haven&amp;rsquo;t noticed, I omitted the brown butter and hot chocolate mix in this batch.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-3/20230225_185243.jpg"
alt="Sonora Blanca chocolate chip cookies"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Chocolate chip cookies batch #2, with roasted beetroot purée.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>They turned out royally delicious. Actually, they reminded me of Mexican &lt;em>polvorones rojas&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-3/20230225_185711.jpg"
alt="Sonora Blanca chocolate chip cookies with beetroots"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>cookies veganos de remolacha y chocolate&lt;/em>, made from scratch with fresh wholegrain Sonora Blanca flour.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Amid global and domestic supply chain turmoils (major supermarkets in the UK have &lt;a href="https://www.cnn.com/2023/02/24/business/uk-vegetable-fruit-shortage-rationing/index.html">started rationing produce&lt;/a>), these cookies really make me wonder what would happen when California&amp;rsquo;s Central Valley falls apart&amp;hellip; What would be the new normal? Time to build out my backyard vegetable garden?&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>&lt;em>This is part 3 of my &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/california-grain-adventure/">California Grain Adventure&lt;/a>. If you enjoyed it, why not check out my other &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/archives/">breadstories&lt;/a> and spread the word?&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>A little-known fact about John Steinbeck is that he was a travel writer. His nonfiction book, &lt;em>Travels With Charley&lt;/em>, preceded other great American road trip novels by Jack Kerouac, Studs Terkel, etc. In 1962, John Steinbeck won the Nobel Prize for his body of work. The Nobel Committee wrote: &amp;ldquo;His sympathies always go out to the oppressed, the misfits, and the distressed; he likes to contrast the simple joy of life with the brutal and cynical craving for money. But in him we find the American temperament also expressed in his great feelings for the tilled soil, the wasteland, the mountains, and the ocean coast&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>I made my diastatic barley malt flour from unhulled malted barley, finely ground and unsifted.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:3" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>Making brown butter at home is &lt;a href="https://food52.com/recipes/7234-beurre-noisette">super easy&lt;/a>. You can totally veganize these cookies by substituting the butter with coconut oil.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:4" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>Substitute with unrefined raw cane sugar.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:4" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:5" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>Making a Mexican hot chocolate mix from scratch takes only a few minutes and can be adjusted to your personal taste. I used freshly ground toasted pecans &amp;amp; almonds, cocoa powder, cinnamon, cardamom, clove, tri-pepper powder (ancho, guajillo, and habanero), and coconut sugar.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:5" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/section></content></item></channel></rss>