<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>grouse malt house on HERESY LEVAIN</title><link>/tags/grouse-malt-house/</link><description>Latest experiments in grouse malt house from HERESY LEVAIN</description><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2023 HERESY LEVAIN 🍞 CC BY-NC-SA 4.0</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 06 Jun 2023 19:09:09 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/grouse-malt-house/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>levure de bière #5.4: Tropical cornucopia</title><link>/posts/byb-5-4/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Jun 2023 19:09:09 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/byb-5-4/</guid><description>Portuguese-inspired &lt;em>broa de milho&lt;/em> with two leavens: a Framgarden kveik barm and a London Tropics yeasted soaker. Baked outdoors and imbued with the wonderful smoky flavor of open-fire bakery. Hearty and rustic.</description><content>&lt;p>&lt;em>Beer = liquid bread. Want to stay updated on my &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/craft-beer-yeast">craft beer yeast bread-plays&lt;/a>? Subscribe to the &lt;a href="https://tinyletter.com/breadbuster">newsletter&lt;/a>!&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Key West, the southernmost point of the continental US, is one of my favorite summer spots. Ernest Hemingway once said Key West was &amp;ldquo;a St. Tropez of the poor.&amp;rdquo; He came for a day and ended up staying for a decade.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The island is still a source of endless joy: fishing, scuba diving, dancing, slumming, and drinking. The most beautiful thing about Key West is spending the night on the beach (not the best in Florida), swimming there as if it were daytime, and tanning, like vampires, under the moonlight. And I always like to bring &lt;em>medianoches&lt;/em> and &lt;em>chicharones&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This time, I drank lots of corn. First of all, a fermented &lt;em>chicha morada&lt;/em> (I can&amp;rsquo;t stand the sweet and fruity non-fermented version), made with Peruvian purple corn, pineapple, apples, lime, and spices. It tasted like a &lt;em>kombucha&lt;/em>. Next, a &lt;em>chicha venezolana&lt;/em>, which turned out more like a Mexican &lt;em>horchata&lt;/em>. On my way out, I drank homemade &lt;em>chicha de jora&lt;/em> and ate &lt;em>estofado de carne&lt;/em> (rich and flavorful beef stew with garden vegetables and &lt;em>chicha de jora&lt;/em>); the stew reminded me of &lt;em>bœuf bourguignon&lt;/em> and was a lot better than this Ohio &amp;ldquo;delicacy&amp;rdquo; called Cincinnati chili 3-way I had earlier at Skyline just outside Fort Lauderdale, which is a pound of shredded cheese on top of mediocre chili on top of poorly cooked spaghetti.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>These brought back good memories of backpacking in Peru and eating at &lt;em>picanterías&lt;/em>, where &lt;em>chicha morada&lt;/em> and &lt;em>chicha de jora&lt;/em> are commonly brewed in-house.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Chicha&lt;/em> is an ancient pre-Columbian corn drink widespread in the Andes. It was absolutely essential to the Incas; for them it was a fundamental domestic product, traded from coast to inland, up and down the continent. &lt;em>Chicha&lt;/em> was a community necessity, a ritual libation, an imperative social lubricant to the Incas' communication with the gods, a drink worthy of being sipped by a farmer straight out of a clay pot as well as lapped up by the sun itself out of a gold vessel.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The brewing process for &lt;em>chicha&lt;/em> is essentially &lt;a href="https://beerconnoisseur.com/articles/chicha-bolivias-tart-beer">similar&lt;/a> to that of European-style beer.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Doña Leonor Mariscal, 70 years old, does just that for her fellow villagers. In her tiny ramshackle building, once a chicheria itself, she steeps the corn and lets it germinate a bit on a large piece of cloth laid out in the sun, directly on the cobblestone street in front of her building. The sun is sometimes hot enough to dry out her corn malt, but she admits to using ashes sometimes to complete the process. She then bags the malt and lets the area chicha brewers grind this corn into a flour at their own breweries. &amp;hellip;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The fermentation therefore seems to be nearly entirely carried out by the natural content of the corn. Many traditional cochabambina brewers like Doña Narcissa do not seem aware that the lactic acid bacteria contained within the corn is the true origin of the alcohol, light fizz and acidic flavor of their brew. But what matters is that they are always able to quench chicha lovers' thirst for delicate tartness; the science behind their brewing methods isn&amp;rsquo;t a major concern.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Outside Latin America, the one thing most people remember about &lt;em>chicha&lt;/em> is that it&amp;rsquo;s often fermented with human saliva. In particular, &lt;em>chicha de jora&lt;/em> (&lt;em>jora&lt;/em> is a specific kind of yellow maize) is typically prepared by chewing said corn into a clump before fermenting it into a boozy concoction. Since the starch in corn is well locked into the grain kernel and thus unavailable for fermentation on its own, chewing allows the enzymes (e.g. amylases) in your mouth to break down the starch into sugar.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-4/20230604_224406.jpg"
alt="malted yellow corn"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>malted yellow corn from Grouse Malt House&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The chewing inevitably raises many eyebrows. The idea of consuming a drink brewed from someone else&amp;rsquo;s saliva is viscerally disturbing, particularly in the post-COVID era. Using saliva as a fermentation starter is not unique to South America, however; there&amp;rsquo;s evidence that chewing as a way of kicking off fermentation was practiced in prehistoric Europe before the emergence of malting; Finnish folklore tells the legend of a woman by the name of Kalevatar, who invented beer by mixing honey with bear saliva; some traditional Japanese &lt;em>sakes&lt;/em>, such as &lt;em>kuchikamizake&lt;/em> (口噛み酒, meaning &amp;ldquo;mouth-chewed &lt;em>sake&lt;/em>&amp;quot;), are made from chewed rice; and &lt;em>kava&lt;/em>, produced by the peoples of the Pacific Islands from chewing the roots of kava (aka. &lt;em>Piper methysticum G. Forst&lt;/em>), was born in this way.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Fetishes and aesthetics aside, saliva contains diverse microbiomes, and each person&amp;rsquo;s saliva is different and therefore gives different flavors to the fermented product.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;ve been smitten with grain corns. You may remember the loaf of &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/byb-4/">blue corn bread&lt;/a> I made with East Coast ale yeast a few weeks ago. This time, inspired by the wonderful Peruvian corn dishes and drinks I had in Key West, I&amp;rsquo;d like to up the corn percentage and make a Portuguese-style &lt;em>broa de milho&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-4/20230606_161110.jpg"
alt="broa de milho"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Portuguese-style &lt;em>broa de milho&lt;/em> (corn bread), crumbshot.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;h3 id="corn-mash">Corn mash&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Some brewers have described dealing with malted corn as &amp;ldquo;pure, unadulterated pain from hell&amp;rdquo; that comes in many folds:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Malted corn has low diastatic power &amp;ndash; barely 35 °L. That&amp;rsquo;s hardly enough to fully convert itself, and requires exogenous amylase from either malted barley or powdered additive.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Corn has a higher gelatinization temperature than barley to break apart the starch molecules. Boiling corn would do the trick. However, high temperatures will kill those natural enzymes meant to convert the starches to fermentable sugars.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Also, while corncobs as a whole do have husks, the corn kernels do not contain husks, making lautering comparable to the 9th layer of hell. Luckily, this challenge doesn&amp;rsquo;t exist in solid beer (aka. bread).&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Undermodifed malts, including corn, have dimethyl sulfide (DMS) in spades, so when you combine the two you may develop unpleasant off-flavors if the proper precautions aren&amp;rsquo;t taken.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>You know, none of this sounds that excruciating to me.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you really are a single-malt purist, you will&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>chew the corn to break it into smaller bits for the mash and add the enzymes from your saliva that will break down the starches to sugars; or&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>go through European-style triple-decoction mashing.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>If you aren&amp;rsquo;t that much of a purist, then you need to add exogenous enzymes. One way is to add dry amylase powder; another is to use some pale barley malt to get the enzymes.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-4/20230605_004913.jpg"
alt="malted yellow corn"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Freshly ground malted yellow corn delivers an earthy, sweet flavor reminiscent of a classic Southern cornbread.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>I wanted to do the single-malt triple-decoction mashing, because mashing is fun and I had never done an all-corn mash before.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>%&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>yellow corn malt (Grouse Malt House)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>375g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>tap water&lt;/td>
&lt;td>87.2%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>327g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Total: 702g&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Since maize doesn&amp;rsquo;t contain large amounts of phytase, acid rest isn&amp;rsquo;t necessary.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I started the mixture at ~125°F where I left it for 2 hours (protein rest). Then I decocted 1/3 of the mash and boiled it for 2 minutes. I tasted a small sample of the decoction &amp;ndash; it was insanely sweet, and reminded me of a Southern cornbread but slightly more starchy.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>After a few minutes, I added the boiled decoction back to the main mash and it raised the temperature to 150°F. I held the mash at ~150°F for the next 5 hours, turning the stove top burner on occasionally to keep the temperature consistent. Further sweetness didn&amp;rsquo;t begin to manifest until the end of it, with plenty of residual starchiness. So I decocted 1/3 of the mash again, and boiled for 2 minutes; when I returned the decoction to the main mash, it brought up the temperature to 158°F, where I left it for another 2.5 hours. Lastly, I decocted 1/3 of the mash again, raising the temperature of the main mash to 168°F &amp;ndash; and held it there for 1 hour.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>After all that, starch was no longer perceivable to my tongue. The saccharified corn mash had the fragrance of sweet corn cookies, with intriguing background notes of chestnuts. It tasted insanely sweet and malty, and had a distinct caramelized corn flavor &amp;ndash; almost like a corn muffin. I quite enjoyed the mash, and honestly could have devoured it as is (like a breakfast porridge or dessert).&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="corn-barm">Corn barm&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Once the saccharified corn mash had cooled off to body temperature, I measured 150g out into a separate bowl for yeast inoculation, reserving the remaining 552g in the fridge until needed.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>%&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>saccharified corn mash&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>150g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Framgarden liquid yeast (Escarpment Labs)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1.5g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Total: 151.5g&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Framgarden expresses a tropical profile with lots of pineapple leading the way and subtler notes of hay and white pepper in the background.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Escarpment&amp;rsquo;s recommended temperature range for Framgarden is quite wide (68-95°F). I let the inoculated mash ferment, loosely covered, at 80-85°F for 12 hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="yeasted-rye-soaker">Yeasted rye soaker&lt;/h3>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>%&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Gazelle rye flour, 100% extraction&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>75g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>London Tropics liquid yeast (Berkeley Yeast)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>75g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Total: 150g (100% extraction = whole grain)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I mixed the wholegrain rye flour with the yeast slurry until thoroughly hydrated, and let the mixture ferment (loosely covered) at ~68°F for 12 hours. I didn&amp;rsquo;t expect this to biotransform or ferment much &amp;ndash; it was more of a soaker (à la Peter Reinhart&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em>Whole Grain Breads&lt;/em>) that utilized excess liquid yeast, in this case, to thoroughly hydrate the whole grains and enhance flavors in the final bread.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Oh boy, biotransformation kicked off as soon as I mixed everything together; the artificial fruit aroma didn&amp;rsquo;t get as overwhelming as in my first &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/byb-5-1/">POG bomb&lt;/a>, but very noticeable. I started to regret underestimating this &amp;ldquo;weapon of mass thiolization&amp;rdquo;&amp;hellip;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>After ~12 hours, the soaker showed slight signs of fermentation and smelled pungently fruity &amp;ndash; Mr. Fusion-powered DeLorean time machine was back in full stride. A hyperrealistic simulacrum. A hallucinatory fantasy. It reminded me of a quote from Jean Baudrillard:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;What every society looks for in continuing to produce, and to overproduce, is to restore the real that escapes it.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Interestingly, Untitled Art in Waunakee, WI just released a &lt;a href="https://www.drinkuntitled.com/product/non-alcoholic-berliner-weisse/">non-alcoholic &lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em>&lt;/a> brewed with London Tropics, de-alcoholized with membrane filtration technologies.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Since thiols are more soluble in alcohols than in water, doesn&amp;rsquo;t the filtration remove quite a bit of the thiols as well? I wonder how much of the fruity aroma/flavor from Tropics remains in the NA beer. As far as I know, de-alcoholization generally removes the fermentation products &amp;ndash; which can be added back in, but that process can be pretty violent to the flavor structure of the beer and, most notably, quite expensive.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Wouldn&amp;rsquo;t arrested fermentation (e.g. interrupting full attenuation) with Tropics make more sense in producing NA beers? In my bread experiments, London Tropics kicks off biotransformation waaaay before attenuation.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="final-dough">Final dough&lt;/h3>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>%&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>einkorn flour, 100% extraction&lt;/td>
&lt;td>50.0%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>khorasan wheat flour, 100% extraction&lt;/td>
&lt;td>50.0%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>corn mash&lt;/td>
&lt;td>276.0%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>552g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>corn barm&lt;/td>
&lt;td>75.8%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>151.5g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>yeasted rye soaker&lt;/td>
&lt;td>75.0%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>150g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sea salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2.0%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>4g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>(100% extraction = whole grain)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I mixed all of the ingredients together into a homogeneous dough, and let it ferment at ~73°F for 2 hours. Then I shaped it into a &lt;em>boule&lt;/em>, and placed it in a proofing colander liberally coated with toasted oat bran. The dough was left to proof at ~58°F for 14 hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Once I got the BBQ grill to 400°F, I flipped the dough into a cast-iron skillet and slid it onto the grill. I added black walnut shells to the bottom of the grill, closed the lid, and let the bread bake at 400°F for 1 hour.⁠&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-4/20230606_131550.jpg"
alt="broa de milho"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Portuguese-style &lt;em>broa de milho&lt;/em> (corn bread), in cast-iron skillet.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Summer is a completely different experience when you know how to grill.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The crust came out thick, smoky, charred, and crunchy; the inside moist and tender, plush with a flavor that absolutely reverberated with corn. Mouthfuls of smokiness, too. The tropical fruit profile got subdued by the wonderful smoky flavor of open-fire bakery.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It&amp;rsquo;s that perfect, forever corn bread that I want to bring to the beach. The summer wish I never knew I had.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-4/20230606_161227.jpg"
alt="broa de milho"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Portuguese-style &lt;em>broa de milho&lt;/em> (corn bread), crumbshot.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>This corn bread went so well with summer salads and snacky things. I took it to a park today, along with some butter (not optional), and enjoyed the hell out of it under a tree, while watching the clouds float across the sky.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>And so with the sunshine and the great bursts of leaves growing on the trees, just as things grow in fast movies, I had that familiar conviction that life was beginning over again with the summer.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&amp;ndash; F. Scott Fitzgerald&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote></content></item><item><title>levure de bière #5.3: Tropical buckwheat dream</title><link>/posts/byb-5-3/</link><pubDate>Thu, 25 May 2023 01:54:31 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/byb-5-3/</guid><description>An audacious &lt;em>Buchweizenbrot&lt;/em> (46.88% caramel buckwheat malt + 46.88% ancient grains + 6.25% pale barley malt). Mixed-fermentations with Escarpment Labs' traditional Latvian Kolnasāta, Berkeley Yeast&amp;rsquo;s GM thiolized London Tropics, and Imperial Yeast&amp;rsquo;s Suburban Brett. Boldly earth, charmingly fruity, and deeply satisfying.</description><content>&lt;p>&lt;em>Beer = liquid bread. Want to stay updated on my &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/craft-beer-yeast">craft beer yeast bread-plays&lt;/a>? Subscribe to the &lt;a href="https://tinyletter.com/breadbuster">newsletter&lt;/a>!&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;m surprised how many people watch only HBO and whatever the Netflix algorithm recommends. It&amp;rsquo;s kind of like the folks who email me asking factual questions &amp;ndash; have they never heard of the internet? There&amp;rsquo;s a vast cornucopia of streaming series out there; if you pick the right one, your life will be enhanced.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Last night I watched the final two episodes of &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Farzi">Farzi&lt;/a>&amp;rdquo; while licking a plate of buttery &lt;a href="https://authenticsimplifiedrecipes.wordpress.com/2019/02/21/pav-bhaji/">&lt;em>pav bhaji&lt;/em>&lt;/a>. When the show was over, I spontaneously exclaimed, &amp;ldquo;That was great!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Frankly, not as great as &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Bureau_(TV_series)">&lt;em>Le Bureau des Légendes&lt;/em>&lt;/a>&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt2324587/">&lt;em>Počivali u miru&lt;/em>&lt;/a>&amp;rdquo;, but really fulfilling. And it&amp;rsquo;s hard to find those shows these days.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;Farzi&amp;rdquo; is about the rigid caste system in India, where upward mobility is extremely limited. But that doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean you can&amp;rsquo;t dream. Opportunities are closed. But that doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean you&amp;rsquo;re not smart or willful.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Most people are so addicted to brands (e.g. HBO or Apple TV+). They watch only light stuff like comedy; they say real life is daunting enough, they don&amp;rsquo;t want to be brought down by a show.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>That&amp;rsquo;s what life is all about: new experiences, stretching your horizons, because otherwise you&amp;rsquo;d end up living on repeats, waiting to die.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Which is why I&amp;rsquo;ve been experimenting with uncommon grains.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Wheat has been the hegemony in the bread world, while barley reigns supreme in the brewing industry. Malt has become synonymous with barley the way that flour has with wheat, but malt can be made from any type of (pseudo)grain.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="buckwheat">Buckwheat&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The only exposure most people in the West have to buckwheat is in pancakes, which is quite sad.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-3/20230520_124107.jpg"
alt="buckwheat soba"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Handmade &lt;em>soba&lt;/em> noodles from scratch, with caramel buckwheat malt, &lt;em>bonito&lt;/em>, London Tropics liquid yeast, and sourdough starter. All done within 30 minutes by a newbie! Contrary to popular belief, it doesn&amp;rsquo;t take 10 years of training to master making 100% &lt;em>soba&lt;/em> noodles.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Buckwheat (&lt;em>Fagopyrum sagittatum syn. F. esculentum&lt;/em>) is a curious and misunderstood food. It&amp;rsquo;s not a &amp;ldquo;wheat&amp;rdquo;, but is treated like one. It&amp;rsquo;s actually a shrub, related to rhubarb; it produces seeds on the flower heads. These seeds (or kernels) are what get ground into flour.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Like other seeds, buckwheat is high in both protein (18% by weight!) and fiber, but it&amp;rsquo;s unique among the seeds we typically eat, because it&amp;rsquo;s mainly composed of carbs, with lower fat and higher starch content than, say, sunflower seeds or chia seeds. IMO, buckwheat has a well-balanced starch, protein, fat, and mineral composition, and is absolutely delicious. Hands-down one of my favorite &amp;ldquo;cereals.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Buckwheat was long thought to have originated in central Asia, somewhere between Lake Baikal and Manchuria. Recent &lt;a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/BF02861199">research&lt;/a> now leans toward southwest China and the Himalayan region as the center of origin. The two cultivated species of buckwheat, &lt;em>Fagopyrum esculentum&lt;/em> (common buckwheat) and &lt;em>Fagopyrum tataricum&lt;/em> (tartary buckwheat) are Chinese domesticates, presumably originating in upland southwest China, outside the major rice and millet centers.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Buckwheat is known as &lt;em>grano saraceno&lt;/em> in Italian and &lt;em>sarrasin&lt;/em> in French, leading the late food writer Waverly Root to assume that buckwheat originated in Asia Minor and was introduced by either the Turks, the Crusaders, and/or the Moors to places in Europe where other grains didn&amp;rsquo;t grow well and where the people ate &amp;ldquo;robustly&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; such as Brittany, Finland, Styria, central France and the Tyrolian Alps. Europeans of the Middle Ages, however, used the term &amp;ldquo;saracen&amp;rdquo; to describe many things that simply came from the East, whether they were Arabian or not.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>According to the contemporary Italian botanist Valerio Giacomini, who has made a thorough study of buckwheat, there are three possible ways buckwheat arrived in Europe:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>through southern Russia, Poland, and Germany &amp;ndash;&amp;gt; Belgium and France;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>through Turkey &amp;ndash;&amp;gt; Greece, Hungary, and southern Russia; and&lt;/li>
&lt;li>through the maritime contacts of Venice, which might explain in part the ascription of &amp;ldquo;saracen.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>There is a legend that Joos van Ghistele brought it back with him from his journey to the Holy Land in 1485. Who knows. In any case, the origin of buckwheat is unknown, even if its name in Latin languages suggests an Arab provenance. The plant&amp;rsquo;s English name, &amp;ldquo;buckwheat&amp;rdquo;, came from the Dutch word for &amp;ldquo;beech&amp;rdquo; (&lt;em>boec&lt;/em>) and wheat, because it can be used in food, like wheat.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-3/20230520_131249.jpg"
alt="buckwheat soba"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>100% buckwheat &lt;em>soba&lt;/em> noodles made with caramel buckwheat malt, &lt;em>bonito&lt;/em>, London Tropics liquid yeast, and a little sourdough starter; cooked in &lt;em>kombu dashi&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>What seems certain, though, is that buckwheat has been a traditional food around the world, particularly in regions with short growing seasons and poor soil. Eastern Europeans eat a porridge of toasted buckwheat groats (&lt;em>kasha&lt;/em>). In the mountainous valley of Lombardy, Italy, a traditional winter dish is &lt;em>pizzoccheri&lt;/em>, basically short buckwheat pasta tossed with butter, cabbage, cheese, garlic, and sage &amp;ndash; a poor &amp;ldquo;peasant&amp;rdquo; tradition.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Buckwheat has a rich history in the United States as well, unlike other ancient grains. It was common during the Colonial era, but began to decline in popularity after the Civil War ended.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="malted-buckwheat">Malted buckwheat&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>I had the good fortune of experimenting with some caramel buckwheat malt from &lt;a href="https://grousemalthouse.com/">Grouse Malt House&lt;/a>, a dedicated gluten-free craft malthouse in Wellington, Colorado. (I was not looking for gluten-free alternatives &lt;em>per se&lt;/em>, but rather malts made from uncommon grains. Grouse has been crafting a ton of those since ~2013.)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The dark, triangular-shaped hulls covering the buckwheat seeds are left on, to help brewers lauter/filter more easily. The hull is very tough, but is edible when ground and provides a good source of fiber. Even after soaking and boiling, though, unhulled buckwheat is too chewy and too earthy for most people&amp;rsquo;s palates.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-3/20230522_200750.jpg"
alt="Grouse BK1060 caramel buckwheat malt"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Caramel buckwheat malt (BK1060), from Grouse Malt House (Wellington, Colorado).&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>This malt, out of the box, smelled like a forest right after a rain.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Buckwheat can be milled with or without the hull. The traditional method is milling with the hulls. And yes, some millers even add extra hulls. Flour ground from unhulled buckwheat will be greyish, with tiny black specks &amp;ndash; it looks darker and tastes a tad stronger than flour made from hulled buckwheat (groats).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>When freshly ground, this caramel buckwheat malt has an unmistakable earthy aroma &amp;ndash; it creates a woodsy vibe that&amp;rsquo;s bold but not overly aggressive, evoking mental imagery of a deep, verdant forest. There&amp;rsquo;s also a little sunflower seed-like nutty aroma. It tastes predominantly earthy &amp;ndash; like unmalted buckwheat or yellow split peas &amp;ndash; with a hint of malty sweetness. Just how I like my buckwheat, despite the lack of a quintessential &amp;ldquo;caramel&amp;rdquo; malt vibe.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-3/20230522_201317.jpg"
alt="Grouse BK1060 caramel buckwheat malt"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Freshly ground caramel buckwheat malt (BK1060), from Grouse Malt House. Listed color value is 3-6 SRM.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Many Westerners don&amp;rsquo;t like that robust flavor of unhulled buckwheat. So there&amp;rsquo;s a large market for buckwheat flour &lt;em>sans&lt;/em> the hulls.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I know pretty well how buckwheat performs and tastes in food, but in beer? I&amp;rsquo;m not so sure. Enzymatic activities are &lt;a href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/228618138_The_Impact_of_Kilning_on_Enzymatic_Activity_of_Buckwheat_Malt">found&lt;/a> to be low in pale buckwheat malt. I would probably agree with what &lt;a href="https://www.homebrewtalk.com/threads/buckwheat-questions.449416/#post-5789674">this brewer&lt;/a> said about buckwheat:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>I suspect that you will be disappointed with the flavor and diastatic power of pale-malt buckwheat, though. If my experience with Colorado Malting Company&amp;rsquo;s buckwheat malt is any indicator, about the only way to coax any flavor out of it is to make crystal malt; but even that doesn&amp;rsquo;t do much, considering very little saccharification takes place during the crystal-making process so you don&amp;rsquo;t get much in the way of caramelized sugars. The only use I have for buckwheat in my beers is unmalted as an adjunct to improve head retention (the malted stuff doesn&amp;rsquo;t do as well in that regard due to changes in protein contents), or else roasted really dark, as a stand-in for Briess &amp;ldquo;Midnight Wheat&amp;rdquo; to impart a smooth roast character to darker beers.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Which is why I picked &amp;ldquo;caramel&amp;rdquo; buckwheat malt, not the other two buckwheat options (BK1001 pale and BK1100 roasted) offered by Grouse.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Caramel malt is typically made from &amp;ldquo;green malt&amp;rdquo; (wet germinated malt) or rehydrated base malt, mashed at 140-160°F so that the amylase in each individual grain kernel degrades the starch within into simple sugars, and subsequently dried out at &amp;gt;=170°F, which causes the sugars inside the malt to crystallize. It also causes the sugars and nitrogen-based compounds (mostly amino acids and proteins) to combine to form melanoidins. The major variable in the process is the kilning temperature, which determines the depth of the color and the degree of caramelization. The higher the drying temperature, the darker the color will be.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>During roasting, most (if not all) of the enzymes in the malt become denatured, and many of the sugars in the malt become caramelized and thus unfermentable, which is why caramel malt is usually used (like an adjunct) to add sweetness and body to the finished beer, instead of as a base malt.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="buckwheat-mash">Buckwheat mash&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>In &amp;ldquo;caramel&amp;rdquo; malts made from common grains like barley and wheat, the starch is already gelatinized and saccharified in the core. Malted buckwheat gelatinizes at a temperature that is higher than that at which the amylase becomes denatured. To get any significant fermentables out of buckwheat, a decoction mash or exogenous enzymes may be necessary. Andrew Lavery has some &lt;a href="https://glutenfreehomebrewing.com/lavery_brewing_tutorial.php">good info&lt;/a> on mashing gluten-free grains.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Total dry malts: 80g&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>%&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>pale barley malt (Genie - Gallatin Valley Malt)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>50%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>40g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>caramel buckwheat malt (Grouse Malt House)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>50%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>40g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>water&lt;/td>
&lt;td>125%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Total: 180g&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I mixed everything together and did a triple-decoction mash starting at 95°F:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>30 minutes at 95°F&lt;/li>
&lt;li>1 hour at ~113°F&lt;/li>
&lt;li>1 hour at ~130°F (decocted 1/3 at the end; boiled for 5 minutes)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>3 hours at ~150°F (decocted 1/3 at the end; and boiled for 5 minutes)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>1 hour at ~160°F (decocted 1/3 at the end; boiled for 5 minutes)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>1 hour at ~170°F&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>The buckwheat malt soaks up water like a sponge, so this mash turned out very thick. It smelled mildly sweet and smoky, reminiscent of toasted sesame seeds. Not at all what you&amp;rsquo;d expect with a typical &amp;ldquo;caramel&amp;rdquo; malt made from barley or wheat.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>After saccharification, the mash tasted sweet-ish and boldly buckwheaty.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="buckwheat-barm">Buckwheat barm&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>A lot of people consider the flavor of buckwheat to be in the same general category as rye, but far more rustic, earthy, and flavorful than any of the routinely used grains. Part of that character derives from buckwheat&amp;rsquo;s caprylic acid content. Caprylic acid (octanoic acid) is a medium-chain fatty acid that is naturally found in palm oil, coconut oil, and milk. It&amp;rsquo;s a part of medium-chain triglyceride (MCT) products, and believed to have potent antibacterial, antifungal, and anti-inflammatory properties. FYI, &lt;em>capr&lt;/em>- comes from Latin &lt;em>capra&lt;/em>, meaning &amp;ldquo;goat&amp;rdquo;; a lot of people say buckwheat adds a load of &amp;ldquo;goaty&amp;rdquo; flavor, which I disagree with.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-3/20230522_205356.jpg"
alt="Buckwheat mash, before fermentation"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>50% buckwheat 50% barley mash, before fermentation.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>One great thing about some &amp;ldquo;off&amp;rdquo;-tasting fatty acids is that they provide appealing aromas after &lt;em>Brettanomyces&lt;/em> combines them with a molecule of ethanol to form an ester. Buckwheat has been &lt;a href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/228761224_Processing_of_a_Top_Fermented_Beer_Brewed_from_100_Buckwheat_Malt_with_Sensory_and_Analytical_Characterisation">researched&lt;/a> for its possible caprylic acid contribution to &lt;em>Brettanomyces&lt;/em> fermentation, during which the Brett might convert these fatty acid precursors to create ethyl caprylate, an ester often described as sweet, waxy, floral, fruity, pineapple, and wine.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Stage 1: Kolnasāta&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>%&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>saccharified mash&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>180g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Kolnasāta liquid yeast (Escarpment Labs)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>0.5%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Total: 181g&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I added 1g of liquid &lt;a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20220925144154/https://escarpmentlabs.com/products/the-kveik-ring-kolnasata">Kolnasāta&lt;/a>, a continental European farmhouse ale yeast sourced from Bērzpils, Latvia by Escarpment Labs.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-3/20230522_105944.jpg"
alt="Kolnasāta from Escarpment Labs"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Kolnasāta liquid yeast from Escarpment Labs (Guelph, Ontario)&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Kolnasāta is traditionally used to &lt;a href="https://www.kulinaraismantojums.lv/en/biedri/home-producers/production-of-home-brewed-beer-kolnasata/">brew beers at home in Latgale&lt;/a> (aka. the land of blue lakes), a historical region in eastern Latvia. The brewing usually takes place in wooden tuns, and calls for locally-grown barley malt that&amp;rsquo;s dried in a smoke sauna.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This yeast is expected to produce &amp;ldquo;ample doses of pineapple esters along with medium attenuation and flocculation.&amp;rdquo; I thought this profile would pair well with the other yeasts I was going to add to the barm later on.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Escarpment&amp;rsquo;s recommended temperature range for Kolnasāta is 68-86°F, so I let the inoculated mash (aka. barm) ferment, loosely covered, at 80-84°F for 12 hours. The barm began to show signs of fermentation and exude a subtle fruity aroma like peach and pineapple.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Stage 2: London Tropics&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>%&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>stage 1 barm&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>181g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>London Tropics (Berkeley Yeast)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>0.5%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>0.9g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Total: 181.9g&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Next, I added 0.9g of London Tropics from Berkeley Yeast. This London ale yeast-derived thiolized strain produced a POG bomb in a &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/byb-5-1/">previous experiment&lt;/a>, and I&amp;rsquo;d like to tone down the thiol level this time to see how the final bread might turn out.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-1/20230429_140316.jpg"
alt="London Tropics from Berkeley Yeast"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>London Tropics liquid yeast from Berkeley Yeast (Oakland, California)&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Berkeley&amp;rsquo;s recommended temperature range for London Tropics is 64-72°F. I let the barm ferment at 66-70°F for 24 hours. By the end, the thick mash had nearly risen by 50%-70% and felt fluffy. It smelled much more fruity, pleasantly balanced between guava and pineapple.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Stage 3: Brettanomyces&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I intended to add 2g of &lt;em>Brettanomyces bruxellensis&lt;/em>. Due to a squirting accident with the homebrew pouch, I ended up adding 6g of the liquid yeast. The 6% inoculation rate was not intentional, but it is what it is.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>%&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>stage 2 barm&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>181.9g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Suburban Brett (Imperial Yeast)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>3.3%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>6g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Total: 187.9g&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I let this barm sit in my fermentation fridge (set to ~45°F) for 4 days. The barm puffed up like my Italian &lt;em>lievito madre&lt;/em>, and developed a more complex aroma that was very pleasing, but hard to put into words.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="buckwheat-soaker">Buckwheat soaker&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>I thought another way to get the best flavor out of buckwheat is to cold-soak it for 12+ hours. Let hydrolysis do all the work.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>%&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>caramel buckwheat malt (Grouse Malt House)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>92.9%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>260g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>golden flax seeds, whole&lt;/td>
&lt;td>7.1%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>20g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>water (room temperature)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>120%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>336g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sea salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2.8g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Total: 618.8g&lt;/p>
&lt;p>After mixing everything together, I let the stiff paste rest, covered, at room temperature for 2 hours; then I moved it into the fridge (~38°F) and left it there until needed.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-3/20230522_223804.jpg"
alt="Buckwheat soaker"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Caramel buckwheat malt soaker, with golden flax seeds and sea salt.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;h4 id="final-dough">Final dough&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>Total flours: 300g (100%)&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>%&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>einkorn flour, 100% extraction&lt;/td>
&lt;td>65%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>195g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Asturian spelt flour, 100% extraction&lt;/td>
&lt;td>20%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>60g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Ethiopian Blue Tinge emmer flour, 100% extraction&lt;/td>
&lt;td>15%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>45g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>water (room temperature)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>73.3%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>220g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>buckwheat soaker&lt;/td>
&lt;td>206.3%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>618.8g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>buckwheat barm&lt;/td>
&lt;td>62.7%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>187.9g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sea salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>3g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Total: 1,329.7g (100% extraction = whole grain)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I mixed all ingredients together into a supple and sticky dough.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>bulk fermentation: 2 hours at ~70°F (the dough started to ferment so fast that I had to slow it down by chilling it) + 14 hours at ~45°F&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>final proof: 3 hours at ~70°F&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>bake: 45 minutes in total; 10 minutes at 400°F and 35 minutes at 350°F.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>I was delightfully surprised by how much the bread rose during fermentation and baking.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-3/20230524_160701.jpg"
alt="Buckwheat bread sliced"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>Buchweizenbrot&lt;/em> (German-style buckwheat bread), freshly sliced.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The bread had a pleasant fruity fragrance, far less overpowering than in my &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/byb-5-1/">first experiment&lt;/a>. I detected some tantalizing notes of pineapple with a hint of lemon. The subtle tropical complexity and breezy tiki vibe complemented the toasty, earthy aroma of buckwheat quite nicely.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Flavor-wise, it was predominantly earthy buckwheat (reminding me of toasted black sesame seeds), with a charming malty character and mildly fruity undertone. I liked it, a lot. While biting into it, I pictured myself in a hammock swaying on a sun-soaked island in the Black Sea.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-3/20230524_161334.jpg"
alt="Buckwheat bread sliced"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>Buchweizenbrot&lt;/em> (German-style buckwheat bread), crumbshot.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>If you grew up poor like me and got used to eating &amp;ldquo;peasant food&amp;rdquo; like &lt;em>galettes de sarrasin&lt;/em>, &lt;em>kissel&lt;/em>, &lt;em>inaka soba&lt;/em>, etc., then you&amp;rsquo;ll most likely find the deep and earthy flavor of unhulled buckwheat satisfying and nourishing. Otherwise, it&amp;rsquo;s probably an acquired taste.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I guess quartering thiol levels in this bread worked out well. Once again, more isn&amp;rsquo;t (always) better. It&amp;rsquo;s all about understanding what you want to achieve and how your yeast will behave. Recipes are very overrated.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-3/20230524_160927.jpg"
alt="Buckwheat bread sliced"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>Buchweizenbrot&lt;/em> (German-style buckwheat bread)&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>🍻🍻🍻🍻&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Special thanks to Richard Preiss (&lt;a href="https://escarpmentlabs.com/">Escarpment Labs&lt;/a>) for offering me the opportunity to experiment with unique yeasts.&lt;/p></content></item></channel></rss>