<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>warthog on HERESY LEVAIN</title><link>/tags/warthog/</link><description>Latest experiments in warthog from HERESY LEVAIN</description><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2023 HERESY LEVAIN 🍞 CC BY-NC-SA 4.0</copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 31 Aug 2020 22:42:43 -0500</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/warthog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Orange Sunshine</title><link>/posts/orange-sunshine/</link><pubDate>Mon, 31 Aug 2020 22:42:43 -0500</pubDate><guid>/posts/orange-sunshine/</guid><description>A seedelicious bread made with 100% Warthog whole wheat flour and a bucket of orange juice.</description><content>&lt;p>The first time I ate homemade bread was in 2011 in Kansas City, when I was backpacking across the US. I had no idea that bread was something you could make at home. Prior to that, my experience with bread had been exclusively limited to the typical white mush served at school cafeterias. It was so disgustingly bland, empty, and unfulfilling &amp;ndash; not to mention it was also emblematic of everything that was wrong with America &amp;ndash; that I developed a sort of White Bread PTSD and swore I&amp;rsquo;d never eat another slice of bread after college.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Funny how the Covid lockdown has inspired/forced a lot of people to bake breads at home &amp;ndash; and even sell their homemade breads on Etsy. It has forced me to pay more attention to where I source my food from and whether they will always be available.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A number of artisan-ish bakeries across the country are selling their bread flours nicely packaged in eco-friendly brown paper bags at &amp;ldquo;pandemic special&amp;rdquo; prices, to make up for their lost business &amp;amp; revenue due to the shutdown and retain customer relationships.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Last month, King Arthur Flour rebranded itself to King Arthur Baking Company. The flour company was founded in 1790, and is America&amp;rsquo;s first flour company. They have re-aligned the company to reflect their mission &amp;ndash; &amp;ldquo;bake joy.&amp;rdquo; King Arthur is now a lifestyle company, like Lululemon, Peloton and Chipotle. I don&amp;rsquo;t buy King Arthur&amp;rsquo;s flours or care for its recipes, but I do find that rebranding &amp;ndash; particularly the timing &amp;ndash; interesting.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Literally every state has a &amp;ldquo;local&amp;rdquo; flagship producer. IL has Janie&amp;rsquo;s. NY has Farmer Ground Flour. OR has Camas Country Mill. NC has Carolina Ground. TX has Barton Springs Mill. AZ has Hayden Flour Mills. Who is MO&amp;rsquo;s local artisan flagship producer?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If I were going to bring coastal friends &amp;ldquo;Missouri-grown&amp;rdquo; non-touristy gifts, I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t know what to get &amp;ndash; other than t-ravs, provel, and maybe some local booze. I know the MO Department of Agriculture has a program called Missouri Grown, but the local goodies gift box it has put together is a joke.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Missouri always feels like a giant black hole of locally grown grains. Sure, Missouri grows a ton of soybeans, corn and soft wheat. I mean, it&amp;rsquo;s a Corn Belt state. But most of them are exported via the Mississippi River, and the rest processed into animal feed, industrial inputs, and biofuels. Only a tiny percentage stays local. The US Soybean Export Council and American Soybean Association (which has a political action committee called SoyPAC) are both headquartered in St. Louis (STL). Monsanto was founded in STL and headquartered here for over 100 years, and its new parent, Bayer AG, still established its North American HQ here. The world&amp;rsquo;s biggest grain traders &amp;ndash; Archer Daniel Midland (ADM), Bunge, and Cargill &amp;ndash; all have major operations in STL as well. (These 3, along with Louis Dreyfus, control ~90% of global grain trade and have enormous power over grain prices.) Evidently, their presence here impacts local farmers and agri-food system.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Missouri certainly doesn&amp;rsquo;t have a shortage of local producers, and the flagship local product with (inter)national recognition doesn&amp;rsquo;t have to be bread wheat &amp;ndash; South Carolina has done exceptionally well with heirloom rice renaissance, for example.&lt;/p>
&lt;div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
&lt;iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/cgpgwBXKYHI" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video">&lt;/iframe>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>I had the good fortune of living a stone&amp;rsquo;s throw away from Anson Mills in Charleston for a number of years, and got to witness its metamorphosis to the Palmetto State&amp;rsquo;s flagship artisan producer/purveyor, an explosive commercial success with international fame. Tourists from all over the world flock to Charleston, SC to visit Anson Mills and experience the antebellum culinary past. It has become a culinary tourist destination in and of itself. More incredibly, the entrepreneurs behind Anson Mills are not even SC natives. What&amp;rsquo;s the MO equivalent of Anson Mills or Carolina Gold rice, or of even San Francisco&amp;rsquo;s Tartine? My point is, MO local producers have a branding/PR problem. Tom Cruise is a globally recognizable brand. Janie&amp;rsquo;s of Illinois is a national brand. What&amp;rsquo;s the most recognizable MO brand? The only local product brand (even remotely) familiar to people from out of state or overseas might be Hammons Black Walnuts, which does have a D2C web store, but its branding and packaging leave a lot to be desired.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Kansas City (the Wheat Belt&amp;rsquo;s buckle) seems rife for a &amp;ldquo;single-origin wheat&amp;rdquo; renaissance that will help rebuild &lt;a href="https://thecounter.org/rural-kansas-depopulation-commodity-agriculture/">local economy&lt;/a> and reclaim the Wheat State&amp;rsquo;s agricultural heritage. In the late 19th and early 20th centuries, Kansas City had dozens of flour mills. Grain magnate Frank A. Theis (namesake of Theis Park) wrote in a 1938 article in The Kansas City Star, &amp;ldquo;No other industry, directly or indirectly, has been more closely identified with the growth of Kansas City.&amp;rdquo; In South Carolina and North Carolina, the cultivation of revival grains is a rapidly expanding enterprise.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I desperately wanted to find a Missouri-grown bread wheat. I went on a relentless hunt for this elusive prize, with little success. All neighboring states grow bread wheats, why not Missouri? My curiosity took me down a rabbit hole&amp;hellip; What started out as a seemingly trivial question turned into a herculean quest and then Mission Impossible.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Obviously, most people buy flours, not grains. So flour was where I started.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A bearded guitarist and baker used to sell his sourdough breads at farmers' markets and some restaurants in STL. One of his breads was &lt;em>pan bigio&lt;/em>, an Italian country loaf made with &amp;ldquo;local Cape Girardeau whole wheat flour.&amp;rdquo; I tried to find out which Cape Girardeau farm/mill that was (since I wasn&amp;rsquo;t aware there even was one), but he shut down his operations in March and went dark.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I called up the few artisan-ish bakeries in STL that pride themselves on using &amp;ldquo;locally grown and milled wheat&amp;rdquo; to ask what flours they use and where they source them from. Not only did they refuse to tell me anything, but also they got very confused and in some cases suspicious&amp;hellip; as if I had broken an unspoken cultural taboo. One of the nicer bakers directed me to the proverbial purveyors of &amp;ldquo;unique local organic artisanal products,&amp;rdquo; aka. specialty retailers that label everything with 10+ &lt;em>haute&lt;/em> adjectives and lists everything 1,000% higher than MSRP. Well, that was a very curious experience. I&amp;rsquo;m not sure whether these bakeries 1) genuinely use local ingredients as much as they claim, 2) severely lack business acumen to begin with, or 3) are simply too small-minded and uncreative.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I went back to the drawing board and started doing some research, when I found out that the band, from Delaware, Maryland, northern Virginia and southern Illinois and through Missouri to the eastern part of Kansas, is known for growing soft winter wheat. In fact, whatever wheat ends up flourishing on a commercially viable scale in Missouri is usually soft winter wheat and mostly exported, although Mizzou Cooperative Extension&amp;rsquo;s hard winter wheat trials in several locations around the state are successful. Most of the commercial bakeries here source their bread flours by truckloads from western Kansas.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>After a few days of hopeless internet research, I was on the verge of giving up. Serendipitously, a couple of small farms in central/western MO came across my radar &amp;ndash; they grow organic hard red winter wheat!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>So this is how I found 180 Farms in Sweet Springs, MO. I called up Greg Guier earlier last week week, to inquire about his organic wheat berries. Holy shit, Greg is one of the nicest and most down-to-earth people I&amp;rsquo;ve ever talked to. Some Midwesterners are just frighteningly friendly! He told me this year&amp;rsquo;s Warthog Red, a hard red winter wheat, was still being harvested and would be ready in a few days, and last year&amp;rsquo;s Darby White, a hard white winter wheat, was readily available. He said he delivers only to Kansas City, because he tried for years to set up delivery arrangements in STL but couldn&amp;rsquo;t get anyone interested.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I was going camping in the Ozarks this weekend anyway, so I took a detour and stopped by Greg&amp;rsquo;s farm to scoop up some freshly harvested Warthog wheat berries. (Heck, even swung by the Overland Park Farmer&amp;rsquo;s Market and procured some heritage Meishan pork from Odd Bird Farm in Weston, MO.) Turns out, that was a great decision.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>Warthog is a modern HRWW with a moderate protein content (10%-11%). I remember Warthog was hugely popular at the NYC Greenmarket a few years ago (thanks to GrowNYC Grains, a distributor/hub that promotes and sells local grains in the Northeast). Farmer-miller Thor Oechsner planted Warthog for the first time in 2010, loved it, and grew to become the largest Warthog producer in the Northeast. Then Janie&amp;rsquo;s Mill picked it up, too.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I did read about Warthog&amp;rsquo;s relatively low protein level for a HRWW, and kept that in mind while working with the flour. In fact, Oechsner recommended blending Warthog with a spring wheat flour to boost protein content while letting Warthog&amp;rsquo;s special flavor shine through.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Nah. I&amp;rsquo;m gonna go Warthog all the way through.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/orange-sunshine/202008311430.jpg"
alt="Orange Sunshine"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>First step: mill the Warthog wheat berries several times to get the finest grind possible.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>whole wheat flour (Warthog - 180 Farms, MO)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>rye levain&lt;/td>
&lt;td>40%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>water&lt;/td>
&lt;td>42%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>fresh orange juice&lt;/td>
&lt;td>42%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>diastatic barley malt powder&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>flaxseeds, freshly ground&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>soaker&lt;/td>
&lt;td>33%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>seed mix (for coating)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>The science behind incorporating orange juice and diastatic malt is explained in a later &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/desert-dynamo/">post&lt;/a>. TL;DR: Diastatic malt increases the conversion of starches to sugar, boosting the caramelization of the crust. Ascorbic acid (vitamin C) in orange juice tightens the gluten network and gives the bread a better rise.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Soaker:&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>quinoa&lt;/td>
&lt;td>25%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sunflower seeds&lt;/td>
&lt;td>25%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>whole flax seeds&lt;/td>
&lt;td>25%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>black sesame seeds&lt;/td>
&lt;td>25%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>orange juice&lt;/td>
&lt;td>150%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>You know my usual M.O.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/orange-sunshine/202008311432.jpg"
alt="Orange Sunshine"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The crumb doesn&amp;rsquo;t look too bad. Excuse my cutting.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/orange-sunshine/202008311437.jpg"
alt="Orange Sunshine"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Pretty darn tender and juicy.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/orange-sunshine/202008311438.jpg"
alt="Orange Sunshine"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Yum, the flavor is superb.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/orange-sunshine/202008311455.jpg"
alt="Orange Sunshine"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Orange Sunshine, a seedelicious bread made with 100% Warthog whole wheat flour and a bucket of orange juice.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>A great backpacking bread.&lt;/p></content></item></channel></rss>