<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>brown rice on HERESY LEVAIN</title><link>/tags/brown-rice/</link><description>Latest experiments in brown rice from HERESY LEVAIN</description><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2023 HERESY LEVAIN 🍞 CC BY-NC-SA 4.0</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 29 Jan 2023 23:55:42 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/brown-rice/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Ricemonger</title><link>/posts/ricemonger/</link><pubDate>Sun, 29 Jan 2023 23:55:42 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/ricemonger/</guid><description>When life gives you brown rice, make yourself a marvelous loaf of double-fermented brown rice bread.</description><content>&lt;p>I love the nighttime. The early-risers have already put in their time. Now the day is mine. It&amp;rsquo;s dark. My mind can percolate, like steam through the coffee grounds in a Moka pot. There&amp;rsquo;s a reason why most creative work is done at night. When e-mails, texts, discords, etc. quiet down. When people drink and smoke and sleepwalk in front of the TV&amp;hellip;that&amp;rsquo;s when I come alive.&lt;/p>
&lt;div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
&lt;iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/8wvtXp84VkQ" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video">&lt;/iframe>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>I had an atrocious dream on Saturday night: I was back in elementary school and my class went on a long camping trip. I was assigned the top level of a triple bunk bed. Every night I almost had to climb up to the ceiling to get to my bed. And the bunk bed wobbled and squeaked every time I was on it. Everyone was mocking me &amp;ndash; they said it was all because my family was the poorest. I was stunned and speechless, because that was something I had never realized before. Everyone cheated to get ahead. And everyone successful was doing it. And I was not, I was a schmuck, I was not going to make it&amp;hellip;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I woke up feeling indignant. I&amp;rsquo;m indignant like that oftentimes. I guess that&amp;rsquo;s a result of growing up poor IRL and feeling powerless. In order to have power, you must have position. The way most people get that is via the organizational hierarchy, where you have to get along and kiss a$$ to move up the food chain. All that bollocks about doing what you love and the money following&amp;hellip;is just bollocks. Making money is a skill in and of itself. And none of my family had it. Salesmanship isn&amp;rsquo;t in my genes. Ultimately, to succeed you need to be a salesman, to foist things upon people. I don&amp;rsquo;t want to fake it to make it, I don&amp;rsquo;t want to justify my actions by saying it&amp;rsquo;s a &amp;ldquo;dog eat dog&amp;rdquo; world, or I&amp;rsquo;m just trying to survive. But it took me a decade and a ton of psychotherapy to both learn how to get along enough to make money and to understand and own who I am.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>One of my friends just lost his wife to cancer last week, at age 35. I always wonder what people think about in their last moments. A &lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/lifeandstyle/2012/feb/01/top-five-regrets-of-the-dying">top regret of dying&lt;/a> is reportedly: &amp;ldquo;I wish I&amp;rsquo;d had the courage to live a life true to myself, not the life others expected of me.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Life is short. No doubt.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I almost died in a head-on car crash just before Covid. During my dark days in the hospital, I kept pondering what might happen if I never woke up again&amp;hellip;. Would I be satisfied and happy with the life I&amp;rsquo;d lived so far? No, I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t. There are still so many things I want to do, and so many places I want to go. I want to live.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It was a fleeting moment. And moments never come back. They can change your life, they can mark you for it, but they never return as they were. I recovered, moved on, and made new moments happen. Because the best is always yet to come.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>You&amp;rsquo;ve never lived until you&amp;rsquo;ve almost died. For those who have fought for it, life has a flavor the protected shall never know.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Guy de Maupassant&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>One thing for sure: The experience has made me a lot stronger.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It also made me think about many other things, including our food systems. When the electrical grid goes down or when fuel supplies are interrupted, a resilient food system should be able to recover quickly &amp;ndash; in a way that ensures a sufficient supply of acceptable and accessible food for all. But that is evidently not what most of us have experienced since the start of Covid.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We have a loooong way to go towards building a truly robust, flexible food system.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/ricemonger/202301291120.jpg"
alt="Ricemonger brown rice bread"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>We don&amp;rsquo;t know what may or may not be in store tomorrow. But when life gives me brown rice, I&amp;rsquo;m gonna make myself a bloody glorious loaf of brown rice bread &amp;ndash; twice fermented to coax every particle of flavor out of the rice kernel.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The formula:&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>whole [sprouted] brown rice flour (Braggadocio Basmati - McKaskle Family Farm, MO)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>85%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>whole mung bean flour (backyard)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>whole [roasted] &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->black-eyed pea&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --> flour (Richard&amp;rsquo;s farm, MO)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>water&lt;/td>
&lt;td>150%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sourdough discard&lt;/td>
&lt;td>30%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>fenugreek seeds, crushed&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sea salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Sprouting the brown rice is optional. I sprouted mine. White rice is an okay substitute.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Toast black-eyed peas in a 350°F oven for about 10 minutes, until slightly brown and aromatic, to take off the raw bean flavor.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Grind the rice and legumes, in a grain mill or a coffee grinder. The resulting flours don&amp;rsquo;t have to be super-fine. I didn&amp;rsquo;t bolt or sift them.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Boil 1/2 of the water, and scald 1/3 of the brown rice flour in it. Stir rigorously to make sure every rice particle is hydrated. Let the scald sit for ~30 mins and cool off to room temperature.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Add the rest of the ingredients. Mix until lump-free and thoroughly combined. It should be thicker than a pancake batter.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>(Alternatively, soak all of the rice and legumes in water overnight, and then grind them wet in a high-speed blender into a smooth batter. Gently simmer 1/3 of the batter until gelatinized. Let it cool off, before combining with the rest of the batter, sourdough, etc.)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Cover and let the mixture ferment at ~70°F for 12 hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>When it has bubbled up and risen by ~50%, stir it back down. It should smell moderately sour. Ferment a second time at ~70°F for 2 hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>When the batter has grown back by ~50% in volume, it&amp;rsquo;s time to cook it. I steamed mine in a Pyrex bowl in an Instant Pot for 25 mins. You can bake it in the oven, of course. I prefer to steam rice bread so it rises better and turns out fluffier.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/ricemonger/202301291121.jpg"
alt="Ricemonger brown rice bread"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>This brown rice bread has a rather interesting flavor and texture. It tastes bland when you first put it in your month, but in a few seconds flavors start to explode everywhere. The more you chew, the more flavorful it gets. It&amp;rsquo;s like opening a large Russian &lt;em>matryoshka&lt;/em> nesting doll. The taste gets more and more powerful with each bite.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>There&amp;rsquo;s a very pleasant tang that co-exists majestically with the herbaceous and nutty flavor of fenugreek.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The crumb texture is endearingly soft and springy.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Best enjoyed warm.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/ricemonger/202301291124.jpg"
alt="Ricemonger brown rice bread"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>I like it sliced thin and topped with goat cheese and honey. It also sops up curry excellently.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I would make this again &amp;ndash; at a higher hydration.&lt;/p>
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>Carolus Linnaeus (1707–1778), a Swedish botanist and zoologist who invented the biological binomial nomenclature system still used today, was a great benefactor of mankind. Now we know that &lt;em>Vigna unguiculata&lt;/em> is not the same as green peas, even though they share a common name. This particular pea was brought to the Americas by enslaved Africans, whose cultivation of it caught the eyes of the slaveholders. Cowpeas, as they are also known, were described by Thomas Jefferson in 1798 as a vegetable that &amp;ldquo;is very productive [and an] excellent food for man and beast.&amp;rdquo;&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/section></content></item></channel></rss>