<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>funky on HERESY LEVAIN</title><link>/tags/funky/</link><description>Latest experiments in funky from HERESY LEVAIN</description><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2023 HERESY LEVAIN 🍞 CC BY-NC-SA 4.0</copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 19 Oct 2020 20:28:06 -0600</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/funky/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Dr. Funkenstein</title><link>/posts/dr-funkenstein/</link><pubDate>Mon, 19 Oct 2020 20:28:06 -0600</pubDate><guid>/posts/dr-funkenstein/</guid><description>A zero-waste science experiment to salvage a batch of unbeloved Karl92 wheat, through a long fermendation. It metamorphosed into a whole wheat alveolate ecstasy that you never knew existed.</description><content>&lt;p>A few weeks ago, I got some organic Karl92 wheat from Richard, grown by a local farmer.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Karl92 is a modern high-quality HRWW variety, selected from &amp;ldquo;Karl&amp;rdquo; by R. G. Sears, leader of the Manhattan wheat program from 1982 to 2000. Karl92 has higher yield and better disease resistance than the OG variety. Protein content is ~12%.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This lot of Karl92 got invaded by wild onions while still growing in the fields, and the wheat berries picked up an oniony aroma. I thought naturally onion-scented wheat was quite interesting &amp;ndash; I wondered if it would be a great flour for a herbaceous bread. There&amp;rsquo;s a niche market for everything. If I were to market this batch of Karl92, I would label them &amp;ldquo;Funkadelic Ecstasy organic whole wheat: kissed by wild onions, ingrained with Mother Earth&amp;rsquo;s inherent magic.&amp;rdquo; Coastal foodies and food snobs would go crazy about it. No doubt. FWIW, there&amp;rsquo;s a toy company that sells squishy onions &amp;ndash; stress balls in the shape and color of a red onion and, when you squish them, they actually release onion scents to encourage further stress relief.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I also got a batch of Karl92 whole wheat flour that was milled a while ago and starting to smell musty. I know, 99% of people would just toss it in the trash. But the zero-waster in me was curious whether this batch of flour could be &lt;a href="https://ift.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1111/1541-4337.12481">salvaged through fermentation&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>So I dumped the flour (1,722g) on a BBQ grill, and let it smoke over a bunch of corn husks for a few hours. The smelly flour picked up a nutty, endearing, almost bacon-y aroma. Then I sifted the smoked flour twice: got 237g coarse bran (14%) out the first time, and 220g middlings (13%) the second time, leaving 1,265g flour (73% extraction).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I divided the 237g coarse bran into&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>200g: for levain&lt;/li>
&lt;li>37g: for dusting/coating&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>And thus began my cosmic adventure into the funky world of Karl92.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="levain-425g">Levain: 425g&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>2 builds, in 24h:&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>coarse bran&lt;/td>
&lt;td>200g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>boiling water&lt;/td>
&lt;td>200g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>diastatic barley malt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sourdough starter, stiff WW&lt;/td>
&lt;td>20g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Pour boiling water over the coarse bran in a gass bowl. Mix well. Let it sit for a few hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>You can add the malt while the bran soaker has cooled off some, but add the starter only after the bran soaker has cooled off completely to room temperature.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Based on my previous baking experiments and consumption of scientific studies, the most effective way to process the bran and improve its texture is sourdough starter + alpha amylase + xylanase, let sit for 24 hours at 24°C/75°F. (I&amp;rsquo;ve done this many times on oat hull fiber and have achieved good results. I have a friend who&amp;rsquo;s pathologically obsessed with &amp;ldquo;volume eating&amp;rdquo;, e.g., consuming large volumes of food while taking in minimal calories at the same time. Oat fiber is insanely popular among these volume-eaters, because the boatload of fiber in it increases the volume of food while adding zero net carbs or calories.)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Depending on the genotype, dry wheat bran can contain about 50% dietary fiber and 9%-25% starch. Most of that dietary fiber in bran is insoluble fiber (hemicelluloses):&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>arabinoxylans (~55%)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>celluloses (9-12%)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>lignins (3-5%)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>fructans (3-4%)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>β-glucans (2.2-2.6%).&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Most arabinoxylans are water-unextractable, but a smaller part is water-extractable. Cellulose is insoluble and resistant to many microorganisms and enzymes. Celluloses are often associated with lignins and other non-starchy polysaccharides. Together with lignin and other fibers, cellulose forms a lignocellulose, which is highly resistant towards degradation. Fructans and β-glucans are the main components of the soluble fiber.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Xylanase is an enzyme that can degrade or break down the xylans in insoluble fiber and convert them into a simple sugar (xylose), which then can be metabolized by the yeast and lactic acid bacteria. In the end, this makes insoluble fiber less capable of interfering with and diluting the gluten in grains, so the bread won&amp;rsquo;t lose much volume or taste.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Amylase is another enzyme that breaks down starches, polysaccharides, and complex carbohydrates into easier-to-absorb simple sugars.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Diastatic barley malt packs in amylase and some endogenous xylanase, while wheat bran itself also contains &lt;a href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/10.1021/jf800264a">xylanase and laccase&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Grain kernels themselves usually contain a certain amount of endogenous xylanases for re-modeling and expansion of cell walls during normal cell growth and for more drastic cell wall degradation during seed germination. Additionally, grains also contain microbial xylanases from micro-organisms populating the outer grain kernels layers.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Industrial production of xylanases is mostly manufactured via submerged fermentation of lignocellulolytic substrates such as barley husk, corn cobs, hay, wheat bran or straw.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="scalded-soaker-1100g">Scalded soaker: 1,100g&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>Soak the middlings from the second sift in hot water for 24h.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>middlings&lt;/td>
&lt;td>220g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>boiling water (4x bran weight)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>880g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>I usually give the coarse bits a prolonged, unconstrained hydration to completely satisfy their thirst, before I get the final dough going. (I ended up having to retard both the bran levain and the soaker in the fridge after the first 24 hours, due to traveling.)&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="final-dough">Final dough&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>When you incorporate the levain and the scalded soaker into the final dough, you add every part of the grain back. Not one bit is wasted. Therefore, this bread retains its whole-grain integrity.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sifted Karl92 flour&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1,265g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>scalded soaker&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1,100g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>water&lt;/td>
&lt;td>120g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>levain&lt;/td>
&lt;td>425g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>30g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>No autolyse this time. I simply amalgamated everything and left the shaggy mess in the fridge overnight, à‎ la Jim Lahey&amp;rsquo;s no-knead method.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Another reason I didn&amp;rsquo;t feel like working the dough: The gluten in the sifted Karl92 flour had deteriorated to the point where it performed almost like a pastry flour. The dough was very sticky even at such low hydration.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you must calculate the hydration percentage:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>excluding levain: 1,000g/1,485g = 67%&lt;/li>
&lt;li>including levain: 1,210g/1,700g = 71%&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>The next day, I took the dough out of the fridge and gave it a stretch &amp;amp; fold. Time and cool temperatures worked their magic on the dough &amp;ndash; it was coming together on its own without much manual coaxing.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A few hours later, I pulled the dough out again and laminated it with caramelized onions (not drained), &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->wheat berries&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->, and &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->bread spices&lt;sup id="fnref:2">&lt;a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->. I let the dough rest in the cold until bedtime and gave it a coil-fold. Afterwards, I left it undisturbed in the fridge for 72 hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The overall process was basically similar to what I did with the Turkey Red bread, but at a significantly slower pace.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s percentage&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->flour&lt;sup id="fnref:3">&lt;a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">3&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1,485g (1,265g flour + 220g middlings)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>water&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1,000g (880g + 120g)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>67%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>levain&lt;/td>
&lt;td>425g&lt;/td>
&lt;td>29%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>30g&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>onions&lt;/td>
&lt;td>80g&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5.4%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>spices&lt;/td>
&lt;td>20g&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1.3%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>wheat berries&lt;/td>
&lt;td>107g&lt;/td>
&lt;td>7.2%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>I decided to go for a 72h fermentation for a few reasons:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>to &lt;a href="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/pdf/10.1271/bbb.130027">reduce as much mycotoxin&lt;/a> as possible through prolonged lactic acid bacteria fermentation;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>to mask the musty smell/taste via developing a complex web of flavors;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>to see how long the gluten could hold together before it started to break down.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>72+ hours later, I took the dough out of the fridge and pre-shaped it loosely. The dough had risen by ~30% but felt chock full of air. It hadn&amp;rsquo;t become a soup, so I guess the gluten hadn&amp;rsquo;t collapsed. After a 1-hour bench rest, I shaped it tight (using the reserved 37g coarse bran as coating) and let it proof at room temperature until 100% risen. It took about 5 hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/dr-funkenstein/20201016_1413.jpg"
alt="Funky Karl final proof"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Funky Karl going through final proof.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/dr-funkenstein/20201016_1430.jpg"
alt="Funky Karl final proof"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Funky Karl going through final proof: a closer look.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Then I baked it as usual, in the toaster oven. The dough weighed 3,187g (7.08 lbs) before baking.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It turned out a monstrous loaf: It measured about 11&amp;quot;x9&amp;quot;x5&amp;quot; and weighed just under 6 lbs. after cooling.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Hipsters might call this a &lt;em>miche&lt;/em>, a.k.a. the &lt;a href="https://nypost.com/2017/10/03/new-yorkers-are-paying-20-for-a-loaf-of-bread/">fancy&lt;/a> Parisian way of denoting &amp;ldquo;a supersized rustic sourdough bread,&amp;rdquo; which is in fact a French slang for &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href="https://daysontheclaise.blogspot.com/2009/03/la-miche.html">butt-cheek&lt;/a>.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/dr-funkenstein/20201016_1904.jpg"
alt="Funky Karl baked"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Funky Karl making a glorious debut from the oven.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/dr-funkenstein/20201016_1909.jpg"
alt="Funky Karl baked"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The sweet aroma of freshly baked bread wafted through the whole house &amp;ndash; one of my all-time favorite smells. I let the bread sit in a brown paper bag overnight before slicing.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="crumb-reveal">Crumb reveal&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>The bread was a breeze to cut into. The knife came out clean. A very distinctive and pleasant fragrance immediately hit the nose.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/dr-funkenstein/20201017_1259.jpg"
alt="Funky Karl crumbshot"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The crumb turned out much more aerated than in the Turkey Red loaf and had some large holes; it was also much lighter and fluffier, although a bit less moist, than the TR. (High hydration level promotes bigger holes, but the high percentage of whole grain flours works against them.)&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/dr-funkenstein/20201017_1633.jpg"
alt="Funky Karl crumbshot"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>I don&amp;rsquo;t want to sound like a food snob, but I have to confess that the only words I could think of when slicing this bread were &amp;ldquo;alveolate ecstasy.&amp;rdquo; Each slice felt ethereal, almost weightless, on my hand. In any case, this was a great crumb for sandwiches and toasts.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/dr-funkenstein/20201018_1109.jpg"
alt="Funky Karl baked"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Funky Karl, an alveolate ecstasy you never knew existed.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Now, the flavor: I was struck first by the tender, airy texture &amp;ndash; so delicate on my tongue that it felt like eating cottony clouds &amp;ndash; although there was some nice chew, too.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/dr-funkenstein/20201017_1256.jpg"
alt="Funky Karl crumbshot"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/dr-funkenstein/20201017_1300.jpg"
alt="Funky Karl crumbshot"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Funky Karl crumb porn.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Like the Turkey Red loaf, there was little wheat flavor. Maybe there was, but it was easily overshadowed by a prominent combination of sourness and tanginess. I would describe it as noticeably more tangy than sour &amp;ndash; it likely contained a wider spectrum of piquancy than I could articulate &amp;ndash; and I would compare it to a sour rye bread or even a tamarind/lemon juice combination. Call it a &lt;em>pane picante integrale&lt;/em>?&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/dr-funkenstein/20201018_1103.jpg"
alt="Funky Karl crumbshot"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The brisk flavors of caramelized onions (or was it the wild onions looming in the Karl92?) and crushed spices came through and were nearly assertive enough to go &lt;em>mano a mano&lt;/em> with the lush tartness.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The wheat berries had literally melted into the crumb and were content to stay in the background.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/dr-funkenstein/20201018_2149.jpg"
alt="Funky Karl crumbshot"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The crust was thin, crispy, and chewy except for the ears which crunched. It tasted much more flavorful than the crumb, as usual, and added the nuttiness I always enjoy.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>All in all, I think the long, cold fermentation resulted in a fortified crust giving way to richly complex layers of bold, indulgent, sophisticated flavors. Lots of nutty, earthy and sweet overtones followed by a deep tanginess and a trace of pleasing bitterness. I&amp;rsquo;m a &lt;em>huge&lt;/em> fan of zing and heat, and this bread hit the spot!&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/dr-funkenstein/20201018_2151.jpg"
alt="Funky Karl crumbshot"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/dr-funkenstein/20201018_2153.jpg"
alt="Funky Karl crumbshot"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Best part: I didn&amp;rsquo;t smell or taste any mustiness in it no matter how hard I tried, nor did we feel sick at all from eating it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We devoured half of the loaf in 3 days (delicious as is, but even better toasted), and took the rest to a BBQ at the relatives yesterday. They all grew up eating pre-sliced Wonder Bread (or Bunny® Bread, which &amp;ndash; I just learned yesterday &amp;ndash; has been a household name and an &lt;a href="https://orangebeanindiana.com/2020/05/08/thats-what-i-said-the-story-of-bunny-bread/">iconic brand&lt;/a> in the Midwest for decades, no offense) and have vastly different food preferences than me.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/dr-funkenstein/20201019_1300.jpg"
alt="Funky Karl crumbshot"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Everybody loved the texture of the bread; they thought it was almost as soft and fluffy as the premium mediocre Bunny® Original 100% Whole Wheat Bread! Lol. This may sound like an insult to a coastal foodie, but in a Midwestern context it must be interpreted as the highest form of compliment &amp;ndash; because &amp;ldquo;you can&amp;rsquo;t beat the Bunny!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/dr-funkenstein/20201019_1301.jpg"
alt="Funky Karl crumbshot"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/dr-funkenstein/20201019_1303.jpg"
alt="Funky Karl crumbshot"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>However, nobody liked the pungent flavor of this bread. Someone compared it to balsamic vinegar, and someone else said it tasted as sour as Trolli sour gummy worms (&amp;ldquo;for people who can&amp;rsquo;t get enough tanginess in their life&amp;rdquo;). Still, the bread disappeared quickly &amp;ndash; maybe people just got intense carb cravings.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Oh well. That was fun.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Guess I have just found another failproof (and easier) way of making whole wheat &amp;ldquo;clouds,&amp;rdquo; besides the method I accidentally discovered while making &lt;em>panettone integrale&lt;/em>. What I have done with Karl92 over the last couple of weeks &amp;ndash; from smoking the flour to sifting to the 72h fermentation &amp;ndash; is fairly labor-intensive and time-consuming, not something I&amp;rsquo;d do often or use for production. Just a science experiment for my own curiosity.&lt;/p>
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>Spices consisted of dill seeds, caraway seeds, fennel seeds, coriander, fenugreek seeds, anise, black peppercorns, and papaya seeds; all roasted and coarsely ground just before using.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>I soaked a handful of funky Karl92 wheat berries in liquid whey, and let it ferment for a few days. Drained and incorporated the mushy berries (wet weight 107g).&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:3" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>With 220g midds added back, the total amount of flour used directly in the dough stood at 1,485g (~86% extraction).&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/section></content></item></channel></rss>