<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>hard red spring wheat on HERESY LEVAIN</title><link>/tags/hard-red-spring-wheat/</link><description>Latest experiments in hard red spring wheat from HERESY LEVAIN</description><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2023 HERESY LEVAIN 🍞 CC BY-NC-SA 4.0</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 21 Feb 2023 21:25:13 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/hard-red-spring-wheat/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>California Dreamin' #2: Joaquin Oro</title><link>/posts/california-dreamin-2/</link><pubDate>Tue, 21 Feb 2023 21:25:13 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/california-dreamin-2/</guid><description>[California Grain Adventure #2] &lt;em>Pan de San Joaquín&lt;/em>. One 100% wholegrain Joaquin Oro dough, 2 leavens, baked 2 ways. Total hydration cranked up to 134% to push the flour&amp;rsquo;s limits. Both turned out delightfully light and airy; exceptionally soft and chewy.</description><content>&lt;p>&lt;em>This is part 2 of my &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/california-grain-adventure/">California Grain Adventure&lt;/a>. If you missed part 1, catch up &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/california-dreamin-1/">here&lt;/a>.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Stranger, let me warn you now. If ever you start for California with the intention of seeing anything of the State, do that before you enter San Francisco. If you must land in San Francisco first, jump into a taxi, pull down the curtains, drive through the city, breaking every speed law, to &amp;ldquo;Third and Townsend,&amp;rdquo; sit in the station until a train &amp;ndash; some train, any train &amp;ndash; pulls out, and go with it. If in crossing Market Street, you raise that taxi-curtain as much as an inch, believe me, stranger, it&amp;rsquo;s all off; you&amp;rsquo;re lost. You&amp;rsquo;ll never leave San Francisco. Myself, both times I have gone to California, I have vowed to see Yosemite, the big trees, the string of beautiful old missions which dot the state, some of the quaint, languid, semi-tropical towns of the south, some of the brisk, brilliant, bustling towns of the north. But I have never really done it because I saw San Francisco first.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Inez Haynes Irwin, &lt;em>The Californiacs&lt;/em> (1919)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>NYC boasts the best bagels in the world, which New Yorkers attribute to their magical tap water. San Francisco boasts the finest sourdough in the world, which San Franciscans attribute to their special air. The unseen native inhabitants in San Francisco&amp;rsquo;s damp, foggy micro-climate, they claim, create a special &amp;ldquo;microbial terroir&amp;rdquo; that can&amp;rsquo;t be replicated anywhere else.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>And for a San Francisco sourdough to be truly &amp;ldquo;authentic,&amp;rdquo; the local history and mythology go, it has to be born in San Francisco with proper San Franciscan air, not in Oakland, Richmond, or San Jose. (BTW, everyone hates Oakland, except people who actually live there and pay half the rent of what people pay in San Francisco while still basically living in San Francisco.)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>No one has convinced more people about the unique qualities of San Francisco sourdough than Boudin Bakery, which &lt;a href="https://www.foundsf.org/index.php?title=Yeast_to_Wheat:_How_Boudin_Bakery%E2%80%99s_Yeast_Culture_Shaped_San_Francisco%E2%80%99s_Counterculture">claims&lt;/a> to have been selling the same loaf of bread made with The Original San Francisco Sourdough™ for &amp;gt;170 years. According to the Boudin Bakery museum at the ultra-touristy Fisherman&amp;rsquo;s Wharf, the company&amp;rsquo;s mother dough follows an unbroken line back to the Gold Rush in 1849. Louise Boudin even saved the starter from a burning building during the 1906 earthquake. A museum docent will readily inform you the starter is so special and irreplaceable that the Boudin mothership sends its retail stores fresh starter every 23 days. Without it, they emphasize, the sourdough produced at those stores would stop tasting like San Francisco sourdough &amp;ndash; and start tasting like Sacramento or San Diego sourdough, which is absolutely blasphemous.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Also, according to the museum, Boudin&amp;rsquo;s bread owes its special flavor to a particular strain of lactic acid bacteria that thrives &lt;em>only&lt;/em> in San Francisco&amp;rsquo;s climate. Scientists identified it here in 1970, so they named it &lt;em>Lactobacillus sanfranciscensis&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It&amp;rsquo;s a great, great story. Too bad it&amp;rsquo;s not quite true.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Scientists did identify &lt;em>Lactobacillus sanfranciscensis&lt;/em> in San Francisco. But recent studies have found it in &lt;a href="www.nytimes.com/2012/09/19/dining/for-gastronomists-a-go-to-microbiologist.html">90% of the world&amp;rsquo;s sourdough&lt;/a>, too. So from a biological standpoint, San Francisco sourdough is not all that distinctive &amp;ndash; or unique to San Francisco.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you take your precious local sourdough starter and bake with it in Los Angeles, I bet the resulting bread will taste very similar to what you make in San Francisco. Blasphemy! But likely&amp;hellip;true. Even breads made without &lt;em>Lactobacillus sanfranciscensis&lt;/em> can taste pretty darn good.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>So much for the &amp;ldquo;microbial terroir&amp;rdquo; myth. Even bakers who have been in a position to benefit from the reputation of local sourdough don&amp;rsquo;t embrace the cachet. Call a dog a dog &amp;ndash; it&amp;rsquo;s pure marketing. It sells the city, turning sourdough into another tourist attraction that San Francisco is famous for, besides the bridge and the bay.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-2/20230220_104457.jpg"
alt="Joaquin Oro pan de San Joaquín baked"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>My &lt;em>pan de San Joaquín&lt;/em>, made with home-milled 100% wholegrain Joaquin Oro flour and a non-San Francisco sourdough starter&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>There are 3 bread institutions in the San Francisco Bay Area: Acme, Semifreddi&amp;rsquo;s, and Tartine.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Acme is often credited as an OG pioneer of the San Francisco Bay Area&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Bread Revolution,&amp;rdquo; which in turn galvanized the modern &amp;ldquo;artisan bread&amp;rdquo; movement across America; to this day, Acme&amp;rsquo;s bread remains a &amp;ldquo;benchmark&amp;rdquo; for commercial handmade bread. It was a stalwart of the 1980s artisan baking scene, along with Semifreddi&amp;rsquo;s.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Newer upstarts like Tartine and Josey Baker Bread have brought on some serious competition, and challenged the status quo of what San Francisco bread is &lt;em>supposed&lt;/em> to taste like and, along the way, the status quo of home baking.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In 2006, the NY Times food columnist Mark Bittman &lt;a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2006/12/06/dining/06mini.html">wrote about&lt;/a> a NYC baker named Jim Lahey, the man behind Sullivan Street Bakery who had developed a no-knead bread recipe that consisted of only 4 steps and required just 4 ingredients &amp;ndash; flour, water, salt, and yeast. While not the OG recipe of its kind, the &amp;ldquo;no-knead&amp;rdquo; method spread like wildfire. It revolutionized the food world; its simplicity miraculously democratized breadmaking for the home baker. Lahey became a semi-god figure &amp;ndash; the Prometheus who gifted the art of breadmaking to the masses. He released a cookbook in 2009, titled &lt;em>My Bread: The Revolutionary No-Work, No-Knead Method&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A few years earlier, a transplanted New Yorker named Elizabeth Pruitt and her husband Chad Robertson moved their tiny baking operation from Point Reyes, California south to an unassuming corner of Guerrero Street, at the edge of the Mission District in San Francisco. They named it Tartine, and churned out artisan breads, viennoiseries and sandwiches. The bakery garnered praise from Alice Waters and Martha Stewart, and made the cake for a &lt;a href="https://www.sfgate.com/entertainment/article/Why-the-concert-was-canceled-3314257.php">&amp;ldquo;bohemian bourgeois&amp;rdquo;-themed birthday party&lt;/a> attended by Nancy Pelosi and Hillary Clinton. Mark Bittman &lt;a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2007/01/28/travel/28Bite.html">described&lt;/a> their shop as one of the best French-style bakeries in the country, and particularly raved about Tartine&amp;rsquo;s sandwiches, which were made on &amp;ldquo;Mr. Robertson&amp;rsquo;s exceptional bread, notable because it&amp;rsquo;s a slow-fermented yeast bread in very French style that is a welcome change from the ubiquitous sourdough.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>San Franciscans started lining up outside the shop to get a taste of what Prueitt and Robertson were baking; the queues outside Tartine became a local landmark and a symbol of a changing city. (Lines beget lines; the success of Tartine&amp;rsquo;s OG location is arguably one of the reasons that San Francisco gained a reputation as a place where people would wait in line for any sort of &amp;ldquo;cult&amp;rdquo; food item.) Tartine&amp;rsquo;s bread started to become a Veblen good, just as Prueitt and Robertson started to become food-world celebrities. In 2010, the influential &lt;em>Tartine Bread&lt;/em> was published; Robertson revealed to the world his recipe for French-style sourdough, which called for folding, shaping, scoring, and a grasp of wild yeast. The change from Lahey&amp;rsquo;s no-knead bread to Robertson&amp;rsquo;s sourdough was remarkable; home baking was about to become more technical and more precise.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The complete recipe for Basic Country Bread, the edible hero of &lt;em>Tartine Bread&lt;/em>, runs 38 pages, including photographs. It was instantly celebrated as a &amp;ldquo;masterpiece&amp;rdquo; in media, along the lines of a Martin Scorsese tracking shot or a Marcel Proust sentence.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Robertson wrote about bread in a detailed but flexible way: The prose is lean and direct; the instructions don&amp;rsquo;t just tell you what to do but explain why, what to look for, and how to make corrections, encouraging you to see his laborious artisan craft as adaptable and welcoming of interpretation. Robertson was also a laid-back surfer who radiated a particular kind of Gen X bohemianism, which inadvertently imbued breadmaking with a sort of new masculine sheen.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Seemingly, Robertson gave away the store. The bread he teaches you to make is essentially the same bread that has turned him into one of the most influential bakers in the world; it&amp;rsquo;s what causes otherwise rational adults to mob the line at Tartine Bakery. The fact is, Tartine multiplied its influence by opening up about the way they do things.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Tartine Bread&lt;/em> could have merely been aspirational, but it&amp;rsquo;s just too &lt;em>actionable&lt;/em>. The recipes work, and they inspire. All of a sudden, many of Tartine&amp;rsquo;s fans took up artisan baking at home &amp;ndash; a majority of whom happened to be guys in tech.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For tech geeks in the San Francisco Bay Area, &lt;em>Tartine Bread&lt;/em> had it all:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>a recipe that encouraged iteration and a grasp of the scientific nature of wild fermentation;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>a craft that was not frivolous or quintessentially feminine like making cupcakes; and&lt;/li>
&lt;li>a cool leader that inspires emulation.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Technologists stormed sourdough with a host of tools and techniques that built on Robertson&amp;rsquo;s artisan approach. Ken Forkish, who had quit his job at IBM to become a baker, wrote &lt;em>Flour Water Salt Yeast&lt;/em> and won a James Beard Award in 2013. Nathan Myhrvold, the former CTO of Microsoft and current CEO of patent and investment firm Intellectual Ventures, released a 5-volume cookbook called &lt;em>Modernist Bread&lt;/em> in 2017. It also won a James Beard. High-efficiency tools like $150 Brød &amp;amp; Taylor Folding Bread Proofer that offers &amp;ldquo;precision control&amp;rdquo; over temperature and humidity, or the $300 Fourneau bread oven, which &amp;ldquo;traps steam and radiates powerful heat&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;helps you achieve oven spring&amp;rdquo;, came on the market.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Overnight, Silicon Valley venture capitalists started tweeting about their fine sourdough starters; UX designers started buying $600 bannetons and taking extensive notes about each bake in apps like Evernote, Google Keep, Notion and Bear; and tender #crumbshots popped up all over breadstagram. Everyone in Silicon Valley is Very Publicly Into Sourdough All of a Sudden. People couldn&amp;rsquo;t delight more in the miracles of this alchemy than if it were neolithic times and bread was just invented yesterday. Breadmaking has become the latest form of romantic consumerism.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-2/20230220_110032.jpg"
alt="Joaquin Oro pan de San Joaquín baked"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>pan de San Joaquín&lt;/em>. home-milled unsifted Joaquin Oro flour + non-San Francisco sourdough starter + homemade pineapple yeast water poolish&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The Perfect Loaf, a sourdough bread blog launched in 2013 by Maurizio Leo, a software engineer by trade, is frequently cited as an entry point to baking for men in tech, as his approach speaks to technically-oriented individuals and, as his blog name implies, is pursuant of mastery.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Breadmaking is now seen as a sort of an &amp;ldquo;algorithm&amp;rdquo;; it&amp;rsquo;s expected to produce a certain result and if that result isn&amp;rsquo;t always what you expect, you step back and diagnose the steps along the way. Working on bread recipes has become a new form of &amp;ldquo;debugging.&amp;rdquo; That iterative procedure for optimization appeals to the engineering mind, not to mention the precision part. Breadmaking also offers various degrees of freedom &amp;ndash; it could be implemented in lots of different possible ways.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It&amp;rsquo;s a liberating escape, particularly when you work in tech for a living and can&amp;rsquo;t turn that technical side of your brain off and your work becomes so embedded in your life that it consumes you.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Like religion, romanticism also has its liminal rituals, which decouple the subjective feelings of pleasure and freedom from material goods and mass-marketed symbols, and disrupt the daily tedium and hierarchies, transporting us, through the consumption of goods and services labeled romantic, into a fantastic world in which ordinary annoyances, our own limitations and, with a little luck, even our most objectionable caprices, are temporarily interrupted. Maybe baking is an opportunity for these technologists to rehabilitate their humanity, when they are not busy creating apps that make money off everyone&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;addiction&amp;rdquo;?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Sourdough&lt;/em>, a 2017 novel by Robin Sloan, pokes fun at the obnoxious foodie culture of Silicon Valley while also ribbing the folks who are so eager to innovate it &amp;ndash; the tech guys who obsess over an ancient idea, commit to disrupting it, then get bored and move on.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The reason that Chad Robertson became a god among tech-oriented breadmaking hobbyists is perhaps more shallow than one might think: Robertson and Tartine are instrumental to this whole trend because he was in San Francisco just as this mid-2000s tech wave was taking off. Right place, right time. Right guy, right craft.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>When Robertson &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=tHUU9dcHVng">spoke&lt;/a> about the intersection of tech and bread at a Wired conference in 2015, he said as much, noting that the reason he and Prueitt even moved their bakery to San Francisco in the first place was because the burst of the dotcom bubble in the early 2000s finally made it affordable for them to do so: The median rent for a two-bedroom apartment had fallen from $3,000 a month to just under $2,000. Development had slowed, evictions and unemployment had spiked, and commercial vacancies had risen. In the Mission District, a historically working-class and Latino neighborhood, artists' spaces battled with real-estate developers.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Tartine had thrived during an economic downturn. Now it&amp;rsquo;s operating in one of the most expensive cities in the world, where a 21-year-old earning low six-figures is considered a peasant.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-2/20230220_105833.jpg"
alt="Joaquin Oro pan de San Joaquín baked"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>pan de San Joaquín&lt;/em>. home-milled unsifted Joaquin Oro flour + non-San Francisco sourdough starter + homemade pineapple yeast water poolish&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>Tartine has undergone rapid expansion since Chad Robertson personally manned the ovens at the OG store on Guerrero Street, shuttling out a limited number of loaves every evening.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In 2014, the Oakland-born and San Francisco-raised Blue Bottle, the most dominant company riding the &amp;ldquo;third wave&amp;rdquo; coffee trend, had just &lt;a href="https://valleywag.gawker.com/blue-bottle-which-raised-45-m-cut-health-benefits-fo-1663442765">raised $45 million dollars&lt;/a> in venture capital for its own expansion, and needed a bakery partner to provide food in its coffee shops. Tartine soon announced a &lt;a href="https://www.latimes.com/food/dailydish/la-dd-tartine-blue-bottle-merging-20150420-story.html">merger&lt;/a> with the company; the news turned heads in the northern California food world and beyond. Anticipating a personal windfall, Prueitt and Robertson moved into a luxurious circa 1960 house in the Castro district in 2015. Eater SF did a &lt;a href="https://sf.eater.com/2016/2/23/11098328/tartine-bakery-liz-prueitt-chad-robertson-home-kitchen#11">photo shoot&lt;/a> of their newly remodeled home kitchen, showing off their specialized kitchenware and verdant backyard.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>By February 2016 when the Eater piece went live, the Blue Bottle acquisition had &lt;a href="https://www.sfchronicle.com/restaurants/article/Blue-Bottle-and-Tartine-Bakery-nix-merger-6673950.php">fallen apart&lt;/a>. The couple put the Castro house up for sale and quietly moved out in early 2018. Still, Tartine Manufactory, a restaurant and bar concept conceived in their sleek, airy home kitchen, opened in the summer of 2016. &lt;a href="https://sf.eater.com/2016/8/17/12513334/tartine-manufactory-san-francisco-mission-photos">Eater SF&lt;/a> lauded the 5,000-sqft space as &amp;ldquo;an artisanal utopia in the Mission&amp;rdquo;; every detail was designed to represent &amp;ldquo;a new type of luxury.&amp;rdquo; Meanwhile, Tartine launched its own coffee brand, &lt;a href="https://sprudge.com/tartines-coffee-manufactory-roasting-destiny-san-francisco-107956.html">Coffee Manufactory&lt;/a>, in partnership with a former Starbucks executive who is now the Chief Operations Officer of Tartine.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>One of Tartine&amp;rsquo;s partners and investors is a real-estate private-equity firm called CIM Group, one of the largest property owners in Los Angeles and a prominent commercial landlord in Oakland, managing about $30 billion dollars in assets.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Tartine&amp;rsquo;s Coffee Manufactory planned to move into Jack London Square, a 434,000-sqft waterfront property in Oakland acquired by CIM in 2016 as part of a &lt;a href="https://www.sfchronicle.com/restaurants/article/Jack-London-Square-cooks-up-a-new-generation-of-11231529.php">$131 million deal&lt;/a> for long-term development. CIM billed the Coffee Manufactory as an anchor tenant &amp;ndash; a business that could attract customers and other businesses, increasing the overall value and cachet of the area. The developer was curating the neighborhood with buildings and tenants.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Tartine was a particularly appealing anchor tenant. The food was great, and most of it could be made off-site, requiring a fairly modest square footage for retail sites. And Tartine had a history: the flagship location, with its artistic staff and communal ambiance, radiated the sort of authenticity that a real-estate developer could only dream of cultivating. Year on year, Tartine’s brand had become cooler, airier, and more transportable.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Anna Wiener, &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href="https://www.newyorker.com/news/letter-from-silicon-valley/when-baking-and-real-estate-collide">When Baking and Real Estate Collide&lt;/a>&amp;rdquo;, &lt;em>The New Yorker&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Images of Tartine&amp;rsquo;s pastries and its OG Guerrero Street bakery started to pop up in &lt;a href="hhttps://www.buzzfeed.com/michellerial/morning-bun">Apple commercials and product demos&lt;/a>. Sweetgreen, the East Coast fast-casual salad chain that was now proliferating along the West Coast, started to offer &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href="https://sf.eater.com/2017/8/30/16227094/sweetgreen-tartine-manufactory-salad-bowl-san-francisco-bay">The Tartine Bowl&lt;/a>&amp;rdquo;, plucked from Prueitt&amp;rsquo;s recently published book &lt;em>Tartine All Day&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Tartine&amp;rsquo;s brand became another recognizable symbol of &lt;a href="https://archive.is/mmUwT">gentrification&lt;/a>; the opening of a Tartine seemed to hint that a neighborhood was on the cusp of it. The process of bringing intense, aggressive real-estate development to upper-middle-class neighborhoods, to cater to an even more affluent stratum, is gentrification on steroids.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In January 2019, Tartine opened &lt;a href="https://sf.eater.com/2019/1/22/18193239/manufactory-food-hall-sfo-tartine-cala-kamine-san-francisco-international-airport">the Manufactory Food Hall&lt;/a> in San Francisco International Airport.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>That spring, Tartine opened a splashy &lt;a href="https://la.eater.com/2019/1/28/18200748/manufactory-row-tartine-chris-bianco-los-angeles-photos-inside">new 40,000-sqft Tartine Manufactory&lt;/a> &amp;ndash; three times the size of its first Manufactory in San Francisco &amp;ndash; in the Row, a huge, newly developed compound in Downtown Los Angeles (DTLA). &lt;em>Food &amp;amp; Wine&lt;/em> published a feature on Robertson and Prueitt, with the headline &amp;ldquo;With L.A. Opening, Tartine Positions Itself for World Domination.&amp;rdquo; F*ck yeah, Silicon Valley-style.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>CIM invested in Tartine&amp;rsquo;s 5 new locations in Los Angeles (&lt;a href="https://la.eater.com/2019/1/10/18177207/tartine-silver-lake-sunset-coming-expansion-news">Silver Lake&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://la.eater.com/2019/7/29/20746164/tartine-hollywood-bakery-san-francisco-opening-sycamore-news">West Hollywood&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://la.eater.com/2019/9/6/20853090/tartine-bakery-santa-monica-expansion-opening-funeral-home">Santa Monica&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://www.thebrassy.com/blog/west-adams-tartine-is-a-welcome-neighborhood-addition">West Adams&lt;/a>, and &lt;a href="https://la.eater.com/2022/2/1/22912646/tartine-pasadena-new-cafe-opening-restaurant-los-angeles-morning-am-intel-news">Pasadena&lt;/a>). For any Angeleno who&amp;rsquo;s ever wondered just how all these Tartines landed in the Southland in the first place, here&amp;rsquo;s an answer.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In July 2019, Tartine opened its 3rd San Francisco location, in a CIM-affiliated property in the Inner Sunset neighborhood.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In September 2019, Tartine opened its 5th Bay Area location in &lt;a href="https://sf.eater.com/2019/9/16/20868239/tartine-berkeley-bakery-open-graduate-hotel">Berkeley&lt;/a>. The café is tucked into a sunroom at Berkeley&amp;rsquo;s Graduate Hotel (fka. the Hotel Durant), a chain hotel owned by Adventurous Journeys Capital, a self-described &amp;ldquo;vertically integrated real estate investment manager focused on developing and operating transformative real estate assets in spaces often overlooked or undervalued by traditional investment firms.&amp;rdquo; Tartine&amp;rsquo;s new presence at the hotel came as part of a ~$50 million transformation from the Hotel Durant to the Graduate Hotel.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Customers who walk into any of Tartine&amp;rsquo;s locations may never feel or realize they are entering part of a real-estate empire.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>How much of Tartine is owned by CIM and how deeply these two companies are intertwined has never been publicly disclosed. The daughter of a co-founder of CIM is now Tartine&amp;rsquo;s VP of Brand.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-2/20230220_190301.jpg"
alt="Joaquin Oro pan de San Joaquín baked"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>100% wholegrain &lt;em>pan de San Joaquín&lt;/em>, gleaming in the wintry sun.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Today, Tartine operates 3 locations in the San Francisco Bay Area, 5 in Los Angeles, and 6 licensed locations in Seoul (one of which is located at &lt;a href="https://tartinebakery.com/seoul/dosan">Kinfolk Dosan&lt;/a>, a cultural space created by Kinfolk, an aspirational lifestyle magazine). How can a craft bakery still be artisanal if it has 6 overseas branches?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Tartine&amp;rsquo;s workers in San Francisco watched investment flow into the new locations and increasingly felt neglected. They suspected they were the actual engine that propelled Tartine into an empire, but now they couldn&amp;rsquo;t even get a $1/hour raise. There was a lot of confusion about the company&amp;rsquo;s investors &amp;ndash; who were they, and how much power did they wield? Money to pay invoices wasn&amp;rsquo;t there.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Tartine was expanding, but the OG Mission location was falling apart. In November 2019, the San Francisco Department of Public Health &lt;a href="https://sf.eater.com/2019/11/23/20979306/tartine-rats-rodents-dph-mission">briefly shut down&lt;/a> Tartine&amp;rsquo;s Guerrero Street location, after inspectors say that its operators failed to deal with a persistent rodent infestation in the space.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Workers noticed cultural changes. Shift wine was eliminated, and management introduced a monthly music playlist. Some were dissatisfied with wages, raises, and scheduling. Employees wanted certain benefits, such as paid time off separate from state-mandated sick leave, and raises larger than the annual increases mandated by the city. All this looked feasible to them, given the company’s expansion. When they brought these requests to Tartine’s newly created human-resources department, they were confused to find that it was run out of offices leased from CIM affiliates, in Los Angeles.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Anna Wiener, &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href="https://www.newyorker.com/news/letter-from-silicon-valley/when-baking-and-real-estate-collide">When Baking and Real Estate Collide&lt;/a>&amp;rdquo;, &lt;em>The New Yorker&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>As Tartine expanded rapidly in the last 6-7 years, operational difficulties grew with it. Money was allocated to ventures that didn&amp;rsquo;t pan out. The whole enterprise seemed stretched thin. There seemed to be a fundamental disconnect between perception and reality. New investment was focused on new ventures, but Tartine&amp;rsquo;s expansion relied on the strength of its brand.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Bar Tartine closed in 2016 and had never turned a profit (since it opened in 2005 just a couple of blocks away from the OG Tartine Bakery). The planned Coffee Manufactory retail space in Jack London Square never opened.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In December 2019, Tartine&amp;rsquo;s massive DTLA Manufactory shuttered &amp;ndash; 11 months after it opened. It was a shocking closure. The store laid off its remaining workers 10 days before Christmas.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Tartine’s market, retail baking and takeaway spaces, and multiple restaurants all closed this week after just 11 months of business and a build-out rumored to have run into the tens of millions of dollars. All of the Row is struggling to find sustained weeknight retail traffic right now, but the loss of anchor tenant Tartine has hit the development’s brand particularly hard. There simply were not enough $72 mug buyers around to keep the place afloat, and that seems to say something about Tartine’s visibility and draw, and about the Row overall — not to mention the cost of goods inside. &amp;hellip;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Simply put: Tartine didn’t find a good way to consistently speak to Angelenos, and in a city where driving four miles to have dinner can mean sitting in your car for an hour, answering the “why” of the place not only proved tricky, it likely proved its undoing. &amp;hellip; More than anything, it struggled to define its place at the Row, in Downtown, in a city brimming with home bakers and panaderias and other local bread legends like Friends &amp;amp; Family, Clark Street, and Bub &amp;amp; Grandma’s.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Eater LA, &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href="https://la.eater.com/2019/12/18/21028471/tartine-manufactory-downtown-los-angeles-the-row-closed-why">Tartine&amp;rsquo;s Big DTLA Manufactory Closed After Just One Year. What Happened?&lt;/a>&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Tartine took on a new investor, Monogram Capital Partners, another private-equity firm &amp;ldquo;focused exclusively on consumer and retail companies.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Meanwhile, Chad Robertson started to show up in &lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/BlundstoneUS/videos/live-in-my-blundstones-chad-robertson/2553319681570138/">sponsored content&lt;/a> for &lt;a href="https://www.blundstone.com/limb-chad-robertson">Blundstone boots&lt;/a> on social media. He and Prueitt divorced in 2020.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Given the PE industry&amp;rsquo;s typical M.O. (i.e. the decade-long pyramiding of real estate and overleveraging on ever lower interest rates), I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be surprised if Tartine is sinking deeper and deeper into debt &amp;ndash; or might eventually end up like &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/aquaboogie-di-dolce">Dean &amp;amp; DeLuca&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In February 2020, a few short weeks before the Covid lockdown, 141 of Tartine&amp;rsquo;s &amp;gt;200 San Francisco Bay Area employees signed a letter, announcing their decision to unionize with the International Longshore and Warehouse Union. It came as a huge surprise, especially at a world-renowned bakery that boasts about ​&amp;quot;production at a human scale&amp;quot; and has been a training ground for young bakers from around the globe.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Tartine&amp;rsquo;s management declined to recognize the union, and &lt;a href="https://sf.eater.com/2020/2/11/21133479/tartine-union-management-sam-singer">hired Sam Singer&lt;/a>, a longtime San Francisco crisis communications expert known for his work with controversial companies like Chevron&amp;rsquo;s Richmond oil refinery. After letting him go amid criticism, they then hired a Las Vegas-based firm called Quest Consulting to quash the unionizing effort. Quest&amp;rsquo;s founder, Lupe Cruz, has earned himself a &lt;a href="https://www.pressdemocrat.com/article/news/union-organizers-and-workers-decry-union-busting-consulting-firms-hired-b/">reputation&lt;/a> among labor organizers as &amp;ldquo;a notorious union-buster who specializes in influencing Latino-dominated workforces.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In March 2021, over a year after voting and following a thorny, protracted dispute over 24 challenged ballots, the National Labor Relations Board announced that Tartine&amp;rsquo;s workers in San Francisco had officially unionized. In May 2022, the Tartine Union began negotiations for its first wage and healthcare contract, which &lt;a href="https://sf.eater.com/2022/8/23/23318336/tartine-bakery-union-negotiations">stalled&lt;/a> a few months later.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-2/20230220_105911.jpg"
alt="Joaquin Oro pan de San Joaquín baked"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>pan de San Joaquín&lt;/em>. home-milled unsifted Joaquin Oro flour + non-San Francisco sourdough starter + homemade pineapple yeast water poolish&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>A single person at the right place comes up with a &amp;ldquo;unique&amp;rdquo; recipe at the right time can have the outsized effect of influencing a whole new generation of bakers, and even become a cult figure.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Nothing is more powerful than an idea whose time has come.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Victor Hugo&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>No single part of Tartine&amp;rsquo;s technique or bread is new or original to me. I&amp;rsquo;ve eaten there several times; nothing about it has blown my mind. Maybe it was groundbreaking a decade ago to the culinarily ignorant masses who grew up on industrial wheatish pulp?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>That one guy who lives in San Francisco at the right time with the right trade shouldn&amp;rsquo;t get all the credit for this bread renaissance &amp;ndash; East Coast journalists began to protest. People (mostly women) have been baking bread at home for thousands of years before Robertson and Prueitt opened Tartine.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Apparently, &amp;ldquo;nerds&amp;rdquo; over-engineering breadbaking, turning this homegrown, down-to-earth craft into something more technical and complicated than it should be, and &amp;ldquo;pushing&amp;rdquo; women out in the process is &lt;a href="https://www.eater.com/2018/11/19/18099127/bread-silicon-valley-sourdough-tech-bros-tartine-chad-robertson">a huge problem&lt;/a>. The gendering of baking has become a hot topic.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;hellip;one of my favorite things about JavaScript is when we discover things 20 years after other languages, besides like the concept of baking your own bread at home instead of purchasing it from the store, we act like we invented fat arrow functions, classes, immutable data, restructuring statements, functional programming &amp;ndash; like, it&amp;rsquo;s like truly wild to witness.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&amp;hellip;this baking bread thing seems to have come out of like nowhere and it&amp;rsquo;s interesting to see. &amp;hellip; I was going to make fun of the parallels between baking bread &amp;ndash; like baking bread from a recipe and implementing an algorithm of code, but I think that the real interesting and problematic parallel is the rhetoric with which JavaScript developers talk about bread. It&amp;rsquo;s super elitist and it&amp;rsquo;s mostly dudes.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>why are there no women in tech baking bread? And I feel like &amp;ndash; this is in all seriousness, I feel this pressure now to stop this in its tracks. &amp;hellip; I&amp;rsquo;m worried about fucking bread. Like, you think I&amp;rsquo;d have enough emotional labor as a woman in tech to have to deal with baking bread &amp;ndash; I don&amp;rsquo;t know.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Jenn Schiffer, &lt;a href="https://www.deconstructconf.com/2017/jenn-schiffer-how-to-be-a-real-developer">Deconstruct Conf 2017&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>People in and around San Francisco making sourdough is such a surprising and novel phenomenon that it needs to be picked apart &amp;ndash; because (&lt;em>gasp&lt;/em>!) they happen to be men who work in tech and ruin whatever they lay their hands on for the sake of fashion and &amp;ldquo;disruption.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Perhaps the pseudo-celebrity status of Chad Robertson, the ubiquity of Instagram shots that emphasize only the visual aesthetic of breads, etc. speak to humans' shallowness and egotism more than anything else.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Who cares about some JavaScript developer in San Francisco who bakes bread at home and runs a blog about it? If anything, it&amp;rsquo;s those who follow them keenly on social media that affirm their authority and turn them into some bread gods. Why are you so desperate for external validation?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A lot of people think that to be a real developer/baker, you need to be prolific on social media. If you don&amp;rsquo;t argue about your trade on Twitter, GitHub or Instagram, you don&amp;rsquo;t &lt;em>feel like&lt;/em> you are a real developer/baker. Yeah sure. Only if you &lt;em>choose&lt;/em> to play this game and be stuck in this rat race.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-2/20230220_104703.jpg"
alt="Joaquin Oro pan de San Joaquín baked"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>pan de San Joaquín&lt;/em>. home-milled unsifted Joaquin Oro flour + non-San Francisco sourdough starter + homemade pineapple yeast water poolish&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>I don&amp;rsquo;t think the scientific approach to bread is a futile endeavor. Why can&amp;rsquo;t the scientific and the intuitive approaches co-exist?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The foundation of bread is super simple and those basic principles are still unchanged. I disagree that it&amp;rsquo;s total hubris to be attempting to innovate and move the art forward. Some folks are actually making significant innovations in breadmaking, and innovation is not an &amp;ldquo;American sickness&amp;rdquo; that needs to be cured. (In fact, I would argue that America needs more innovation &amp;ndash; especially in manufacturing and engineering &amp;ndash; that will tangibly improve the standard of living.) Breads produced with some of the new artisan methods today are actually really good &amp;ndash; in ways that their predecessors simply were not. Just because something has been around for thousands of years doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean there aren&amp;rsquo;t many new discoveries to be had. Hell, it wasn&amp;rsquo;t until a couple of decades ago that people picked up on the fact that you &lt;em>don&amp;rsquo;t&lt;/em> have to knead the dough to make great bread. Sometimes little things like this go undiscovered because no one bothered to look.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Only very recently in history has certain technology become available to us that has allowed us to exert super precise control over the baking environment (e.g. ambient temperatures, steam, etc.) and ingredients (e.g. varieties of grain, grinds, flour blends, strains of yeast). Bread keeps getting better and better because some bakers continue to tinker endlessly with these variables. New scientific analysis could herald a &amp;ldquo;golden age of fermentation.&amp;rdquo; Sure, not everyone cares about these things. For most people, bread is bread.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As a baker, you should remove ego from your &lt;em>mise en place&lt;/em>, rethink your take on baking, and do some researching and discovering for new techniques and skills. There&amp;rsquo;s always room for improvement. And maybe, just maybe, you could find some new excitement, or get your mind blown, and impart that joy and passion through your baking. Every person that eats your bakes deserves that.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I haven&amp;rsquo;t been baking my whole life. My mom never baked bread, and I didn&amp;rsquo;t eat much bread growing up. I actually loathed baking for most of my life &amp;ndash; kneading or using a dough mixer (another thing you have to wash) is absolutely tedious, and handling raw ingredients like eggs is totally disgusting. I didn&amp;rsquo;t have &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/harpys-lovesong/">my first taste of artisan sourdough bread&lt;/a> until 2014. In fact, I didn&amp;rsquo;t discover breadmaking until ~2019, well after the &amp;ldquo;tech bros&amp;rdquo; had invaded the sourdough trend and maybe even moved on, and after &lt;a href="https://www.newyorker.com/culture/culture-desk/bread-makes-a-comeback">&lt;em>The New Yorker&lt;/em> declared&lt;/a> a comeback for bread and greeted it as the giddy limit of fake trendspotting.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I was initially drawn to breadmaking because of the science behind it &amp;ndash; the microbiology and cellular gastronomy &amp;ndash; more than the intuitive part. To me, sourdough brought bread back from the dead. Now I&amp;rsquo;m more enthused about transforming different grains into good bread. It&amp;rsquo;s not about making disruptive breads, but making breads that I really like.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;Tech bros invading sourdough&amp;rdquo; is not some panic-inducing mass-epidemic of nerds suddenly swarming every supermarket by the thousands for artisan flours and baking tools. ~4 years in, I&amp;rsquo;m still the only person I know who makes bread on a regular basis. Many types of people all over the world are getting more interested in breadmaking and trying it out, but it&amp;rsquo;s still pretty rare for someone to commit to it at the same level as myself.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As a side note, I think the fact that producing some common food item at home is now seen as &amp;ldquo;novel&amp;rdquo; speaks volumes about how removed we postmodern humans are from our food. Tovala and DoorDash are good examples.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-2/20230220_191147.jpg"
alt="Joaquin Oro pan de San Joaquín"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>100% wholegrain &lt;em>pan de San Joaquín&lt;/em>, gleaming in the wintry sun.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>My second experiment with Joaquin Oro (shared by friends at the California Wheat Commission) pushes the limits of dough hydration. Gorging the Joaquin Oro grown in water-scarce California with an absurd amount of water is quite the California conundrum.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="total">Total&lt;/h4>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Joaquin Oro, 100% extraction (Eck Farms, CA)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>530g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>H₂O&lt;/td>
&lt;td>134%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>710g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>whole wheat poolish&lt;/td>
&lt;td>52%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>275g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>whole wheat levain&lt;/td>
&lt;td>15%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>80g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>azuki bean purée&lt;/td>
&lt;td>7.1%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>37.5g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sea salt (Gustus Vitae, CA)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1.4%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>7.5g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>olive oil (Awake - Brightland, CA)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5.7%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>30g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>tallow (home-rendered), softened&lt;/td>
&lt;td>7.1%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>37.5g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>I used two leavens at different hydration levels in this dough.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="yeast-water-poolish">Yeast water poolish&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>I pre-fermented ~24% of total flour in an overnight poolish, with homemade pineapple &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/yeast-water/">yeast water&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Joaquin Oro, 100% extraction (Eck Farms, CA)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>125g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>pineapple yeast water (homemade)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>120%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>150g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>You could substitute the yeast water with 1%-2% dry yeast + 120% plain H₂O.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I let the poolish ferment for 12 hours at ~70°F. When ripe, the poolish should be brimming with bubbles and double in volume.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Poolish modifies gluten, weakening it somewhat, so the dough stretches better as it ferments. For a strong-flour dough, a poolish will help bread rise taller.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="levain">Levain&lt;/h4>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Joaquin Oro, 100% extraction (Eck Farms, CA)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>40g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>H₂O&lt;/td>
&lt;td>50%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>20g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sourdough starter&lt;/td>
&lt;td>50%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>20g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>I let the levain ripen at ~75°F for 1 hour, and then retarded it in the fridge overnight.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>When ripe, my levain smelt and tasted like a tart yogurt &amp;ndash; or perhaps more like crème fraîche that made me salivate and excited to eat more.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="final-dough">Final dough&lt;/h4>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Joaquin Oro, 100% extraction (Eck Farms, CA)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>365g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>H₂O, divided&lt;/td>
&lt;td>148%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>540g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>whole wheat poolish&lt;/td>
&lt;td>75%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>275g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>whole wheat levain&lt;/td>
&lt;td>22%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>80g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>azuki bean purée&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>37.5g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sea salt (Gustus Vitae, CA)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>7g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>olive oil (Awake - Brightland, CA)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>8%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>30g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>tallow (home-rendered), softened&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>37.5g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>The process is built upon my previous &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/aquaboogie-van-wheatsworth/">wholegrain &lt;em>pan de cristal&lt;/em> loaves&lt;/a>:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Autolyse the flour at 80% hydration for 2 hours in the fridge.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Add the poolish, levain, and azuki bean purée. Mix until well incorporated.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Double hydration: Slowly drizzle in 2/3 of the remaining water, and &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zgz0oAhgwyg">Rubaud-mix&lt;/a> until thoroughly absorbed. This requires a bit of patience, so take your time. Cover the dough and let it rest for 20 minutes at room temperature.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Add the salt, and mix well.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Triple hydration: Slowly add the rest of the water, while &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zgz0oAhgwyg">Rubaud-mixing&lt;/a> until completely combined. Let the dough rest for another 20 minutes at room temperature.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Gently mix in the olive oil and softened tallow. Let the dough rest and relax for 30 minutes.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Bulk ferment the dough at ~70°F for 4 hours, performing a coil-fold every 30 minutes during the first 2.5 hours. Folding a super-high-hydration dough like this kinda feels like handling water.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Transfer the dough into a fridge and retard for 12 hours.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Take the dough out of the fridge; divide it into two or leave it whole as a large loaf. Let it rest at room temperature for 2-3 hours (no shaping necessary).&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Bake as usual: 25-30 minutes at 350°F.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>I divided the dough into two approximately equal portions, baked one in the toaster oven, and kept the other one in the fridge for another 8 hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="bake-1">Bake #1&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>The 1st piece turned out great &amp;ndash; exactly what I had expected from a hard red spring wheat.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-2/20230220_111326.jpg"
alt="Joaquin Oro pan de San Joaquín baked"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The tallow has imparted some savory aroma to the bread.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-2/20230220_104549.jpg"
alt="Joaquin Oro pan de San Joaquín baked"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>toaster oven-baked &lt;em>pan de San Joaquín&lt;/em>. home-milled 100% wholegrain Joaquin Oro flour + non-San Francisco sourdough starter + homemade pineapple yeast water poolish&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The crumb is delightfully light and airy, almost like gossamer; it&amp;rsquo;s exceptionally soft and chewy.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-2/20230220_111631.jpg"
alt="Joaquin Oro pan de San Joaquín baked"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The crust is so thin and crisp that it&amp;rsquo;s almost non-existent.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Sure, it doesn&amp;rsquo;t have Tartine bread&amp;rsquo;s shell of blistered mahogany, but the interior is so chewy and preternaturally moist that it shimmers in the light.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-2/20230220_111504.jpg"
alt="Joaquin Oro pan de San Joaquín baked"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The delicate, nutty flavor of whole wheat Joaquin Oro shines through &amp;ndash; perceptibly different from Turkey Red to me.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I like this &lt;em>pan de San Joaquín&lt;/em> toasted; topped with &lt;em>salsa roja&lt;/em>, crunchy lettuce and thinly-sliced Vadalia onions (for a pleasing texture contrast), and crumbled &lt;em>queso fresco&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-2/20230220_112031.jpg"
alt="Joaquin Oro pan de San Joaquín baked"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>toaster oven-baked &lt;em>pan de San Joaquín&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;h4 id="bake-2">Bake #2&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>Instead of baking the 20-hour retarded piece in an oven, I brought it to a Mardi Gras BBQ thingy and cooked it in a cast-iron skillet on a charcoal-fired grill. Who says February is a month to simply be endured &amp;ndash; a penance to pay before late winter yields to spring?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Magic happens when meat meets charcoal smoke. What about breads?&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-2/20230220_190227.jpg"
alt="Joaquin Oro pan de San Joaquín baked"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>I tossed a handful of black walnut and pistachio shells into the grill towards the end. Nut shells release a great smokey aroma when they burn, due to the oils that naturally occur in the shells. They burn pretty easily and add a marvelous boost of smoky sweetness to food.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-2/20230220_190435.jpg"
alt="Joaquin Oro pan de San Joaquín baked"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>20-hour retarded 100% wholegrain &lt;em>pan de San Joaquín&lt;/em>. cooked on a charcoal-fired BBQ grill. smoked with black walnut and pistachio shells.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>This grilled &lt;em>pan de San Joaquín&lt;/em> delivers an exciting punch of smoky char in first bite.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The crumb is wonderfully airy and springy like the first one, and the subtle tang of the bread becomes more pronounced with each successive bite, finishing on a question mark instead of an exclamation point.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-2/20230220_191648.jpg"
alt="Joaquin Oro pan de San Joaquín baked"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Custardy and glistening.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I like this smoky &lt;em>pan de San Joaquín&lt;/em> fresh or toasted; perfect for dunking in garlicky cioppino.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-2/20230220_190539.jpg"
alt="Joaquin Oro pan de San Joaquín baked"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>smoked wholegrain &lt;em>pan de San Joaquín&lt;/em>, glistening on a BBQ grill in the sun.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>TL;DR&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Joaquin Oro is an excellent bread wheat for sourdough baking.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>You don&amp;rsquo;t need a San Francisco sourdough starter to make excellent bread.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>&lt;em>This is part 2 of my &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/california-grain-adventure/">California Grain Adventure&lt;/a>. If you enjoyed it, why not check out my other &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/archives/">breadstories&lt;/a> or spread the word?&lt;/em>&lt;/p></content></item><item><title>California Dreamin' #1: Joaquin Oro</title><link>/posts/california-dreamin-1/</link><pubDate>Mon, 13 Feb 2023 02:15:44 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/california-dreamin-1/</guid><description>[California Grain Adventure #1] Strawberry rosehip &lt;em>pain d&amp;rsquo;épices au levain&lt;/em>, made with freshly milled Joaquin Oro grown in the San Joaquin Valley of California. Gently sweetened with a homemade spice-infused syrup.</description><content>&lt;p>&lt;em>This is part 1 of my &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/california-grain-adventure/">California Grain Adventure&lt;/a>.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I first got to know California as an undergraduate student on the East Coast, during academic conference trips to the sun-baked campus of the University of California, Davis (UC Davis) where I met my besties; and later as a part-time L-Alien (or Angeleno).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If the rest of America were academic articles, then California would be something like blog posts. The former are often plodding and obtuse, and frequently more concerned with avoiding errors than trying to communicate incisive ideas; the latter may be fuzzy, loosely-defined, or outright mistaken, but tolerable so long as they introduce fresh ideas.&lt;/p>
&lt;div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
&lt;iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/wq-S8CIU7VA" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video">&lt;/iframe>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>To say California is unlike the other 49 states in the US is an understatement. Not just that the Golden State has waaaay more sculpted, sun-bronzed, rich techies with a higher propensity to consume expensive artisan coffees. To this day, I still feel a distinct difference whenever I go to California or do business in the state.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For example:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>California&amp;rsquo;s economy is massive, but two industries dominate popular imagination and exert impact on a global scale: Tech in Silicon Valley/San Francisco, and entertainment in Hollywood/Los Angeles. Far less than 1% of all new startups and movie stars actually break out every year, but those who do achieve exponential success.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>In a country of immigrants, California seems to be &lt;em>the&lt;/em> state of immigrants. Not just that California&amp;rsquo;s population is the most diverse in the US, with no race or ethnic group constituting a majority. About a century and a half ago, California was flooded with serial migrants who came from the East Coast and were willing to decamp once more in search of gold or fame. Does this make California the most American of all states?&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Thinking back, I realize California embodies more of the &amp;ldquo;top line&amp;rdquo; mindset while New York is dominated by the &amp;ldquo;bottom line&amp;rdquo; mindset. In California, venture capital and movie studios try to pick a few outsized winners that makes their losses irrelevant. New York is complicated, obviously finance-driven, and exemplified by the prevalence of insurance in particular.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Insurers apply the law of large numbers to predict the probability and cost of &amp;ldquo;tail events.&amp;rdquo; The insurance business is about collecting a steady stream of revenue (on the liabilities side) without making catastrophic mistakes that wipe out the assets, i.e. picking up nickels in front of a steamroller. Naturally, insurers spend 80% of their time on &amp;ldquo;the losers.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In contrast, venture capital focuses on maximizing &lt;a href="https://medium.com/@quantvc/power-laws-in-venture-capital-why-the-long-tail-matters-22e057c6fa34">fat tails&lt;/a>, by &amp;ldquo;investing in maybe 7 or 8 promising companies from which you think you can get a 10x return&amp;rdquo; (Peter Thiel). Successful VCs spend 80% of their time on a tiny handful of big &amp;ldquo;winners.&amp;rdquo; Their return curves look more like highly skewed power law distributions (&amp;ldquo;the 80/20 curve&amp;rdquo;).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Finding home runs and avoiding catastrophes are very different activities and require different mindsets. Maybe that distinction partly explains why California and New York feel so vastly different.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Subsequently, winner-take-all effects and blockbuster dynamics have continually permeated the Golden State.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="california-optimism">California optimism&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>For nearly a century, California offered ordinary people better lives than they could lead perhaps anywhere else in the world. Sunsets in California are always so singularly beautiful on TV and in movies. No doubt, California is the land of sunny optimism; the Conference Board&amp;rsquo;s California Consumer Confidence Index averaged 113 in the 5 years before Covid, hotter than national baselines.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>I think people who grew up in California have more tolerance for apocalyptic notions. However, mixed up with this tolerance for apocalyptic notions in which the world is going to end dramatically is this belief that the world can’t help but get better and better. It’s really hard for me to believe that everything doesn’t improve, because thinking like that was just so much a part of being in California.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Joan Didion&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Optimism is a valuable form of human capital. Just look at &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->Japan vs. China&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>People want optimism. They don&amp;rsquo;t want to learn that it&amp;rsquo;s almost impossible to make it, that few do, and that even worse it takes years of hard work and dedication and a ton of luck &amp;ndash; and that today even the most talented don&amp;rsquo;t always succeed.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Every now and then, you detect a faint strain of melancholy, a sort of &lt;em>ennui&lt;/em>, that permeates Californians' creative output. You hear it in &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=uU0BOyQRjWM">The Beach Boys&lt;/a> (a rock band instrumental in popularizing a particular California culture of sun, sand, and surfing in the 1960s) and &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=QOOiY0bgrlU">Red Hot Chili Peppers&lt;/a>; see it in &lt;a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt3783958/">&lt;em>La La Land&lt;/em>&lt;/a> (where Los Angeles in the winter and summer scenes looks identical) and &lt;a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt4687880/">&lt;em>Goliath&lt;/em>&lt;/a>; &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/california-books">read it&lt;/a> in Philip K. Dick, Joan Didion, Jack Kerouac, John Steinbeck, etc. What do people have to worry about in the land of sunny beaches and beautiful weather?&lt;/p>
&lt;div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
&lt;iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/w_zz0JNhujE" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video">&lt;/iframe>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>As a matter of fact, California&amp;rsquo;s net migration has been negative in the last two decades, losing about a million more people than it gained through migration. Instead of moving from Oklahoma to California (à la John Steinbeck&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em>The Grapes of Wrath&lt;/em>), traffic has been reversing the other way. This trend has become even more evident in the last few months; when rent is $4k-$5k, making six figures in an industry experiencing mass layoffs is not a comfy situation.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>While tech and entertainment are monstrous sectors with far-reaching impact (even reindeer herders in the arctic forests of Karelia watch Hollywood movies and use Instagram, for instance), altogether they generate only ~10% of the state&amp;rsquo;s GDP (though one could argue for a bigger share under different definitions). The two big blockbuster industries may not have that big of an impact on the daily lives of most Californians.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Maybe that helps to explain a bit of the melancholy in the culture &amp;ndash; a golden age for all has &lt;a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20220517070336/https://isteve.blogspot.com/2009/06/benjamin-schwarzs-laments-end-of.html">passed&lt;/a> and those who were once ahead have tried to lock in their gains.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>You can check out any time you like&lt;/p>
&lt;p>But you can never leave&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&amp;ndash; Eagles, &amp;ldquo;Hotel California&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Maybe the California Dream is more elusive than we believe.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Maybe nothing exemplifies this better than wheat, whose golden age ended ~130 years ago.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="california-wheat">California wheat&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Today, California is a leading producer in &lt;a href="https://asmith.ucdavis.edu/news/we-grow-that">pretty much everything&lt;/a> except for, curiously, the major grains like wheat and corn.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Wheat was brought to California from Mexico; it was first grown by padres during the &amp;ldquo;mission period&amp;rdquo; in the 18th century and later by settlers.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>California became the nation&amp;rsquo;s second largest wheat producer (after Minnesota) in the second half of the 19th century, thanks to the Gold Rush and the associated increased demand for food. Wheat production in California hit a peak in the late 1880s; soon thereafter, it declined as rapidly as it rose, mainly due to soil exhaustion and low farm prices.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>With increasing acreage of irrigated land and better transportation to markets in the eastern US, California began a massive agricultural shift &amp;ndash; diversifying away from grains and towards the more lucrative &lt;a href="https://www.ams.usda.gov/services/grants/scbgp/specialty-crop">specialty crops&lt;/a> like vegetables, fruit, and nuts.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>By 1913, California&amp;rsquo;s wheat-planting area had shrunk to 380,000 acres (from some 3 million acres just three decades earlier). Throughout the 20th century, the wheat acreage fluctuated widely, ranging from a minimum of 270,000 acres in 1966 to a maximum of 1,345,000 acres in 1981. In recent years, the wheat acreage has stabilized somewhat, averaging about half a million acres since the year &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->2000&lt;sup id="fnref:2">&lt;a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->; wheat production averages ~40 million bushels annually. (In comparison, Kansas plants ~7 million acres of wheat annually on average and produces over 300 million bushels.)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Wheat didn&amp;rsquo;t disappear from California; it still is an important rotational crop for many growers, and California&amp;rsquo;s wheat industry is a bit unique.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-1/california-wheat-map.png"
alt="California wheat-producing areas"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>California wheat-producing areas&lt;/p>&lt;p>Source: &lt;a href="http://californiawheat.org/california-wheat/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">California Wheat Commission&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>While Kansas specializes in &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/hard-red-winter-wheat/">hard red winter wheat&lt;/a>, North Dakota in &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/hard-red-spring-wheat/">hard red spring wheat&lt;/a> and durum, and Washington in &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/soft-white-winter-wheat/">soft white wheat&lt;/a>, California grows all of the US wheat classes except soft red, i.e. you can find hard red, hard white, soft white, and durum wheat grown across the state. The two main types of wheat grown in California are &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->hard red winter wheat&lt;sup id="fnref:3">&lt;a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">3&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --> and durum wheat, mainly used for milling.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Given the vast expanse of the state, most of California&amp;rsquo;s wheat production is localized in specific regions. The majority of wheat is grown in the San Joaquin Valley, where Fresno, Kern, Kings and Tulare counties dominate production. (Yolo County in the Sacramento Valley completes the list of the top 5 counties with the largest area harvested.) Eternal sunshine, coupled with a warm and dry climate, produces big plump kernels with low moisture content, consistent kernel size distribution, and high test weight.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-1/TR-vs-Joaquin-Oro.jpg"
alt="Tukey Red (Kansas) vs. Joaquin Oro (California)"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Kernel size comparison: Tukey Red (grown in Kansas) vs. Joaquin Oro (grown in California)&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>It&amp;rsquo;s no surprise that California&amp;rsquo;s wheat yield has been among the highest in the nation. California also happens to have the largest milling capacity in the US, thanks to having the most mills in one state.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Artisan bakers and organic farmers are leading the revival of whole grains and local grain economies. While wheat breeding programs often focus on refined flour markets, UC Davis recently started an organic wheat breeding program to focus on unique wheat varieties for artisan breadmaking and local grain markets. The awesome team (a shout-out to Claudia Carter and Teng Vang) at the California Wheat Commission &amp;ndash; the coolest wheat commission in the country, by the way &amp;ndash; sent me a few of such varieties to experiment with.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-1/cwc-wheats.jpg"
alt="California wheat: Joaquin Oro (HRSW), Sonora Blanca (SWWW), and Desert Gold (durum)."/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>California wheat: Joaquin Oro (HRSW), Sonora Blanca (SWWW), and Desert Gold (durum).&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>The first California-grown wheat that I experimented with was &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/breadford-von-regrainton">Glenn&lt;/a>, a modern hard red spring variety grown by Kenter Canyon Farms along the south side of the Santa Clara River.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This week, I got to play with &lt;strong>Joaquin Oro&lt;/strong>, another California-grown hard red spring wheat. It&amp;rsquo;s a modern cultivar selected from the OG Joaquin variety for morphological, agronomic and quality traits; bred and developed by WestBred to thrive in the wheat-growing areas of the San Joaquin Valley; and released by UC Davis in 2011. Protein content ~14%.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Historically, Joaquin Oro has been the highest-quality bread wheat variety grown in California. It&amp;rsquo;s also one of the highest-rated whole wheat flours by the California Wheat Commission test lab.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-1/joaquin-oro-berries.jpg"
alt="Joaquin Oro wheat berries, from California."/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Plump and vibrant Joaquin Oro wheat berries, grown in the San Joaquin Valley of California.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>This Joaquin Oro was grown by Jon Eck of Eck Farms in Merced County, California. Jon&amp;rsquo;s parents are lifelong farmers, growing primarily almonds and sweet potatoes &amp;ndash; two of the traditional cash crops in the San Joaquin Valley. Jon decided to try growing grain as a rotational crop at the suggestion of a baker friend. John tells of his experience and learning on the excellent &lt;a href="https://www.thesourdoughpodcast.com/episodes/2021/9/27/jon-eck-california-wheat-grower">Sourdough Podcast&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The first thing I noticed with Joaquin Oro was how easily the wheat berries milled to a fine texture on the first run, on a countertop electric WonderMill set to Bread Flour.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The wholegrain Joaquin Oro flour has a finer, smoother texture (and visibly smaller bran particle size) than freshly milled Turkey Red &amp;ndash; and almost boasts of a Unifine feel.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Maybe this is what a French miller would classify as &lt;em>blé tendre&lt;/em> (&amp;ldquo;soft wheat&amp;rdquo;), a bread wheat that shows little &lt;em>résistance&lt;/em> to milling (i.e. requires less force than &lt;em>le blé résistant&lt;/em> to shear the starchy endosperm of the grain).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Despite being categorized as a &amp;ldquo;hard&amp;rdquo; wheat in the US commercial wheat classification system due to its high protein content, Joaquin Oro actually mills quite easily &amp;ndash; like a low-protein wheat. I am amazed.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-1/joaquin-oro-milled.jpg"
alt="Freshly milled Joaquin Oro"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Freshly milled Joaquin Oro.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>My first experiment with Joaquin Oro is inspired by my &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/dulce-locura/">&lt;em>pain d&amp;rsquo;épices au levain&lt;/em>&lt;/a>, in light of the upcoming Valentine&amp;rsquo;s Day. It incorporates strawberries, rosehips, spiced syrup, and dark chocolate. 🌹🍓🍫&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I decided to bolt the freshly milled Joaquin Oro to remove some of the coarsest bran bits and midds, to lighten the load a bit on the gluten in the flour, which shall hold together a boatloat of add-ins. The extracted bits will be used, instead of flour, to dust the workbench and the dough later, so nothing is wasted.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Joaquin Oro, 88% extraction (Eck Farms, CA)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>400g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>strawberry rosehip purée (homemade)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>36%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>145g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;em>sirop d&amp;rsquo;épices&lt;/em> (55% in autolyse + 25% in &lt;em>bassinage&lt;/em>)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>80%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>320g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Joaquin Oro whole wheat levain&lt;/td>
&lt;td>40%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>160g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sea salt (Gustus Vitae, CA)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>8g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>olive oil (Awake - Brightland, CA)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>20g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>dark chocolate, chopped (74% Guatamala Lachuá - Mutari Chocolate, CA)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>20%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>80g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Did you know California is America&amp;rsquo;s largest producer of strawberries? And wild rose (&lt;em>Rosa californica&lt;/em>) grows throughout the coast and foothills of the state?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you are a forager and happen to have collected some wild rosehips and strawberries from Nature&amp;rsquo;s grocery store, you are a hell of &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->a lucky bastard&lt;sup id="fnref:4">&lt;a href="#fn:4" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">4&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->. Otherwise, grab some dried rosehips and good-tasting strawberries from somewhere.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>To make the strawberry rosehip purée 🍓🌹 at home: Boil the rosehips in just enough water until soft; push the pulp through a fine-mesh sieve to remove the seeds and irritating hairs; run the resulting pulp and juice with strawberries (fresh or frozen) in a blender into a smooth purée. Use as much rosehips or strawberries as you like.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Pro tip: Make your own &lt;em>sirop d&amp;rsquo;épices&lt;/em> (spiced syrup), too.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Then proceed as documented in the &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/dulce-locura/">&lt;em>pain d&amp;rsquo;épices au levain&lt;/em>&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>TL;DR, give the dough an overnight bulk fermentation in the fridge, after a series of coil-folds in the initial 4.5 hours; shape; final proof 3-4 hours; bake off.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-1/20230212_195754.jpg"
alt="Pain d&amp;#39;épices au levain, made with freshly milled Joaquin Oro."/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>Pain d&amp;rsquo;épices au levain&lt;/em>, made with freshly milled Joaquin Oro.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Joaquin Oro delivers a nuanced flavor profile. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem to have as much bitterness as many red wheat varieties; instead it&amp;rsquo;s imbued with nutty, malty notes. This pairs exquisitely with the rich fruitiness and faint tartness of rosehips and strawberries. Homemade &lt;em>sirop d&amp;rsquo;épices&lt;/em> cranks up the sweetness and adds a wonderful touch of spice notes.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Joaquin Oro also performs excellently in baking. The dough felt quite elastic during the initial fermentation, and became very pillowy and delicate after overnight cold retard; it showed a pretty decent rise in the oven.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-1/20230212_195908.jpg"
alt="Pain d&amp;#39;épices au levain, made with freshly milled Joaquin Oro."/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>Pain d&amp;rsquo;épices au levain&lt;/em>, made with freshly milled Joaquin Oro.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The crust of this bread turned out crisp and thin; the crumb tender and springy.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The chewy texture reminded me of a traditional stottie cake in Northumberland, northern England. Irresistible.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Go make this bread and share with your sweetheart, Valentine&amp;rsquo;s Day or not, and enjoy it with a good slather of chocolate cheese fudge &amp;ndash; while everyone is getting worked up about Joe Rogan again or Kansas City Chiefs winning another Super Bowl after being underdogs for half a century.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>&lt;em>This is part 1 of my &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/california-grain-adventure/">California Grain Adventure&lt;/a>. If you enjoyed it, why not check out more &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/archives/">breadstories&lt;/a> or spread the word?&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>The current &lt;a href="https://www3.nhk.or.jp/nhkworld/en/news/20230131_12/">unemployment rate in Japan&lt;/a> is 2.5%. Japanese millennials get to enjoy a fairly tight labor market, which means they ought to choose which company to work for. But few of them have an interest in switching employers or jobs, because they rank perfect stability above high wages. This risk aversion is usually attributed to lingering fears of the previous downturn. The country that lost a decade &amp;ndash; or two &amp;ndash; has fostered a generation of youth highly averse to risk-taking. Optimism is &lt;a href="https://archive.is/vqIPO">in very short supply&lt;/a> in Japan. On the other hand, surveys show the Chinese are much more optimistic about the future. Take Cixin Liu&amp;rsquo;s sci-fi series, &lt;em>Three Body Problem&lt;/em>, for an example. The novel is driven by a fundamentally optimistic vision: It asks why aliens should not be 10,000x more advanced than humans, instead of portraying a typical alien civilization that&amp;rsquo;s only 50%-70% more advanced than humans.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>USDA/NASS historical data.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:3" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>Most varieties grown in California are genetically spring wheat (planted in the spring and harvested in late summer or early fall). However, since the majority of California wheat-growing regions have very mild winters, spring wheat can be sown in the fall or early winter like winter wheat. Wheat market classifications are typically based on the season of production rather than growth habit, which is why California&amp;rsquo;s red wheat production is referred to as hard red winter wheat.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:4" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>According to an academic study titled &amp;ldquo;Morphological and Chemical Characteristics of Fruits of Selected Rosa sp,&amp;rdquo; &lt;em>R. californica&lt;/em> contains 863 mg vitamin C per 100 g of fruit. 4 other species were studied: &lt;em>R. villosa&lt;/em> (706 mg), &lt;em>R. rugosa&lt;/em> (974 mg), &lt;em>R. spinosissima&lt;/em> (845 mg), and &lt;em>R. × damascena&lt;/em> (932 mg). Google claims oranges provide 53 mg vitamin C per 100 g. On average, rosehips tend to have at least an order of magnitude more vitamin C then oranges; &lt;em>R. californica&lt;/em> has about 16x more.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:4" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/section></content></item><item><title>Singin' in ze Grain</title><link>/posts/singing-in-ze-grain/</link><pubDate>Sun, 08 Jan 2023 19:21:08 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/singing-in-ze-grain/</guid><description>45% heritage Sangaste rye + 45% heritage Red Fife wheat + 10% buckwheat, with Argentinian &lt;em>yerba maté&lt;/em> and lots of ancient grains &amp;amp; seeds.</description><content>&lt;p>A bunch of new construction homes are popping up across the road from the woods where I often go hiking. Realtors are trying to lure people in with a roadside ad, &amp;ldquo;Enjoyed the park? Why not live here?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I was just complaining the other day about how we had to drive increasingly longer and longer distances these days to get to a truly wild and natural park. More and more green space has been rezoned for residential housing development. Oftentimes I feel mankind has essentially been running a giant Ponzi scheme with Nature &amp;ndash; who might be &lt;a href="https://peaksurfer.blogspot.com/2022/12/who-is-sam-bankman-fried-of.html">the SBF of the ecological space&lt;/a>?&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>A person deals with the natural elements only through a set of technologies which is so complete that he is actually dealing with those technologies themselves. The natural environment itself disappears. We obviously have to make a comparison with the city, an essential product of technology. In the city, man perceives the natural elements only accidentally (parks, sidewalk trees). Nothing spontaneously natural is left here. And outside nature is reserved for spare time, relaxation, etc., given the decreasing importance of agriculture and the decline in the farming population.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Jacques Ellul, &lt;em>The Technological System&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Home prices have been falling&amp;hellip; 1 out of 3 real estate agents in the US couldn&amp;rsquo;t afford to pay rent in November. But when you go to Zillow and actually check the price history of almost any house on the market right now, you will see that current price drop looks like &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/files/Kovach-statement.pdf">a pimple on an elephant&amp;rsquo;s ass&lt;/a>.&amp;rdquo; The only good news is downpayment requirements are falling, too. Still, total cost of home ownership over a 25-year amortization is significantly higher. Few are advertising that fact.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Some quick mortgage math for Canadians: a C$1.5m mortgage at 3% APR with a 25-year amortization is C$86,141/year (C$2,151,545 total cost). A C$1.1m mortgage at 7% APR with a 25-year amortization is C$94,391/year (C$2,359,789 total cost). Housing prices need to drop a lot more.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Pending Home Sales in the United States decreased 37.80% year-on-year in November of 2022, the 18th straight month of declines and the biggest since November of 2021.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>National Association of Realtors&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>A ramification: Private Equity (PE) is going to see a massive write-down of its non-public assets in 2023, whether it&amp;rsquo;s residential real estate (RRE), commercial real estate (CRE), or venture capital (VC). Blackstone&amp;rsquo;s $68Bn &lt;a href="https://www.breit.com/portfolio/">BREIT&lt;/a> and Starwood&amp;rsquo;s $30Bn &lt;a href="https://www.starwoodnav.reit/portfolio/">SREIT&lt;/a> already froze withdrawals last month. This past week, BREIT got a &lt;a href="https://www.businesswire.com/news/home/20230103005410/en/UC-Investments-Creates-Strategic-Venture-with-Blackstone-to-Invest-4-Billion-in-BREIT-Common-Shares">$4Bn &amp;ldquo;Buffett-style&amp;rdquo; last-resort bailout&lt;/a> from the University of California. Given that Blackstone is the world largest institutional landlord, 2023 is off to an ominous start for the US CRE market.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Markdowns will be severe. This will lead to groupthink of re-evaluating the entire PE world. Not all PE is bad, but the decade-long pyramiding of real estate on ever lower interest rates has ended &amp;ndash; and that will bring a big markdown cycle. Opportunity always exists when the crowd thinks it knows an unknowable future.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Another surprise file will be the Pension Fund Bailout Act of 2023. The City of Chicago is the poster child for this phenomenon, but they are not alone. Pension Funds (PFs) have been gouging on PE and RE over the last decade. That horse is now dead, as the return of real interest rates and above-zero commercial papers crushes the valuations of these investments. Slowly at first, and then all of a sudden, the markdowns will rip holes in the PF balance sheets. The fact that the bulk of the boomers are now retiring is not going to help these PFs. (The tight labor market is partly due to early retirements.) As this pull-forward effect ripples through the PF world, more problems will surface and the cry for a bailout will intensify. Good luck to the bond market and RE market when the buyer from the last decade is now a seller. Prepare for &amp;ldquo;higher for longer&amp;rdquo; in the interest rate world as the demand for commercial papers drops &amp;ndash; especially in a negative-carry world. The current bond yield curve is toxic for leveraged financial positions.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A lot of ridiculous things happened in the last couple of years, e.g. cars launched into space for the memes, degenerates becoming millionaires overnight from their basement and then giving it all back. As the calendar turns to 2023, all those moments will be lost in time, like tears in the rain.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The Dominoes are starting to fall, e.g. &lt;a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/dereksaul/2023/01/05/silvergate-stock-crashes-nearly-50-as-bank-grapples-with-crypto-crisis/">Silvergate&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://www.amny.com/transit/ag-james-sues-auto-lender-credit-acceptance-corp-accuses-of-predatory-loans-and-securities-fraud/">Credit Acceptance Corporation&lt;/a> this past week. Bed Bath and Beyond is worried about &lt;a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2023/01/05/business/bed-bath-beyond-bankruptcy.html">a gloomier future&lt;/a>. &amp;ldquo;Slowly at first, then all of a sudden.&amp;rdquo; Second-tier financial institutions and sovereigns will be the trigger. The higher cost of capital is starting to filter into the financial economy, driving valuations lower and lower.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The layoffs in Tech Land are &lt;a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/05/amazon-to-cut-18000-jobs-as-tech-layoffs-continue/">just getting started&lt;/a>, as the seemingly unending stream of capital supporting profitless Ponzi tech is drying up.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>There has been too much money in finance and tech. There are some who can resist, but not many. Plenty of Harvard grads went on to Wall Street. What a waste. You need enough money to live, but how much is that? Which is precisely the point of &lt;a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt15255876/">&lt;em>Emily the Criminal&lt;/em>&lt;/a> &amp;ndash; Emily needs the money and she makes choices. The middle class has evaporated. And the truth is those at the bottom will do anything to survive. Desperate people do desperate things. Emily says you must make your own rules. You are either the boss or the employee (capital vs. labor). If you are the employee, you don&amp;rsquo;t have much power. Sure, there are unions. Then again, everybody agrees to arbitration and the company always wins and&amp;hellip;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Life is hard.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Yet people can still splurge $140 on a dozen &lt;a href="https://lastcrumb.com/">luxury cookies&lt;/a> and $100 on a single panettone. First-class flights from Zurich to Singapore are fully booked. Channel 2.55 bag went from $1600 in 2008 to $9000 in 2022. More draining in the financial ecosystem is on tap.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In &lt;a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt11564570/">&lt;em>Glass Onion&lt;/em>&lt;/a>, Benoit Blanc eventually figures out that the billionaire is just an idiot &amp;ndash; and he should have seen it all along.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Thoroughly caffeinated, I skimmed through Micheline Maynard&amp;rsquo;s new book, &lt;em>Satisfaction Guaranteed: How Zingerman&amp;rsquo;s Built a Corner Deli into a Global Food Community&lt;/em>. It&amp;rsquo;s one of those quintessential boomer hagiography-cum-business books. The author clearly admires Zingerman&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ndash; almost as much as Kamala Harris publicly idolizes civil rights lawyers &amp;ndash; and keeps comparing it to the world&amp;rsquo;s most successful companies, especially Toyota; whereas I find the niche store&amp;rsquo;s business model more clichéd than inspiring. The owners' purportedly unique &amp;ldquo;Visioning&amp;rdquo; process at ZingTrain, for example, recommends that your &amp;ldquo;effective vision&amp;rdquo; be &amp;ldquo;inspiring,&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;strategically sound,&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;written down,&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;communicated&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; four tenets that, on the whole, seem pretty stale. The same could be said about Zingerman&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;12 Natural Laws of Business,&amp;rdquo; which includes such banal points as &amp;ldquo;profit is good&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;greatness takes time.&amp;rdquo; One story I find particularly intriguing is how Zingerman&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href="https://www.michigandaily.com/uncategorized/campus-206/">handled competition&lt;/a> (e.g. Amer&amp;rsquo;s Mediterranean Deli) in the early years, given that 1) restaurant recipes are virtually never patentable, 2) restaurants have basically no &amp;ldquo;moats&amp;rdquo;, and 3) customer loyalty is fragile, particularly during difficult times. TBH, I find Zingerman&amp;rsquo;s mail-order bread a lot fresher than this book. Michigan has historically been hit hard by national recessions because the state&amp;rsquo;s economy (still) depends heavily on the auto industry and durable goods manufacturing, despite recent efforts to diversify. It would be interesting to see what happens in this round.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>There are only patterns. Patterns on top of patterns. Patterns that affect other patterns. Patterns hidden by patterns. Patterns within patterns. If you watch closely, history does nothing but repeat itself. What we call chaos is just patterns we haven&amp;rsquo;t recognized. What we call random is just patterns we can&amp;rsquo;t decipher. What we call nonsense is just patterns we can&amp;rsquo;t understand. What we call gibberish is just patterns we can&amp;rsquo;t read.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/singing-in-ze-grain/202301081352.jpg"
alt="Singin&amp;#39; in Ze Grain"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Singin' in ze grain&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>I made a bread inspired by German baker Tobias Exner&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em>Brandenburger Urkraft&lt;/em>, which he created together with Olympic canoe champion Sebastian Brendel.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="bran-levain">Bran levain&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>I milled some heritage Sangaste rye (45%), Red Fife wheat (45%), and buckwheat (10%).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I bolted the freshly milled wholegrain flours to remove some course bits (~17%), which I fed to the levain (~85% hydration) in 3 increments over 14 hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The sifted flours came out to be ~83% extraction. Every part of the grain will be re-combined in the final dough.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="altus-soaker">Altus soaker&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>I toasted a piece of day-old sourdough rye bread and ground it into breadcrumbs. I scooped some of the breadcrumbs (15% of final flour weight) into a bowl and poured an equal amount of hot water over it.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s % (of final flour weight)&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>old bread, toasted &amp;amp; ground&lt;/td>
&lt;td>15%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>hot water&lt;/td>
&lt;td>15%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>I covered the soaker and left it at room temperature for a few hours, and then moved it into the fridge overnight.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="grain-soaker">Grain soaker&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>The total amount of dry pseudo-grains used here came up to be 20% of final flour weight.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s % (of final flour weight)&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>quinoa (Bolivian royal white)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>kañiwa&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>amaranth (yellow foxtail)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>teff (brown)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>cool water&lt;/td>
&lt;td>40%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>I soaked the pseudo-grains in double the amount of water, and left them to sprout overnight.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="seeds--raisins">Seeds &amp;amp; raisins&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>I toasted the seeds (23% of final flour weight) until aromatic and very lightly browned.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s % (of final flour weight)&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sunflower seeds&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>pumpkin seeds&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>poppy seeds&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>nigella seeds&lt;/td>
&lt;td>3%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>In the meanwhile, I chopped up some Monukka raisins (5% of final flour weight) and set them aside.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s % (of final flour weight)&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>raisins&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;h4 id="final-dough">Final dough&lt;/h4>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>83% extraction rye flour (Sangaste - Laughing Wolf Farm, CO)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>45%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>83% extraction wheat flour (Red Fife - Merrylynd Organics, ON)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>45%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>83% extraction buckwheat flour (Merrylynd Organics, ON)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>freshly brewed &lt;em>yerba maté&lt;/em> (Liebig Original)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>102%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>bran levain&lt;/td>
&lt;td>40%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>altus soaker&lt;/td>
&lt;td>30%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>salt (Sal Marinho)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>chia seeds (black)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>flax seeds (brown)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>grain soaker&lt;/td>
&lt;td>60%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>toasted seeds&lt;/td>
&lt;td>23%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>raisins&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>I mixed the sifted flours, chia and flax seeds, and the altus soaker with 85% of the water, and left the mixture to autolyze for 30 mins. Then I added the levain and salt, and mixed for a few minutes. I let the dough rest for 10 mins, before adding the rest of the water slowly.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>At this point, I put the dough in the fridge. In the next 24 hours, I took the dough out of the fridge 6 times and gave it a coil-fold, adding some of the sprouted pseudo-grains, toasted seeds and raisins during each fold.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>After a 24-hour cold fermentation in the fridge, I shaped the dough, rolled it in extra sunflower seeds, and let it proof at room temperature for 3 hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Lastly, I baked it as usual, in my toaster oven.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/singing-in-ze-grain/202301081432.jpg"
alt="Singin&amp;#39; in ze Grain"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Like a bird singing in the rain, let grateful memories of forgotten foods survive in time of pain.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>I like the bread toasted, and paired with Kentucky old-school country ham.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This year, I hope to bake with more varieties of heritage grains. I would like to go into the woods more often and get to know more native plants before they disappear for good. And maybe I&amp;rsquo;ll try growing some peppers, too.&lt;/p></content></item><item><title>Kornerstone</title><link>/posts/kornerstone/</link><pubDate>Sun, 19 Jun 2022 19:32:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>/posts/kornerstone/</guid><description>An old-school Jewish deli rye, made with a hefty amount of single-grind wholegrain Danko rye flour and two kinds of heritage wheat flours. Infused with caramelized onions, spent brewer&amp;rsquo;s grains, and poppy seeds.</description><content>&lt;p>Charles Bukowski&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em>Ham on Rye&lt;/em> is one of my favorite books. I consider it one of his best works and surely one of the greatest novels in all literature.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A ham on rye sandwich is about the simplest thing an American can eat. Ditto Bukowski&amp;rsquo;s writings are as simple as you get.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The leading rye-producing states in the US are the Dakotas, Nebraska, Minnesota, and Georgia. &amp;lt;50% of the rye grown in the US is harvested for grain, with the rest used as pasture/hay or as a cover crop. ~50% of the amount harvested for grain is fed to livestock or exported, and the remainder is used for distilling, food, and seed. In the Midwest, rye is primarily grown for grain, but occasionally for hay/pasture.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For generations, ham on rye was the proletarian sandwich of choice in the Midwest (pastrami on rye in New York). Rye bread was part of the sacred Midwestern German-American trinity: sauerkraut, dill pickles and chewy rye with caraway seeds. Mothers in America made sandwiches for their kids to take to school, and a ham on rye was what kids would eat. It&amp;rsquo;s boring, but flavorful and filling.&lt;/p>
&lt;div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
&lt;iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/SPkZbJAP7Zc" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video">&lt;/iframe>
&lt;/div>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;Who the hell invented the sandwich? They should write a book about him.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>a fat guy at The Golden Horn in the movie &lt;em>&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SPkZbJAP7Zc">Barfly&lt;/a>&lt;/em> (1987)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;Hamming it up&amp;rdquo; means to overdo something, especially in acting. Bukowski&amp;rsquo;s book has little to do with the sandwich. I interpret the &amp;ldquo;ham&amp;rdquo; as a metaphor for the neon (pretense, not kosher), which he contrasted with the plain humble staple &amp;ldquo;rye,&amp;rdquo; to squeeze all of the pretense out of his life.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="the-rye-pyramid">The rye pyramid&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>In my mind, there are generally 3 categories of rye breads, based on the percentage of rye they have.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Brick ryes&lt;/strong> (&amp;gt;=66% rye): these breads are dense and brick-like; made completely or mostly from rye (rye flour, soaked rye, or cracked rye); leavened with rye levain; very sticky, must be mixed with a paddle; soft, despite the lack of wheat flour.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;em>walliserbrot&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;em>roggenbrot&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;em>gersterbrot&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;em>vollkornbrot&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;em>pumpernickel&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;em>borodinsky&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;em>rugbrød&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;em>rupjmaize&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;em>ruisleipä&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Intermediate ryes&lt;/strong> (30%-65% rye): these breads have a solid backbone of wheat, with varying degrees of rye, making them something akin to farmers' breads but with more rye and less wheat; they are distinctly chewy and flavorful.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;em>kornbroyt&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;em>pain de seigle&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;em>pain de méteil&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Rye-flavored breads&lt;/strong> (&amp;lt;30% rye): the bulk of the flour in these breads is wheat; the wheat provides structure, while the rye adds flavor.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;em>landbrot&lt;/em> (country bread)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;em>bauernbrot&lt;/em> (farmer&amp;rsquo;s bread)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>In this category, there is a sub-group of enriched, flavored ryes (usually &amp;lt;15% rye) that became quite popular in America in the last century or so:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>American &lt;em>pumpernickel&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Jewish deli rye&lt;/li>
&lt;li>marbled rye (the combination of American &lt;em>pumpernickel&lt;/em> and Jewish deli rye)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>onion rye&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>There is another sub-group of lean ryes (&amp;lt;10%) such as the San Francisco Sourdough that add rye for some rustic nuance but I don&amp;rsquo;t consider them to be rye breads.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="the-american-bastardization-of-rye">The American bastardization of rye&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>As a matter of fact, the so-called Jewish rye bread found in a contemporary Jewish bakery or delicatessen is &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/attack-of-the-ryeclops">an American invention&lt;/a> &amp;ndash; an American bastardization of a European rye. It&amp;rsquo;s a light, mild rye loaf made with a large amount of wheat flour and seasoned with caraway seeds, lacking the intensity of Minsk rye and Bavarian rye. It was popularized by Jewish delicatessens, but it&amp;rsquo;s not specific to the Jewish tradition, unlike &lt;em>challah&lt;/em> or &lt;em>matzah&lt;/em>. IMO, it&amp;rsquo;s as Jewish as General Tso&amp;rsquo;s chicken is Chinese.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Rye is the main cereal crop in those areas of Eastern Europe most densely populated by Jews and was correspondingly cheap, especially compared with wheat. Rye has been a staple ingredient of vodkas for centuries.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Over there, the most common type of rye bread &amp;ndash; the one with the highest proportion of rye &amp;ndash; was called &lt;em>razeve broyt&lt;/em>, literally &amp;ldquo;black bread.&amp;rdquo; It was usually prepared at home, and consisted of as much rye flour as the bread could bear. The Yiddish writer and scholar Hirsh Abramovitch, who was born in 1881, described making such bread from single-grind rye flour, as follows:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>The whole kernel was used &amp;ndash; the bran, the starch, the germ, and everything else. Some flour and warm water were mixed together in a kneading trough and left to stand overnight, covered with a tablecloth which was covered in turn with a fur coat or a pillow. The warmth made the mixture start to ferment. Sometime before dawn, the sourdough was kneaded by hand for about three-quarters of an hour, while more flour and water were added. Once everything was thoroughly mixed, the trough was covered up again and left to stand somewhere warm for four or five hours until the mixture had risen, when it would be formed into loaves of between fifteen and twenty-five pounds. &amp;hellip; The loaves would sit in the oven for four to six hours, depending on their size. Women who didn&amp;rsquo;t want the tops of their loaves to be black would sift rye flour in a thick sieve, mix the sifted flour with water, and smear it on the tops of the loaves before putting them into the oven. &amp;hellip; They called this mixture &lt;em>kharmushke&lt;/em>; it gave the bread a &amp;ldquo;Jewish look,&amp;rdquo; in contrast to gentile bread, which was &amp;ldquo;as black as coal.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Michael Wex, &lt;em>Rhapsody in Schmaltz&lt;/em> (2016)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>This doesn&amp;rsquo;t even remotely resemble the wheaty light rye served in most Jewish delis today. Although people in the old days may have guts of iron rather than abs of steel, eating these dense rye bricks (allegedly 2 lbs. a day on average!) was hardly a lifestyle choice. &lt;em>Razeve broyt&lt;/em> was the food of poverty &amp;ndash; the most fundamental food that was available to everyone. The poorest people would stretch their rye flour by grating potatoes into it, and unwillingly eat the bread &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ea6OET3Zi20">dry&lt;/a>.&amp;rdquo; White bread was considered a luxury, and many Jews started switching to the lighter, more wheaty bread as soon as they could afford it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As a matter of historical fact, wherever in Europe Jews settled, they adopted the local breads and slightly modified them to reflect the strictures of &lt;em>kashrut&lt;/em>. Therefore, the dark, sweet-sour ryes of Lithuania are every bit as Jewish as the light caraway-flecked ryes of southern Poland and Ukraine. The rye breads that managed to survive the journey to America, with the thousands of Jewish immigrants at the beginning of the 20th century, were those that best lent themselves to American conditions, namely, lower-percentage ryes that took advantage of the cheaper, easier-to-handle, and more abundant wheat that Eastern European Jewish bakers found when they arrived. The high-percentage ryes that represented the taste of home for Jews from Lithuania, Belarus and northern Poland had morphed into something new and uniquely American by the end of World War II. To mask the change, immigrant bakers loaded their breads with caraway seeds, which lent baked goods a fleeting flavor of anise/licorice.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="the-regression-of-jewish-deli-rye">The regression of Jewish deli rye&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The Jewish rye that caught on in the US &amp;ndash; the iconic bookends for pastrami &amp;ndash; probably began as some variation on the &lt;em>kornbroyt&lt;/em>. The OG unadulterated &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->&lt;em>kornbroyt&lt;/em>&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --> originated in central Europe, where &amp;ldquo;korn&amp;rdquo; is not maize/corn, but &lt;a href="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/%D7%A7%D7%90%D6%B8%D7%A8%D7%9F#Yiddish">Old High German&lt;/a> for &amp;ldquo;grain,&amp;rdquo; which in bread almost always refers to rye, and &amp;ldquo;broyt&amp;rdquo; is derived from Old High German &amp;ldquo;brōt,&amp;rdquo; meaning a loaf of bread. &lt;em>Kornbroyt&lt;/em> (literally &amp;ldquo;rye bread,&amp;rdquo; but nowadays often referred to as &amp;ldquo;Jewish corn rye&amp;rdquo;) is traditionally a heavy sourdough loaf built on a solid backbone of wheat, 30%-60% rye, and no maize/corn at all. It&amp;rsquo;s akin to farmer&amp;rsquo;s breads but with less wheat; it has a distinct chewiness and depth of flavor. As in &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/attack-of-the-ryeclops">Scandinavian &lt;em>smørrebrød&lt;/em>&lt;/a>, the peppery earthiness of rye pairs marvelously with rich and savory fillings like chopped livers, pastrami, and kosher salami.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Obviously, &lt;em>kornbroyt&lt;/em> was one of the building blocks of the Jewish-American bread microcosm. In the early Jewish deli rye inspired by the &lt;em>kornbroyt&lt;/em>, 30%-40% of the total flour was either medium rye (~85% extraction) or white rye (65%-70% extraction, with the bran and germ removed), and the rest was wheat flour. The blend lets the rye shine through without taking over. The whiter the rye, the milder the flavor &amp;ndash; sometimes just a hint of rye.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>By mid-20th century, an even lighter (~20% rye), mildly tangy, &amp;ldquo;shissel&amp;rdquo; (Yiddish for caraway, also spelt &amp;ldquo;sissel&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;cissel&amp;rdquo;) rye bread had swept across the US like wildfire. It&amp;rsquo;s fluffier, whiter, and less crusty than the old-fashioned 40% version, but closer to American-style white bread. It&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Jewish&amp;rdquo; because one could routinely find it on the shelves of the bakeries and delis that anchored Jewish settlements in major US cities and wherever else they established communities.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This &amp;ldquo;Jewish deli rye&amp;rdquo; became the American default, towering over other American rye breads such as sweet earthy &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->&lt;a href="https://www.allneedfulthings.net/NT_Breads/Old_Milwaukee_Rye.html">Old Milwaukee Rye&lt;/a>&lt;sup id="fnref:2">&lt;a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->, austere &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->Dakota rye&lt;sup id="fnref:3">&lt;a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">3&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->, and &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->Boston brown bread&lt;sup id="fnref:4">&lt;a href="#fn:4" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">4&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->, all of which use at least &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/joeliath/">1/3 rye&lt;/a>. Its popularity probably contributed to people&amp;rsquo;s biggest misconception about rye bread: rye = caraway. Rye has &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/attack-of-the-ryeclops">so many faces, possibilities, and flavor elements&lt;/a> that to denigrate it to that one astringent note is to do it a tremendous injustice. People who think they don&amp;rsquo;t like rye probably just don&amp;rsquo;t like caraway.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Unfortunately, in today&amp;rsquo;s delis, a 20% rye begrudgingly tossed with a tiny amount of &lt;em>shissel&lt;/em> is considered the standard of good deli rye &amp;ndash; and even such a loaf is hard to find these days. The Jewish deli rye at Zingerman&amp;rsquo;s, reputedly &lt;a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120305231242/http://www.saveur.com/article/Travels/best-rye-breads-in-america">America&amp;rsquo;s very best deli rye&lt;/a>, contains ~25% rye. By contrast, most commercial Jewish rye breads have &amp;lt;= 5% rye and rarely come with any &lt;em>shissel&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The shift came about during the post-WWII years, when white flour became cheaper, and easier to work with, than rye flour. The modern &amp;ldquo;rye&amp;rdquo; bread didn&amp;rsquo;t just lack in flavor and quality compared to traditional Jewish rye loaves: It was cheaper and lasted longer. In the 1960s-70s, industrial bakeries, such as Levy&amp;rsquo;s in Brooklyn, hooked many &lt;a href="https://forward.com/culture/482193/levys-jewish-rye-you-dont-have-to-be-jewish-model-joseph-attean-native/">conspicuously non-Jewish&lt;/a> New Yorkers on the taste of a packaged rye bread (pasteurized for a longer shelf life), with the &lt;a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2014/01/12/business/judy-protas-writer-of-slogan-for-levys-real-jewish-rye-dies-at-91.html?_r=0">viral slogan&lt;/a> &amp;ldquo;You don&amp;rsquo;t have to be Jewish to love Levy&amp;rsquo;s Real Jewish Rye.&amp;rdquo; That was a watershed moment. As independent Jewish bakeries failed to beat their larger, industrial competition, quality rye bread disappeared from delis.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/kornerstone/Levys-jewish-rye-walmart.png"
alt="Levy&amp;#39;s Real Jewish Rye"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Levy&amp;rsquo;s Real Jewish Rye (from Walmart)&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Over the past 40-50 years, according to Stan Ginsberg and Norm Berg in their book &lt;em>Inside the Jewish Bakery&lt;/em>, the flavor and texture of commercial rye bread have been drastically watered down as baking companies went national &amp;ndash; and Americanized with it. Rye bread became paler and lighter in texture, with less and less rye flour and more and more additives (oils, conditioners, and preservatives). Commercial bakeries also started using commercial dry yeast instead of sourdough; the latter takes too long (as time has become the most precious commodity) and, for a long time, wasn&amp;rsquo;t generally considered reliable or controlled enough a process for mass production &amp;ndash; probably not good for FDA and local health inspectors, either. So most commercial rye bread lacks the true rye sour starter flavor, and is no longer naturally chewy or dark. Or crusty.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The Jewish delicatessens of New York are often sacrosanct institutions. Landmarks like Katz&amp;rsquo;s, Carnegie Deli, and 2nd Ave Deli serve up lovingly spiced pastrami and corned beef, but their bread is a disgrace. There, I said it! Rye at these &amp;ldquo;legendary&amp;rdquo; NYC delis is shoddy slices of dry, thin, bland, and oftentimes stale white bread that pass for Jewish rye by default, similar to the way DiGiorno can technically be called pizza.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Orwasher&amp;rsquo;s, one of NYC&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ChZ4ZBQ1dkQ">most legendary&lt;/a> bakeries, still make 10-lb. loaves of &lt;em>shissel&lt;/em> rye daily, and customers can buy as much or as little as they need.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/kornerstone/Orwashers-community-rye_2022-06-17.png"
alt="Orwasher&amp;#39;s community rye in 2022"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Orwasher&amp;rsquo;s community rye in 2022, on UberEats.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The original Orwasher&amp;rsquo;s opened in 1916 on East 78th Street between 1st and 2nd Avenues, by a Hungarian immigrant named Abraham Orwasher, when a stretch of Yorkville used to be known as &amp;ldquo;Little Hungary.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Under current owner Keith Cohen, who took over in 2007, the bakery has become more internationally-focused (i.e. more French baguettes and brioches, and American-style white bread) while maintaining its mom-and-pop feel. They have paid heed to the &amp;ldquo;local movement&amp;rdquo; (who hasn&amp;rsquo;t?) by incorporating regionally-grown grains.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Cohen has pushed hard to build out the distribution arm of the business, and the bakery now churns out ~10,000 loaves a day and sells to 100+ different places around NYC. Cohen &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=yfrOH5OwKBk&amp;amp;t=270s">says&lt;/a> Orwasher&amp;rsquo;s still makes its rye bread from an OG rye sour starter that hasn&amp;rsquo;t been remade in 100+ years, but the bakery&amp;rsquo;s rye bread is no longer what it was.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Cohen published &lt;em>Orwasher&amp;rsquo;s Artisan Bread&lt;/em> in 2014. Out of curiosity, I looked it up. Bingo, the book has a recipe for the bakery&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;New York rye bread.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/kornerstone/NY_Rye_Orwashers_Artisan_Bread_2014.png"
alt="book recipe for Orwasher&amp;#39;s NY classic deli rye"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Recipe for Orwasher&amp;rsquo;s NY classic deli rye, published in &amp;lsquo;Orwasher&amp;rsquo;s Artisan Bread&amp;rsquo; (2014)&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The recipe doesn&amp;rsquo;t list any rye flour as an ingredient, but does call for a &amp;ldquo;rye biga.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The book says the bakery keeps two rye bigas: one white at 46% hydration and one dark at 133% hydration. I would guess that the dark rye biga is built with dark rye flour, which is usually a wholegrain (100% extraction) flour complete with all the bran and germ; and the white rye biga is built with all-purpose rye flour (65%-70% extraction, with the bran and germ removed).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The book specifies &amp;ldquo;white rye biga&amp;rdquo; as such wherever it&amp;rsquo;s called. Elsewhere, it lists simply &amp;ldquo;rye biga,&amp;rdquo; such as in this recipe. I&amp;rsquo;m assuming it either refers to the dark rye biga by default or they are meant to be interchangeable.&lt;/p>
&lt;pre tabindex="0">&lt;code>453.6g of dark rye biga (133% hydration) = 194.6g dark rye flour + 259g water
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;p>This means the total amount of (dark) rye present in the entire loaf is&lt;/p>
&lt;pre tabindex="0">&lt;code>194.6g / (194.6g + 1110g) = 14.9%
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/kornerstone/NY_Rye_photo_Orwashers_Artisan_Bread_2014.png"
alt="book photo for Orwasher&amp;#39;s NY classic deli rye"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Photo for Orwasher&amp;rsquo;s NY classic deli rye, published in &amp;lsquo;Orwasher&amp;rsquo;s Artisan Bread&amp;rsquo; (2014)&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>But in case it uses the white rye biga,&lt;/p>
&lt;pre tabindex="0">&lt;code>453.6g of white rye biga (46% hydration) = 310.6 white rye flour + 143g water
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;p>The total amount of (white) rye present in the entire loaf would be&lt;/p>
&lt;pre tabindex="0">&lt;code>310.6g / (310.6g + 1110g) = 21.9%
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;p>Even if this &amp;ldquo;rye biga&amp;rdquo; turns out to be a blend of the dark and the white, you know the range of rye percentages in Orwasher&amp;rsquo;s NY rye bread: &lt;code>14.9% dark rye&lt;/code> ~ &lt;code>21.9% white rye&lt;/code>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>And caraway is a skimpy 4% of the total flour weight. That will probably get even skimpier given the caraway shortage caused by Covid-related supply disruptions.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/kornerstone/Orwashers-rye-2019.png"
alt="Orwasher&amp;#39;s NY classic deli rye in 2019"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Orwasher&amp;rsquo;s NY classic deli rye in 2019&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/kornerstone/Orwashers_rye_bread_UberEats_20220617.png"
alt="Orwasher&amp;#39;s NY classic deli rye in 2022"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Orwasher&amp;rsquo;s NY classic deli rye in 2022, on UberEats.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>I guess trying to run the business as a bakery, sandwich shop and café simultaneously that serves breakfast, lunch and dinner has diluted the quality of the oldie that made it famous. Still, kudos to Orwasher&amp;rsquo;s for being able to pay Manhattan rents every month and stay in business for 100+ years.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>On weekends, Orwasher&amp;rsquo;s also makes a postmodern &amp;ldquo;corn rye&amp;rdquo; with a local spin, using local Sixpoint Brewery&amp;rsquo;s Righteous Rye Ale in the dough.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/kornerstone/Corn_Rye_Orwashers_Artisan_Bread_2014.png"
alt="book recipe for Orwasher&amp;#39;s corn rye"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Recipe for Orwasher&amp;rsquo;s corn rye, published in &amp;lsquo;Orwasher&amp;rsquo;s Artisan Bread&amp;rsquo; (2014)&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/kornerstone/Orwashers-righteous-rye_2022-06-17"
alt="Orwasher&amp;#39;s Righteous Rye bread in 2022"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Orwasher&amp;rsquo;s Righteous Rye bread in 2022, on UberEats.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>A traditionally made &lt;em>kornbroyt&lt;/em> is highly prized by Jewish bread aficionados today because 1) as George Greenstein says in his 1993 book, &lt;em>Secrets of a Jewish Baker&lt;/em>, &amp;ldquo;there are few bakeries left that haven&amp;rsquo;t compromised its real flavor, moisture, and texture&amp;rdquo;; and 2) in this hyper-Instagrammable era of openest-crumb breadporn and hypnotizing unicorn bagels, the rougher-textured, leathery-looking loaf still has the pull and tang of tradition that transcends time.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Jewish deli rye made with &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->&amp;gt;=20% of coarse rye flour&lt;sup id="fnref:5">&lt;a href="#fn:5" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">5&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --> hasn&amp;rsquo;t existed for years in NYC. Sadly, most New Yorkers don&amp;rsquo;t know the difference between good and &lt;a href="https://larissazimberoff.com/articles/2014/07/why-is-new-york-rye-bread-so-bad.html">bad rye bread&lt;/a>. They just firmly believe in the superiority of their ryes, and foolishly brag about the magic of &lt;a href="https://www.ediblemanhattan.com/food-for-thought/why-is-new-york-tap-water-good/">NYC tap water&lt;/a>, which they love to credit for bestowing everything from pizzas to bagels to coffee with the city&amp;rsquo;s unique flavor. Apparently, that holy water has done nothing to save NYC&amp;rsquo;s rye bread from condemnation.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The author Andrew Coe &lt;a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20141230123837/https://www.seriouseats.com/2014/06/rebuilding-the-jewish-bakery.html">explained&lt;/a> in a 2014 article:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;You may have never heard of Shissel Rye before &amp;ndash; it&amp;rsquo;s a bread that didn&amp;rsquo;t survive the softening and blandification of the New York rye tradition. &amp;ldquo;Shissel&amp;rdquo; means bowl in Yiddish, and maybe it&amp;rsquo;s so named because the loaf looks like an inverted bowl. From the outside, it&amp;rsquo;s easy to mistake it for a corn rye, because it has a similar leathery crust. But it&amp;rsquo;s made from wetter dough than corn rye, which gives the loaf a denser crumb and more pronounced sour twang.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Sure, there are dozens of new artisan bakeries that have tried to revive the real Deli rye bread and &lt;em>kornbroyt&lt;/em>. They are not rye bread as such, but &amp;ldquo;Old World&amp;rdquo; artisan wholegrain sourdough breads that seek to imitate &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WUxClvWBHtk">Poilâne&amp;rsquo;s legendarily crusty boules&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="heartland--jewish-soul-food-mecca">Heartland = Jewish soul food mecca&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Few have looked west and figured out &lt;a href="https://www.myjewishlearning.com/the-nosher/the-best-jewish-food-in-detroit/">the plethora of Jewish delis in Detroit&lt;/a> are some of America&amp;rsquo;s best-kept culinary secrets. That&amp;rsquo;s where the process of double-baking rye bread was pioneered and where legit Jewish rye breads are still made.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Jews have lived in Detroit for &amp;gt;200 years. The earliest Jewish immigrants were mostly German, but plenty of Hungarian, Russian, and Polish Jews settled in the Detroit-Ann Arbor-Ypsilanti area as well and brought their family recipes with them.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Many of the region&amp;rsquo;s early Jewish families opened grocery stores (Farmer Jack&amp;rsquo;s, Hiller&amp;rsquo;s, Freeman &amp;amp; Reese Grocers, etc.) and delis (Zingerman&amp;rsquo;s, the Stage Deli, etc). It was at the Stage Deli in Oak Park, in the post-WWII years when the composition of rye bread started incorporating larger and larger portions of cheaper and longer-lasting white flour, where the now-famed Detroit-style rye bread really began.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In the 1960s, Jack Goldberg, founder of the Stage Deli, was intent on serving the freshest rye bread to customers. Local bakeries delivered bread early in the morning, but most of Jack&amp;rsquo;s customers were coming in at lunch, when the rye bread they wanted was already cold. So he started ordering his rye bread partially cooked (baking halted ~80% of the way through). Just before the lunch rush, he would finish baking the bread in a steaming oven in house, so they were still warm in time for lunch. That last-minute steam gives the bread a soft, moist center and a crackly crispy crust. Additionally, forgoing the thin slicer that everyone else was using, Jack put the loaves on a deli meat slicer and cut the hot bread, fresh to order, into roughly 1&amp;quot; thick slices &amp;ndash; perfect for supporting the hulking pile of fatty meat without falling apart.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Most [sandwiches] are served on Jack Goldberg&amp;rsquo;s famous double-baked rye, a Detroit specialty. The rye in New York generally comes pre-sliced, in small disks about half an inch thick. The best deli ryes have a crisp, amber-colored crust and soft center, though these are increasingly difficult to find, especially in New York. Back when he started, Jack Goldberg pioneered the process of double-baking his rye breads. &amp;hellip; The warm loaf is cut into inch-thick slices on a diagonal. When you bite into a slice of double-baked rye, the difference in taste and texture is astounding. A thick, rustic crust greets your teeth, recalling the pleasurable chewiness of sourdough. The warm center of a double-baked rye has an airier density about it and doesn&amp;rsquo;t break apart when stressed with a Bye-Bye-Birdie (house-roasted turkey breast, chopped liver and Russian dressing). It makes New York&amp;rsquo;s rye taste like pigeon food.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>David Sax, &lt;em>Save the Deli&lt;/em> (2009)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Jack&amp;rsquo;s double-baked rye distinguished the Stage Deli from the competition. The method caught on, and soon enough every single Jewish deli across the Motor City was selling warm rye bread that held up well under pressure. Jack&amp;rsquo;s winning business formula is still used today at the Stage Deli in West Bloomfield.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The Stage Deli, along with other local joints like Steve&amp;rsquo;s Deli and the Bread Basket Deli, all use thick-cut rye that employs a decent amount of rye flour blended with the white flour, unlike most of the rye-less loaves in New York masquerading as Jewish rye.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>I first experienced double baked rye at the Bread Basket, a small chain of Detroit delicatessens, with Sy Ginsberg, the corned beef king of Michigan and much of the Midwest. As the waitress set down a sandwich of Ginsberg&amp;rsquo;s trademark corned beef in front of us, I was equally impressed with the bread. It had a darker flecked color to it, with a golden crust that reminded me of good sourdough. The crumb was warm to the touch, and the heat of the oven had released a tangy perfume of yeast. It felt like a little pillow in my hand, cradling the tender corned beef slicked with mustard. The crust had crackle and chew, the crumb was soft and doughy. It tasted like rye bread ought to.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>David Sax&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Those who grew up in eastern Missouri / southern Illinois would vividly recall the taste of &amp;ldquo;tzitzel&amp;rdquo; rye from Pratzel&amp;rsquo;s Bakery, the last Jewish-owned kosher bakery in St. Louis. This round caraway rye bread came coated in cornmeal, and was the pride of the bakery&amp;rsquo;s founders, who opened shop in ~1913, and of their successors who operated the business until 2011.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A 2011 book, &lt;em>From the Jewish Heartland: Two Centuries of Midwest Foodways&lt;/em>, by Ellen F. Steinberg and Jack H. Prost, includes a long interview with the descendants of Max Pratzel, with particular fervor about the &lt;em>tzitzel&lt;/em> rye, which also appears in many other food memories about this bakery.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.losttables.com/pratzels/pratzels.htm">Lost Tables&lt;/a>, an amazing website that chronicles lost restaurants in St. Louis, tells the story behind Pratzel&amp;rsquo;s rye:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Long before sourdough was a word associated with San Francisco, Jewish bakers were creating ryes and pumpernickel breads using sourdough starters they brought with them from Europe. When Max Pratzel came to St. Louis, he went to another Jewish baker and asked him for a small portion of his sour culture. Pratzel&amp;rsquo;s continued to grow that culture for almost 100 years and used it to make their rye bread.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Bakers used cornmeal to glide loaves in and out of the baking ovens. Nate Pratzel liked the taste of the cornmeal coated rye bread bottoms so much that he would cut them off and take them home. Eventually, it occurred to him that it might be a good idea to cover the entire loaf with cornmeal, which is how one of Pratzel&amp;rsquo;s bestseller, tzizel rye bread, was born.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Luckily, the sister site Lost Dishes has posted a &lt;a href="https://www.lostdishes.com/pratzels/tzizel.htm">recipe&lt;/a> for the &lt;em>tzitzel&lt;/em> rye, for anyone who&amp;rsquo;s interested. It&amp;rsquo;s from a &lt;a href="http://littlecreekpress.com/bookstore/manna-cafe-and-bakery-cookbooka-memoir-of-two-businesses-a-community-and-the-food-that-connected-them/">recent cookbook&lt;/a> by descendants of the Pratzel family who moved to Wisconsin, opened a bakery there, and shipped the tzizel rye bread to hungry former St. Louisans around the country. The bakery &lt;a href="https://www.northsidenews.org/manna-cafe-bakery-closes-after-15-years-nourishing-the-northside/">closed&lt;/a> in the midst of Covid, as the Pratzels were at the end of their lease and approaching their own retirement age.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Like everything else these days, Jewish deli rye &amp;ndash; like the bagel &amp;ndash; is becoming &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->an endangered species&lt;sup id="fnref:6">&lt;a href="#fn:6" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">6&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->, with fewer and fewer bakeries making it the traditional way.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="diy-old-school-deli-rye">DIY old-school deli rye&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>If you want a good deli rye, you gotta make it at home. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t take years to bake yourself a decent loaf of rye bread that tastes delicious and can stand up to corned beef. Your great-(great-etc.) grandmothers most likely didn&amp;rsquo;t apprentice at a Paris &lt;em>boulangrie&lt;/em> and still churned out great rye bread with whatever starters they had and kept going throughout some pretty challenging winters. I also highly doubt they had the luxury of building a sour culture meticulously with all kinds of grains à la Tartine, discarding &amp;gt;=90% of it, replenishing it with a new supply of flour, and letting it mature for the right number of days until it was ready to set up in loaves.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>You just have to be willing to experiment and fail a couple of times and pay attention to how it looks, feels, smells, and be willing to fiddle around and adjust the next time. Early delivery, continual improvement, and flexible adjustment, much like agile software development.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This rye I made is a variation of the old-school deli rye, closer to a &lt;em>kornbroyt&lt;/em> than a contemporary rye-flavored bread at delis.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/kornerstone/202206181714.jpg"
alt="kornerstone: Jewish deli rye"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>I used a whole lot of single-grind wholegrain rye flour: 30% of final flour weight, and 45% of total flour weight (including the levain).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Since this dough contains a relatively high percentage of whole grains, I used a 2-dough lamination method to make it stronger. It has &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/breadford-von-regrainton/">worked well&lt;/a> for me before. I was able to give it a long fermentation.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I also added some &amp;ldquo;altus,&amp;rdquo; which was originally a way for bakers to re-use bread they hadn&amp;rsquo;t sold. They would cut &amp;ldquo;old&amp;rdquo; rye bread into small pieces, soak in water until saturated and wrung out. It makes for a more tender and flavorful bread. I didn&amp;rsquo;t &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/zombie-dust/">soak my &amp;ldquo;old&amp;rdquo; rye bread&lt;/a> (you can use any type of bread); I just let it dry out a bit and ground it into crumbs in a coffee grinder.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Instead of caraway seeds, I used caramelized onions, spent brewer&amp;rsquo;s grains, and poppy seeds. If you are concerned about the opioids in poppy seeds, &lt;a href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fchem.2021.692045/full">studies&lt;/a> have shown that crushing and intensively cooking them significantly decrease their morphine content. Additionally, poppy seeds only truly develop their nutty flavor after crushing and baking.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The rye flour I used is freshly milled &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/files/danko-rye.pdf">Danko&lt;/a> (&lt;em>Dańkowskie Nowe&lt;/em> in Polish), which is a high-yielding winter rye developed in 1976 by the Poznań Plant Breeding Center in Poland, for the purpose of milling. It was bred from a lineage of northern European ryes known for their high starch content and excellent baking performance in traditional whole rye loaves. Quite a few &lt;a href="https://danko.pl/en/odmiany-categories/rye/">newer Dańkowskie varieties&lt;/a> have been developed since. Danko itself hails from Poland&amp;rsquo;s Warta River Valley and adapts well to the Mid-Atlantic climate. It has a floral aroma when freshly milled, and a good flavor balance between bready and spicy. (I haven&amp;rsquo;t been able to track down a &lt;a href="https://www.ryerevival.org/projects">Midwestern source&lt;/a> for Danko rye. If you know of any, &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/say-hi/">drop me a line&lt;/a>!)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Similar to how grape varietals and terroir influence the style and character of wines, so do varieties of rye &amp;ndash; and the soils and micro-climates they grow in. Rye whiskey derives its unique spicy and flavorful characteristics from the complexity of the grain. A traditional rye bread is definitively more flavorful than white bread. Many of the ryes that grow well in the US are old varieties brought over from Europe. There are also some newer hybrids that are being tested especially for local climate and soil conditions.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/kornerstone/202206191549.jpg"
alt="kornerstone: Jewish deli rye"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>As usual, I refreshed the levain 3 times with freshly milled wholegrain rye flour (80% hydration) over a period of 24 hours, and let it ferment at 60°F-70°F until it doubled in volume and was brimming with bubbles and a clean vinegary smell. Alternatively, you could sift the wholegrain rye into a medium rye flour and some coarse bits; use the former in the final dough, and feed the latter to the levain. You can manipulate the balance of acetic acid to lactic acid in the rye sour by changing the hydration: a dryer, more dough-like sour will contain more acetic acid and give a more vinegary flavor, while a wetter one (more like a thick paste at the start and a pancake batter once it&amp;rsquo;s developed) will tend more towards the lactic side and a yogurty/cheesy flavor.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>80% extraction wheat flour (Marquis - Anarchy Acres, WI)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>50%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>100% extraction wheat flour (Wisconsin #2 - Anarchy Acres, WI)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>15%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>100% extraction rye flour (Danko - Zeng Farm, NJ)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>30%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>old rye bread crumbs (aka. altus)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>cold water (50°F)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>92%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>rye levain (80% hydration)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>50%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>caramelized onions&lt;/td>
&lt;td>20%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>spent brewer&amp;rsquo;s grains&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Dutch blue poppy seeds, crushed (Savory Spice)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>kosher salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>America loves sweet onions! They are so popular that nowadays you can find them in any grocery store anytime of the year. I used a large Vidalia onion from a farmers' market. I cut the onion into medium-width slices, and cooked them on a George Foreman grill until brown and fragrant.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Dough #1: Autolyze the rye flour, whole wheat flour and breadcrumbs with just a little over half (~55%) of the total water. Mix thoroughly to hydrate every particle of the grain, cover, and leave for ~2 hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Dough #2: Mix together the 80% extraction wheat flour with the rest of the water. Cover and leave for ~2 hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Next, add equal portion of the levain and the salt to each dough. Mix or slap &amp;amp; fold for 5-10 mins. The wholegrain rye-wheat dough is weak and sticky, but it&amp;rsquo;s OK. The 80% extraction wheat flour dough should be strong and extensible.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Fold each dough 3 times in the next 2 hours, at 30-min intervals.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Now, the lamination: Wet your work surface with a spray bottle filled with water, to prevent the dough from sticking to it. Turn each dough out onto the damp surface, and gently spread it out as thinly and evenly as possible without tearing, into one large rectangle.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Carefully place the wholegrain rye-wheat dough on top of the other one. Try to line them up as much as possible.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Sprinkle all of the add-ins (onions, spent grains, and poppy seeds) all over the dough. Fold the dough into thirds (left-right, up-down) evenly and symmetrically to create the lamination and layer everything together.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Transfer the dough into a fridge to finish bulk fermentation overnight. I did take it out a few hours later to do another couple of coil-folds, and returned it to the fridge immediately after. Total bulk-fermentation: 2.5 hours at room temperature (~70°F) and 12 hours in the fridge (~40°F).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Next morning, take the dough out of the fridge. Mine doubled in volume overnight and felt so full of air pockets.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Pre-shape it loosely via a coil-fold. After a 30-min rest, shape the dough tightly into whatever form you desire. I shaped mine into a log, rolled it in additional onions and spent grains, and placed it in a parchment paper-lined loaf pan for final proof. You can, of course, roll the dough in a copious amount of caraway seeds or coarsely ground cornmeal.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>After 2 hours of final rise at room temperature, I baked it, as usual, in my ghetto toaster oven. The first 20 mins at 350°F, followed by another 30 mins at 300°F.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/kornerstone/202206181722.jpg"
alt="kornerstone: Jewish deli rye"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>It turned out a magnificent rye, without a fancy pizza stone or preheated Le Creuset Dutch oven.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/kornerstone/202206181715.jpg"
alt="kornerstone: Jewish deli rye"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>I waited 24 hours before cutting it. Patience is a virtue in short supply.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The crumb is highly moist and delicate. As soft as the finest goose down pillow.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/kornerstone/202206191228.jpg"
alt="kornerstone: Jewish deli rye"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>It tastes much bolder than a typical deli rye.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I like it toasted, smeared with cream cheese, and topped with olives.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>That tender crumb mingles marvelously with fatty, flaky corned beef, conjuring up a guilty pleasure so heavenly that it&amp;rsquo;s worth the heartburn.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/kornerstone/202206191239.jpg"
alt="kornerstone: Jewish deli rye"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>A real Jewish treat, before everyone became uber health-conscious, used to be a roast beef sandwich on rye with Bermuda onions and &lt;em>schmaltz&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The bread also pairs exquisitely with &lt;em>komijnekaas&lt;/em> (a classic Dutch gouda-style cheese seasoned with cumin and caraway seeds) or Veldhuizen&amp;rsquo;s caraway cheddar.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/kornerstone/202206191542.jpg"
alt="kornerstone: Jewish deli rye"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Bon appétit!&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>2022/12/31 update&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Just watched a Hallmark movie called &lt;em>Hanukkah on Rye&lt;/em>. All the sandwich breads featured in the movie looked so white that it made me think of this rye&amp;hellip; So I made another loaf &amp;ndash; with &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/attack-of-the-ryeclops">heritage Finnish rye&lt;/a>. I put some raw onions in the rye levain and added more caramelized onions to the final dough. Seriously onion-y.&lt;/p>
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>For recipes, see either &lt;em>Inside the Jewish Bakery: Recipes and Memories from the Golden Age of Jewish Baking&lt;/em> by Stanley Ginsberg and Norman Berg, or &lt;em>Secrets of a Jewish Baker&lt;/em> by George Greenstein.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>Bernard Clayton&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em>New Complete Book of Breads&lt;/em> includes a recipe for Old Milwaukee Rye, originally from Bernadine Landsberg of Milwaukee. Additionally, the 1st edition (2001-2002) of &lt;em>Home Cooking: Dickinson County Style&lt;/em> features a &lt;a href="https://cookingwithbarryandmeta.blogspot.com/2012/12/old-milwaukee-rye-bread.html">recipe&lt;/a> for Old Milwaukee Rye from Rethie Foster, who initially discovered this bread in the newspaper and it became a favorite.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:3" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>North Dakota is rye country as well as wheat country, a rich land where 19th-century Norwegian settlers come to life in Ole Edvart Rølvaag&amp;rsquo;s classic family saga, &lt;em>Giants in the Earth&lt;/em>. Dakota Harvest Bakers in Grand Forks, ND developed a quintessentially American interpretation of a traditional rye bread, for its Scandinavian-American customers who craved &amp;ldquo;bread like Nana used to make.&amp;rdquo; Stanley Ginsberg included a recipe in his 2016 book, &lt;em>The Rye Baker&lt;/em>.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:4" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>17th-century settlers in the Massachusetts Bay Colony tried to grow wheat, but the unfavorable climate and soil forced them to switch to rye.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:4" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:5" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>20% rye and 80% wheat is roughly the ratio that George Greenstein uses in his 1993 book, &lt;em>Secrets of a Jewish Baker&lt;/em>.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:5" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:6" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>See David Sax&amp;rsquo;s 2009 book, &lt;em>Save the Deli: In Search of Perfect Pastrami, Crusty Rye, and the Heart of Jewish Delicatessen&lt;/em>.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:6" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/section></content></item><item><title>Arctic Maplemoon</title><link>/posts/arctic-maplemoon/</link><pubDate>Fri, 14 Jan 2022 22:44:20 -0600</pubDate><guid>/posts/arctic-maplemoon/</guid><description>An oaty raisiny whole wheat bread, made with Québécois ingredients.</description><content>&lt;p>Just came back from a Christmas vacation in Québec, with a boatload of good memories and bagfuls of grains. Took the Old Canada Road Scenic Byway from Maine to Québec City, and felt like I had teleported across the Atlantic Ocean to Europe.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Québec sits just below the Arctic, which means it&amp;rsquo;s literally frozen half of the year. Holy shit, winter in Québec is cold &amp;ndash; temperatures could easily drop to -35°C (-31°F) with the windchill. I had to get a parka. But I love how Canadians like to one-up each other over how cold their town is, as if winter was an acquired taste.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>But Québec &amp;ndash; especially la Ville de Québec &amp;ndash; at Christmastime is a true winter wonderland, full of &lt;em>joie de vivre&lt;/em>. It&amp;rsquo;s like Québécois have perfected the art of winter aversion therapy.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Québec is quite different from the rest of Canada (sort of like Scotland vs. England, or Puerto Rico vs. the US mainland). It&amp;rsquo;s a wonder that they have stayed together for this long. Québec gets a bunch of benefits (e.g. tax revenue, currency, and a governmental framework) from Canada that its own constantly-impoverished legislature could never provide, and Canada gets to enjoy a slice of Europe in between Ontario and New Brunswick. Friends with benefits.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Au Québec, on parle français.&lt;/em> But my French is rusty. Québec&amp;rsquo;s language issues are too deep, and some places absolutely refuse to speak a word of English. I wanted to have a good time and experience Québec City like a local, so I brushed up on my &lt;em>français&lt;/em> before arriving.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Holy poutine, Montmorency Falls is actually taller than Niagara Falls and absolutely stunning &amp;ndash; even in the winter. The ice toboggan at Le Château Frontenac was incredibly thrilling and fun.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The two cornerstones of the Québécois cuisine are bread and meat (particularly pork), both of which I&amp;rsquo;m fond of. So I had the good fortune of sampling many local gourmet foods made by &lt;em>les artisans charcutiers&lt;/em> and &lt;em>les boulangers des grains nobles&lt;/em>. If you&amp;rsquo;ve never had &lt;em>saucissons&lt;/em> (&amp;ldquo;French salami&amp;rdquo;) from La Ferme des Quatre-Temps and Charcuterie Charlevoisienne, or cheeses from Fromagerie des Grondines and Laiterie Charlevoix, then you haven&amp;rsquo;t lived!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I found an interesting indie magazine on Québécois food culture, &lt;a href="https://cariboumag.com/">Caribou&lt;/a>. Oh, there&amp;rsquo;s also a 5-volume tome about the history of family cooking in Québec, &lt;em>Histoire de la cuisine familiale du Québec&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Given that Québec produces an overwhelming majority of the world&amp;rsquo;s maple syrup (&lt;em>sirop d&amp;rsquo;érable&lt;/em>), it&amp;rsquo;s not surprising Québécois drizzle maple syrup on everything, even the eggs.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Anyway, I brought back some La Meunerie Milanaise wheat berries. No clue what specific cultivar these wheat berries are, other than some kind of hard red wheat grown in Québec. The nutrition label says it has 11.11% protein.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>According to the Spring 2018 issue of Bread Lines, published by the Bread Baker&amp;rsquo;s Guild of America, La Milanaise whole wheat flour is a blend of hard red winter/spring wheats. The nutrition label says it has 11.67% protein. I doubt La Milanaise uses vastly different blends in its wheat berries and WW flours.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The way the grain industry works in Canada reminds me a lot of America&amp;rsquo;s three-tier system of alcohol distribution: producers sell only to processors, who then &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->sell only through their distributors&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->, and distributors sell only to businesses. You rarely know which specific farm the grains come from, let alone meeting the farmers. You can&amp;rsquo;t buy La Milanaise products directly from La Milanaise anymore. You gotta find them at local retailers or place special orders through Avril Supermarché Santé.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I confess I hesitated about buying these wheat berries because I didn&amp;rsquo;t know what cultivars they were or who grew them, which is against &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/about">my philosophy&lt;/a>, but I decided to fuck it because YOLO&amp;hellip;and it&amp;rsquo;s Canada where the face of flour is Robin Hood, owned by US multinational Cargill.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I also got some La Milanaise oat groats. Québec doesn&amp;rsquo;t exactly grow a lot of oats. There are &amp;gt;=30 organic oat producers in eastern Québec, mostly in Saguenay-Lac-Saint-Jean and Bas-Saint-Laurent, but altogether they produce just ~5% of Canada&amp;rsquo;s oats. The Prairies (especially Saskatchewan) produces 93%.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Obviously, Canada is great at growing oats, but not so great at processing them. Most of them are exported as raw commodities. &lt;a href="https://oatcanada.com/">Oat Canada&lt;/a> gets its crops from Alberta, but only &lt;em>after&lt;/em> the oats have been shipped to a facility in the US or Europe and processed into a concentrated protein powder. That&amp;rsquo;s the Canadian way.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Something else I learned about Québécois grains: a few decades ago, nobody believed that quality bread wheat could be grown in Québec. The hot, dry summers of Western Canada produced hard spring wheat, which yielded the ideal flour for bread.&lt;/p>
&lt;div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
&lt;iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/HHT86JsCpRI" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video">&lt;/iframe>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>Just before the turn of the millennium, the move towards artisan bread was starting to take hold in Québec. Bakers from France arrived in droves, and had an excruciatingly hard time producing French breads locally with the strong flours (~14% protein) milled from hard spring wheat. A growing demand thus emerged for a type of wheat that didn&amp;rsquo;t interest the Western Canadian farmers.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>La Milanaise, which started out as a mixed farming business in &lt;a href="https://lamilanaise.com/en/history/">the 1970s&lt;/a> in the village of Milan in the Estrie region, rose up to the challenge of filling that void. With strong government support, La Milanaise pioneered the organic grain industry in Québec and nurtured the province&amp;rsquo;s wheat culture. Québec now dominates organic farming growth in Canada, and produces winter wheat with far more complex aromas than spring wheat.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>La Milanaise has become a leading &lt;em>processor&lt;/em> of organic grains in Canada, exporting grain products to the US, Europe and Latin America. It sources &amp;gt;=60% of its grain from Québec farmers, and only purchases out West what cannot be grown locally. (Obviously, agriculture is heavily subsidized and protected by &lt;em>le gouvernement du Québec&lt;/em>.) It&amp;rsquo;s hard to tell which La Milanaise grains are grown in Québec and which are from elsewhere.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Additionally, La Milanaise has joined hands with Québécois bakery chain Première Moisson to found another mill, &lt;a href="https://moulinsdesoulanges.com/language/en/home/">Les Moulins de Soulanges&lt;/a>, to develop specialty flours tailor-made to the needs of Québécois artisan bakers. Flours from La Milanaise are featured in Daniel Leader&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em>Local Breads&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;m not as keen on pre-milled flours as whole grains. But I did stop by Première Moisson (majority-owned by supermarket chain Metro since 2014) on Boulevard Lebourgneuf and got a WW buckwheat bread with Charlevoix hemp seeds. It was delicious and I felt fuckin' Canadian.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/arctic-maplemoon/202201091337a.jpg"
alt="Arctic Maplemoon"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>From Canada with love: Arctic Maplemoon, an oaty raisiny whole wheat bread.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>So I made a bread with La Milanaise grains:&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>whole wheat flour&lt;/td>
&lt;td>85%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>whole oat flour&lt;/td>
&lt;td>15%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>whole wheat levain&lt;/td>
&lt;td>45%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->water&lt;sup id="fnref:2">&lt;a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->&lt;/td>
&lt;td>95%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Grade A dark maple syrup (Escuminac)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>grey Guérande salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>raisins (&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->NaturellementBio&lt;sup id="fnref:3">&lt;a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">3&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>I did the usual 24-hour cold ferment.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The whole wheat flour milled from La Milanaise wheat berries is very soft, but not as &lt;em>rouge&lt;/em> as Turkey Red.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/arctic-maplemoon/202201091337c.jpg"
alt="Arctic Maplemoon"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The bread is very aromatic during and after baking. The crust smells like caramel, chocolate and roasted nuts. The crumb is light, open and soft.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/arctic-maplemoon/202201091338.jpg"
alt="Arctic Maplemoon"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>It tastes sweet and creamy, with some toasty wheatiness.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/arctic-maplemoon/202201091338c.jpg"
alt="Arctic Maplemoon"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Madame Benoît, a 20th-century Québécois food writer, once said:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;A recipe is only a theme, which an intelligent cook can play each time with a variation.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>I wholeheartedly agree with her.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/arctic-maplemoon/202201121944.jpg"
alt="Arctic Maplemoon"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Wholegrain rich sweet Hawaiian rolls served, using slight variations of the above recipe.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/arctic-maplemoon/202211190919.jpg"
alt="Arctic Maplemoon"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>La Milanaise whole wheat rolls, ready to go into the air fryer.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>2022/12/23 - Round out the year with &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt15351648/">Three Pines&lt;/a>&amp;rdquo;, a deliciously moreish crime drama set in a small Québec village.&lt;/p>
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>A few small millers in Canada sell directly to consumers.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>Just plain h₂o. I did not bring back any fancy &amp;ldquo;vortex structured water&amp;rdquo; from Québec.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:3" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>Avril Supermarché Santé&amp;rsquo;s private brand. Avril recently invested in its private lines, including Rolland Naturellement (French and Spanish wines), NaturellementBio (canned &amp;amp; dried goods), and Naturellement Gourmet (specialty products like gelato, balsamic vinegar and maple syrup).&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/section></content></item><item><title>Squirrels Hoard</title><link>/posts/squirrels-hoard/</link><pubDate>Wed, 13 Oct 2021 22:33:41 -0600</pubDate><guid>/posts/squirrels-hoard/</guid><description>A forager&amp;rsquo;s bread, loaded with wild acorns, black walnuts, and hickory nuts.</description><content>&lt;p>Last few weeks I went on multiple wild food foraging expeditions. It was a blast. Came back with a boatload of pawpaws, acorns, hickory nuts, and black walnuts.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Acorns are not delicious right off the tree, which is likely what started the modern misconception that they are inedible. Acorns are definitely edible. They just require a process called &amp;ldquo;leaching&amp;rdquo; to remove the bitter tannins and become palatable, and all it takes is water and time. The internet has a ton of information on how to do that.&lt;/p>
&lt;div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
&lt;iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/4zyI6vn9Azg" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video">&lt;/iframe>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>Black walnuts are a pain in the butt to process. So I took the whole load to a local hulling station, and paid a small fee (60¢/lb) to have the black walnuts dehulled and cleaned. Just got a big sack of clean and dry whole black walnuts back. All I needed to do was crack the black walnuts and hickory nuts on my vintage metal nut cracker, and pick out the nut meat. A tedious yet meditative activity.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Once the acorns were done leaching and the nuts shelled, I wanted to make a bread to celebrate the beautiful season.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I came up with a Midwest Blend of heritage wheat flours:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>50% Red Fife (Anarchy Acres, WI): a HRSW first grown in Canada in 1842 by farmer David Fife; aka. the OG Canadian Wheat&lt;/li>
&lt;li>30% Turkey Red (Ben Penner Farms, MN): a beautiful HRWW, as &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/the-wheatwalker/">previously demonstrated&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>20% Goldcoin (Anarchy Acres, WI): a SWWW with &amp;lt;10% protein&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>After reading up on acorns, I decided to infuse them into the dough in 3 different ways:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>roasted acorn flour: dehydrate leached acorn meal, grind into a fine flour, and roast slowly in an oven until dark brown and caramelized (but not burnt)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>acorn levain: build a levain with leached wet acorn meal&lt;/li>
&lt;li>cream of acorn: cook leached acorn meal into a porridge, with flaxseeds, poppyseeds, chia seeds, and sunflower seeds&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>So, yeah, a boatload of acorns in this bread. Because, why not?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Formula for the dough:&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>88% extraction Midwest Blend heritage flour&lt;/td>
&lt;td>75%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>roasted acorn flour&lt;/td>
&lt;td>25%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>acorn levain&lt;/td>
&lt;td>40%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>cream of acorn&lt;/td>
&lt;td>30%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>h₂o&lt;/td>
&lt;td>83%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1.5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>hickory nuts, toasted&lt;/td>
&lt;td>7%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>black walnuts, toasted&lt;/td>
&lt;td>7%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>No autolyse. Simply mix everything together and cold-ferment for 44 hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/squirrels-hoard/202110121749.jpg"
alt="forager&amp;#39;s bread"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/squirrels-hoard/202110121750.jpg"
alt="forager&amp;#39;s bread"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/squirrels-hoard/202110121751.jpg"
alt="forager&amp;#39;s bread"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The baked bread took on a beautiful chocolate color with a purplish hue.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/squirrels-hoard/202110121132.jpg"
alt="forager&amp;#39;s bread"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The sweet nutty aroma was absolutely wonderful &amp;ndash; it reminded me of hazelnuts (or even nutella).&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/squirrels-hoard/202110121956.jpg"
alt="forager&amp;#39;s bread"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/squirrels-hoard/202110121957.jpg"
alt="forager&amp;#39;s bread"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The crumb was very moist, tender and custardy, yet still springy like a sponge cake.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It tasted totally different than how it smelt. The bold earthiness of the wild nuts dominated the flavor profile.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/squirrels-hoard/202110121131.jpg"
alt="forager&amp;#39;s bread"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Squirrels Hoard, a forager&amp;rsquo;s dream.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Only a mild sweet nutty flavor from the acorn, and a subtle hint of tang.&lt;/p></content></item><item><title>Madame Pepita Von Mustardshire</title><link>/posts/madame-pepita-von-mustardshire/</link><pubDate>Sat, 18 Sep 2021 22:02:10 -0600</pubDate><guid>/posts/madame-pepita-von-mustardshire/</guid><description>My scandalous twist on the German &lt;em>senfbrot&lt;/em>.</description><content>&lt;p>Baking a criminally un-German &lt;em>senfbrot&lt;/em> for Oktoberfest.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>80% extraction wheat flour (Java - Anarchy Acres, WI)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>85%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>100% extraction spelt flour (Oberkülmer - Tom and Mary Klein, OH)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>15%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>rye levain&lt;/td>
&lt;td>40%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>water&lt;/td>
&lt;td>80%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>hot jalapeño mustard (homemade)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>hickory smoked cheddar, grated (Tillamook)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>20%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>toasted pepita&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>toasted poppy seeds&lt;/td>
&lt;td>7%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>toasted mustard seeds&lt;/td>
&lt;td>3%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>24h+ cold ferment.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Brush the dough with mustard before baking.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/madame-pepita-von-mustardshire/202109181223.jpg"
alt="Madame Pepita Von Mustardshire"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/madame-pepita-von-mustardshire/202109181226.jpg"
alt="Madame Pepita Von Mustardshire"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Fiery and tasty, like gangbusters.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/madame-pepita-von-mustardshire/202109181129.jpg"
alt="Madame Pepita Von Mustardshire"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/madame-pepita-von-mustardshire/202109181351.jpg"
alt="Madame Pepita Von Mustardshire"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Madame Pepita Von Mustardshire, my criminally un-German senfbrot.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure></content></item><item><title>Cosmic Coconut</title><link>/posts/cosmic-coconut/</link><pubDate>Wed, 22 Apr 2020 21:25:44 -0500</pubDate><guid>/posts/cosmic-coconut/</guid><description>A resilience bread inspired by the Caribbean &lt;em>pan de coco&lt;/em>.</description><content>&lt;p>The first time I learned about fermentation was in Puerto Rico in 2017, shortly after Christmas. I traveled to the island a few months after Hurricane Maria. A lot of businesses on the island were closed, and people were running out of everything &amp;ndash; much like everywhere in the world right now, as a result of the Covid lockdown.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Back in Viejo San Juan, I stumbled across a community event on sustainable agriculture called Agro + Cultura. I hung out there all day as probably the only &amp;ldquo;no hablo español&amp;rdquo; attendee, and fumbled my way through a few classes on canning taught by the &lt;a href="https://archive.ph/0J0Dq">Queer Kitchen Brigade&lt;/a>. It was there and then that I made &lt;em>kimchi&lt;/em> for the first time in my life, and learned about the difference between pickling and fermentation. It didn&amp;rsquo;t click with me, until my contacts introduced me to a local politician (who was formerly a very high-ranking official at the broadly powerful &lt;em>Banco Gubernamental de Fomento para Puerto Rico&lt;/em>, a &lt;a href="https://archive.ph/lxHU6">driving force&lt;/a> behind Puerto Rico&amp;rsquo;s debt crisis). In private, he bashed solar energy and dismissed local grassroots agricultural resilience movements as &amp;ldquo;inefficient and ineffective,&amp;rdquo; and said the island &amp;ndash; which imports ~90% of its food and raw materials &amp;ndash; was &amp;ldquo;better off left alone to big corporations.&amp;rdquo; That was a wake-up call for me.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>That&amp;rsquo;s how I got interested in fermentation, as a way to preserve food and build resilience. I grew up with food insecurity. Even though I&amp;rsquo;m fortunate enough to have not experienced scarcity since college, I worry I could again someday.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Stories about bread lines outside food pantries across the country make me feel tremendously grateful to have learned different methods of food preservation during the golden age of American farming.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Over the last few years, America&amp;rsquo;s agricultural abundance allowed me to indulge my curiosity, fortuitously at a time when commodity and consumer prices hit a new decade low. I was completely unaware that the world economy was going through a mild recession in 2019. I was able to fill up my pantry with 25-lb. bags of miscellaneous organic (pseudo)grains &amp;ndash; wheat, rye, durum, buckwheat, teff, amaranth, quinoa, corn, barley, oat, millet, sorghum, etc. &amp;ndash; at rock-bottom prices, just a few months before Covid. I remember Aldi was selling 5-lb. bags of all purpose flour for ~$1 back then (it costs $2.12 as of November 2022). With so much grains on hand, I made a lot of rejuvelac and built a sourdough starter from scratch. That was the beginning of my breadmaking journey.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Breadbaking is one of those almost hypnotic businesses, like a dance from some ancient ceremony. It leaves you filled with one of the world&amp;rsquo;s sweetest smells&amp;hellip; There is no chiropractic treatment, no Yoga exercise, no hour of meditation in a music-throbbing chapel, that will leave you emptier of bad thoughts than this homely ceremony of making bread.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>M.F.K. Fisher, &lt;em>The Art of Eating&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Like Fisher, &amp;ldquo;I came to believe that since nobody else dared feed me as I wished to be fed, I must do it myself, and with as much aplomb as I could muster.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This bread is inspired by the Caribbean &lt;em>pan de coco&lt;/em>, to remind myself of that shock moment in Puerto Rico &amp;ndash; resilience is independence.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>G.Y.O.G. = Grind Your Own Grains&lt;/p>
&lt;p>B.Y.O.B. = Bake Your own Bread&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>80% extraction wheat flour (Bolles - Ben Penner Farms, MN)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>75%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>whole einkorn flour (Jovial)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>25%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>rye levain&lt;/td>
&lt;td>40%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>homemade coconut milk&lt;/td>
&lt;td>90%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>coconut pulp (strained from coconut milk)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>30%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>dates &amp;amp; raisins&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>walnuts, toasted&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Autolyze the flour with coconut milk. Add the levain and salt. Perform 5 folds during a 5-hour warm bulk-fermentation. Incorporate the dried fruits and most of the coconut pulp during the lamination fold. Shape and coat completely in grated coconut. Proof in the fridge for 12 hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I made a few ginormous loaves of this bread and gave all but one away.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The caramelized coconut-covered crust makes my mouth water.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/cosmic-coconut/202004211326.jpg"
alt="Cosmic Coconut"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/cosmic-coconut/202004211451c.jpg"
alt="Cosmic Coconut"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/cosmic-coconut/202004211329.jpg"
alt="Cosmic Coconut"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The crumb is soft and creamy. It tastes a little tangy, but nicely balanced by the sweetness of dried fruits.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/cosmic-coconut/202004211458a.jpg"
alt="Cosmic Coconut"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/cosmic-coconut/202004211456c.jpg"
alt="Cosmic Coconut"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Cosmic Coconut, a resilience bread inspired by the Caribbean pan de coco.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Bake your own f*cking bread, because resilience is independence.&lt;/p></content></item><item><title>Breadford von Regrainton</title><link>/posts/breadford-von-regrainton/</link><pubDate>Mon, 09 Dec 2019 16:41:45 -0800</pubDate><guid>/posts/breadford-von-regrainton/</guid><description>A hearty re-grained bread, made with spent grains and Glenn whole wheat flour.</description><content>&lt;p>I picked up a bag of Glenn wheat berries from Kenter Canyon Farms at the Atwater Village Farmers' Market in Los Angeles. It cost ~$2/lb, not cheap but not ridiculously overpriced either. The Glenn wheat was grown on Kenter Canyon Farms in Ventura County, along the south side of the Santa Clara River.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/files/Glenn.pdf">Glenn&lt;/a> is a modern HRSW developed by a NDSU breeding program to provide better scab resistance and higher yield. It was released by the North Dakota Agricultural Experiment Station in the spring of 2005. It has a fairly high protein content of 13%-14%. I have seen quite a few local and regional mills across the country label Glenn as a &amp;ldquo;heritage&amp;rdquo; wheat &amp;ndash; very curious.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I had long wanted to bake a &lt;em>treberbrot&lt;/em>, a hearty German bread made with the addition of spent grains from brewing beers. The spent grain adds some sweetness, texture and a lot of fiber to the bread.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/regrainton/201912082109.jpg"
alt="Breadford von Regrainton"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Breadford von Regrainton, a hearty re-grained bread that re-uses a lot of brewer&amp;rsquo;s spent grains.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>First, I milled the Glenn wheat berries, and &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/joeliath/">sifted&lt;/a> half into a 80% extraction flour, leaving the other half wholegrain (100% extraction).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Next, I built a levain with&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>sifted-out wheat bran; and&lt;/li>
&lt;li>a smooth purée of spent grains (from brewing Berliner Weiss) and &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fvtmBuTyu1c">boiled jackfruit seeds&lt;/a>.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>To make the dough stronger, I decided to use a 2-dough lamination method.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Dough #1:&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>80% extraction wheat flour (Glenn - Kenter Canyon Farms, CA)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>h&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->2&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->o&lt;/td>
&lt;td>85%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>bran levain&lt;/td>
&lt;td>40%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>This will be the stronger half of the dough that lifts the whole bread. You can totally swap water for beer here.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Dough #2:&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>whole wheat flour (Glenn - Kenter Canyon Farms, CA)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>h&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->2&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->o&lt;/td>
&lt;td>70%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>spent grain purée&lt;/td>
&lt;td>60%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>bran levain&lt;/td>
&lt;td>20%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>toasted flaxseeds&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>I mixed 1 part spent grains to 1 part water, and puréed the mixture in a blender. Then I autolyzed the flour, along with the flaxseeds, in this thick grainy smoothie diluted with water.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>With all of the wheat bran added back to the dough through the levain, this bread retains its whole-wheat integrity.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Add-ins:&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>spent grains&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sunflower seeds&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>roasted papaya seeds, ground&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>raisins&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.taste.com.au/quick-easy/articles/want-use-up-seeds/f45slcr4">Roasted papaya seeds&lt;/a> have a dark cocoa brown color and smell deeply aromatic. They taste like peppercorns.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I did 4 folds with each dough during the first 3 hours. Then I combined both doughs by gently stretching them out into big rectangles and placing dough #2 on top of dough #1. I sprinkled the add-ins during lamination.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The dough was bulk-fermented for 5 hours in total at room temperature, shaped into a taut boule (dusted with grated coconut), and then retarded at 40°F for 10 hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Next day, I let the dough warm up for a few hours until ~100% risen. I baked it on a shitty pizza pan in my ghetto toaster oven.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/regrainton/201912082113.jpg"
alt="Breadford von Regrainton"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>It grew so big during baking that it nearly filled up every cubic inch of the toaster oven!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The crust came out crispy and thin. The crumb is so freakin' airy.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/regrainton/201912082135.jpg"
alt="Breadford von Regrainton"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The taste is deeply flavorful with a mild tang and a subtle sweetness from spent grains and raisins.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/regrainton/201912091249.jpg"
alt="Breadford von Regrainton"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Superbly delightful.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>NGL, it tasted even better the next day.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/regrainton/201912091255.jpg"
alt="Breadford von Regrainton"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>A later variation:&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/regrainton/201912301643.jpg"
alt="Breadford von Regrainton"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Breadford von Regrainton v2.0, an incredibly flavorful re-grained bread that rises from dead spent grains.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Can&amp;rsquo;t believe it&amp;rsquo;s already December. Where did the year go?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In review, 2019 has been my Year of Fermentation. I read Sandor Katz&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em>The Art of Fermentation&lt;/em> and René Redzepi&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em>The Noma Guide to Fermentation.&lt;/em> I got into sourdough breadmaking (and bread chemistry) seriously for the firs time. I experimented audaciously with literally anything I could get my hands on: vegetables, beans, grains, milk, fish&amp;hellip; From lactic acid bacteria (LAB), I ventured into fungi &amp;ndash; koji (&lt;em>Aspergillus oryzae&lt;/em>) and tempeh (&lt;em>Rhizopus oligosporus&lt;/em>). It&amp;rsquo;s been a very memorable year and an unbelievably fulfilling one.&lt;/p></content></item></channel></rss>