<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>red fife on HERESY LEVAIN</title><link>/tags/red-fife/</link><description>Latest experiments in red fife from HERESY LEVAIN</description><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2023 HERESY LEVAIN 🍞 CC BY-NC-SA 4.0</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 08 Jan 2023 19:21:08 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/red-fife/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Singin' in ze Grain</title><link>/posts/singing-in-ze-grain/</link><pubDate>Sun, 08 Jan 2023 19:21:08 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/singing-in-ze-grain/</guid><description>45% heritage Sangaste rye + 45% heritage Red Fife wheat + 10% buckwheat, with Argentinian &lt;em>yerba maté&lt;/em> and lots of ancient grains &amp;amp; seeds.</description><content>&lt;p>A bunch of new construction homes are popping up across the road from the woods where I often go hiking. Realtors are trying to lure people in with a roadside ad, &amp;ldquo;Enjoyed the park? Why not live here?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I was just complaining the other day about how we had to drive increasingly longer and longer distances these days to get to a truly wild and natural park. More and more green space has been rezoned for residential housing development. Oftentimes I feel mankind has essentially been running a giant Ponzi scheme with Nature &amp;ndash; who might be &lt;a href="https://peaksurfer.blogspot.com/2022/12/who-is-sam-bankman-fried-of.html">the SBF of the ecological space&lt;/a>?&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>A person deals with the natural elements only through a set of technologies which is so complete that he is actually dealing with those technologies themselves. The natural environment itself disappears. We obviously have to make a comparison with the city, an essential product of technology. In the city, man perceives the natural elements only accidentally (parks, sidewalk trees). Nothing spontaneously natural is left here. And outside nature is reserved for spare time, relaxation, etc., given the decreasing importance of agriculture and the decline in the farming population.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Jacques Ellul, &lt;em>The Technological System&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Home prices have been falling&amp;hellip; 1 out of 3 real estate agents in the US couldn&amp;rsquo;t afford to pay rent in November. But when you go to Zillow and actually check the price history of almost any house on the market right now, you will see that current price drop looks like &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/files/Kovach-statement.pdf">a pimple on an elephant&amp;rsquo;s ass&lt;/a>.&amp;rdquo; The only good news is downpayment requirements are falling, too. Still, total cost of home ownership over a 25-year amortization is significantly higher. Few are advertising that fact.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Some quick mortgage math for Canadians: a C$1.5m mortgage at 3% APR with a 25-year amortization is C$86,141/year (C$2,151,545 total cost). A C$1.1m mortgage at 7% APR with a 25-year amortization is C$94,391/year (C$2,359,789 total cost). Housing prices need to drop a lot more.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Pending Home Sales in the United States decreased 37.80% year-on-year in November of 2022, the 18th straight month of declines and the biggest since November of 2021.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>National Association of Realtors&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>A ramification: Private Equity (PE) is going to see a massive write-down of its non-public assets in 2023, whether it&amp;rsquo;s residential real estate (RRE), commercial real estate (CRE), or venture capital (VC). Blackstone&amp;rsquo;s $68Bn &lt;a href="https://www.breit.com/portfolio/">BREIT&lt;/a> and Starwood&amp;rsquo;s $30Bn &lt;a href="https://www.starwoodnav.reit/portfolio/">SREIT&lt;/a> already froze withdrawals last month. This past week, BREIT got a &lt;a href="https://www.businesswire.com/news/home/20230103005410/en/UC-Investments-Creates-Strategic-Venture-with-Blackstone-to-Invest-4-Billion-in-BREIT-Common-Shares">$4Bn &amp;ldquo;Buffett-style&amp;rdquo; last-resort bailout&lt;/a> from the University of California. Given that Blackstone is the world largest institutional landlord, 2023 is off to an ominous start for the US CRE market.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Markdowns will be severe. This will lead to groupthink of re-evaluating the entire PE world. Not all PE is bad, but the decade-long pyramiding of real estate on ever lower interest rates has ended &amp;ndash; and that will bring a big markdown cycle. Opportunity always exists when the crowd thinks it knows an unknowable future.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Another surprise file will be the Pension Fund Bailout Act of 2023. The City of Chicago is the poster child for this phenomenon, but they are not alone. Pension Funds (PFs) have been gouging on PE and RE over the last decade. That horse is now dead, as the return of real interest rates and above-zero commercial papers crushes the valuations of these investments. Slowly at first, and then all of a sudden, the markdowns will rip holes in the PF balance sheets. The fact that the bulk of the boomers are now retiring is not going to help these PFs. (The tight labor market is partly due to early retirements.) As this pull-forward effect ripples through the PF world, more problems will surface and the cry for a bailout will intensify. Good luck to the bond market and RE market when the buyer from the last decade is now a seller. Prepare for &amp;ldquo;higher for longer&amp;rdquo; in the interest rate world as the demand for commercial papers drops &amp;ndash; especially in a negative-carry world. The current bond yield curve is toxic for leveraged financial positions.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A lot of ridiculous things happened in the last couple of years, e.g. cars launched into space for the memes, degenerates becoming millionaires overnight from their basement and then giving it all back. As the calendar turns to 2023, all those moments will be lost in time, like tears in the rain.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The Dominoes are starting to fall, e.g. &lt;a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/dereksaul/2023/01/05/silvergate-stock-crashes-nearly-50-as-bank-grapples-with-crypto-crisis/">Silvergate&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://www.amny.com/transit/ag-james-sues-auto-lender-credit-acceptance-corp-accuses-of-predatory-loans-and-securities-fraud/">Credit Acceptance Corporation&lt;/a> this past week. Bed Bath and Beyond is worried about &lt;a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2023/01/05/business/bed-bath-beyond-bankruptcy.html">a gloomier future&lt;/a>. &amp;ldquo;Slowly at first, then all of a sudden.&amp;rdquo; Second-tier financial institutions and sovereigns will be the trigger. The higher cost of capital is starting to filter into the financial economy, driving valuations lower and lower.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The layoffs in Tech Land are &lt;a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/05/amazon-to-cut-18000-jobs-as-tech-layoffs-continue/">just getting started&lt;/a>, as the seemingly unending stream of capital supporting profitless Ponzi tech is drying up.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>There has been too much money in finance and tech. There are some who can resist, but not many. Plenty of Harvard grads went on to Wall Street. What a waste. You need enough money to live, but how much is that? Which is precisely the point of &lt;a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt15255876/">&lt;em>Emily the Criminal&lt;/em>&lt;/a> &amp;ndash; Emily needs the money and she makes choices. The middle class has evaporated. And the truth is those at the bottom will do anything to survive. Desperate people do desperate things. Emily says you must make your own rules. You are either the boss or the employee (capital vs. labor). If you are the employee, you don&amp;rsquo;t have much power. Sure, there are unions. Then again, everybody agrees to arbitration and the company always wins and&amp;hellip;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Life is hard.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Yet people can still splurge $140 on a dozen &lt;a href="https://lastcrumb.com/">luxury cookies&lt;/a> and $100 on a single panettone. First-class flights from Zurich to Singapore are fully booked. Channel 2.55 bag went from $1600 in 2008 to $9000 in 2022. More draining in the financial ecosystem is on tap.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In &lt;a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt11564570/">&lt;em>Glass Onion&lt;/em>&lt;/a>, Benoit Blanc eventually figures out that the billionaire is just an idiot &amp;ndash; and he should have seen it all along.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Thoroughly caffeinated, I skimmed through Micheline Maynard&amp;rsquo;s new book, &lt;em>Satisfaction Guaranteed: How Zingerman&amp;rsquo;s Built a Corner Deli into a Global Food Community&lt;/em>. It&amp;rsquo;s one of those quintessential boomer hagiography-cum-business books. The author clearly admires Zingerman&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ndash; almost as much as Kamala Harris publicly idolizes civil rights lawyers &amp;ndash; and keeps comparing it to the world&amp;rsquo;s most successful companies, especially Toyota; whereas I find the niche store&amp;rsquo;s business model more clichéd than inspiring. The owners' purportedly unique &amp;ldquo;Visioning&amp;rdquo; process at ZingTrain, for example, recommends that your &amp;ldquo;effective vision&amp;rdquo; be &amp;ldquo;inspiring,&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;strategically sound,&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;written down,&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;communicated&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; four tenets that, on the whole, seem pretty stale. The same could be said about Zingerman&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;12 Natural Laws of Business,&amp;rdquo; which includes such banal points as &amp;ldquo;profit is good&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;greatness takes time.&amp;rdquo; One story I find particularly intriguing is how Zingerman&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href="https://www.michigandaily.com/uncategorized/campus-206/">handled competition&lt;/a> (e.g. Amer&amp;rsquo;s Mediterranean Deli) in the early years, given that 1) restaurant recipes are virtually never patentable, 2) restaurants have basically no &amp;ldquo;moats&amp;rdquo;, and 3) customer loyalty is fragile, particularly during difficult times. TBH, I find Zingerman&amp;rsquo;s mail-order bread a lot fresher than this book. Michigan has historically been hit hard by national recessions because the state&amp;rsquo;s economy (still) depends heavily on the auto industry and durable goods manufacturing, despite recent efforts to diversify. It would be interesting to see what happens in this round.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>There are only patterns. Patterns on top of patterns. Patterns that affect other patterns. Patterns hidden by patterns. Patterns within patterns. If you watch closely, history does nothing but repeat itself. What we call chaos is just patterns we haven&amp;rsquo;t recognized. What we call random is just patterns we can&amp;rsquo;t decipher. What we call nonsense is just patterns we can&amp;rsquo;t understand. What we call gibberish is just patterns we can&amp;rsquo;t read.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/singing-in-ze-grain/202301081352.jpg"
alt="Singin&amp;#39; in Ze Grain"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Singin' in ze grain&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>I made a bread inspired by German baker Tobias Exner&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em>Brandenburger Urkraft&lt;/em>, which he created together with Olympic canoe champion Sebastian Brendel.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="bran-levain">Bran levain&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>I milled some heritage Sangaste rye (45%), Red Fife wheat (45%), and buckwheat (10%).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I bolted the freshly milled wholegrain flours to remove some course bits (~17%), which I fed to the levain (~85% hydration) in 3 increments over 14 hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The sifted flours came out to be ~83% extraction. Every part of the grain will be re-combined in the final dough.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="altus-soaker">Altus soaker&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>I toasted a piece of day-old sourdough rye bread and ground it into breadcrumbs. I scooped some of the breadcrumbs (15% of final flour weight) into a bowl and poured an equal amount of hot water over it.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s % (of final flour weight)&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>old bread, toasted &amp;amp; ground&lt;/td>
&lt;td>15%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>hot water&lt;/td>
&lt;td>15%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>I covered the soaker and left it at room temperature for a few hours, and then moved it into the fridge overnight.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="grain-soaker">Grain soaker&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>The total amount of dry pseudo-grains used here came up to be 20% of final flour weight.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s % (of final flour weight)&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>quinoa (Bolivian royal white)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>kañiwa&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>amaranth (yellow foxtail)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>teff (brown)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>cool water&lt;/td>
&lt;td>40%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>I soaked the pseudo-grains in double the amount of water, and left them to sprout overnight.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="seeds--raisins">Seeds &amp;amp; raisins&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>I toasted the seeds (23% of final flour weight) until aromatic and very lightly browned.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s % (of final flour weight)&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sunflower seeds&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>pumpkin seeds&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>poppy seeds&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>nigella seeds&lt;/td>
&lt;td>3%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>In the meanwhile, I chopped up some Monukka raisins (5% of final flour weight) and set them aside.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s % (of final flour weight)&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>raisins&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;h4 id="final-dough">Final dough&lt;/h4>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>83% extraction rye flour (Sangaste - Laughing Wolf Farm, CO)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>45%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>83% extraction wheat flour (Red Fife - Merrylynd Organics, ON)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>45%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>83% extraction buckwheat flour (Merrylynd Organics, ON)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>freshly brewed &lt;em>yerba maté&lt;/em> (Liebig Original)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>102%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>bran levain&lt;/td>
&lt;td>40%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>altus soaker&lt;/td>
&lt;td>30%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>salt (Sal Marinho)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>chia seeds (black)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>flax seeds (brown)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>grain soaker&lt;/td>
&lt;td>60%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>toasted seeds&lt;/td>
&lt;td>23%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>raisins&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>I mixed the sifted flours, chia and flax seeds, and the altus soaker with 85% of the water, and left the mixture to autolyze for 30 mins. Then I added the levain and salt, and mixed for a few minutes. I let the dough rest for 10 mins, before adding the rest of the water slowly.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>At this point, I put the dough in the fridge. In the next 24 hours, I took the dough out of the fridge 6 times and gave it a coil-fold, adding some of the sprouted pseudo-grains, toasted seeds and raisins during each fold.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>After a 24-hour cold fermentation in the fridge, I shaped the dough, rolled it in extra sunflower seeds, and let it proof at room temperature for 3 hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Lastly, I baked it as usual, in my toaster oven.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/singing-in-ze-grain/202301081432.jpg"
alt="Singin&amp;#39; in ze Grain"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Like a bird singing in the rain, let grateful memories of forgotten foods survive in time of pain.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>I like the bread toasted, and paired with Kentucky old-school country ham.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This year, I hope to bake with more varieties of heritage grains. I would like to go into the woods more often and get to know more native plants before they disappear for good. And maybe I&amp;rsquo;ll try growing some peppers, too.&lt;/p></content></item><item><title>Squirrels Hoard</title><link>/posts/squirrels-hoard/</link><pubDate>Wed, 13 Oct 2021 22:33:41 -0600</pubDate><guid>/posts/squirrels-hoard/</guid><description>A forager&amp;rsquo;s bread, loaded with wild acorns, black walnuts, and hickory nuts.</description><content>&lt;p>Last few weeks I went on multiple wild food foraging expeditions. It was a blast. Came back with a boatload of pawpaws, acorns, hickory nuts, and black walnuts.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Acorns are not delicious right off the tree, which is likely what started the modern misconception that they are inedible. Acorns are definitely edible. They just require a process called &amp;ldquo;leaching&amp;rdquo; to remove the bitter tannins and become palatable, and all it takes is water and time. The internet has a ton of information on how to do that.&lt;/p>
&lt;div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
&lt;iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/4zyI6vn9Azg" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video">&lt;/iframe>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>Black walnuts are a pain in the butt to process. So I took the whole load to a local hulling station, and paid a small fee (60¢/lb) to have the black walnuts dehulled and cleaned. Just got a big sack of clean and dry whole black walnuts back. All I needed to do was crack the black walnuts and hickory nuts on my vintage metal nut cracker, and pick out the nut meat. A tedious yet meditative activity.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Once the acorns were done leaching and the nuts shelled, I wanted to make a bread to celebrate the beautiful season.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I came up with a Midwest Blend of heritage wheat flours:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>50% Red Fife (Anarchy Acres, WI): a HRSW first grown in Canada in 1842 by farmer David Fife; aka. the OG Canadian Wheat&lt;/li>
&lt;li>30% Turkey Red (Ben Penner Farms, MN): a beautiful HRWW, as &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/the-wheatwalker/">previously demonstrated&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>20% Goldcoin (Anarchy Acres, WI): a SWWW with &amp;lt;10% protein&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>After reading up on acorns, I decided to infuse them into the dough in 3 different ways:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>roasted acorn flour: dehydrate leached acorn meal, grind into a fine flour, and roast slowly in an oven until dark brown and caramelized (but not burnt)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>acorn levain: build a levain with leached wet acorn meal&lt;/li>
&lt;li>cream of acorn: cook leached acorn meal into a porridge, with flaxseeds, poppyseeds, chia seeds, and sunflower seeds&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>So, yeah, a boatload of acorns in this bread. Because, why not?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Formula for the dough:&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>88% extraction Midwest Blend heritage flour&lt;/td>
&lt;td>75%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>roasted acorn flour&lt;/td>
&lt;td>25%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>acorn levain&lt;/td>
&lt;td>40%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>cream of acorn&lt;/td>
&lt;td>30%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>h₂o&lt;/td>
&lt;td>83%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1.5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>hickory nuts, toasted&lt;/td>
&lt;td>7%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>black walnuts, toasted&lt;/td>
&lt;td>7%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>No autolyse. Simply mix everything together and cold-ferment for 44 hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/squirrels-hoard/202110121749.jpg"
alt="forager&amp;#39;s bread"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/squirrels-hoard/202110121750.jpg"
alt="forager&amp;#39;s bread"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/squirrels-hoard/202110121751.jpg"
alt="forager&amp;#39;s bread"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The baked bread took on a beautiful chocolate color with a purplish hue.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/squirrels-hoard/202110121132.jpg"
alt="forager&amp;#39;s bread"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The sweet nutty aroma was absolutely wonderful &amp;ndash; it reminded me of hazelnuts (or even nutella).&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/squirrels-hoard/202110121956.jpg"
alt="forager&amp;#39;s bread"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/squirrels-hoard/202110121957.jpg"
alt="forager&amp;#39;s bread"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The crumb was very moist, tender and custardy, yet still springy like a sponge cake.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It tasted totally different than how it smelt. The bold earthiness of the wild nuts dominated the flavor profile.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/squirrels-hoard/202110121131.jpg"
alt="forager&amp;#39;s bread"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Squirrels Hoard, a forager&amp;rsquo;s dream.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Only a mild sweet nutty flavor from the acorn, and a subtle hint of tang.&lt;/p></content></item></channel></rss>