<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>green tea on HERESY LEVAIN</title><link>/tags/green-tea/</link><description>Latest experiments in green tea from HERESY LEVAIN</description><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2023 HERESY LEVAIN 🍞 CC BY-NC-SA 4.0</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Dec 2020 17:41:59 -0600</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/green-tea/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Kyoto by Blimp</title><link>/posts/kyoto-by-blimp/</link><pubDate>Fri, 11 Dec 2020 17:41:59 -0600</pubDate><guid>/posts/kyoto-by-blimp/</guid><description>Marbled &lt;em>matcha&lt;/em> cocoa bread, made with Kyoto Uji &lt;em>matcha&lt;/em> and a blend of Southern flours. A kaleidoscope of fun flavors.</description><content>&lt;p>I love &lt;em>matcha&lt;/em> (抹茶), which is basically powdered green tea. Like anything in life, it&amp;rsquo;s an acquired taste. I hated bitter beers when I first tried them, but now I love the likes of Chimay Cinq Cents and Stone Ruination. If you&amp;rsquo;ve never had &lt;em>matcha&lt;/em> before, you will likely not love it the first time you try it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>So how is &lt;em>matcha&lt;/em> different from other green teas, you ask? Well, first of all, it differs in the preparation process. Most teas are infused with water and the leaves are strained out and discarded, whereas &lt;em>matcha&lt;/em> is actually whisked into hot water, i.e. the tea leaves are consumed directly.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Secondly, &lt;em>matcha&lt;/em> actually goes through extra processes during cultivation compared to the general category of green tea usually referred to as &lt;em>sencha&lt;/em> (煎茶, steamed, rolled, and dried green tea leaves). Once the buds of the &lt;em>Camellia sinensis&lt;/em> tea leaves start to sprout, the entire crop is kept in the shade for about a month before harvesting. This slows down the rate of photosynthesis, increasing the amount of chlorophyll in the leaves. In the end, this produces a tea leaf with a sweet flavor and bold &lt;em>umami&lt;/em>. Lastly, the steamed and then thoroughly dried tea leaves are meticulously ground on a stone mill into a fine powder. This powder form is what makes it possible to add a concentrated green tea flavor to many products.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The Chinese were the first to grow and grind green tea. However, the Japanese were the ones who invented the method of creating &lt;em>matcha&lt;/em> as we know it today.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Japanese tea cultivation started when a 12th-century monk named Myouan Eisai (明菴栄西) brought green tea seeds &amp;ndash; along with the Rinzai school of Zen Buddhism &amp;ndash; from China and planted them on Mt. Sefuri. In addition, he gave tea seeds to Myoue Shounin (明恵上人), a monk from Kousan-ji temple (高山寺) in Toganoo (栂尾), Kyoto. Shounin planted the seeds near the temple and &amp;ndash; voilà! &amp;ndash; this was the start of Uji tea. Oh, Eisai also wrote a book about tea, called Kissa Yojoki (喫茶養生記), often translated as &amp;ldquo;How to Stay Healthy by Drinking Tea.&amp;rdquo; The book begins with &amp;ldquo;Tea is the ultimate mental and medical remedy and has the ability to make one’s life more full and complete”.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For a long time, only the nobility and upper echelons of the Japanese society drank green tea. It was not until the Meiji Restoration at the end of the 19th century that the cultivation, consumption and preparation of green tea became widespread in Japan.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Modern Japan has developed the most advanced and refined industry for the cultivation of a few varieties of green tea. Furthermore, it&amp;rsquo;s the world&amp;rsquo;s second largest green tea producer after China. As green tea became more popular in the West over the last two decades, China has begun to produce more and more of its own &amp;ldquo;&lt;em>matcha&lt;/em>&amp;rdquo; under &amp;ldquo;simulated&amp;rdquo; Japanese farming conditions.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Like wine grapes, the quality and growth of green tea are greatly affected by the region&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em>terroir&lt;/em>. Being Japan&amp;rsquo;s oldest and most famous green tea region means Uji is inevitably a hot spot for tea tourism. People love to visit Kyoto tea country&amp;rsquo;s traditional tea shops and modern tea emporiums, stroll through rolling hills of tea fields, and sample a variety of teas. I know people who have travelled to Uji, Japan to taste &lt;em>matcha&lt;/em> and still feel only so-so about it. Lol.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>There is a Japanese proverb that says &amp;ldquo;good medication is bitter in taste&amp;rdquo; (良薬は口に苦し), and &lt;em>matcha&lt;/em> is one of them. Matcha has a unique, complex taste. It&amp;rsquo;s slightly bitter, with a sweet aftertaste; it&amp;rsquo;s buttery and nutty, with a seaweedy undertone.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>David&amp;rsquo;s Tea &lt;em>matcha&lt;/em> is a good place to start, although it&amp;rsquo;s likely not the best &lt;em>matcha&lt;/em> that you&amp;rsquo;ll ever have.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>One way to enjoy the mild bitterness of &lt;em>matcha&lt;/em> more is to add it to baked goods. Baking enhances the rich aroma of the &lt;em>matcha&lt;/em>, and that&amp;rsquo;s why there are gazillion forms of &lt;em>matcha&lt;/em>-flavored baked goods in Asia.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For this bread, I selected flours from below the Mason Dixon line. The American South is synonymous with sweet tea, and South Carolina remains the only US state that commercially produces tea on a large scale.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;Generally, soft wheats have a high starch yield on milling and a low protein content. They are grown in areas of high rainfall and lower soil fertility, primarily east of the Mississippi River. Low-protein southern flours are deployed to their best advantage in their growing region&amp;rsquo;s specialties-biscuits, pies, and cakes where tenderness is prized over strength. Beyond wheat&amp;rsquo;s given genetic quotient of hardness or softness, environmental conditions determine the hardness of any given crop. Not only the overall protein content but also the quality and specific amounts of each protein present can be affected by seasonal variations.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Joseph Amendola &amp;amp; Nicole Rees, &lt;em>Understanding Baking: The Art and Science of Baking&lt;/em>, 3rd edition, page 7.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Wheats grown in the South generally aren&amp;rsquo;t very strong. This bread is another reminder to pay attention to the quality and property of ingredients grown in a particular region.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="matcha-dough">Matcha dough&lt;/h4>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>88% extraction wheat flour (Rouge de Bordeaux - Dayspring Farms, GA)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;em>matcha&lt;/em>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>3%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>brewed &lt;em>genmaicha&lt;/em>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>80%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>The &lt;em>matcha&lt;/em> I used here is Marukyu-Koyamaen &lt;em>aoarashi matcha&lt;/em> (丸久小山園の抹茶青嵐). It&amp;rsquo;s an entry-grade &lt;em>matcha&lt;/em> with intense flavors &amp;ndash; better for baking than sipping.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>3% &lt;em>matcha&lt;/em> may seem too little, but &lt;em>matcha&lt;/em> is only consumed about 1-2g at a time. &lt;em>Usucha&lt;/em> (薄茶), the common &lt;em>matcha&lt;/em> preparation, usually calls for 1 tsp/2g of &lt;em>matcha&lt;/em> per 70-80ml of water.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Everyday/ceremonial (not cooking) &lt;em>matcha&lt;/em> is usually made from high-grade &lt;em>gyokuro&lt;/em> (玉露), not &lt;em>sencha&lt;/em>. But for cooking &lt;em>matcha&lt;/em>, you don&amp;rsquo;t need such high grade. You could technically make your own at home, by pulverizing some high-quality green tea leaves in a coffee grinder and sifting a few times to get a fine powder. It&amp;rsquo;s totally fine in lattes, smoothies and baked goods. Some heresy right here.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>So, wtf is &lt;em>genmaicha&lt;/em> and why did I use it instead of plain h₂o? Well, &lt;em>genmaicha&lt;/em> (玄米茶) is basically a Japanese popcorn tea: a blend of roasted puffed brown rice and &lt;em>sencha&lt;/em>. You taste green tea and popcorn at the same time &amp;ndash; the best of both worlds!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I wanted a robust green tea flavor in this bread. That&amp;rsquo;s why I brewed a pot of Ippodo&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em>genmaicha&lt;/em> and soaked the flour in the cooled tea.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Rouge de Bordeaux was the OG baguette wheat from the Bordeaux region of France. It gained popularity in the 19th century among artisan bakers who loved the smooth, mellow flavor, aroma of spices, and robust performance.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="cocoa-dough">Cocoa dough&lt;/h4>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>whole spelt flour (Sungold spelt - Grapewood Farm, VA)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>50%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>cornmeal (Bloody Butcher red corn - Five Maples Farm, VA)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>whole rye flour (Abruzzi rye - Carter Farms, NC)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>brown rice flour (Charleston Gold - Anson Mills, SC)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>whole pea flour (Sea Island red peas - Marsh Hen Mill, SC)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>roasted soybean flour (Maehara Seifun kuromame kinako - Tanba, Kyoto)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>cocoa powder (Pernigotti cacao amaro)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>h₂o&lt;/td>
&lt;td>90%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Spelt is an ancient wheat with a golden color and notes of honey and fresh hay. It&amp;rsquo;s quite versatile &amp;ndash; strong enough for bread and pasta, but delicate enough for pastry doughs, cakes and cookies.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Just mix everything together, and leave them in two separate containers in the fridge overnight. Yes, overnight autolyse.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Obviously, the green dough is going to be the stronger sibling and do most of the heavy-lifting.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Next day, I let them warm up to room temperature before adding 40% ripe levain and 2% salt. The green dough was very extensible and easy to work with. The cocoa dough, not so much.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I laminated both &lt;em>pâtes&lt;/em> together and added 10% toasted walnuts and 20% dried fruits (raisins, dates, and jujubes).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The dough went through 4 hours of bulk fermentation at room temperature with 3 folds, and had ~50% rise in volume before preshaping.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>2 hours of warm proof in a loaf pan before baking. Fantastic oven spring.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/kyoto-by-blimp/202012111150.jpg"
alt="85% extraction Turkey Red wheat bread"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Cooled overnight and sliced next morning.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The bread turned out less airy than I expected. The &lt;em>matcha&lt;/em> turned out more hydroscopic than I thought it would be, and the green &lt;em>pâte&lt;/em> was a little too taut. Next time I&amp;rsquo;ll definitely increase the hydration. The green tea flavor was noticeable but mellow.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The crumb was tender, moist, and mildly chewy. A taster said the sweet fruity aroma immediately reminded him of spiced apple cider!&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/kyoto-by-blimp/202012111327.jpg"
alt="85% extraction Turkey Red wheat bread"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>This one was a lot of fun to eat: one bite tasted tart like a granny smith apple, the next bite was reminiscent of a &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/shinsekai-ambrosia/">Lärabar&lt;/a>, yet the next brought to mind mocha, nougat, hazelnut&amp;hellip; A kaleidoscope of flavors.&lt;/p></content></item></channel></rss>