<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>high hydration on HERESY LEVAIN</title><link>/tags/high-hydration/</link><description>Latest experiments in high hydration from HERESY LEVAIN</description><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2023 HERESY LEVAIN 🍞 CC BY-NC-SA 4.0</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 25 Mar 2023 02:31:32 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/high-hydration/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>California Dreamin' #7: Desert Gold</title><link>/posts/california-dreamin-7/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Mar 2023 02:31:32 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/california-dreamin-7/</guid><description>[California Grain Adventure #7] &lt;em>Pane Ricco&lt;/em>, a luxuriously high-hydration bread with 100% wholegrain Desert Gold durum, sour cream, cracked black pepper, and salty addictive cheeses.</description><content>&lt;p>&lt;em>This is part 7 of my &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/california-grain-adventure/">California Grain Adventure&lt;/a>.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>The West begins where the average annual rainfall drops below twenty inches.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Bernard DeVoto&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>The Imperial Valley in southern California is often cited as a great example of modern desert agriculture.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>From what I&amp;rsquo;ve seen, the Imperial Valley is a place of jarring contrasts. Half of the valley remains in its natural state, aka. a bone-dry desert with some breathtaking sand dunes; the other half exemplifies a modern engineering marvel &amp;ndash; mile after mile of green fields lined by irrigation canals and sometimes shrouded by showers of water from sprinklers.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-7/california-imperial-valley.jpg"
alt="Map of Imperial Valley, California"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Imperial Valley is one of the oldest farming communities in the Colorado River basin. It lies in the Colorado Desert section of the Sonoran Desert, with overwhelming heat and meager average rainfall (about 3&amp;quot; or 76 mm per year). Dirt was carried here over millions of years by the Colorado River, as it carved the Grand Canyon ever deeper.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Thanks to irrigation &amp;ndash; that is, thanks to the US Bureau of Reclamation &amp;ndash; states such as California, Arizona, and Idaho became populous and wealthy; millions settled in regions where nature, left alone, would have countenanced thousands at best; great valleys and hemispherical basins metamorphosed from desert blonde to semi-tropical green.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Agriculture is the economic backbone of the Imperial Valley due to irrigation, which is supplied entirely from the Colorado River via the All-American Canal. Thousands of acres of prime farmland have transformed the desert into one of the most productive farming regions in California with an annual crop production of over $1 billion. Evidently, agriculture accounts for nearly half of all local employment.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-7/SaltonSeaArielFromSouth.jpg"
alt="Aerial view of Imperial Valley and Salton Sea"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Aerial view of the Imperial Valley and Salton Sea from the south.&lt;/p>&lt;p>Source: &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Imperial_Valley,_California#/media/File:SaltonSeaArielFromSouth.jpg" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">Samboy&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Unlike the Central Valley in the north which draws its water from rain and snow in the Sierra Mountains or pumps it from shrinking underground aquifers, the Imperial Valley has only one source of water: the Colorado River, 80 miles to the east.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The most basic principle governing water use in the western US is &amp;ldquo;first in time, first in right.&amp;rdquo; These lush fields in the Imperial Valley owe their existence to fortune-seeking land speculators and engineers who arrived early and, starting in 1901, dug the first canal to ship water here from the Colorado River. (Prior to the 20th century, this patch was mostly unsettled.) Since most of the Imperial Valley actually lies below sea level &amp;ndash; and well below the canal&amp;rsquo;s starting point on the Colorado River near Yuma, Arizona &amp;ndash; water is able to flow there by gravity alone.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Thanks to the stunning wealth that irrigation farming had produced, California came rolling out of the 1920s like Jay Gatsby in his alabaster phaeton. Agriculture was California; there were no sprawling defense and aerospace industries, no Silicon Valley.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The Salton Sea was an unfortunate consequence of the engineering failure that marked the construction of the original canal. The current canal, built during the New Deal and named the &lt;a href="https://www.iid.com/water/water-transportation-system/colorado-river-facilities/all-american-canal">All-American Canal&lt;/a>, began delivering water to the Imperial Valley in 1940; two years later, it became the sole water source for Imperial Valley&amp;rsquo;s residents and farmlands.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-7/ImperialValleyfromBC.jpg"
alt="The Imperial Valley from the highway between Tijuana and Mexicali"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Looking north at the Imperial Valley, from the highway between Tijuana and Mexicali.&lt;/p>&lt;p>Source: &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Imperial_Valley,_California#/media/File:ImperialValleyfromBC.jpg" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">CharismaticDespot&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Water delivered to the Imperial Irrigation District (IID) each year by the All-American Canal &amp;ndash; through a vast system of canals, dams, and pipelines &amp;ndash; is enough to cover the entire irrigated land, roughly 500,000 acres, with 5 feet of water.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Imported water and a long growing season allow two crop cycles each year; the Imperial Valley now supplies over 2/3 of winter fruits and vegetables, cotton, and grain for domestic and international markets. The valley also produces most of the lamb and sheep in the US. (This raises a bunch of uncomfortable questions: What&amp;rsquo;s the rest of America doing? Why is the whole nation dependent on a few hundred farms concentrated in an irrigated desert for its food? How did this situation come to be? What happened to Eliot Coleman&amp;rsquo;s four-season farming revolution? &amp;hellip; )&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>Alfalfa is the king crop produced in the Imperial Valley. 1 out of every 3 farmed acres in the valley is dedicated to growing alfalfa, which dries into a high-protein hay commonly used as food for livestock. It&amp;rsquo;s also one of the thirstiest drop; its deep roots sucking up water in a region scorched by a 22-year drought.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Another contradiction of California: How does irrigating alfalfa in 120°F temperatures in the dead of July make any sense at all?&lt;/p>
&lt;div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
&lt;iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/AYBZISNYk8I" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video">&lt;/iframe>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>The Imperial Valley&amp;rsquo;s alfalfa industry is not only one of the largest water users in the basin, but also one of the most powerful.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Large-scale production of water-gorging, low-value crops like alfalfa during a megadrought is possible only because the Imperial Valley is the single biggest controller of rights to Colorado River water and the IID farmers have access to cheap (subsidized) water.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Due to these massive irrigation projects, south of the canal, the Colorado River no longer flows above ground at all for much of the year into Mexico.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The Colorado River, which supplies freshwater to more than 40 million people in the southwestern US and northern Mexico, has been in rapid decline. Reduced snowpack, drought conditions and higher average temperatures have all reduced the river&amp;rsquo;s flow in recent decades. The two biggest reservoirs along the river, Lake Mead and Lake Powell, are each creeping towards a &amp;ldquo;dead pool,&amp;rdquo; an ominous sign that the Colorado River could stop flowing entirely.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Agriculture accounts for ~80% of total water consumption in the Colorado River basin, with roughly half of that going towards the production of alfalfa hay, according to a 2020 &lt;a href="https://core.ac.uk/download/pdf/323061602.pdf">study&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
&lt;iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/g-pygL1-yzM" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video">&lt;/iframe>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>What has all this irrigation amounted to?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Massive industrial storehouses line the area, packed with thousands upon thousands of stacks of alfalfa bales ready to be fed to dairy cows &amp;ndash; but not cows in California&amp;rsquo;s Central Valley or Montana&amp;rsquo;s rangelands. Instead, the alfalfa will be fed to cows across the Pacific &amp;ndash; in China, Japan and Korea, and farther away in Saudi Arabia, the United Arab Emirates, etc. An increasing percentage of the alfalfa produced here is exported.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Growers say the reasons boil down to simple economics. The market for alfalfa hay in southern California has shrunk over the years as dairies have closed or moved elsewhere, while demand for dairy products has grown exponentially in other parts of the world. Meanwhile, it costs little to freight goods on the back haul to China, because the US runs a persistently high trade deficit with China; containers from Asia arrive full but often return empty. Some claim it&amp;rsquo;s actually cheaper to ship hay to China than to haul the same load by truck to dairy farms 400 miles north in the San Joaquin Valley.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Brokers regularly fly in from overseas, some staying at a local golf course and country club. Chinese buyers are wined and dined across the border in Mexicali, which has a long-established Chinese community.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>According to a 2015 &lt;a href="https://pacinst.org/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/CA-Ag-Water-Use.pdf">analysis&lt;/a> by the Pacific Institute, alfalfa production in California uses around 5 acre-feet (6,167 cubic meters) of water. In comparison, sugar beets use roughly 3 acre-feet (3,700 cubic meters), and grains as little as 1 acre-foot (1,233 cubic meters).&lt;/p>
&lt;div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
&lt;iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/EE4uMOtqIc8" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video">&lt;/iframe>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>The top water-using activity in California is growing alfalfa. Farmers in Imperial County currently draw more water from the Colorado River than all of Arizona and Nevada combined. An alfalfa farmer can grow alfalfa 10-12 times a year and sell it for $260-$280/ton. These are not the hardworking family farmers of yesteryear. They are giant agribusiness corporations pulling in $1.8 billion from selling 7 million tons of alfalfa every year in California, according to a University of California, Davis study by Daniel Geisseler and William R. Horwath.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This business has been extremely profitable because alfalfa farmers get 3.4 million acre-feet (1 acre foot =325,851 gallons) of water every year for only $35-$60 per acre-foot. The water you get for your house costs you $800 per acre-foot today, and it could be double that in 10 years' time. You could supply the water needs of 40 million people with that 3.4 million acre-feet. It&amp;rsquo;s likely that enough water for greater Los Angeles is being used to raise irrigated pasture for livestock.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Feeding irrigated grass to cows is as wasteful a use of water as you can conceive. Pasture is hydrologically inefficient in the extreme, and, metabolically speaking, so are cows: You need 7-8 feet of water in the hot deserts to keep grass alive, which means that you need ~50,000 pounds of water to raise 1 pound of cow. (Feeding alfalfa to cows requires even more water, but at least alfalfa fixes nitrogen in the soil.)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If the livestock industry earned California any real money, and if cows (unlike avocados or artichokes) couldn&amp;rsquo;t be raised on rainfall in 35 other states, then giving more water to cows than to humans in the nation&amp;rsquo;s richest and most populous state &amp;ndash; a semi-desert state at the mercy of a precarious water supply &amp;ndash; might make a grain or two of sense.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>During the last few years, companies from Saudi Arabia and the United Arab Emirates have established farming operations on thousands of acres around the Imperial Valley and the adjacent Palo Verde Valley.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Saudi Arabian companies are pumping up groundwater from beneath land they have purchased and are using it to grow alfalfa for export to the Middle East. They have no plan for replacing this scarce and finite groundwater that accumulated over thousands of years.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As a matter of fact, foreign corporations have increased purchases of farmland in the US, particularly in the southwest where longstanding laws on water rights give land owners unlimited access to the valuable water underneath the soil.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Why don&amp;rsquo;t they grow their own alfalfa? Because they are short of water and it&amp;rsquo;s so much cheaper to buy from the US.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Growing water-intensive crops in the US and exporting them to water-scarce countries is a form of geo-economic arbitrage, a natural consequence of the globalization of everything. Essentially, water is exported out of the US in the form of crops like alfalfa, rice, or almonds. Guess who is currently one of the largest net exporters of virtual water in the world?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This trend has been accelerating for decades, despite concerns that this &amp;ldquo;virtual water trading&amp;rdquo; is unsustainable in the long term, especially in drought-plagued areas such as California. If California is &lt;em>really&lt;/em> short of water, why are we shipping it to Asia?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>What this means is, ultimately, the US is not in control of its own farmland &amp;ndash; or food production.&lt;/p>
&lt;div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
&lt;iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/QPEN0o5pbA4" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video">&lt;/iframe>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>Some argue the Imperial Valley is doing good by growing food and feeding the country, and point the finger at some desert metropolises such as Las Vegas, which boasts some 50 million visitors each year and wastes way more &lt;a href="https://www.latimes.com/environment/story/2023-01-29/colorado-river-in-crisis-cracking-down-on-grass">water from Colorado River&lt;/a> with its gushing fountains. The truth is, Las Vegas and Reno represent 95% of Nevada&amp;rsquo;s economy but use 10% of its water &amp;ndash; alfalfa growers use most of the rest.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Water overuse is a prisoner&amp;rsquo;s dilemma and a tragedy of the commons. If free-market mechanisms &amp;ndash; which much of western ag publicly applauds and privately abhors &amp;ndash; were actually allowed to work, the West&amp;rsquo;s water &amp;ldquo;shortage&amp;rdquo; would be exposed for what it is: the sort of shortage you expect when inexhaustible demand chases an almost free good. (If someone were selling Porsches for $3,000 apiece, there would be a shortage of those, too.) California has a shortage of water because it has a surfeit of cows &amp;ndash; it&amp;rsquo;s really almost as simple as that.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If history is any guide, the odds that we can sustain a &amp;ldquo;civilization&amp;rdquo; in deserts would have to be regarded as low. Only one desert civilization, out of dozens that grew up in antiquity, has survived uninterrupted into modern times. And Egypt&amp;rsquo;s approach to irrigation was fundamentally different from all the rest.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-7/imperial-valley-google-maps-review.png"
alt="Review of Imperial Valley, California"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>A user review for Imperial County, California (posted on Google Maps)&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h3 id="pane-ricco">pane ricco&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>It just struck me that I should make a &lt;em>pane ricco&lt;/em> (rich bread). I named it as such because in the western US, it&amp;rsquo;s often said that water flows uphill toward money. And it literally does. Water leaps 3,000 feet across the Tehachapi Mountains in gigantic siphons to slay the thirst of Los Angeles, as it&amp;rsquo;s shoved 1,000 feet out of Colorado River canyons to hydrate Phoenix and Palm Springs and the irrigated lands around them. Water is wealth in the West.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-7/20230324_174201.jpg"
alt="pane ricco with Desert Gold durum"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>handmade &lt;em>pane ricco&lt;/em> with wholegrain Desert Gold durum flour&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>This durum dough uses as much water and milk derivatives as it could handle, which, by the West Coast&amp;rsquo;s definition, is rich.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Desert Gold durum flour, 100% extraction&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>400g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>water, divided&lt;/td>
&lt;td>125%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>500g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>whole-milk sour cream&lt;/td>
&lt;td>20%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>80g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>whole durum levain (60% hydration)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>30%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>120g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sea salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>4g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>olive oil&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>40g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>black peppercorns, crushed&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>4g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->cheeses, finely grated&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>40g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>The process is pretty much the same as &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/california-dreamin-4">&lt;em>pan integral de sonora blanca&lt;/em>&lt;/a>. Basically, keep going with &lt;em>bassinage&lt;/em> until the dough became so fragile that it might break down anytime.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I baked the bread on a BBQ grill (again!).&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-7/20230324_174619.jpg"
alt="pane ricco with Desert Gold durum"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>handmade &lt;em>pane ricco&lt;/em> with wholegrain Desert Gold durum flour&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The classic flavor combination of &lt;em>cacio e pepe&lt;/em> never disappoints.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The crust is beautifully caramelized; firm and crisp, with a distinct smokey char.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-7/20230324_173604.jpg"
alt="pane ricco with Desert Gold durum"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>handmade &lt;em>pane ricco&lt;/em> with wholegrain Desert Gold durum flour&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The crumb is light, fluffy, and airy, with distinct honeycomb layers.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-7/20230324_173653.jpg"
alt="pane ricco with Desert Gold durum"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>handmade &lt;em>pane ricco&lt;/em> with wholegrain Desert Gold durum flour&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The texture is soft and tender, yet springy and chewy. The taste reminds me of roasted chickpeas. Black peppercorns provide a interesting texture contrast, and lend a mild spiced kick to the flavor of the crumb. The combination with salty addictive cheeses is mouthwatering.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-7/20230324_175617.jpg"
alt="pane ricco with Desert Gold durum"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>handmade &lt;em>pane ricco&lt;/em> with wholegrain Desert Gold durum flour&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>And this bread toasts like a dream.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="gnocchi">Gnocchi&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>I made a plate of plump sourdough &lt;em>gnocchi&lt;/em> as well, with Desert Gold durum, &lt;em>masa harina&lt;/em>, and Yukon Gold potatoes.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-7/20230324_102531.jpg"
alt="handmade sourdough gnocchi with Desert Gold durum"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>handmade sourdough gnocchi with Yukon Gold potatoes, wholegrain Desert Gold durum flour, and &lt;em>masa harina&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Formula:&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Desert Gold durum flour, 100% extraction&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>50g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;em>masa harina&lt;/em>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>50g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Yukon Gold potatoes, roasted &amp;amp; riced&lt;/td>
&lt;td>80%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>400g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>butter, softened&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>50g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sourdough discard&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>50g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>These fork-sized orbs were sauced with garlicky sun-dried tomatoes, topped with fresh basil leaves and shaved parmigiano-reggiano.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I could eat this every day and be happy.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-7/20230324_194435.jpg"
alt="handmade potato gnocchi with Desert Gold durum sauced"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>handmade sourdough gnocchi, served with sun-dried tomatoes, fresh basil, and shaved parmigiano-reggiano&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>&lt;code>Note&lt;/code>:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Kamut (khorasan) wheat is actually very close to durum, just a larger grain size. If you can&amp;rsquo;t get durum, try kamut.&lt;/p>
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>I used equal amounts of Parmigiano-Reggiano Stravecchio (aged for 5 years), Gruyère Vieux (aged for 18 months), and Pecorino Romano (aged for 12 months).&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/section></content></item><item><title>California Dreamin' #2: Joaquin Oro</title><link>/posts/california-dreamin-2/</link><pubDate>Tue, 21 Feb 2023 21:25:13 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/california-dreamin-2/</guid><description>[California Grain Adventure #2] &lt;em>Pan de San Joaquín&lt;/em>. One 100% wholegrain Joaquin Oro dough, 2 leavens, baked 2 ways. Total hydration cranked up to 134% to push the flour&amp;rsquo;s limits. Both turned out delightfully light and airy; exceptionally soft and chewy.</description><content>&lt;p>&lt;em>This is part 2 of my &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/california-grain-adventure/">California Grain Adventure&lt;/a>. If you missed part 1, catch up &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/california-dreamin-1/">here&lt;/a>.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Stranger, let me warn you now. If ever you start for California with the intention of seeing anything of the State, do that before you enter San Francisco. If you must land in San Francisco first, jump into a taxi, pull down the curtains, drive through the city, breaking every speed law, to &amp;ldquo;Third and Townsend,&amp;rdquo; sit in the station until a train &amp;ndash; some train, any train &amp;ndash; pulls out, and go with it. If in crossing Market Street, you raise that taxi-curtain as much as an inch, believe me, stranger, it&amp;rsquo;s all off; you&amp;rsquo;re lost. You&amp;rsquo;ll never leave San Francisco. Myself, both times I have gone to California, I have vowed to see Yosemite, the big trees, the string of beautiful old missions which dot the state, some of the quaint, languid, semi-tropical towns of the south, some of the brisk, brilliant, bustling towns of the north. But I have never really done it because I saw San Francisco first.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Inez Haynes Irwin, &lt;em>The Californiacs&lt;/em> (1919)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>NYC boasts the best bagels in the world, which New Yorkers attribute to their magical tap water. San Francisco boasts the finest sourdough in the world, which San Franciscans attribute to their special air. The unseen native inhabitants in San Francisco&amp;rsquo;s damp, foggy micro-climate, they claim, create a special &amp;ldquo;microbial terroir&amp;rdquo; that can&amp;rsquo;t be replicated anywhere else.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>And for a San Francisco sourdough to be truly &amp;ldquo;authentic,&amp;rdquo; the local history and mythology go, it has to be born in San Francisco with proper San Franciscan air, not in Oakland, Richmond, or San Jose. (BTW, everyone hates Oakland, except people who actually live there and pay half the rent of what people pay in San Francisco while still basically living in San Francisco.)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>No one has convinced more people about the unique qualities of San Francisco sourdough than Boudin Bakery, which &lt;a href="https://www.foundsf.org/index.php?title=Yeast_to_Wheat:_How_Boudin_Bakery%E2%80%99s_Yeast_Culture_Shaped_San_Francisco%E2%80%99s_Counterculture">claims&lt;/a> to have been selling the same loaf of bread made with The Original San Francisco Sourdough™ for &amp;gt;170 years. According to the Boudin Bakery museum at the ultra-touristy Fisherman&amp;rsquo;s Wharf, the company&amp;rsquo;s mother dough follows an unbroken line back to the Gold Rush in 1849. Louise Boudin even saved the starter from a burning building during the 1906 earthquake. A museum docent will readily inform you the starter is so special and irreplaceable that the Boudin mothership sends its retail stores fresh starter every 23 days. Without it, they emphasize, the sourdough produced at those stores would stop tasting like San Francisco sourdough &amp;ndash; and start tasting like Sacramento or San Diego sourdough, which is absolutely blasphemous.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Also, according to the museum, Boudin&amp;rsquo;s bread owes its special flavor to a particular strain of lactic acid bacteria that thrives &lt;em>only&lt;/em> in San Francisco&amp;rsquo;s climate. Scientists identified it here in 1970, so they named it &lt;em>Lactobacillus sanfranciscensis&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It&amp;rsquo;s a great, great story. Too bad it&amp;rsquo;s not quite true.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Scientists did identify &lt;em>Lactobacillus sanfranciscensis&lt;/em> in San Francisco. But recent studies have found it in &lt;a href="www.nytimes.com/2012/09/19/dining/for-gastronomists-a-go-to-microbiologist.html">90% of the world&amp;rsquo;s sourdough&lt;/a>, too. So from a biological standpoint, San Francisco sourdough is not all that distinctive &amp;ndash; or unique to San Francisco.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you take your precious local sourdough starter and bake with it in Los Angeles, I bet the resulting bread will taste very similar to what you make in San Francisco. Blasphemy! But likely&amp;hellip;true. Even breads made without &lt;em>Lactobacillus sanfranciscensis&lt;/em> can taste pretty darn good.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>So much for the &amp;ldquo;microbial terroir&amp;rdquo; myth. Even bakers who have been in a position to benefit from the reputation of local sourdough don&amp;rsquo;t embrace the cachet. Call a dog a dog &amp;ndash; it&amp;rsquo;s pure marketing. It sells the city, turning sourdough into another tourist attraction that San Francisco is famous for, besides the bridge and the bay.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-2/20230220_104457.jpg"
alt="Joaquin Oro pan de San Joaquín baked"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>My &lt;em>pan de San Joaquín&lt;/em>, made with home-milled 100% wholegrain Joaquin Oro flour and a non-San Francisco sourdough starter&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>There are 3 bread institutions in the San Francisco Bay Area: Acme, Semifreddi&amp;rsquo;s, and Tartine.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Acme is often credited as an OG pioneer of the San Francisco Bay Area&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Bread Revolution,&amp;rdquo; which in turn galvanized the modern &amp;ldquo;artisan bread&amp;rdquo; movement across America; to this day, Acme&amp;rsquo;s bread remains a &amp;ldquo;benchmark&amp;rdquo; for commercial handmade bread. It was a stalwart of the 1980s artisan baking scene, along with Semifreddi&amp;rsquo;s.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Newer upstarts like Tartine and Josey Baker Bread have brought on some serious competition, and challenged the status quo of what San Francisco bread is &lt;em>supposed&lt;/em> to taste like and, along the way, the status quo of home baking.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In 2006, the NY Times food columnist Mark Bittman &lt;a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2006/12/06/dining/06mini.html">wrote about&lt;/a> a NYC baker named Jim Lahey, the man behind Sullivan Street Bakery who had developed a no-knead bread recipe that consisted of only 4 steps and required just 4 ingredients &amp;ndash; flour, water, salt, and yeast. While not the OG recipe of its kind, the &amp;ldquo;no-knead&amp;rdquo; method spread like wildfire. It revolutionized the food world; its simplicity miraculously democratized breadmaking for the home baker. Lahey became a semi-god figure &amp;ndash; the Prometheus who gifted the art of breadmaking to the masses. He released a cookbook in 2009, titled &lt;em>My Bread: The Revolutionary No-Work, No-Knead Method&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A few years earlier, a transplanted New Yorker named Elizabeth Pruitt and her husband Chad Robertson moved their tiny baking operation from Point Reyes, California south to an unassuming corner of Guerrero Street, at the edge of the Mission District in San Francisco. They named it Tartine, and churned out artisan breads, viennoiseries and sandwiches. The bakery garnered praise from Alice Waters and Martha Stewart, and made the cake for a &lt;a href="https://www.sfgate.com/entertainment/article/Why-the-concert-was-canceled-3314257.php">&amp;ldquo;bohemian bourgeois&amp;rdquo;-themed birthday party&lt;/a> attended by Nancy Pelosi and Hillary Clinton. Mark Bittman &lt;a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2007/01/28/travel/28Bite.html">described&lt;/a> their shop as one of the best French-style bakeries in the country, and particularly raved about Tartine&amp;rsquo;s sandwiches, which were made on &amp;ldquo;Mr. Robertson&amp;rsquo;s exceptional bread, notable because it&amp;rsquo;s a slow-fermented yeast bread in very French style that is a welcome change from the ubiquitous sourdough.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>San Franciscans started lining up outside the shop to get a taste of what Prueitt and Robertson were baking; the queues outside Tartine became a local landmark and a symbol of a changing city. (Lines beget lines; the success of Tartine&amp;rsquo;s OG location is arguably one of the reasons that San Francisco gained a reputation as a place where people would wait in line for any sort of &amp;ldquo;cult&amp;rdquo; food item.) Tartine&amp;rsquo;s bread started to become a Veblen good, just as Prueitt and Robertson started to become food-world celebrities. In 2010, the influential &lt;em>Tartine Bread&lt;/em> was published; Robertson revealed to the world his recipe for French-style sourdough, which called for folding, shaping, scoring, and a grasp of wild yeast. The change from Lahey&amp;rsquo;s no-knead bread to Robertson&amp;rsquo;s sourdough was remarkable; home baking was about to become more technical and more precise.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The complete recipe for Basic Country Bread, the edible hero of &lt;em>Tartine Bread&lt;/em>, runs 38 pages, including photographs. It was instantly celebrated as a &amp;ldquo;masterpiece&amp;rdquo; in media, along the lines of a Martin Scorsese tracking shot or a Marcel Proust sentence.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Robertson wrote about bread in a detailed but flexible way: The prose is lean and direct; the instructions don&amp;rsquo;t just tell you what to do but explain why, what to look for, and how to make corrections, encouraging you to see his laborious artisan craft as adaptable and welcoming of interpretation. Robertson was also a laid-back surfer who radiated a particular kind of Gen X bohemianism, which inadvertently imbued breadmaking with a sort of new masculine sheen.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Seemingly, Robertson gave away the store. The bread he teaches you to make is essentially the same bread that has turned him into one of the most influential bakers in the world; it&amp;rsquo;s what causes otherwise rational adults to mob the line at Tartine Bakery. The fact is, Tartine multiplied its influence by opening up about the way they do things.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Tartine Bread&lt;/em> could have merely been aspirational, but it&amp;rsquo;s just too &lt;em>actionable&lt;/em>. The recipes work, and they inspire. All of a sudden, many of Tartine&amp;rsquo;s fans took up artisan baking at home &amp;ndash; a majority of whom happened to be guys in tech.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For tech geeks in the San Francisco Bay Area, &lt;em>Tartine Bread&lt;/em> had it all:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>a recipe that encouraged iteration and a grasp of the scientific nature of wild fermentation;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>a craft that was not frivolous or quintessentially feminine like making cupcakes; and&lt;/li>
&lt;li>a cool leader that inspires emulation.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Technologists stormed sourdough with a host of tools and techniques that built on Robertson&amp;rsquo;s artisan approach. Ken Forkish, who had quit his job at IBM to become a baker, wrote &lt;em>Flour Water Salt Yeast&lt;/em> and won a James Beard Award in 2013. Nathan Myhrvold, the former CTO of Microsoft and current CEO of patent and investment firm Intellectual Ventures, released a 5-volume cookbook called &lt;em>Modernist Bread&lt;/em> in 2017. It also won a James Beard. High-efficiency tools like $150 Brød &amp;amp; Taylor Folding Bread Proofer that offers &amp;ldquo;precision control&amp;rdquo; over temperature and humidity, or the $300 Fourneau bread oven, which &amp;ldquo;traps steam and radiates powerful heat&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;helps you achieve oven spring&amp;rdquo;, came on the market.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Overnight, Silicon Valley venture capitalists started tweeting about their fine sourdough starters; UX designers started buying $600 bannetons and taking extensive notes about each bake in apps like Evernote, Google Keep, Notion and Bear; and tender #crumbshots popped up all over breadstagram. Everyone in Silicon Valley is Very Publicly Into Sourdough All of a Sudden. People couldn&amp;rsquo;t delight more in the miracles of this alchemy than if it were neolithic times and bread was just invented yesterday. Breadmaking has become the latest form of romantic consumerism.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-2/20230220_110032.jpg"
alt="Joaquin Oro pan de San Joaquín baked"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>pan de San Joaquín&lt;/em>. home-milled unsifted Joaquin Oro flour + non-San Francisco sourdough starter + homemade pineapple yeast water poolish&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The Perfect Loaf, a sourdough bread blog launched in 2013 by Maurizio Leo, a software engineer by trade, is frequently cited as an entry point to baking for men in tech, as his approach speaks to technically-oriented individuals and, as his blog name implies, is pursuant of mastery.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Breadmaking is now seen as a sort of an &amp;ldquo;algorithm&amp;rdquo;; it&amp;rsquo;s expected to produce a certain result and if that result isn&amp;rsquo;t always what you expect, you step back and diagnose the steps along the way. Working on bread recipes has become a new form of &amp;ldquo;debugging.&amp;rdquo; That iterative procedure for optimization appeals to the engineering mind, not to mention the precision part. Breadmaking also offers various degrees of freedom &amp;ndash; it could be implemented in lots of different possible ways.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It&amp;rsquo;s a liberating escape, particularly when you work in tech for a living and can&amp;rsquo;t turn that technical side of your brain off and your work becomes so embedded in your life that it consumes you.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Like religion, romanticism also has its liminal rituals, which decouple the subjective feelings of pleasure and freedom from material goods and mass-marketed symbols, and disrupt the daily tedium and hierarchies, transporting us, through the consumption of goods and services labeled romantic, into a fantastic world in which ordinary annoyances, our own limitations and, with a little luck, even our most objectionable caprices, are temporarily interrupted. Maybe baking is an opportunity for these technologists to rehabilitate their humanity, when they are not busy creating apps that make money off everyone&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;addiction&amp;rdquo;?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Sourdough&lt;/em>, a 2017 novel by Robin Sloan, pokes fun at the obnoxious foodie culture of Silicon Valley while also ribbing the folks who are so eager to innovate it &amp;ndash; the tech guys who obsess over an ancient idea, commit to disrupting it, then get bored and move on.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The reason that Chad Robertson became a god among tech-oriented breadmaking hobbyists is perhaps more shallow than one might think: Robertson and Tartine are instrumental to this whole trend because he was in San Francisco just as this mid-2000s tech wave was taking off. Right place, right time. Right guy, right craft.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>When Robertson &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=tHUU9dcHVng">spoke&lt;/a> about the intersection of tech and bread at a Wired conference in 2015, he said as much, noting that the reason he and Prueitt even moved their bakery to San Francisco in the first place was because the burst of the dotcom bubble in the early 2000s finally made it affordable for them to do so: The median rent for a two-bedroom apartment had fallen from $3,000 a month to just under $2,000. Development had slowed, evictions and unemployment had spiked, and commercial vacancies had risen. In the Mission District, a historically working-class and Latino neighborhood, artists' spaces battled with real-estate developers.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Tartine had thrived during an economic downturn. Now it&amp;rsquo;s operating in one of the most expensive cities in the world, where a 21-year-old earning low six-figures is considered a peasant.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-2/20230220_105833.jpg"
alt="Joaquin Oro pan de San Joaquín baked"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>pan de San Joaquín&lt;/em>. home-milled unsifted Joaquin Oro flour + non-San Francisco sourdough starter + homemade pineapple yeast water poolish&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>Tartine has undergone rapid expansion since Chad Robertson personally manned the ovens at the OG store on Guerrero Street, shuttling out a limited number of loaves every evening.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In 2014, the Oakland-born and San Francisco-raised Blue Bottle, the most dominant company riding the &amp;ldquo;third wave&amp;rdquo; coffee trend, had just &lt;a href="https://valleywag.gawker.com/blue-bottle-which-raised-45-m-cut-health-benefits-fo-1663442765">raised $45 million dollars&lt;/a> in venture capital for its own expansion, and needed a bakery partner to provide food in its coffee shops. Tartine soon announced a &lt;a href="https://www.latimes.com/food/dailydish/la-dd-tartine-blue-bottle-merging-20150420-story.html">merger&lt;/a> with the company; the news turned heads in the northern California food world and beyond. Anticipating a personal windfall, Prueitt and Robertson moved into a luxurious circa 1960 house in the Castro district in 2015. Eater SF did a &lt;a href="https://sf.eater.com/2016/2/23/11098328/tartine-bakery-liz-prueitt-chad-robertson-home-kitchen#11">photo shoot&lt;/a> of their newly remodeled home kitchen, showing off their specialized kitchenware and verdant backyard.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>By February 2016 when the Eater piece went live, the Blue Bottle acquisition had &lt;a href="https://www.sfchronicle.com/restaurants/article/Blue-Bottle-and-Tartine-Bakery-nix-merger-6673950.php">fallen apart&lt;/a>. The couple put the Castro house up for sale and quietly moved out in early 2018. Still, Tartine Manufactory, a restaurant and bar concept conceived in their sleek, airy home kitchen, opened in the summer of 2016. &lt;a href="https://sf.eater.com/2016/8/17/12513334/tartine-manufactory-san-francisco-mission-photos">Eater SF&lt;/a> lauded the 5,000-sqft space as &amp;ldquo;an artisanal utopia in the Mission&amp;rdquo;; every detail was designed to represent &amp;ldquo;a new type of luxury.&amp;rdquo; Meanwhile, Tartine launched its own coffee brand, &lt;a href="https://sprudge.com/tartines-coffee-manufactory-roasting-destiny-san-francisco-107956.html">Coffee Manufactory&lt;/a>, in partnership with a former Starbucks executive who is now the Chief Operations Officer of Tartine.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>One of Tartine&amp;rsquo;s partners and investors is a real-estate private-equity firm called CIM Group, one of the largest property owners in Los Angeles and a prominent commercial landlord in Oakland, managing about $30 billion dollars in assets.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Tartine&amp;rsquo;s Coffee Manufactory planned to move into Jack London Square, a 434,000-sqft waterfront property in Oakland acquired by CIM in 2016 as part of a &lt;a href="https://www.sfchronicle.com/restaurants/article/Jack-London-Square-cooks-up-a-new-generation-of-11231529.php">$131 million deal&lt;/a> for long-term development. CIM billed the Coffee Manufactory as an anchor tenant &amp;ndash; a business that could attract customers and other businesses, increasing the overall value and cachet of the area. The developer was curating the neighborhood with buildings and tenants.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Tartine was a particularly appealing anchor tenant. The food was great, and most of it could be made off-site, requiring a fairly modest square footage for retail sites. And Tartine had a history: the flagship location, with its artistic staff and communal ambiance, radiated the sort of authenticity that a real-estate developer could only dream of cultivating. Year on year, Tartine’s brand had become cooler, airier, and more transportable.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Anna Wiener, &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href="https://www.newyorker.com/news/letter-from-silicon-valley/when-baking-and-real-estate-collide">When Baking and Real Estate Collide&lt;/a>&amp;rdquo;, &lt;em>The New Yorker&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Images of Tartine&amp;rsquo;s pastries and its OG Guerrero Street bakery started to pop up in &lt;a href="hhttps://www.buzzfeed.com/michellerial/morning-bun">Apple commercials and product demos&lt;/a>. Sweetgreen, the East Coast fast-casual salad chain that was now proliferating along the West Coast, started to offer &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href="https://sf.eater.com/2017/8/30/16227094/sweetgreen-tartine-manufactory-salad-bowl-san-francisco-bay">The Tartine Bowl&lt;/a>&amp;rdquo;, plucked from Prueitt&amp;rsquo;s recently published book &lt;em>Tartine All Day&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Tartine&amp;rsquo;s brand became another recognizable symbol of &lt;a href="https://archive.is/mmUwT">gentrification&lt;/a>; the opening of a Tartine seemed to hint that a neighborhood was on the cusp of it. The process of bringing intense, aggressive real-estate development to upper-middle-class neighborhoods, to cater to an even more affluent stratum, is gentrification on steroids.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In January 2019, Tartine opened &lt;a href="https://sf.eater.com/2019/1/22/18193239/manufactory-food-hall-sfo-tartine-cala-kamine-san-francisco-international-airport">the Manufactory Food Hall&lt;/a> in San Francisco International Airport.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>That spring, Tartine opened a splashy &lt;a href="https://la.eater.com/2019/1/28/18200748/manufactory-row-tartine-chris-bianco-los-angeles-photos-inside">new 40,000-sqft Tartine Manufactory&lt;/a> &amp;ndash; three times the size of its first Manufactory in San Francisco &amp;ndash; in the Row, a huge, newly developed compound in Downtown Los Angeles (DTLA). &lt;em>Food &amp;amp; Wine&lt;/em> published a feature on Robertson and Prueitt, with the headline &amp;ldquo;With L.A. Opening, Tartine Positions Itself for World Domination.&amp;rdquo; F*ck yeah, Silicon Valley-style.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>CIM invested in Tartine&amp;rsquo;s 5 new locations in Los Angeles (&lt;a href="https://la.eater.com/2019/1/10/18177207/tartine-silver-lake-sunset-coming-expansion-news">Silver Lake&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://la.eater.com/2019/7/29/20746164/tartine-hollywood-bakery-san-francisco-opening-sycamore-news">West Hollywood&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://la.eater.com/2019/9/6/20853090/tartine-bakery-santa-monica-expansion-opening-funeral-home">Santa Monica&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://www.thebrassy.com/blog/west-adams-tartine-is-a-welcome-neighborhood-addition">West Adams&lt;/a>, and &lt;a href="https://la.eater.com/2022/2/1/22912646/tartine-pasadena-new-cafe-opening-restaurant-los-angeles-morning-am-intel-news">Pasadena&lt;/a>). For any Angeleno who&amp;rsquo;s ever wondered just how all these Tartines landed in the Southland in the first place, here&amp;rsquo;s an answer.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In July 2019, Tartine opened its 3rd San Francisco location, in a CIM-affiliated property in the Inner Sunset neighborhood.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In September 2019, Tartine opened its 5th Bay Area location in &lt;a href="https://sf.eater.com/2019/9/16/20868239/tartine-berkeley-bakery-open-graduate-hotel">Berkeley&lt;/a>. The café is tucked into a sunroom at Berkeley&amp;rsquo;s Graduate Hotel (fka. the Hotel Durant), a chain hotel owned by Adventurous Journeys Capital, a self-described &amp;ldquo;vertically integrated real estate investment manager focused on developing and operating transformative real estate assets in spaces often overlooked or undervalued by traditional investment firms.&amp;rdquo; Tartine&amp;rsquo;s new presence at the hotel came as part of a ~$50 million transformation from the Hotel Durant to the Graduate Hotel.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Customers who walk into any of Tartine&amp;rsquo;s locations may never feel or realize they are entering part of a real-estate empire.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>How much of Tartine is owned by CIM and how deeply these two companies are intertwined has never been publicly disclosed. The daughter of a co-founder of CIM is now Tartine&amp;rsquo;s VP of Brand.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-2/20230220_190301.jpg"
alt="Joaquin Oro pan de San Joaquín baked"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>100% wholegrain &lt;em>pan de San Joaquín&lt;/em>, gleaming in the wintry sun.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Today, Tartine operates 3 locations in the San Francisco Bay Area, 5 in Los Angeles, and 6 licensed locations in Seoul (one of which is located at &lt;a href="https://tartinebakery.com/seoul/dosan">Kinfolk Dosan&lt;/a>, a cultural space created by Kinfolk, an aspirational lifestyle magazine). How can a craft bakery still be artisanal if it has 6 overseas branches?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Tartine&amp;rsquo;s workers in San Francisco watched investment flow into the new locations and increasingly felt neglected. They suspected they were the actual engine that propelled Tartine into an empire, but now they couldn&amp;rsquo;t even get a $1/hour raise. There was a lot of confusion about the company&amp;rsquo;s investors &amp;ndash; who were they, and how much power did they wield? Money to pay invoices wasn&amp;rsquo;t there.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Tartine was expanding, but the OG Mission location was falling apart. In November 2019, the San Francisco Department of Public Health &lt;a href="https://sf.eater.com/2019/11/23/20979306/tartine-rats-rodents-dph-mission">briefly shut down&lt;/a> Tartine&amp;rsquo;s Guerrero Street location, after inspectors say that its operators failed to deal with a persistent rodent infestation in the space.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Workers noticed cultural changes. Shift wine was eliminated, and management introduced a monthly music playlist. Some were dissatisfied with wages, raises, and scheduling. Employees wanted certain benefits, such as paid time off separate from state-mandated sick leave, and raises larger than the annual increases mandated by the city. All this looked feasible to them, given the company’s expansion. When they brought these requests to Tartine’s newly created human-resources department, they were confused to find that it was run out of offices leased from CIM affiliates, in Los Angeles.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Anna Wiener, &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href="https://www.newyorker.com/news/letter-from-silicon-valley/when-baking-and-real-estate-collide">When Baking and Real Estate Collide&lt;/a>&amp;rdquo;, &lt;em>The New Yorker&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>As Tartine expanded rapidly in the last 6-7 years, operational difficulties grew with it. Money was allocated to ventures that didn&amp;rsquo;t pan out. The whole enterprise seemed stretched thin. There seemed to be a fundamental disconnect between perception and reality. New investment was focused on new ventures, but Tartine&amp;rsquo;s expansion relied on the strength of its brand.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Bar Tartine closed in 2016 and had never turned a profit (since it opened in 2005 just a couple of blocks away from the OG Tartine Bakery). The planned Coffee Manufactory retail space in Jack London Square never opened.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In December 2019, Tartine&amp;rsquo;s massive DTLA Manufactory shuttered &amp;ndash; 11 months after it opened. It was a shocking closure. The store laid off its remaining workers 10 days before Christmas.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Tartine’s market, retail baking and takeaway spaces, and multiple restaurants all closed this week after just 11 months of business and a build-out rumored to have run into the tens of millions of dollars. All of the Row is struggling to find sustained weeknight retail traffic right now, but the loss of anchor tenant Tartine has hit the development’s brand particularly hard. There simply were not enough $72 mug buyers around to keep the place afloat, and that seems to say something about Tartine’s visibility and draw, and about the Row overall — not to mention the cost of goods inside. &amp;hellip;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Simply put: Tartine didn’t find a good way to consistently speak to Angelenos, and in a city where driving four miles to have dinner can mean sitting in your car for an hour, answering the “why” of the place not only proved tricky, it likely proved its undoing. &amp;hellip; More than anything, it struggled to define its place at the Row, in Downtown, in a city brimming with home bakers and panaderias and other local bread legends like Friends &amp;amp; Family, Clark Street, and Bub &amp;amp; Grandma’s.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Eater LA, &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href="https://la.eater.com/2019/12/18/21028471/tartine-manufactory-downtown-los-angeles-the-row-closed-why">Tartine&amp;rsquo;s Big DTLA Manufactory Closed After Just One Year. What Happened?&lt;/a>&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Tartine took on a new investor, Monogram Capital Partners, another private-equity firm &amp;ldquo;focused exclusively on consumer and retail companies.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Meanwhile, Chad Robertson started to show up in &lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/BlundstoneUS/videos/live-in-my-blundstones-chad-robertson/2553319681570138/">sponsored content&lt;/a> for &lt;a href="https://www.blundstone.com/limb-chad-robertson">Blundstone boots&lt;/a> on social media. He and Prueitt divorced in 2020.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Given the PE industry&amp;rsquo;s typical M.O. (i.e. the decade-long pyramiding of real estate and overleveraging on ever lower interest rates), I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be surprised if Tartine is sinking deeper and deeper into debt &amp;ndash; or might eventually end up like &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/aquaboogie-di-dolce">Dean &amp;amp; DeLuca&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In February 2020, a few short weeks before the Covid lockdown, 141 of Tartine&amp;rsquo;s &amp;gt;200 San Francisco Bay Area employees signed a letter, announcing their decision to unionize with the International Longshore and Warehouse Union. It came as a huge surprise, especially at a world-renowned bakery that boasts about ​&amp;quot;production at a human scale&amp;quot; and has been a training ground for young bakers from around the globe.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Tartine&amp;rsquo;s management declined to recognize the union, and &lt;a href="https://sf.eater.com/2020/2/11/21133479/tartine-union-management-sam-singer">hired Sam Singer&lt;/a>, a longtime San Francisco crisis communications expert known for his work with controversial companies like Chevron&amp;rsquo;s Richmond oil refinery. After letting him go amid criticism, they then hired a Las Vegas-based firm called Quest Consulting to quash the unionizing effort. Quest&amp;rsquo;s founder, Lupe Cruz, has earned himself a &lt;a href="https://www.pressdemocrat.com/article/news/union-organizers-and-workers-decry-union-busting-consulting-firms-hired-b/">reputation&lt;/a> among labor organizers as &amp;ldquo;a notorious union-buster who specializes in influencing Latino-dominated workforces.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In March 2021, over a year after voting and following a thorny, protracted dispute over 24 challenged ballots, the National Labor Relations Board announced that Tartine&amp;rsquo;s workers in San Francisco had officially unionized. In May 2022, the Tartine Union began negotiations for its first wage and healthcare contract, which &lt;a href="https://sf.eater.com/2022/8/23/23318336/tartine-bakery-union-negotiations">stalled&lt;/a> a few months later.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-2/20230220_105911.jpg"
alt="Joaquin Oro pan de San Joaquín baked"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>pan de San Joaquín&lt;/em>. home-milled unsifted Joaquin Oro flour + non-San Francisco sourdough starter + homemade pineapple yeast water poolish&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>A single person at the right place comes up with a &amp;ldquo;unique&amp;rdquo; recipe at the right time can have the outsized effect of influencing a whole new generation of bakers, and even become a cult figure.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Nothing is more powerful than an idea whose time has come.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Victor Hugo&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>No single part of Tartine&amp;rsquo;s technique or bread is new or original to me. I&amp;rsquo;ve eaten there several times; nothing about it has blown my mind. Maybe it was groundbreaking a decade ago to the culinarily ignorant masses who grew up on industrial wheatish pulp?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>That one guy who lives in San Francisco at the right time with the right trade shouldn&amp;rsquo;t get all the credit for this bread renaissance &amp;ndash; East Coast journalists began to protest. People (mostly women) have been baking bread at home for thousands of years before Robertson and Prueitt opened Tartine.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Apparently, &amp;ldquo;nerds&amp;rdquo; over-engineering breadbaking, turning this homegrown, down-to-earth craft into something more technical and complicated than it should be, and &amp;ldquo;pushing&amp;rdquo; women out in the process is &lt;a href="https://www.eater.com/2018/11/19/18099127/bread-silicon-valley-sourdough-tech-bros-tartine-chad-robertson">a huge problem&lt;/a>. The gendering of baking has become a hot topic.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;hellip;one of my favorite things about JavaScript is when we discover things 20 years after other languages, besides like the concept of baking your own bread at home instead of purchasing it from the store, we act like we invented fat arrow functions, classes, immutable data, restructuring statements, functional programming &amp;ndash; like, it&amp;rsquo;s like truly wild to witness.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&amp;hellip;this baking bread thing seems to have come out of like nowhere and it&amp;rsquo;s interesting to see. &amp;hellip; I was going to make fun of the parallels between baking bread &amp;ndash; like baking bread from a recipe and implementing an algorithm of code, but I think that the real interesting and problematic parallel is the rhetoric with which JavaScript developers talk about bread. It&amp;rsquo;s super elitist and it&amp;rsquo;s mostly dudes.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>why are there no women in tech baking bread? And I feel like &amp;ndash; this is in all seriousness, I feel this pressure now to stop this in its tracks. &amp;hellip; I&amp;rsquo;m worried about fucking bread. Like, you think I&amp;rsquo;d have enough emotional labor as a woman in tech to have to deal with baking bread &amp;ndash; I don&amp;rsquo;t know.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Jenn Schiffer, &lt;a href="https://www.deconstructconf.com/2017/jenn-schiffer-how-to-be-a-real-developer">Deconstruct Conf 2017&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>People in and around San Francisco making sourdough is such a surprising and novel phenomenon that it needs to be picked apart &amp;ndash; because (&lt;em>gasp&lt;/em>!) they happen to be men who work in tech and ruin whatever they lay their hands on for the sake of fashion and &amp;ldquo;disruption.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Perhaps the pseudo-celebrity status of Chad Robertson, the ubiquity of Instagram shots that emphasize only the visual aesthetic of breads, etc. speak to humans' shallowness and egotism more than anything else.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Who cares about some JavaScript developer in San Francisco who bakes bread at home and runs a blog about it? If anything, it&amp;rsquo;s those who follow them keenly on social media that affirm their authority and turn them into some bread gods. Why are you so desperate for external validation?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A lot of people think that to be a real developer/baker, you need to be prolific on social media. If you don&amp;rsquo;t argue about your trade on Twitter, GitHub or Instagram, you don&amp;rsquo;t &lt;em>feel like&lt;/em> you are a real developer/baker. Yeah sure. Only if you &lt;em>choose&lt;/em> to play this game and be stuck in this rat race.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-2/20230220_104703.jpg"
alt="Joaquin Oro pan de San Joaquín baked"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>pan de San Joaquín&lt;/em>. home-milled unsifted Joaquin Oro flour + non-San Francisco sourdough starter + homemade pineapple yeast water poolish&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>I don&amp;rsquo;t think the scientific approach to bread is a futile endeavor. Why can&amp;rsquo;t the scientific and the intuitive approaches co-exist?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The foundation of bread is super simple and those basic principles are still unchanged. I disagree that it&amp;rsquo;s total hubris to be attempting to innovate and move the art forward. Some folks are actually making significant innovations in breadmaking, and innovation is not an &amp;ldquo;American sickness&amp;rdquo; that needs to be cured. (In fact, I would argue that America needs more innovation &amp;ndash; especially in manufacturing and engineering &amp;ndash; that will tangibly improve the standard of living.) Breads produced with some of the new artisan methods today are actually really good &amp;ndash; in ways that their predecessors simply were not. Just because something has been around for thousands of years doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean there aren&amp;rsquo;t many new discoveries to be had. Hell, it wasn&amp;rsquo;t until a couple of decades ago that people picked up on the fact that you &lt;em>don&amp;rsquo;t&lt;/em> have to knead the dough to make great bread. Sometimes little things like this go undiscovered because no one bothered to look.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Only very recently in history has certain technology become available to us that has allowed us to exert super precise control over the baking environment (e.g. ambient temperatures, steam, etc.) and ingredients (e.g. varieties of grain, grinds, flour blends, strains of yeast). Bread keeps getting better and better because some bakers continue to tinker endlessly with these variables. New scientific analysis could herald a &amp;ldquo;golden age of fermentation.&amp;rdquo; Sure, not everyone cares about these things. For most people, bread is bread.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As a baker, you should remove ego from your &lt;em>mise en place&lt;/em>, rethink your take on baking, and do some researching and discovering for new techniques and skills. There&amp;rsquo;s always room for improvement. And maybe, just maybe, you could find some new excitement, or get your mind blown, and impart that joy and passion through your baking. Every person that eats your bakes deserves that.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I haven&amp;rsquo;t been baking my whole life. My mom never baked bread, and I didn&amp;rsquo;t eat much bread growing up. I actually loathed baking for most of my life &amp;ndash; kneading or using a dough mixer (another thing you have to wash) is absolutely tedious, and handling raw ingredients like eggs is totally disgusting. I didn&amp;rsquo;t have &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/harpys-lovesong/">my first taste of artisan sourdough bread&lt;/a> until 2014. In fact, I didn&amp;rsquo;t discover breadmaking until ~2019, well after the &amp;ldquo;tech bros&amp;rdquo; had invaded the sourdough trend and maybe even moved on, and after &lt;a href="https://www.newyorker.com/culture/culture-desk/bread-makes-a-comeback">&lt;em>The New Yorker&lt;/em> declared&lt;/a> a comeback for bread and greeted it as the giddy limit of fake trendspotting.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I was initially drawn to breadmaking because of the science behind it &amp;ndash; the microbiology and cellular gastronomy &amp;ndash; more than the intuitive part. To me, sourdough brought bread back from the dead. Now I&amp;rsquo;m more enthused about transforming different grains into good bread. It&amp;rsquo;s not about making disruptive breads, but making breads that I really like.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;Tech bros invading sourdough&amp;rdquo; is not some panic-inducing mass-epidemic of nerds suddenly swarming every supermarket by the thousands for artisan flours and baking tools. ~4 years in, I&amp;rsquo;m still the only person I know who makes bread on a regular basis. Many types of people all over the world are getting more interested in breadmaking and trying it out, but it&amp;rsquo;s still pretty rare for someone to commit to it at the same level as myself.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As a side note, I think the fact that producing some common food item at home is now seen as &amp;ldquo;novel&amp;rdquo; speaks volumes about how removed we postmodern humans are from our food. Tovala and DoorDash are good examples.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-2/20230220_191147.jpg"
alt="Joaquin Oro pan de San Joaquín"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>100% wholegrain &lt;em>pan de San Joaquín&lt;/em>, gleaming in the wintry sun.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>My second experiment with Joaquin Oro (shared by friends at the California Wheat Commission) pushes the limits of dough hydration. Gorging the Joaquin Oro grown in water-scarce California with an absurd amount of water is quite the California conundrum.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="total">Total&lt;/h4>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Joaquin Oro, 100% extraction (Eck Farms, CA)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>530g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>H₂O&lt;/td>
&lt;td>134%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>710g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>whole wheat poolish&lt;/td>
&lt;td>52%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>275g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>whole wheat levain&lt;/td>
&lt;td>15%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>80g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>azuki bean purée&lt;/td>
&lt;td>7.1%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>37.5g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sea salt (Gustus Vitae, CA)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1.4%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>7.5g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>olive oil (Awake - Brightland, CA)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5.7%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>30g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>tallow (home-rendered), softened&lt;/td>
&lt;td>7.1%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>37.5g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>I used two leavens at different hydration levels in this dough.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="yeast-water-poolish">Yeast water poolish&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>I pre-fermented ~24% of total flour in an overnight poolish, with homemade pineapple &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/yeast-water/">yeast water&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Joaquin Oro, 100% extraction (Eck Farms, CA)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>125g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>pineapple yeast water (homemade)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>120%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>150g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>You could substitute the yeast water with 1%-2% dry yeast + 120% plain H₂O.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I let the poolish ferment for 12 hours at ~70°F. When ripe, the poolish should be brimming with bubbles and double in volume.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Poolish modifies gluten, weakening it somewhat, so the dough stretches better as it ferments. For a strong-flour dough, a poolish will help bread rise taller.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="levain">Levain&lt;/h4>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Joaquin Oro, 100% extraction (Eck Farms, CA)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>40g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>H₂O&lt;/td>
&lt;td>50%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>20g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sourdough starter&lt;/td>
&lt;td>50%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>20g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>I let the levain ripen at ~75°F for 1 hour, and then retarded it in the fridge overnight.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>When ripe, my levain smelt and tasted like a tart yogurt &amp;ndash; or perhaps more like crème fraîche that made me salivate and excited to eat more.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="final-dough">Final dough&lt;/h4>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Joaquin Oro, 100% extraction (Eck Farms, CA)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>365g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>H₂O, divided&lt;/td>
&lt;td>148%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>540g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>whole wheat poolish&lt;/td>
&lt;td>75%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>275g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>whole wheat levain&lt;/td>
&lt;td>22%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>80g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>azuki bean purée&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>37.5g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sea salt (Gustus Vitae, CA)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>7g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>olive oil (Awake - Brightland, CA)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>8%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>30g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>tallow (home-rendered), softened&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>37.5g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>The process is built upon my previous &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/aquaboogie-van-wheatsworth/">wholegrain &lt;em>pan de cristal&lt;/em> loaves&lt;/a>:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Autolyse the flour at 80% hydration for 2 hours in the fridge.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Add the poolish, levain, and azuki bean purée. Mix until well incorporated.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Double hydration: Slowly drizzle in 2/3 of the remaining water, and &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zgz0oAhgwyg">Rubaud-mix&lt;/a> until thoroughly absorbed. This requires a bit of patience, so take your time. Cover the dough and let it rest for 20 minutes at room temperature.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Add the salt, and mix well.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Triple hydration: Slowly add the rest of the water, while &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zgz0oAhgwyg">Rubaud-mixing&lt;/a> until completely combined. Let the dough rest for another 20 minutes at room temperature.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Gently mix in the olive oil and softened tallow. Let the dough rest and relax for 30 minutes.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Bulk ferment the dough at ~70°F for 4 hours, performing a coil-fold every 30 minutes during the first 2.5 hours. Folding a super-high-hydration dough like this kinda feels like handling water.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Transfer the dough into a fridge and retard for 12 hours.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Take the dough out of the fridge; divide it into two or leave it whole as a large loaf. Let it rest at room temperature for 2-3 hours (no shaping necessary).&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Bake as usual: 25-30 minutes at 350°F.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>I divided the dough into two approximately equal portions, baked one in the toaster oven, and kept the other one in the fridge for another 8 hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="bake-1">Bake #1&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>The 1st piece turned out great &amp;ndash; exactly what I had expected from a hard red spring wheat.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-2/20230220_111326.jpg"
alt="Joaquin Oro pan de San Joaquín baked"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The tallow has imparted some savory aroma to the bread.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-2/20230220_104549.jpg"
alt="Joaquin Oro pan de San Joaquín baked"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>toaster oven-baked &lt;em>pan de San Joaquín&lt;/em>. home-milled 100% wholegrain Joaquin Oro flour + non-San Francisco sourdough starter + homemade pineapple yeast water poolish&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The crumb is delightfully light and airy, almost like gossamer; it&amp;rsquo;s exceptionally soft and chewy.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-2/20230220_111631.jpg"
alt="Joaquin Oro pan de San Joaquín baked"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The crust is so thin and crisp that it&amp;rsquo;s almost non-existent.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Sure, it doesn&amp;rsquo;t have Tartine bread&amp;rsquo;s shell of blistered mahogany, but the interior is so chewy and preternaturally moist that it shimmers in the light.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-2/20230220_111504.jpg"
alt="Joaquin Oro pan de San Joaquín baked"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The delicate, nutty flavor of whole wheat Joaquin Oro shines through &amp;ndash; perceptibly different from Turkey Red to me.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I like this &lt;em>pan de San Joaquín&lt;/em> toasted; topped with &lt;em>salsa roja&lt;/em>, crunchy lettuce and thinly-sliced Vadalia onions (for a pleasing texture contrast), and crumbled &lt;em>queso fresco&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-2/20230220_112031.jpg"
alt="Joaquin Oro pan de San Joaquín baked"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>toaster oven-baked &lt;em>pan de San Joaquín&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;h4 id="bake-2">Bake #2&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>Instead of baking the 20-hour retarded piece in an oven, I brought it to a Mardi Gras BBQ thingy and cooked it in a cast-iron skillet on a charcoal-fired grill. Who says February is a month to simply be endured &amp;ndash; a penance to pay before late winter yields to spring?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Magic happens when meat meets charcoal smoke. What about breads?&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-2/20230220_190227.jpg"
alt="Joaquin Oro pan de San Joaquín baked"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>I tossed a handful of black walnut and pistachio shells into the grill towards the end. Nut shells release a great smokey aroma when they burn, due to the oils that naturally occur in the shells. They burn pretty easily and add a marvelous boost of smoky sweetness to food.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-2/20230220_190435.jpg"
alt="Joaquin Oro pan de San Joaquín baked"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>20-hour retarded 100% wholegrain &lt;em>pan de San Joaquín&lt;/em>. cooked on a charcoal-fired BBQ grill. smoked with black walnut and pistachio shells.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>This grilled &lt;em>pan de San Joaquín&lt;/em> delivers an exciting punch of smoky char in first bite.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The crumb is wonderfully airy and springy like the first one, and the subtle tang of the bread becomes more pronounced with each successive bite, finishing on a question mark instead of an exclamation point.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-2/20230220_191648.jpg"
alt="Joaquin Oro pan de San Joaquín baked"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Custardy and glistening.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I like this smoky &lt;em>pan de San Joaquín&lt;/em> fresh or toasted; perfect for dunking in garlicky cioppino.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-2/20230220_190539.jpg"
alt="Joaquin Oro pan de San Joaquín baked"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>smoked wholegrain &lt;em>pan de San Joaquín&lt;/em>, glistening on a BBQ grill in the sun.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>TL;DR&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Joaquin Oro is an excellent bread wheat for sourdough baking.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>You don&amp;rsquo;t need a San Francisco sourdough starter to make excellent bread.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>&lt;em>This is part 2 of my &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/california-grain-adventure/">California Grain Adventure&lt;/a>. If you enjoyed it, why not check out my other &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/archives/">breadstories&lt;/a> or spread the word?&lt;/em>&lt;/p></content></item></channel></rss>