<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>abruzzi rye on HERESY LEVAIN</title><link>/tags/abruzzi-rye/</link><description>Latest experiments in abruzzi rye from HERESY LEVAIN</description><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2023 HERESY LEVAIN 🍞 CC BY-NC-SA 4.0</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 Apr 2021 19:22:12 -0600</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/abruzzi-rye/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Harpy's Lovesong</title><link>/posts/harpys-lovesong/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Apr 2021 19:22:12 -0600</pubDate><guid>/posts/harpys-lovesong/</guid><description>A magical multigrain bread.</description><content>&lt;p>The first time I tasted naturally leavened bread was in April 2014, in Athens, Georgia. I was hitting a low point in life. A friend brought me a loaf of multigrain bread from &lt;a href="https://www.independentbaking.com/">Independent Baking Co.&lt;/a>, a new bakery in the heart of Five Points.&lt;/p>
&lt;div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
&lt;iframe src="https://player.vimeo.com/video/82806228" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" title="vimeo video" webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen>&lt;/iframe>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>I didn&amp;rsquo;t have the faintest idea what sourdough was, but that loaf of bread &amp;ndash; dark caramel-colored crackly crusts enrobed a cream-colored nutty crumb, with a slight tang and a satisfying flavor &amp;ndash; cheered me up somehow and remained etched in my memory.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This bread is an attempt to recreate that magical warm moment.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/harpys-lovesong/202104030952.jpg"
alt="Harpy&amp;#39;s Lovesong"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;h4 id="levain">Levain&lt;/h4>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>100g freshly milled brown teff (Desert Oasis, NV)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>100g whole milk&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>stiff WW starter&lt;/td>
&lt;td>15%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>In case you didn&amp;rsquo;t know, teff is the world&amp;rsquo;s smallest &amp;ldquo;grain&amp;rdquo; (actually the seed of an Ethiopian grass) that&amp;rsquo;s mostly bran and germ.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Microwave freshly milled teff flour and milk for 2 mins, until a porridge consistency is reached. Add the starter after the mixture has cooled off completely. Leave the levain to mature for 14+ hours at ~65°F.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="soaker">Soaker&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>Soak as many varieties of grains and seeds as you would like. Total dry weight is 40% of the flour weight in the final dough.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>millet&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>quinoa&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>kaniwa&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>amaranth&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>pumpkin seeds&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>rolled oats&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>flaxseeds&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sunflower seeds&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>poppy seeds&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sesame seeds&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>water&lt;/td>
&lt;td>150%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Let the soaker stand at room temperature for 12 hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="dough">Dough&lt;/h4>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>80% extraction wheat flour (Rouge de Bordeaux - Dayspring Farms, GA)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>80%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>whole spelt flour (Sungold spelt - Grapewood Farm, VA)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>whole rye flour (Abruzzi rye - Carter Farms, NC)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>brown rice flour (Charleston Gold - Anson Mills, SC)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>water&lt;/td>
&lt;td>85%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>soaker (not drained)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>shredded coconut (for dusting)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2%-5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Cold-ferment for 24+ hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/harpys-lovesong/202104030955.jpg"
alt="Harpy&amp;#39;s Lovesong"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/harpys-lovesong/202104031001.jpg"
alt="Harpy&amp;#39;s Lovesong"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/harpys-lovesong/202104031002.jpg"
alt="Harpy&amp;#39;s Lovesong"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/harpys-lovesong/202104031029.jpg"
alt="Harpy&amp;#39;s Lovesong"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Harpy&amp;rsquo;s Lovesong, a magical multigrain bread.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure></content></item><item><title>Kyoto by Blimp</title><link>/posts/kyoto-by-blimp/</link><pubDate>Fri, 11 Dec 2020 17:41:59 -0600</pubDate><guid>/posts/kyoto-by-blimp/</guid><description>Marbled &lt;em>matcha&lt;/em> cocoa bread, made with Kyoto Uji &lt;em>matcha&lt;/em> and a blend of Southern flours. A kaleidoscope of fun flavors.</description><content>&lt;p>I love &lt;em>matcha&lt;/em> (抹茶), which is basically powdered green tea. Like anything in life, it&amp;rsquo;s an acquired taste. I hated bitter beers when I first tried them, but now I love the likes of Chimay Cinq Cents and Stone Ruination. If you&amp;rsquo;ve never had &lt;em>matcha&lt;/em> before, you will likely not love it the first time you try it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>So how is &lt;em>matcha&lt;/em> different from other green teas, you ask? Well, first of all, it differs in the preparation process. Most teas are infused with water and the leaves are strained out and discarded, whereas &lt;em>matcha&lt;/em> is actually whisked into hot water, i.e. the tea leaves are consumed directly.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Secondly, &lt;em>matcha&lt;/em> actually goes through extra processes during cultivation compared to the general category of green tea usually referred to as &lt;em>sencha&lt;/em> (煎茶, steamed, rolled, and dried green tea leaves). Once the buds of the &lt;em>Camellia sinensis&lt;/em> tea leaves start to sprout, the entire crop is kept in the shade for about a month before harvesting. This slows down the rate of photosynthesis, increasing the amount of chlorophyll in the leaves. In the end, this produces a tea leaf with a sweet flavor and bold &lt;em>umami&lt;/em>. Lastly, the steamed and then thoroughly dried tea leaves are meticulously ground on a stone mill into a fine powder. This powder form is what makes it possible to add a concentrated green tea flavor to many products.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The Chinese were the first to grow and grind green tea. However, the Japanese were the ones who invented the method of creating &lt;em>matcha&lt;/em> as we know it today.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Japanese tea cultivation started when a 12th-century monk named Myouan Eisai (明菴栄西) brought green tea seeds &amp;ndash; along with the Rinzai school of Zen Buddhism &amp;ndash; from China and planted them on Mt. Sefuri. In addition, he gave tea seeds to Myoue Shounin (明恵上人), a monk from Kousan-ji temple (高山寺) in Toganoo (栂尾), Kyoto. Shounin planted the seeds near the temple and &amp;ndash; voilà! &amp;ndash; this was the start of Uji tea. Oh, Eisai also wrote a book about tea, called Kissa Yojoki (喫茶養生記), often translated as &amp;ldquo;How to Stay Healthy by Drinking Tea.&amp;rdquo; The book begins with &amp;ldquo;Tea is the ultimate mental and medical remedy and has the ability to make one’s life more full and complete”.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For a long time, only the nobility and upper echelons of the Japanese society drank green tea. It was not until the Meiji Restoration at the end of the 19th century that the cultivation, consumption and preparation of green tea became widespread in Japan.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Modern Japan has developed the most advanced and refined industry for the cultivation of a few varieties of green tea. Furthermore, it&amp;rsquo;s the world&amp;rsquo;s second largest green tea producer after China. As green tea became more popular in the West over the last two decades, China has begun to produce more and more of its own &amp;ldquo;&lt;em>matcha&lt;/em>&amp;rdquo; under &amp;ldquo;simulated&amp;rdquo; Japanese farming conditions.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Like wine grapes, the quality and growth of green tea are greatly affected by the region&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em>terroir&lt;/em>. Being Japan&amp;rsquo;s oldest and most famous green tea region means Uji is inevitably a hot spot for tea tourism. People love to visit Kyoto tea country&amp;rsquo;s traditional tea shops and modern tea emporiums, stroll through rolling hills of tea fields, and sample a variety of teas. I know people who have travelled to Uji, Japan to taste &lt;em>matcha&lt;/em> and still feel only so-so about it. Lol.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>There is a Japanese proverb that says &amp;ldquo;good medication is bitter in taste&amp;rdquo; (良薬は口に苦し), and &lt;em>matcha&lt;/em> is one of them. Matcha has a unique, complex taste. It&amp;rsquo;s slightly bitter, with a sweet aftertaste; it&amp;rsquo;s buttery and nutty, with a seaweedy undertone.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>David&amp;rsquo;s Tea &lt;em>matcha&lt;/em> is a good place to start, although it&amp;rsquo;s likely not the best &lt;em>matcha&lt;/em> that you&amp;rsquo;ll ever have.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>One way to enjoy the mild bitterness of &lt;em>matcha&lt;/em> more is to add it to baked goods. Baking enhances the rich aroma of the &lt;em>matcha&lt;/em>, and that&amp;rsquo;s why there are gazillion forms of &lt;em>matcha&lt;/em>-flavored baked goods in Asia.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For this bread, I selected flours from below the Mason Dixon line. The American South is synonymous with sweet tea, and South Carolina remains the only US state that commercially produces tea on a large scale.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;Generally, soft wheats have a high starch yield on milling and a low protein content. They are grown in areas of high rainfall and lower soil fertility, primarily east of the Mississippi River. Low-protein southern flours are deployed to their best advantage in their growing region&amp;rsquo;s specialties-biscuits, pies, and cakes where tenderness is prized over strength. Beyond wheat&amp;rsquo;s given genetic quotient of hardness or softness, environmental conditions determine the hardness of any given crop. Not only the overall protein content but also the quality and specific amounts of each protein present can be affected by seasonal variations.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Joseph Amendola &amp;amp; Nicole Rees, &lt;em>Understanding Baking: The Art and Science of Baking&lt;/em>, 3rd edition, page 7.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Wheats grown in the South generally aren&amp;rsquo;t very strong. This bread is another reminder to pay attention to the quality and property of ingredients grown in a particular region.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="matcha-dough">Matcha dough&lt;/h4>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>88% extraction wheat flour (Rouge de Bordeaux - Dayspring Farms, GA)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;em>matcha&lt;/em>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>3%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>brewed &lt;em>genmaicha&lt;/em>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>80%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>The &lt;em>matcha&lt;/em> I used here is Marukyu-Koyamaen &lt;em>aoarashi matcha&lt;/em> (丸久小山園の抹茶青嵐). It&amp;rsquo;s an entry-grade &lt;em>matcha&lt;/em> with intense flavors &amp;ndash; better for baking than sipping.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>3% &lt;em>matcha&lt;/em> may seem too little, but &lt;em>matcha&lt;/em> is only consumed about 1-2g at a time. &lt;em>Usucha&lt;/em> (薄茶), the common &lt;em>matcha&lt;/em> preparation, usually calls for 1 tsp/2g of &lt;em>matcha&lt;/em> per 70-80ml of water.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Everyday/ceremonial (not cooking) &lt;em>matcha&lt;/em> is usually made from high-grade &lt;em>gyokuro&lt;/em> (玉露), not &lt;em>sencha&lt;/em>. But for cooking &lt;em>matcha&lt;/em>, you don&amp;rsquo;t need such high grade. You could technically make your own at home, by pulverizing some high-quality green tea leaves in a coffee grinder and sifting a few times to get a fine powder. It&amp;rsquo;s totally fine in lattes, smoothies and baked goods. Some heresy right here.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>So, wtf is &lt;em>genmaicha&lt;/em> and why did I use it instead of plain h₂o? Well, &lt;em>genmaicha&lt;/em> (玄米茶) is basically a Japanese popcorn tea: a blend of roasted puffed brown rice and &lt;em>sencha&lt;/em>. You taste green tea and popcorn at the same time &amp;ndash; the best of both worlds!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I wanted a robust green tea flavor in this bread. That&amp;rsquo;s why I brewed a pot of Ippodo&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em>genmaicha&lt;/em> and soaked the flour in the cooled tea.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Rouge de Bordeaux was the OG baguette wheat from the Bordeaux region of France. It gained popularity in the 19th century among artisan bakers who loved the smooth, mellow flavor, aroma of spices, and robust performance.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="cocoa-dough">Cocoa dough&lt;/h4>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>whole spelt flour (Sungold spelt - Grapewood Farm, VA)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>50%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>cornmeal (Bloody Butcher red corn - Five Maples Farm, VA)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>whole rye flour (Abruzzi rye - Carter Farms, NC)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>brown rice flour (Charleston Gold - Anson Mills, SC)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>whole pea flour (Sea Island red peas - Marsh Hen Mill, SC)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>roasted soybean flour (Maehara Seifun kuromame kinako - Tanba, Kyoto)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>cocoa powder (Pernigotti cacao amaro)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>h₂o&lt;/td>
&lt;td>90%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Spelt is an ancient wheat with a golden color and notes of honey and fresh hay. It&amp;rsquo;s quite versatile &amp;ndash; strong enough for bread and pasta, but delicate enough for pastry doughs, cakes and cookies.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Just mix everything together, and leave them in two separate containers in the fridge overnight. Yes, overnight autolyse.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Obviously, the green dough is going to be the stronger sibling and do most of the heavy-lifting.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Next day, I let them warm up to room temperature before adding 40% ripe levain and 2% salt. The green dough was very extensible and easy to work with. The cocoa dough, not so much.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I laminated both &lt;em>pâtes&lt;/em> together and added 10% toasted walnuts and 20% dried fruits (raisins, dates, and jujubes).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The dough went through 4 hours of bulk fermentation at room temperature with 3 folds, and had ~50% rise in volume before preshaping.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>2 hours of warm proof in a loaf pan before baking. Fantastic oven spring.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/kyoto-by-blimp/202012111150.jpg"
alt="85% extraction Turkey Red wheat bread"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Cooled overnight and sliced next morning.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The bread turned out less airy than I expected. The &lt;em>matcha&lt;/em> turned out more hydroscopic than I thought it would be, and the green &lt;em>pâte&lt;/em> was a little too taut. Next time I&amp;rsquo;ll definitely increase the hydration. The green tea flavor was noticeable but mellow.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The crumb was tender, moist, and mildly chewy. A taster said the sweet fruity aroma immediately reminded him of spiced apple cider!&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/kyoto-by-blimp/202012111327.jpg"
alt="85% extraction Turkey Red wheat bread"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>This one was a lot of fun to eat: one bite tasted tart like a granny smith apple, the next bite was reminiscent of a &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/shinsekai-ambrosia/">Lärabar&lt;/a>, yet the next brought to mind mocha, nougat, hazelnut&amp;hellip; A kaleidoscope of flavors.&lt;/p></content></item><item><title>Joeliath</title><link>/posts/joeliath/</link><pubDate>Wed, 28 Aug 2019 22:19:17 -0700</pubDate><guid>/posts/joeliath/</guid><description>Joe vs. Bread: Freshly milled grains and spent coffee grounds fuse to create pure magic.</description><content>&lt;h4 id="coffee-grounds-are-edible">Coffee grounds are edible&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>Back in my college days, whenever I needed to pull some all-nighters, I would always chew on a handful of chocolate-covered Colombian coffee beans.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A while ago, I got some Ethiopian Amaro Gayo green coffee beans. I roasted them at home until just after the first crack, and have been drinking the cold brew as my summer morning Joe. It&amp;rsquo;s acidic, floral and citrusy, reminding me of orange marmalade and cocoa.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The zero-waster in me couldn&amp;rsquo;t stand the thought of just throwing out these spent coffee grounds, so memories of chewing gourmet coffee beans in college gave me the idea of incorporating these spent coffee grounds into baked goods. ☕🍞&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A Danish startup has come up with &lt;a href="https://www.kaffebueno.com/post/introducing-kaffe-bueno-coffee-flour">Kaffe Bueno Flour&lt;/a>!&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Kaffe Bueno Flour® comes from used coffee grounds, recycled from selected hotels and offices in Copenhagen. Then, we extract the oil inside the grounds and further sterilise them. &lt;/p>
&lt;p>The result is a naturally gluten-free coffee flour. Although it comes from coffee, its coffee taste is mostly gone along with the oil extracted. Its taste leans towards nutty, chocolaty side. &lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>They even have a &lt;a href="https://www.kaffebueno.com/post/how-to-make-sourdough-bread-with-coffee-flour-vegan-recipe">recipe&lt;/a> for a coffee sourdough, in which the coffee flour is ~11% of flour weight in the final dough.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Dan Lepard has a formula for his famous &lt;a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20190908145402/https://www.jeremycherfas.net/blog/dan-lepard-s-black-pepper-rye">Black Pepper Rye&lt;/a>, which uses brewed black coffee to make a roux with a rye first.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>So, on the spur of the moment, I strained some coffee grounds from my cold brew, and left them to dry over a dehumidifier for a few hours. When the grounds were thoroughly dry, I ground them again in a coffee grinder to yield a much finer &amp;ldquo;coffee flour.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="white-wheat--white-flour">White wheat =/= white flour&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>I wanted to use mild-tasting flour for this bread, so the coffee flavor can come through. Colorado Windy White, a modern hard white winter wheat (HWWW) variety grown by Sunflower Acres (the retail front is Grains from the Plains), fits the bill.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>When you grind up white wheat to make flour, it looks off-white, kind of like unbleached &amp;ldquo;white flour.&amp;rdquo; But they are not the same thing. Most commercial white flour is made from red wheat that has been refined (the bitter, bulky parts of bran and germ are removed, leaving only the starchy endosperm) &amp;ndash; and in most cases it has been treated with bleach and potassium bromate, and then &amp;ldquo;enriched&amp;rdquo; with artificial vitamins since the natural ones have been lost during processing. This results in a homogeneous product with a long shelf life, which produces consistently fluffy baked goods &amp;ndash; but at the cost of nutrition and flavor.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>White wheat is pretty much the same as red wheat, except that it has no major genes for bran color. White whole wheat flour has a milder, sweeter flavor than red whole wheat flour, due to lack of phenolic compounds and lower tannin content.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In the US, many breads are made with hard white (whole) wheat containing &amp;gt;= 10% protein:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Brands owned by Bimbo, the largest bakery company in the US: Arnold, Sara Lee, Mrs. Bairds, Stroehmann, Freihofer&amp;rsquo;s, EarthGrains, Brownberry, Francisco, Grandma Sycamore&amp;rsquo;s, J.J. Nissen, Lender&amp;rsquo;s Bagels, Oroweat, etc.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Brands owned by Flowers Foods, the second largest bakery company in the US: Wonder Bread, Nature&amp;rsquo;s Own, Captain John Derst&amp;rsquo;s, Sunbeam, Evangeline Maid, Mrs. Freshley&amp;rsquo;s, Merita, Cobblestone Mill, European Bakers, Mi Casa, Bunny Bread, HomePride, Tastykake, and Dave&amp;rsquo;s Killer Bread.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Pepperidge Farm (Campbell&amp;rsquo;s)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Wholesome Harvest (Maple Leaf Bakery)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Aunt Millie&amp;rsquo;s (Perfection Bakeries, Inc)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Soft white wheat (typically &amp;lt; 10% protein) is the star ingredient in Kellogg&amp;rsquo;s Mini Wheats and Wheat Flakes, as well as Nabisco&amp;rsquo;s Triscuit crackers. Kellogg&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Open for Breakfast&amp;rdquo; website tells the stories of a 4,000-acre soft white wheat farm in Michigan, close to the company&amp;rsquo;s HQ. There is some evidence that breakfast cereals made with white whole wheat hold their crispness longer in milk. Triscuit&amp;rsquo;s product description goes, &amp;ldquo;We like to think of Soft White Winter Wheat as a kind of cashmere of wheat because of its soft texture and delicious taste. It&amp;rsquo;s what gives Triscuit its golden color, distinctive crunch and 24 grams of delicious whole grain goodness per serving.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Asians love soft white wheat, too, because they believe it makes better noodles &amp;ndash; bright, clear white, soft inside but firm on the surface. When made with white wheat, fresh refrigerated noodles will not develop black specks.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In the Japanese prefecture Kagawa, the home of the &lt;em>udon&lt;/em> noodle, a white wheat reclamation is underway. Before the 1960s, fields of wheat covered the town of Sanuki (the old name of Kagawa). The local Sanuki wheat would be harvested, milled and sifted to make flour for Sanuki &lt;em>udon&lt;/em>. But after repeated bad weather in the early 1960s, wheat production declined sharply and imported Australian Standard White (ASW) wheat soon became the major variety. Some local noodle makers and aficionados found imported wheat to be inferior and produced subpar &lt;em>udon&lt;/em> flour, so they worked together with small farmers to revive Kagawa&amp;rsquo;s soul food, i.e. &lt;em>udon&lt;/em> made from Sanuki-grown wheat. In 2000, they developed a new variety of wheat for &lt;em>udon&lt;/em> named &lt;em>sanuki no yume&lt;/em> (&amp;ldquo;Sanuki&amp;rsquo;s dream&amp;rdquo;) and later in 2009 a newer variety based on the OG. Since 2013, almost the entire wheat field in Kawaga grows &lt;em>sanuki no yume&lt;/em> 2009. Kinoshita Flour Mills in Kagawa sells a &lt;em>udon&lt;/em> flour made with 100% Kagawa-grown wheat (8.5% protein). They use a meticulous milling process to remove all the bran because, as explained on their website, &amp;ldquo;speck, a small piece of bran, would damage the taste and the food texture of the Udon.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>They can keep their noodles, I will make bread. There are thousands of other foods I would rather eat. &lt;em>Mon pain quotidien&lt;/em>, first and foremost.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="milling">Milling&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>Bread made from finely milled wholegrain flour has a tender texture, a slight chew, a rustic hue, and robust wheat flavor.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;code>Note&lt;/code>: Working with freshly milled single-varietal whole grains is not as predictable as a standard bag of King Arthur or other name-brand ﬂour, which remain consistent by blending varieties of wheats from multiple years or regions. Whole grains are living and vibrant; shelf-stable flours are dead. Working with whole grains is challenging and requires you to be willing to learn new skills and pay greater attention to the process, rather than relying on recipes where you can simply plug in your ingredients and yield the same results. Grains are a lot like coffee &amp;ndash; you have to think about, &amp;ldquo;When was this roasted? When was this ground?&amp;rdquo; You can taste the difference in ﬂavor and texture.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Freshly milled flour works a bit differently from shelf-stable flour:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>It contains more enzymes and minerals, and ferments faster than store-bought ones;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>It contains volatile oils from the bran and germ; store-bought flour has had some oils evaporated off or may not even have had the germ in it, depending on the brand.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>Freshly milled wholegrain flour is best for Desem, the old Flemish method specifically developed for 100% wholegrain bread.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="bolting">Bolting&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>I ground up the wheat berries in a grain mill, and sifted the flour through a mesh sieve to screen out the coarsest bits.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Bolted flour contains almost all of the germ, and the softer parts of the bran. In exchange for a loss of mainly fiber and minerals, the resulting flour performs more like a bread or all-purpose flour while maintaining some of the rich flavor, nutritional benefits, and lovely color of wholegrain flours. It has a creamy texture.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Historically, bolted flour was sifted through &lt;a href="https://www.angelfire.com/journal/millbuilder/boulting.html">a piece of cloth&lt;/a>. Nowadays it&amp;rsquo;s typically done through a metal or plastic screen.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The total flour out of the sifter divided by the total flour out of the mill would give you the extraction percentage. The higher the percentage, the closer to whole grain flour it is. 100% extraction is whole wheat. Home-milling and bolting wheat will give you incredible flavor that&amp;rsquo;s impossible to beat.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="formula">Formula&lt;/h4>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>85% extraction wheat flour (Windy White - Sunflower Acres, CO)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>83%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>whole rye flour (Abruzzi rye - Jones Farms, CO)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>homemade coffee flour&lt;/td>
&lt;td>12%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>homemade cold brew coffee&lt;/td>
&lt;td>88%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;em>zakvaska&lt;/em> levain&lt;/td>
&lt;td>40%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>flaxseeds (for coating)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>3%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Do the same thing with whole rye berries &amp;ndash; mill them, but skip the bolting. Leave the rye flour coarse and wholesome. Rye is a cousin to wheat and mills similarly, but the two have very different baking qualities.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>IMO, rye is one of the tastiest, most nutrient-dense grains. It yields a peppery-earthy flavor and improves the keeping quality of whatever you make with it. Feeding sourdough starter with rye keeps it vigorous, sour and fruity.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Abruzzi rye is an Italian heirloom variety. The kernels are bluish-gold in appearance, and smell nutty and sweet like a blend of herbal spices and citrus. It was famous in the Carolinas during the colonial era. Did you know it was the very rye flour used in &amp;ldquo;thirded bread&amp;rdquo;, a cost-cutting recipe that combined rye, wheat, and cornmeal (instead of oats) plus the sweet upgrade of molasses, such as Boston brown bread.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Small amounts have big results. Blending merely 5% of rye into a wheat bread will add a depth of flavor, without overpowering others.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="method">Method&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>I have a big batch of &lt;em>zakvaska&lt;/em> left from making rye bread &lt;em>kvass&lt;/em>. So I used some &lt;em>zakvaska&lt;/em>, instead of the usual WW sourdough starter, to build a 100% hydration levain for this bread. It doubled in volume overnight, brimming with bubbles.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I autolysed all of the flours with coffee for 1 hour. Then I added the levain and salt.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I did 5 folds during the first 3 hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>After 5 hours of warm bulk-fermentation, I shaped the dough into a log, coated it with a handful of flaxseeds, and placed it in my ghetto banneton. I left it in the fridge overnight to proof.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Next day, I left the dough in a warm place for 2.5 hours to finish proofing. The dough rose 80%-90%, and felt so jiggly! Then I baked it.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/joeliath/20190828182954.jpg"
alt="Joeliath"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The bread almost tripled from the initial dough! The crust bloomed nicely from the seams and had beautifully caramelized spots.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/joeliath/20190828183154.jpg"
alt="Joeliath"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/joeliath/20190828183208.jpg"
alt="Joeliath"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;h4 id="cooling">Cooling&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>The final stage of baking bread is letting it cool properly. If you were to slice into a hot loaf of bread, you would not be doing it any justice. The heat retained inside the bread continues to cook it and develop flavor/texture, so slicing it too early interrupts this process prematurely. Also, cutting warm bread allows moisture to escape into the air, which means it will go stale faster.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As the breads cool, the process of starch retrogradation is completed and the water molecules move outward, evenly, toward the crust. If you were to cut into a hot loaf, the crumb is still too soft and the bread won&amp;rsquo;t slice neatly, it will tend to be gummy and stick to your knife. Allow your loaves to firm up and cool to about body temperature before slicing. Breads that can be eaten while they are still warm are rolls and baguettes, because the crust-to-crumb ratio is so high, and there is not much further internal cooking that has to take place.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/joeliath/20190828201251.jpg"
alt="Joeliath"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;h4 id="tasting">Tasting&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>The crust is thin and crispy, and the crumb springy and soft. The cold brew coffee lent a nice color to the bread. The coffee flour definitely added a unique bite and a smoky accent. There is no smell or taste of morning Joe, but you can feel the coffee grounds caressing your tongue.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/joeliath/20190828201313.jpg"
alt="Joeliath"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Joeliath, a wonderful bread made with cold brew coffee and spent coffee grounds.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>I enjoyed the bread with a wedge of Comté &amp;ndash; a flavor explosion! The pair reminded me of condensed milk, cocoa and macadamia nut. Washed it down with some &lt;em>el cheapo&lt;/em> Pacific Peaks merlot. The smokiness of the wine reminded me of the coffee notes in this bread.&lt;/p></content></item></channel></rss>