<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>california on HERESY LEVAIN</title><link>/tags/california/</link><description>Latest experiments in california from HERESY LEVAIN</description><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2023 HERESY LEVAIN 🍞 CC BY-NC-SA 4.0</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 25 Mar 2023 02:31:32 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/california/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>California Dreamin' #7: Desert Gold</title><link>/posts/california-dreamin-7/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Mar 2023 02:31:32 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/california-dreamin-7/</guid><description>[California Grain Adventure #7] &lt;em>Pane Ricco&lt;/em>, a luxuriously high-hydration bread with 100% wholegrain Desert Gold durum, sour cream, cracked black pepper, and salty addictive cheeses.</description><content>&lt;p>&lt;em>This is part 7 of my &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/california-grain-adventure/">California Grain Adventure&lt;/a>.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>The West begins where the average annual rainfall drops below twenty inches.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Bernard DeVoto&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>The Imperial Valley in southern California is often cited as a great example of modern desert agriculture.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>From what I&amp;rsquo;ve seen, the Imperial Valley is a place of jarring contrasts. Half of the valley remains in its natural state, aka. a bone-dry desert with some breathtaking sand dunes; the other half exemplifies a modern engineering marvel &amp;ndash; mile after mile of green fields lined by irrigation canals and sometimes shrouded by showers of water from sprinklers.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-7/california-imperial-valley.jpg"
alt="Map of Imperial Valley, California"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Imperial Valley is one of the oldest farming communities in the Colorado River basin. It lies in the Colorado Desert section of the Sonoran Desert, with overwhelming heat and meager average rainfall (about 3&amp;quot; or 76 mm per year). Dirt was carried here over millions of years by the Colorado River, as it carved the Grand Canyon ever deeper.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Thanks to irrigation &amp;ndash; that is, thanks to the US Bureau of Reclamation &amp;ndash; states such as California, Arizona, and Idaho became populous and wealthy; millions settled in regions where nature, left alone, would have countenanced thousands at best; great valleys and hemispherical basins metamorphosed from desert blonde to semi-tropical green.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Agriculture is the economic backbone of the Imperial Valley due to irrigation, which is supplied entirely from the Colorado River via the All-American Canal. Thousands of acres of prime farmland have transformed the desert into one of the most productive farming regions in California with an annual crop production of over $1 billion. Evidently, agriculture accounts for nearly half of all local employment.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-7/SaltonSeaArielFromSouth.jpg"
alt="Aerial view of Imperial Valley and Salton Sea"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Aerial view of the Imperial Valley and Salton Sea from the south.&lt;/p>&lt;p>Source: &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Imperial_Valley,_California#/media/File:SaltonSeaArielFromSouth.jpg" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">Samboy&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Unlike the Central Valley in the north which draws its water from rain and snow in the Sierra Mountains or pumps it from shrinking underground aquifers, the Imperial Valley has only one source of water: the Colorado River, 80 miles to the east.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The most basic principle governing water use in the western US is &amp;ldquo;first in time, first in right.&amp;rdquo; These lush fields in the Imperial Valley owe their existence to fortune-seeking land speculators and engineers who arrived early and, starting in 1901, dug the first canal to ship water here from the Colorado River. (Prior to the 20th century, this patch was mostly unsettled.) Since most of the Imperial Valley actually lies below sea level &amp;ndash; and well below the canal&amp;rsquo;s starting point on the Colorado River near Yuma, Arizona &amp;ndash; water is able to flow there by gravity alone.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Thanks to the stunning wealth that irrigation farming had produced, California came rolling out of the 1920s like Jay Gatsby in his alabaster phaeton. Agriculture was California; there were no sprawling defense and aerospace industries, no Silicon Valley.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The Salton Sea was an unfortunate consequence of the engineering failure that marked the construction of the original canal. The current canal, built during the New Deal and named the &lt;a href="https://www.iid.com/water/water-transportation-system/colorado-river-facilities/all-american-canal">All-American Canal&lt;/a>, began delivering water to the Imperial Valley in 1940; two years later, it became the sole water source for Imperial Valley&amp;rsquo;s residents and farmlands.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-7/ImperialValleyfromBC.jpg"
alt="The Imperial Valley from the highway between Tijuana and Mexicali"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Looking north at the Imperial Valley, from the highway between Tijuana and Mexicali.&lt;/p>&lt;p>Source: &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Imperial_Valley,_California#/media/File:ImperialValleyfromBC.jpg" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">CharismaticDespot&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Water delivered to the Imperial Irrigation District (IID) each year by the All-American Canal &amp;ndash; through a vast system of canals, dams, and pipelines &amp;ndash; is enough to cover the entire irrigated land, roughly 500,000 acres, with 5 feet of water.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Imported water and a long growing season allow two crop cycles each year; the Imperial Valley now supplies over 2/3 of winter fruits and vegetables, cotton, and grain for domestic and international markets. The valley also produces most of the lamb and sheep in the US. (This raises a bunch of uncomfortable questions: What&amp;rsquo;s the rest of America doing? Why is the whole nation dependent on a few hundred farms concentrated in an irrigated desert for its food? How did this situation come to be? What happened to Eliot Coleman&amp;rsquo;s four-season farming revolution? &amp;hellip; )&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>Alfalfa is the king crop produced in the Imperial Valley. 1 out of every 3 farmed acres in the valley is dedicated to growing alfalfa, which dries into a high-protein hay commonly used as food for livestock. It&amp;rsquo;s also one of the thirstiest drop; its deep roots sucking up water in a region scorched by a 22-year drought.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Another contradiction of California: How does irrigating alfalfa in 120°F temperatures in the dead of July make any sense at all?&lt;/p>
&lt;div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
&lt;iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/AYBZISNYk8I" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video">&lt;/iframe>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>The Imperial Valley&amp;rsquo;s alfalfa industry is not only one of the largest water users in the basin, but also one of the most powerful.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Large-scale production of water-gorging, low-value crops like alfalfa during a megadrought is possible only because the Imperial Valley is the single biggest controller of rights to Colorado River water and the IID farmers have access to cheap (subsidized) water.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Due to these massive irrigation projects, south of the canal, the Colorado River no longer flows above ground at all for much of the year into Mexico.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The Colorado River, which supplies freshwater to more than 40 million people in the southwestern US and northern Mexico, has been in rapid decline. Reduced snowpack, drought conditions and higher average temperatures have all reduced the river&amp;rsquo;s flow in recent decades. The two biggest reservoirs along the river, Lake Mead and Lake Powell, are each creeping towards a &amp;ldquo;dead pool,&amp;rdquo; an ominous sign that the Colorado River could stop flowing entirely.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Agriculture accounts for ~80% of total water consumption in the Colorado River basin, with roughly half of that going towards the production of alfalfa hay, according to a 2020 &lt;a href="https://core.ac.uk/download/pdf/323061602.pdf">study&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
&lt;iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/g-pygL1-yzM" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video">&lt;/iframe>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>What has all this irrigation amounted to?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Massive industrial storehouses line the area, packed with thousands upon thousands of stacks of alfalfa bales ready to be fed to dairy cows &amp;ndash; but not cows in California&amp;rsquo;s Central Valley or Montana&amp;rsquo;s rangelands. Instead, the alfalfa will be fed to cows across the Pacific &amp;ndash; in China, Japan and Korea, and farther away in Saudi Arabia, the United Arab Emirates, etc. An increasing percentage of the alfalfa produced here is exported.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Growers say the reasons boil down to simple economics. The market for alfalfa hay in southern California has shrunk over the years as dairies have closed or moved elsewhere, while demand for dairy products has grown exponentially in other parts of the world. Meanwhile, it costs little to freight goods on the back haul to China, because the US runs a persistently high trade deficit with China; containers from Asia arrive full but often return empty. Some claim it&amp;rsquo;s actually cheaper to ship hay to China than to haul the same load by truck to dairy farms 400 miles north in the San Joaquin Valley.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Brokers regularly fly in from overseas, some staying at a local golf course and country club. Chinese buyers are wined and dined across the border in Mexicali, which has a long-established Chinese community.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>According to a 2015 &lt;a href="https://pacinst.org/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/CA-Ag-Water-Use.pdf">analysis&lt;/a> by the Pacific Institute, alfalfa production in California uses around 5 acre-feet (6,167 cubic meters) of water. In comparison, sugar beets use roughly 3 acre-feet (3,700 cubic meters), and grains as little as 1 acre-foot (1,233 cubic meters).&lt;/p>
&lt;div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
&lt;iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/EE4uMOtqIc8" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video">&lt;/iframe>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>The top water-using activity in California is growing alfalfa. Farmers in Imperial County currently draw more water from the Colorado River than all of Arizona and Nevada combined. An alfalfa farmer can grow alfalfa 10-12 times a year and sell it for $260-$280/ton. These are not the hardworking family farmers of yesteryear. They are giant agribusiness corporations pulling in $1.8 billion from selling 7 million tons of alfalfa every year in California, according to a University of California, Davis study by Daniel Geisseler and William R. Horwath.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This business has been extremely profitable because alfalfa farmers get 3.4 million acre-feet (1 acre foot =325,851 gallons) of water every year for only $35-$60 per acre-foot. The water you get for your house costs you $800 per acre-foot today, and it could be double that in 10 years' time. You could supply the water needs of 40 million people with that 3.4 million acre-feet. It&amp;rsquo;s likely that enough water for greater Los Angeles is being used to raise irrigated pasture for livestock.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Feeding irrigated grass to cows is as wasteful a use of water as you can conceive. Pasture is hydrologically inefficient in the extreme, and, metabolically speaking, so are cows: You need 7-8 feet of water in the hot deserts to keep grass alive, which means that you need ~50,000 pounds of water to raise 1 pound of cow. (Feeding alfalfa to cows requires even more water, but at least alfalfa fixes nitrogen in the soil.)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If the livestock industry earned California any real money, and if cows (unlike avocados or artichokes) couldn&amp;rsquo;t be raised on rainfall in 35 other states, then giving more water to cows than to humans in the nation&amp;rsquo;s richest and most populous state &amp;ndash; a semi-desert state at the mercy of a precarious water supply &amp;ndash; might make a grain or two of sense.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>During the last few years, companies from Saudi Arabia and the United Arab Emirates have established farming operations on thousands of acres around the Imperial Valley and the adjacent Palo Verde Valley.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Saudi Arabian companies are pumping up groundwater from beneath land they have purchased and are using it to grow alfalfa for export to the Middle East. They have no plan for replacing this scarce and finite groundwater that accumulated over thousands of years.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As a matter of fact, foreign corporations have increased purchases of farmland in the US, particularly in the southwest where longstanding laws on water rights give land owners unlimited access to the valuable water underneath the soil.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Why don&amp;rsquo;t they grow their own alfalfa? Because they are short of water and it&amp;rsquo;s so much cheaper to buy from the US.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Growing water-intensive crops in the US and exporting them to water-scarce countries is a form of geo-economic arbitrage, a natural consequence of the globalization of everything. Essentially, water is exported out of the US in the form of crops like alfalfa, rice, or almonds. Guess who is currently one of the largest net exporters of virtual water in the world?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This trend has been accelerating for decades, despite concerns that this &amp;ldquo;virtual water trading&amp;rdquo; is unsustainable in the long term, especially in drought-plagued areas such as California. If California is &lt;em>really&lt;/em> short of water, why are we shipping it to Asia?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>What this means is, ultimately, the US is not in control of its own farmland &amp;ndash; or food production.&lt;/p>
&lt;div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
&lt;iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/QPEN0o5pbA4" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video">&lt;/iframe>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>Some argue the Imperial Valley is doing good by growing food and feeding the country, and point the finger at some desert metropolises such as Las Vegas, which boasts some 50 million visitors each year and wastes way more &lt;a href="https://www.latimes.com/environment/story/2023-01-29/colorado-river-in-crisis-cracking-down-on-grass">water from Colorado River&lt;/a> with its gushing fountains. The truth is, Las Vegas and Reno represent 95% of Nevada&amp;rsquo;s economy but use 10% of its water &amp;ndash; alfalfa growers use most of the rest.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Water overuse is a prisoner&amp;rsquo;s dilemma and a tragedy of the commons. If free-market mechanisms &amp;ndash; which much of western ag publicly applauds and privately abhors &amp;ndash; were actually allowed to work, the West&amp;rsquo;s water &amp;ldquo;shortage&amp;rdquo; would be exposed for what it is: the sort of shortage you expect when inexhaustible demand chases an almost free good. (If someone were selling Porsches for $3,000 apiece, there would be a shortage of those, too.) California has a shortage of water because it has a surfeit of cows &amp;ndash; it&amp;rsquo;s really almost as simple as that.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If history is any guide, the odds that we can sustain a &amp;ldquo;civilization&amp;rdquo; in deserts would have to be regarded as low. Only one desert civilization, out of dozens that grew up in antiquity, has survived uninterrupted into modern times. And Egypt&amp;rsquo;s approach to irrigation was fundamentally different from all the rest.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-7/imperial-valley-google-maps-review.png"
alt="Review of Imperial Valley, California"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>A user review for Imperial County, California (posted on Google Maps)&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h3 id="pane-ricco">pane ricco&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>It just struck me that I should make a &lt;em>pane ricco&lt;/em> (rich bread). I named it as such because in the western US, it&amp;rsquo;s often said that water flows uphill toward money. And it literally does. Water leaps 3,000 feet across the Tehachapi Mountains in gigantic siphons to slay the thirst of Los Angeles, as it&amp;rsquo;s shoved 1,000 feet out of Colorado River canyons to hydrate Phoenix and Palm Springs and the irrigated lands around them. Water is wealth in the West.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-7/20230324_174201.jpg"
alt="pane ricco with Desert Gold durum"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>handmade &lt;em>pane ricco&lt;/em> with wholegrain Desert Gold durum flour&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>This durum dough uses as much water and milk derivatives as it could handle, which, by the West Coast&amp;rsquo;s definition, is rich.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Desert Gold durum flour, 100% extraction&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>400g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>water, divided&lt;/td>
&lt;td>125%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>500g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>whole-milk sour cream&lt;/td>
&lt;td>20%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>80g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>whole durum levain (60% hydration)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>30%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>120g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sea salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>4g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>olive oil&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>40g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>black peppercorns, crushed&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>4g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->cheeses, finely grated&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>40g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>The process is pretty much the same as &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/california-dreamin-4">&lt;em>pan integral de sonora blanca&lt;/em>&lt;/a>. Basically, keep going with &lt;em>bassinage&lt;/em> until the dough became so fragile that it might break down anytime.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I baked the bread on a BBQ grill (again!).&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-7/20230324_174619.jpg"
alt="pane ricco with Desert Gold durum"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>handmade &lt;em>pane ricco&lt;/em> with wholegrain Desert Gold durum flour&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The classic flavor combination of &lt;em>cacio e pepe&lt;/em> never disappoints.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The crust is beautifully caramelized; firm and crisp, with a distinct smokey char.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-7/20230324_173604.jpg"
alt="pane ricco with Desert Gold durum"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>handmade &lt;em>pane ricco&lt;/em> with wholegrain Desert Gold durum flour&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The crumb is light, fluffy, and airy, with distinct honeycomb layers.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-7/20230324_173653.jpg"
alt="pane ricco with Desert Gold durum"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>handmade &lt;em>pane ricco&lt;/em> with wholegrain Desert Gold durum flour&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The texture is soft and tender, yet springy and chewy. The taste reminds me of roasted chickpeas. Black peppercorns provide a interesting texture contrast, and lend a mild spiced kick to the flavor of the crumb. The combination with salty addictive cheeses is mouthwatering.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-7/20230324_175617.jpg"
alt="pane ricco with Desert Gold durum"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>handmade &lt;em>pane ricco&lt;/em> with wholegrain Desert Gold durum flour&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>And this bread toasts like a dream.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="gnocchi">Gnocchi&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>I made a plate of plump sourdough &lt;em>gnocchi&lt;/em> as well, with Desert Gold durum, &lt;em>masa harina&lt;/em>, and Yukon Gold potatoes.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-7/20230324_102531.jpg"
alt="handmade sourdough gnocchi with Desert Gold durum"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>handmade sourdough gnocchi with Yukon Gold potatoes, wholegrain Desert Gold durum flour, and &lt;em>masa harina&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Formula:&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Desert Gold durum flour, 100% extraction&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>50g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;em>masa harina&lt;/em>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>50g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Yukon Gold potatoes, roasted &amp;amp; riced&lt;/td>
&lt;td>80%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>400g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>butter, softened&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>50g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sourdough discard&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>50g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>These fork-sized orbs were sauced with garlicky sun-dried tomatoes, topped with fresh basil leaves and shaved parmigiano-reggiano.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I could eat this every day and be happy.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-7/20230324_194435.jpg"
alt="handmade potato gnocchi with Desert Gold durum sauced"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>handmade sourdough gnocchi, served with sun-dried tomatoes, fresh basil, and shaved parmigiano-reggiano&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>&lt;code>Note&lt;/code>:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Kamut (khorasan) wheat is actually very close to durum, just a larger grain size. If you can&amp;rsquo;t get durum, try kamut.&lt;/p>
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>I used equal amounts of Parmigiano-Reggiano Stravecchio (aged for 5 years), Gruyère Vieux (aged for 18 months), and Pecorino Romano (aged for 12 months).&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/section></content></item><item><title>California Dreamin' #6: Desert Gold</title><link>/posts/california-dreamin-6/</link><pubDate>Sun, 19 Mar 2023 01:15:42 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/california-dreamin-6/</guid><description>[California Grain Adventure #6] My interpretation of the ancient Sicilian &lt;em>pane nero&lt;/em>: 100% wholegrain Desert Gold durum flour at 140% hydration, leavened with sourdough, flavored with tahini, and coated in black sesame seeds. A nutty and custardy crumb enrobed in a crunchy sesame crust. Soft like a brioche, chewy like a pasta.</description><content>&lt;p>&lt;em>This is part 6 of my &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/california-grain-adventure/">California Grain Adventure&lt;/a>.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A few years ago I drove through Tucson, Arizona with a friend. We stopped by an unbelievably highly rated artisan bakery in town and tried a few different kinds of their bread (some loaves contained a small percentage of locally grown &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/white-sonora/">White Sonora&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/desert-gold-durum/">Desert Durum&lt;/a>). Each single one of these breads we got tasted like burnt toast. A big question mark popped into my head: Do professional bakers not know that they can score bread with beautiful designs &lt;em>without&lt;/em> burning it and making it so bitter, so hard to bite through the crust, and so tough to eat? I was more than disappointed because of all the hype. Literally every loaf needed to come out 10 minutes sooner. Luckily, the interior was decent enough to be edible; not great, still better than all the other bakeries in Tucson combined, which says a lot about bread culture in Tucson &amp;ndash; heck, city is better known for flour tortillas than levain. I swore next time I&amp;rsquo;d skip Tucson and check out some &lt;em>panaderías&lt;/em> in Sonora, Mexico instead. &amp;ldquo;Artisan&amp;rdquo; is one of the most used/abused words today; it just means &amp;ldquo;we are new to this.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We kept on going along I-8 E towards San Diego. Soon after we crossed the Arizona-California state border, we passed the Imperial Valley, a sprawling patch in the Sonoran Desert, hemmed in by the Salton Sea to the north and Mexico to the south.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I probably would haven&amp;rsquo;t thought about the place again if it weren&amp;rsquo;t for the Desert Durum® wheat.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-6/20230318_173853.jpg"
alt="pane nero with Desert Gold durum"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>handmade Desert Gold durum &lt;em>pane nero&lt;/em>: 100% wholegrain Desert Gold durum flour at 140% hydration, leavened with sourdough, flavored with nutty tahini, and coated in black sesame seeds.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>Today the Imperial Valley produces more than half of the durum in California. Durum used to grown mainly in Siskiyou and Modoc Counties in the northernmost part of the state, until a few decades ago, when durum production moved to the southernmost part.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Durum (&lt;em>Triticum turgidum, spp. Durum&lt;/em>) is an ancient variety of hard red spring wheat, a close relative of ancient emmer that is exceptionally hard &amp;ndash; hence the name &amp;ldquo;durum,&amp;rdquo; which is Latin for &amp;ldquo;hard,&amp;rdquo; and the species is the hardest of all wheats. As such, it requires significant force to mill into sandy-textured, golden-colored semolina for pasta and more finely ground durum flour for breads and pastries. Coupled with a high protein content (typically &amp;gt;12%), durum is a miller&amp;rsquo;s delight (or challenge).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Durum is genetically less evolved than the modern bread wheat (&lt;em>Triticum aestivum&lt;/em>), but stands out among other wheat varieties with its unique characteristics. Most of the durum grown today is amber durum; the grains are larger than other types of wheat berries, and have a beautiful amber color due to the extra carotenoid pigments (the naturally occurring compounds that give red, orange, and yellow vegetables their vibrant color), which also contribute to its distinct flavor that can be described as nuttier and slightly sweeter than modern wheat.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-6/desert-durum-berries.jpg"
alt="Desert Gold durum wheat berries"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Desert Gold durum wheat berries, from the Imperial Valley of California. Durum wheat berries are the source of the semolina flour used to make one of the food staples of the world &amp;ndash; pasta &amp;ndash; as well as other traditional delicacies such as couscous and bulgur.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Durum has a yellow endosperm, which gives pasta its distinct color. When durum is initially milled, the endosperm is ground into a granular product called &lt;em>semolina&lt;/em>, which has a texture more like cornmeal and is ideal for pasta. Typically, the endosperm is separated from the bran and germ of the grain; only the endosperm is milled. It&amp;rsquo;s also possible to keep all the components, resulting in a wholegrain durum semolina.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you have ever tried making Jeff Hamelman&amp;rsquo;s durum bread from his &lt;em>Bread&lt;/em>, you may have tripped over &amp;ldquo;durum flour.&amp;rdquo; This usually refers to very finely milled durum flour, aka. &lt;em>semola rimacinata&lt;/em> (remilled semolina, sometimes labeled &amp;ldquo;extra fancy&amp;rdquo; durum flour). After separating coarse durum midds, the semolina flour is re-milled several times until it resembles a fine powder. It&amp;rsquo;s the finest grind possible for durum and has the palest color, though it still looks yellow due to durum&amp;rsquo;s high carotenoid pigment concentration. Durum flour is great for softer-type noodles and some types of artisan bread that don&amp;rsquo;t require the elasticity of a high-rising flour. Again, durum flour can either be refined or wholegrain.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Despite its relatively high protein content, durum&amp;rsquo;s gluten quality is different from that of modern bread wheat. While it forms a relatively stretchy dough, the dough structure tends to be fragile and weak, easily breaking down if mixed too much or fermented for too long. As such, breads made with mostly semolina or durum flours tend to have a dense and chewy texture. In some parts of the world, such as Altamura, Italy, &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->durum breads&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --> are beloved for that specific texture as well as distinct flavor.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-6/ravioli-raw.jpg"
alt="Desert Gold durum ravioli"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>handmade wholegrain Desert Gold durum sourdough ravioli, stuffed with mozzarella, fresh basil leaves, and parmigiano-reggiano&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>So why is durum so prized for pasta-making?&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Texture&lt;/strong>: The main reason is the gluten in durum is strong but not particularly elastic, which means pasta made from this type of flour will keep its shape and the cherished &lt;em>al dente&lt;/em> texture after cooking.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Taste&lt;/strong>: Durum has a delicious nutty flavor with an earthy aroma.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Aesthetics&lt;/strong>: Durum has a rich golden color, which naturally evokes a happy feeling about the quality of the pasta and meals made with it. High-quality pasta awakens all the senses &amp;ndash; it&amp;rsquo;s an immersive experience to be savored.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>California is recognized for growing the best durum in the world. California durum varieties tend to have high yellow pigment, high gluten strength, and make a perfect &lt;em>al dente&lt;/em> whole-wheat pasta.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you have ever enjoyed Barilla pasta in your favorite Italian dish, you have most likely consumed Desert Durum® wheat from Imperial County, CA. The Imperial Valley is the main location for the production of the Desert Durum®, a special type of durum with excellent quality that is highly demanded by various local and international pasta makers like Barilla Pasta. The success of the Desert Durum® wheat is owed to the hard work of UC-Davis professor and researcher, Jorge Dubcovsky.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-6/ravioli-cooked.jpg"
alt="Desert Gold durum ravioli sauced"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>handmade wholegrain Desert Gold durum sourdough ravioli, cooked and served with creamy sun-dried tomato sauce, shredded Parmigiano-Reggiano, and fresh basil&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Desert Gold is a Desert Durum® variety with high-yield potential and excellent pasta quality; it&amp;rsquo;s also well adapted to the San Joaquin Valley and the Imperial Valley of California. It&amp;rsquo;s very similar to Desert King, but has two genes for improved yellow pigment in pasta and one gene for reduced grain cadmium content (a beneficial human health trait).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>To be labeled as Desert Durum® commercially, the grain must be at least 90% produced under irrigation in the desert valleys and lowland of Arizona or California. These are areas of high temperatures (May-June temperatures average 90°F) and low rainfall (annual precipitation averages less than 200 mm). Desert Durum® is planted November through February and harvested in May and June.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="milling">milling&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Most of the durum produced (under irrigation) in the desert valleys and lowlands of Arizona and California are rated &lt;strong>No. 1 Hard Amber Durum (HAD)&lt;/strong>, a subclass of durum under the Official US Standards for Grain. HAD has &amp;gt;=75% hard, vitreous kernels of amber color, and sets the &amp;ldquo;gold standard&amp;rdquo; for premium pasta, couscous, etc.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-6/desert-durum-joaquin.jpg"
alt="Desert Gold durum vs. Joaquin Oro"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Desert Gold durum (left) vs. Joaquin Oro (right), both grown in California.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The vitreousness of durum wheat has traditionally been regarded by the wheat industry worldwide as an important quality factor. The average vitreous kernel content (HVAC) of Desert Durum® is &amp;gt;=90%. When compared to non-vitreous (starchy and piebald) kernels, vitreous kernels generally have improved cooking quality, better pasta color, coarser granulation, and higher protein content &amp;ndash; and thus sell at a premium. That comes with a string attached, of course: The glassy and translucent vitreous kernels are significantly harder to mill than the opaque starchy kernels, which are as hard as common bread wheats. (Piebald kernels are intermediate in protein content, but comparable in hardness to vitreous kernels.)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;ve never milled durum before, but I&amp;rsquo;ve often heard that durum milling is a complex procedure involving repetitive grinding and sieving, in order to obtain maximal semolina yield and the least amount of bran powder. Since the durum endosperm is extremely hard and vitreous, millers usually peel or pearl the kernels first to remove the outer layers of bran, to help improve the efficiency of durum processing.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>These Desert Gold durum berries shared by friends at the California Wheat Commission were super easy to mill. I ran them through a countertop electric WonderMill only once (on Bread Flour setting), and it turned out fine enough for my use.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-6/desert-durum-flour.jpg"
alt="Desert Gold durum flour"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Freshly milled Desert Gold durum, unsifted. It smells nutty and toasty, like roasted chickpeas!&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>I guess this first grind would be called &lt;em>semola di grano duro integrale&lt;/em> in Italy. The texture is somewhat gritty, less coarse than typical semolina but not as fine as flour. It has an amber yellow color and contains every part of the grain.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>OMG, freshly milled Desert Gold durum has such an intoxicating aroma, reminiscent of roasted chickpeas!&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="pane-nero">&lt;em>pane nero&lt;/em>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>This is my first durum bake in a looooong time. I made a loaf of 100% semolina sourdough bread ~3 years ago, and used semolina (&lt;em>rava&lt;/em>/&lt;em>suji&lt;/em>) from an Indian grocery store. That experiment gave me a good idea of how durum/semolina would behave in a bread dough.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This time, I set my sight on delving into the flavorful versatility of durum. I would like to find out what makes whole durum wheat tick from both a milling and baking standpoint and how I might incorporate it into my freshly milled wholegrain repertoire.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>To get the best flavor out of durum, you have to to push the limits. In my experience with durum, a long autolyse helps develop the dough; a ripe levain makes a better bread; after which, all it needs is a quick shape and bake.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The conventional rules of thumb for baking with durum/semolina is 1) low hydration and 2) gentle mixing. For example, &lt;em>pane di Altamura&lt;/em> usually comes in at 65%-70% hydration and &lt;em>pane di Matera&lt;/em> at 70%-80%.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-6/20230318_102411.jpg"
alt="pane nero with Desert Gold durum"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>handmade Desert Gold wholegrain durum &lt;em>pane nero&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;m not exactly keen on sticking to tried-and-true methods. I wanted to get out of my comfort zone and bake my interpretation of &lt;em>pane nero&lt;/em> (black bread from Sicily).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In this bread:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>total Desert Gold durum milled: &lt;strong>400g&lt;/strong> (100%)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>total hydration: &lt;strong>560g&lt;/strong> (140%)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Using the same fine-mesh sieve that I used to bolt Turkey Red, I bolted 400g freshly milled wholegrain durum flour into&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>360g flour (90% extraction)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>40g coarse bits (10%)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>That&amp;rsquo;s pretty high extraction for the first run through the mill.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="semolina-porridge">semolina porridge&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>Given that the bran of the durum wheat kernel is actually thinner than most hard wheats &amp;ndash; it&amp;rsquo;s the starchy endosperm that&amp;rsquo;s actually the hardest to shatter &amp;ndash; the bigger pieces in wholegrain durum flour don&amp;rsquo;t always end up being mostly bran.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Pre-cooking the coarse pieces will help bring out the wonderful flavors and nutrition benefits of the bran and the germ &amp;ndash; aromatic oils, minerals, and fiber, to name a few.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Desert Gold, coarse semolina&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>40g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>whole milk&lt;/td>
&lt;td>300%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>120g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Process:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Toast the dry semolina mix in a 300°F oven (or in a skillet on the stovetop) for 3-4 minutes, until a slight toasty aroma hits your nose. This step is optional but will enhance the flavor enormously. Just be careful not to go overboard &amp;ndash; it will burn in a flash.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Put the toasties in a small pot and pour in milk; bring to a full boil, whisking frequently.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Reduce heat and simmer until a thick, creamy consistency. Turn off heat and let it cool off.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>The semolina mix cooks fast &amp;ndash; the whole thing takes 10-15 minutes tops.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Note:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>You can make this in a microwave, too, just make sure to pause and stir frequently.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Any kind of milk will work. You can use plain water, too.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>The porridge will also improve the texture of the baked bread through a process called &lt;em>starch gelatinization&lt;/em>, where starch and water meet heat, causing the starch molecules to swell. As a result, the water is gradually absorbed in an irreversible manner (&amp;ldquo;locked in&amp;rdquo;). This turns the mixture into a viscous and transparent gel, which is then used in sauces, puddings, creams and other food products to provide a pleasing texture. One of the most recognizable Chinese &lt;em>dim sum&lt;/em> delicacies, &lt;a href="https://tasteasianfood.com/har-gow/">&lt;em>har gow&lt;/em>&lt;/a> (shrimp dumplings), utilizes this technique to create an ultra-thin, translucent, and chewy skin. (The most common example to explain this phenomenon is pasta preparation: Pasta is made ​​mostly of semolina that contains high amounts of starch; when it&amp;rsquo;s cooked in boiling water, the size increases because it absorbs water and gets a soft texture.)&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-6/20230318_174944.jpg"
alt="pane nero with Desert Gold durum"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>handmade Desert Gold wholegrain durum &lt;em>pane nero&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;h4 id="final-dough">Final dough&lt;/h4>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Desert Gold durum flour, 90% extraction&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>360g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>water, divided&lt;/td>
&lt;td>111%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>400g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>wholegrain durum &lt;em>lievito madre&lt;/em>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>39%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>140g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>semolina porridge&lt;/td>
&lt;td>44%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>160g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sea salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>7g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>tahini&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>36g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>black sesame seeds&lt;/td>
&lt;td>15%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>55g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>I built the &lt;em>lievito madre&lt;/em> (20g sourdough starter + 40g water + 80g wholegrain durum flour) 8 hours before making the final dough, refreshing it every 3 hours or so.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I also toasted 1/2 of the black sesame seeds, leaving the other 1/2 raw for coating the dough.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-6/20230317_211057.jpg"
alt="Desert Gold durum dough"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Desert Gold wholegrain durum dough.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Process:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Autolyse&lt;/strong> @ ~70% hydration: Combine the flour with 252g water; mix until a shaggy mass; let autolyze for 6-8 hours (or overnight) in the fridge.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Levain&lt;/strong>: Squeeze the levain into the dough; mix until combined; let rest for 10-20 minutes at room temperature.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Double hydration&lt;/strong>: Add 100g or 2/3 of the remaining water gradually, &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zgz0oAhgwyg">Rubaud-mixing&lt;/a> (lifting, stretching, and dropping) until thoroughly absorbed. This requires a bit patience, so take your time. If there&amp;rsquo;s one thing I&amp;rsquo;m good at, it&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em>bassinage&lt;/em>. And I usually put on some &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLlQWGGham__4sBxnwVyKbM8n91Xb9vwUG">music&lt;/a> or &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCkB8eF4ATHl4Jm1BeCZgQ9A">podcasts&lt;/a> while I do this. Hand-mixing a dough is a type of alternative physical therapy; I find it tremendously therapeutic and cathartic. Gorging the dough with soooo much water feels like a crime, TBH. I keep going until the dough tells me to stop&amp;hellip;&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Salt&lt;/strong>: Mix in the salt. Then let rest for 20 minutes at room temperature.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Semolina porridge&lt;/strong>: Divide the porridge into 3-4 portions; spread over the dough one portion at a time; mix until evenly distributed. With the porridge added back, no part of the grain is removed. Let rest for 20 minutes at room temperature.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Triple hydration&lt;/strong>: Add the rest of the water, Rubaud-mixing until completely incorporated. Let rest for 20 minutes at room temperature.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Tahini&lt;/strong>: Drizzle in the tahini, Rubaud-mixing until entirely combined.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Cold ferment&lt;/strong>: Transfer the dough to a fridge (or somewhere 38°F-43°F) right away and ferment for 24 hours; take it out every few hours and perform a &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6JQm2n4aVZc">coil-fold&lt;/a> with a sprinkle of toasted sesame seeds. I did 4 folds in total and folded in all of the toasted sesame seeds.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Shape &amp;amp; final proof&lt;/strong>: After 24 hours of bulk fermentation (~85% volume increase), shape the dough into whatever form you want. Roll it in the rest of black sesame seeds. Let it warm up to room temperature for 2-3 hours before baking.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>The dough had a subtle toasty aroma, and surprised me with its softness and ease of handling.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-6/20230318_102524.jpg"
alt="pane nero with Desert Gold durum"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>handmade Desert Gold wholegrain durum &lt;em>pane nero&lt;/em>, a few hours out of the oven.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Artisanal boules look visually stunning, but are a &lt;em>de facto&lt;/em> pain in the butt to slice and freeze. Since I&amp;rsquo;m more pragmatic than artistic, I prefer the humble shape of a sandwich loaf &amp;ndash; much more space-efficient in the freezer.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>So I shaped the dough into a log, proofed it seam-side up in a wide loaf pan, and baked with no scoring/slashing. The bread cracked open all on its own.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Keep in mind I baked this bread in my countertop toaster oven. It probably comes out prettier and crustier in a better oven with some fancy steaming apparatus &amp;ndash; or even a wood-fired oven.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-6/20230318_103523.jpg"
alt="pane nero with Desert Gold durum"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>handmade Desert Gold wholegrain durum &lt;em>pane nero&lt;/em>: crust closeup&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The crumb has a marvelous golden color, light texture with a natural nutty flavor. Great to enjoy with with cheese and a glass of red wine.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>At first glance, the crumb doesn&amp;rsquo;t look open because air holes are really tiny, but the softness is extreme because the increase in volume was incredible.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-6/20230318_105256.jpg"
alt="pane nero with Desert Gold durum"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>handmade Desert Gold wholegrain durum &lt;em>pane nero&lt;/em>: crumb reveal&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>With a long fermentation and crispy aromatic sesame seeds (toasted during baking) on the outside, you get an irresistible bread that gives you the distinct flavors of the whole durum wheat, the chew from the hardness of this wheat (after all, it&amp;rsquo;s the wheat of choice for pasta), and its wonderful infusion with the toasted sesame seeds.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-6/20230318_121745.jpg"
alt="pane nero with Desert Gold durum"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>handmade Desert Gold wholegrain durum &lt;em>pane nero&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The crust is so thin and soft that it would be non-existent if it weren&amp;rsquo;t for the sesame seeds.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Each slice feels light, soft, and springy in my hand. It tastes soft like a brioche, chewy like a pasta; exceptionally smooth, custardy, and creamy.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The flavor is subtly sweet, reminiscent of pasta, and does not taste like whole wheat at all. There is a hint of saltiness and tanginess.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-6/20230318_173945.jpg"
alt="pane nero with Desert Gold durum"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>handmade Desert Gold wholegrain durum &lt;em>pane nero&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Most of the &lt;em>pani puglisi&lt;/em> I have eaten in Italy have those characteristics: a high percentage of fine durum wheat, an light crumb with irregular holes, a very chewy texture, and a long keeping time (days and days).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The semolina porridge contributes a cotton-like softness to the crumb. As an extra perk, it improved the bread&amp;rsquo;s keeping quality (after it&amp;rsquo;s first sliced). During baking, the porridge releases water slowly, resulting in a continuous softening of both the crumb and the crust.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-6/20230318_174403.jpg"
alt="pane nero with Desert Gold durum"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>handmade Desert Gold wholegrain durum &lt;em>pane nero&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>How does this 100% whole durum bread compare to the semolina breads I made before? For starters, I could smell the difference during baking. Both had wonderful aromas, but the 100% whole durum version had a strikingly richer and more vibrant aroma that I didn&amp;rsquo;t recall from the semolina. On the inside, this wholesome version has a slightly juicier and softer crumb with a richer hue of yellow, thanks to the gorgeous load of the freshly milled wholegrain durum flour. Now, you can simply taste more of the grain &amp;ndash; it&amp;rsquo;s sweeter, nuttier, and to me, more satisfying.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The durum bread is a perfect example of how you can take an already great grain &amp;ndash; especially freshly milled &amp;ndash; to the next level. hence the bread&amp;rsquo;s golden color &amp;ndash; it is a combination of coarsely milled semolina and finely milled durum flours.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I tried a slice of this bread dipped in olive oil with a little balsamic vinegar. That was spectacular! The magical combination of flavors was delightful. I thought about using this bread in other characteristic Italian ways &amp;ndash; as garlic bread, toasted and smeared with almond butter, or eaten with a hearty &lt;em>ribollito&lt;/em> &amp;ndash; but didn&amp;rsquo;t get that far. The bread was gone in 2 days.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-6/20230318_174657.jpg"
alt="pane nero with Desert Gold durum"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>handmade Desert Gold wholegrain durum &lt;em>pane nero&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>If there is one bread that I wish everyone could taste to see how wonderful a freshly milled wholegrain bread can be, this may be it: Light, fluffy, and soft in texture, with an airy crumb; the rich, nutty, sweet durum flavor shines right through; and the crunch of the sesame seeds on the exterior offers a pleasing contrast against the tenderness of the interior.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>&lt;em>This is part 6 of my &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/california-grain-adventure/">California Grain Adventure&lt;/a>. If you enjoyed this, why not check out my other &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/archives/">breadstories&lt;/a> and spread the word?&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>&lt;em>Pane di Altamura&lt;/em> is probably the most famous &lt;em>pane pugliese&lt;/em> (bread from the Puglia region of Italy); it&amp;rsquo;s even a DOP product. Other interesting durum breads include &lt;em>pane di Matera&lt;/em> and &lt;em>pane nero&lt;/em>; I attempted to bake my interpretation of the latter in this breadpost.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/section></content></item><item><title>California Dreamin' #5: Sonora Blanca</title><link>/posts/california-dreamin-5/</link><pubDate>Sun, 12 Mar 2023 23:07:37 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/california-dreamin-5/</guid><description>[California Grain Adventure #5] Sonora Blanca coma: 30-hour wholegrain &lt;em>bomboloni con lievito madre&lt;/em>, with unsifted Sonora flour, &lt;em>beurre noisette&lt;/em>, caramelized kabocha purée, and cinnamon sugar. Decadent, melt-in-your-mouth creamy, one-of-a-kind pumpkin donuts. The bomb diggity.</description><content>&lt;p>&lt;em>This is part 5 of my &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/california-grain-adventure/">California Grain Adventure&lt;/a>.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Californians invented the concept of life-style. This alone warrants their doom.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Don DeLillo, &lt;em>White Noise&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Virginia Postrel&amp;rsquo;s book, &lt;em>The Power of Glamour&lt;/em>, highlights California as a particularly glamorous icon. It has always attracted some of the most ambitious, gifted, and can-do people in the world. But for all the innovations of Silicon Valley and Hollywood, northern California&amp;rsquo;s NIMBYism is paradoxically antithetical to a culture that embraces change and risk. The local governments don&amp;rsquo;t seem so can-do, either. Longtime residents and Uber drivers are eager to tell you how their city &lt;a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2023/02/26/opinion/san-francisco-democrats-board-of-supervisors.html">isn&amp;rsquo;t what it once was&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Despite all the media blitz, maybe Silicon Valley is imprinted with more of the East Coast finance culture than the techies would like to admit.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>On Friday (10 March 2023), the 16th largest commercial bank in the US, a S&amp;amp;P 500 component, and $209 billion in assets got &lt;a href="https://www.cbsnews.com/news/silicon-valley-bank-sivb-stock-fdic-cbs-explains/">wiped out&lt;/a> overnight.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>California regulators on Friday abruptly shuttered Silicon Valley Bank, closing a 40-year-old financial institution that catered to the tech industry and that was the 16th largest U.S. bank before its sudden collapse. The company&amp;rsquo;s stock tumbled 60% on Thursday and had plunged another 70% on Friday before trading of its shares was halted.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The nosedive reflected fears of a bank run, concerns that materialized as depositors &amp;ndash; mostly technology company workers and venture capital-backed companies &amp;ndash; rushed to withdraw money this week as anxiety over the bank&amp;rsquo;s balance sheet spread.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Regulators stepped in to take control, with the California Department of Financial Protection and Innovation closing the bank and appointing the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation (FDIC) as receiver. It&amp;rsquo;s the largest failure of a financial institution since Washington Mutual in 2008 at the height of the financial crisis more than a decade ago.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Two things were happening on Wall Street this weekend: Junior analysts were watching &lt;em>&lt;a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0038650/">It&amp;rsquo;s a Wonderful Life&lt;/a>&lt;/em> to see what a good old-fashioned bank run looks like; mid-level analysts were hammering the F9 key to see what higher &lt;a href="https://www.investopedia.com/terms/w/wacc.asp">weighted average cost of capital&lt;/a> (WACC) was doing to valuations.&lt;/p>
&lt;div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
&lt;iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/EOzMdEwYmDU" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video">&lt;/iframe>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>Nearly every major US bank has mark-to-market losses on its held-to-maturity (HTM) Treasury bond portfolio. For Wells Fargo, it&amp;rsquo;s ~20%. For Bank of America, it&amp;rsquo;s closer to 40%. For Silicon Valley Bank, those losses exceeded total equity.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>SVB is a unique outlier &amp;ndash; it made terrible decisions that were several orders of magnitude worse than other banks. The truly unique feature of SVB was its deposit profile, instead of its investment profile. Because SVB was not a retail bank, but rather a corporate bank focused on serving startups and VCs, the vast majority of its deposit accounts were corporate in nature and well above the FDIC-insured limits of $250k. (If that sounds like an extreme amount to you, then you don&amp;rsquo;t realize America is inundated with millionaires and billionaires &amp;ndash; thanks to their real estate holdings, if nothing else. SVB had almost no insured deposits. It was literally a bank for millionaires and billionaires, who are called &amp;ldquo;oligarchs&amp;rdquo; in Russia.) As news began to percolate that SVB was raising equity capital to offset losses in a HTM portfolio, VCs and startups scampered away at the first sign of trouble.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Risk happens slowly, then all at once. Deposit outflows from SVB likely hit full stride on Friday, with Peter Thiel&amp;rsquo;s Founders Fund calling for VCs to pull their money out. Nothing like biting the hand that feeds you. Nowadays one tweet is all it takes to trigger a &amp;ldquo;bank run.&amp;rdquo; On Saturday, desperate customers &lt;a href="https://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-11849049/Customers-line-outside-Republic-Bank-money-SVB-bank-collapsed.html">lined up outside First Republic Bank&lt;/a> in southern California to take their money out.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>California Gov. Gavin Newsom said Saturday that he&amp;rsquo;s talking with the White House to help &amp;ldquo;stabilize the situation as quickly as possible, to protect jobs, people&amp;rsquo;s livelihoods, and the entire innovation ecosystem that has served as a &lt;em>tent pole&lt;/em> for our economy.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>A &lt;em>tent pole&lt;/em> is a fragile skeleton. If it breaks, your tent may wobble, flap or completely collapse.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>To anyone who works in or follows tech, SVB is &lt;em>not&lt;/em> &amp;ldquo;a little-known California bank&amp;rdquo; as portrayed by East Coast mainstream media. It&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em>the go-to bank&lt;/em> for US tech startups &amp;ndash; it provided funding to &lt;a href="https://www.svb.com/venture-funded">44%&lt;/a> of all VC-backed tech and healthcare companies that publicly listed on a stock exchange last year.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet">&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr">In a deep sense — though not a legal sense — what SVB actually did was a kind of affinity fraud a la Madoff. It managed to convince the VC/startup/crypto etc world that it was one of them, part of their community, and hence trustworthy 5/&lt;/p>&amp;mdash; Paul Krugman (@paulkrugman) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/paulkrugman/status/1634911360227201025?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">March 12, 2023&lt;/a>&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8">&lt;/script>
&lt;p>And when it comes to money, people aren&amp;rsquo;t concerned with getting Covid&amp;hellip; FWIW, yesterday marked the 3-year anniversary of the official declaration of the &amp;ldquo;COVID-19 Pandemic.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The sophisticated investors, those with far in excess of $250k and saw the writing on the wall ahead of the crowd, began pulling their money from SVB weeks ago. Which means the bank had to have the cash to pay them. Which means the bank had to sell assets to raise the cash. And if the assets are long-duration bonds with rising yields, they had to be liquidated at a loss. SVB lost ~$2 billion trying to meet withdrawals.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>But it still wasn&amp;rsquo;t enough. The bank collapsed. The government took it over. Which means if you had &amp;lt;$250k in your account, you are good. If you had more&amp;hellip;you get a piece of paper saying you will hopefully get 100% back, but it depends on the liquidation of the bank. During the 2008-2009 financial crisis, with IndyMac, you got 50 cents on the dollar.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>That&amp;rsquo;s why people were rushing to those non-diversified banks like First Republic to get their money out ASAP.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>When the tide goes out, you find out who is swimming naked.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Bill.com had to come out and assure investors that its banking relationship with SVB is easily replaceable. Roku held ~$487 million, or ~26%, of its $1.9 billion cash and cash equivalents at SVB, and most of its deposits with the bank are &lt;em>uninsured&lt;/em>. Toronto-based AcuityAds Holding held &amp;gt;90% of its deposits (USD $55 million) in SVB. BlockFi also had $227 million with SVB, but it&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em>not FDIC-insured&lt;/em> because it was in a money market mutual fund. Business continuity concerns are high for many companies exposed to SVB, which will cause reverberations across sectors.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A lot of analogies to Long-Term Capital Management (LTCM) and even Bear Stearns are being made. If SVB wants to have a chance to be remembered as &amp;ldquo;fondly&amp;rdquo; as those, it will take more than a 2-day SPX decline of 3.3%. No movie is made about little blips.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet">&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr">The failure of &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/SVB_Financial?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@SVB_Financial&lt;/a> could destroy an important long-term driver of the economy as VC-backed companies rely on SVB for loans and holding their operating cash. If private capital can’t provide a solution, a highly dilutive gov’t preferred bailout should be considered.&lt;/p>&amp;mdash; Bill Ackman (@BillAckman) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/BillAckman/status/1634028534107602944?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">March 10, 2023&lt;/a>&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8">&lt;/script>
&lt;p>Is SVB as important to the national financial plumbing as Bank of America? Not even close. Is this another Lehman or Bear Stearns? Absolutely not. But still, to think this massive banking entity exists in a vacuum with no implications for the rest of the economy is naive. There will be ripple effects.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The odds of your local bank failing, which is probably a national bank anyway, are low, but once consumer &lt;em>con&lt;/em>fidence fades&amp;hellip;you have no idea what might happen. Western banks and financial markets are already fragile, and psychology is fracturing. Pile on deteriorating asset quality from emerging markets and toxic CRE exposures&amp;hellip;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>You can&amp;rsquo;t count on anyone but yourself these days. And be wary of listening to your friends or people you run into. Most people are not sophisticated, and full of sh*t anyway. They want to make themselves look good; some are &lt;em>con&lt;/em>fident salesmen&amp;hellip;.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We live in an information economy, which means those with the most information win. It&amp;rsquo;s true in each and every business. After all, the executives at SVB got paid, as always. As for the depositors&amp;hellip;the savvy ones with the most information got their money out. The rest?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Silicon Valley appears to be great at massive differential equations, but has difficulty balancing a check book. Probably because they do not know what a check book is.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet">&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr">How financially innumerate is Silicon Valley…?! The FDIC has already indicated that uninsured depositors will be receiving substantial proceeds(50%)as early as tomorrow. Shouldn’t that be enough for one payroll? &lt;a href="https://t.co/3VJxuXPvbi">https://t.co/3VJxuXPvbi&lt;/a>&lt;/p>&amp;mdash; Diogenes (@WallStCynic) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/WallStCynic/status/1634948491704434688?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">March 12, 2023&lt;/a>&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8">&lt;/script>
&lt;p>Now the biggest question: Is the SVB failure another isolated / non-systemic / contained event?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>History is the poet that loves to rhyme. FTX was the spark that lit the fuse.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>~24 hours earlier, Silvergate Bank, a cornerstone in the crypto world, &lt;a href="https://www.theverge.com/2023/3/8/23631320/silvergate-wind-down-liquidiation-announcement">announced it would shut down&lt;/a> &amp;ldquo;in light of recent industry and regulatory developments.&amp;rdquo; Signature Bank, another key crypto bank with more than $110 billion in assets, &lt;a href="https://www.reuters.com/business/finance/new-york-state-regulators-close-signature-bank-2023-03-12/">crashed this morning&lt;/a>. The second &lt;em>and&lt;/em> third largest bank failures in US history, after Washington Mutual in 2008, happened in the span of 48 hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Bank liquidity is front and center, and mark-to-market shenanigans are leaving a capital crater. SVB has many valuable assets (people/relationships) that got caught in a classic bank run (using short-term financing to buy long-term assets). EVERYTHING hinges on what the regulators decide this weekend. My prediction is the Fed opens the discount window for all assets to provide short-term financing for all FDIC banks. Some entity will buy the carcass of SVB. (12 months ago, every banker wanted this bank. That&amp;rsquo;s still the case and SVB is now 75% off.) Peter Thiel hitting the button has set the wheels in motion. The &amp;ldquo;bad loans&amp;rdquo; will be shoved onto Uncle Sam, the best government money can buy. Play the cards you are dealt, not the ones you want.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet">&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr">At my direction, &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/SecYellen?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@SecYellen&lt;/a> and my National Economic Council Director worked with banking regulators to address problems at Silicon Valley Bank and Signature Bank.&lt;br>&lt;br>I’m pleased they reached a solution that protects workers, small businesses, taxpayers, and our financial system. &lt;a href="https://t.co/CxcdvLVP6l">https://t.co/CxcdvLVP6l&lt;/a>&lt;/p>&amp;mdash; President Biden (@POTUS) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/POTUS/status/1635080376572956672?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">March 13, 2023&lt;/a>&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8">&lt;/script>
&lt;p>Once again, it&amp;rsquo;s not just SVB, it&amp;rsquo;s the system that is being examined. A month ago, Brookfield Corp., parent of the largest office landlord in downtown Los Angeles, &lt;a href="https://archive.is/v4Ike">defaulted&lt;/a> on two office towers in DTLA. The news was ignored. Why are major asset players defaulting on mortgages on CRE? Negative carry. Raising capital at 7% to finance a 4% cap rate building is a losing trade. Brookfield is one of many entities that has levered up their CRE to pay their owners and buy other assets. This plan worked well in a 0% interest rate world, but not so much in the current environment. The question is, who owns the mortgages on these and many other half-filled CRE? Pension funds? Private equity? Insurance companies? Regional Banks? Wall Street? Time will tell. Economic iceberg dead ahead.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Bank runs, like war, are big business for the establishment. Never let a crisis go to waste.&lt;/p>
&lt;div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
&lt;iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/qAt7Rg1u2l8" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video">&lt;/iframe>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>What created California, economically and politically, was actually constant support from the eastern web of American society, industry, and, especially, the federal government. The sheer geographical isolation of different parts of the state tends to obscure the elementary fact of its interrelatedness. The refusal to acknowledge this public interrelatedness, to insist on the determining value of the personal, the private, and the exceptional, has been California&amp;rsquo;s fragmenting delusion.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This assertion that California is a stronghold of urbanity and groundedness is contrary, even petulant. The national narrative of the West Coast &amp;ndash; what goes on there, what it means &amp;ndash; has been fashioned by editors and emissaries from the East Coast. But, where the East Coast press had decided that California once stood for futurism, beaches, lush life, and togetherness, now you find a California full of dusty houses, arid inland landscapes, fires and blackouts, dotcom bust 2.0, and social alienation.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-5/20230312_151044.jpg"
alt="bomboloni integrali di sonora blanca"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>30-hour wholegrain &lt;em>bomboloni con lievito madre&lt;/em>, with unsifted Sonora flour.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>I keep coming back to the San Joaquin Valley-grown Sonora Blanca. The wheat&amp;rsquo;s unique terroir and wonderful flavor profile linger in my mind.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The more I use it, the more special this wheat feels to me. Each kernel holds a universe of long-forgotten flavors. I think too many people are afraid to try new things with Sonora because of its commercial classification as a &amp;ldquo;soft&amp;rdquo; wheat, which is sad. Sonora has soooo much potential &amp;ndash; yet to be discovered. I&amp;rsquo;d use it for everything. &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/california-dreamin-3">Wholegrain Sonora cookies&lt;/a> turned out absolutely scrumptious, and &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/california-dreamin-4">wholegrain &lt;em>pan de sonora&lt;/em>&lt;/a> was equally delectable.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Baking, in my mind, is one of those &amp;ldquo;low-stakes&amp;rdquo; activities that require significantly less risk-taking than, say, starting a company. If it takes this much guts for bakers to try a new flour, then there&amp;rsquo;s no hope for this country.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I remember someone once told me the closest they got to winning the Hunger Games was when they spotted the last donut in the office kitchen. So I decided to make some wholegrain sourdough &lt;em>bomboloni&lt;/em> (Italian-style donuts).&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-5/20230312_152238.jpg"
alt="bomboloni integrali di sonora blanca"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>30-hour wholegrain &lt;em>bomboloni con lievito madre&lt;/em>, with unsifted Sonora flour.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>These turned out, hands down, the best pumpkin donuts I&amp;rsquo;d ever made! With a handful of simple yet unexpected ingredients, you can turn your old-school pumpkin pie into crispy-fried perfection.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Sonora Blanca flour, 100% extraction&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>250g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->diastatic barley malt powder&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2.5g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>whole milk&lt;/td>
&lt;td>20%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>50g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>fresh carrot juice&lt;/td>
&lt;td>20%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>50g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>roasted caramelized kabocha purée&lt;/td>
&lt;td>50%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>125g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->&lt;em>lievito madre&lt;/em>&lt;sup id="fnref:2">&lt;a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->&lt;/td>
&lt;td>30%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>75g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;em>beurre noisette&lt;/em> (brown &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->butter&lt;sup id="fnref:3">&lt;a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">3&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->), softened&lt;/td>
&lt;td>16%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>40g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->&lt;em>piloncillo oscuro&lt;/em>&lt;sup id="fnref:4">&lt;a href="#fn:4" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">4&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->, softened &amp;amp; chopped&lt;/td>
&lt;td>12%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>30g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sea salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2.5g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>ground spices (cinnamon, allspice, ginger, cloves)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2.5g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>citrus zest&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2.5g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>As &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/california-dreamin-3">mentioned&lt;/a> a few weeks ago, I haven&amp;rsquo;t been using eggs due to the ongoing egg shortage. Feel free to use eggs instead of milk.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Kabocha is a squat and round hard squash with a dull green rind, but the inside hidden beneath that unassuming exterior is sweet, nutty, and delightfully starchy. The flavor of kabocha is a mix of sweet potato and pumpkin; the texture is drier and airier than butternut squash, which makes it perfect for &lt;a href="https://www.thespruceeats.com/kabocha-tempura-recipe-2031602">tempura&lt;/a>. Roasting kabocha is one of my favorite ways to enjoy it. Simply, cut kabocha into wedges, toss with some olive oil, and roast in a 400°F oven until tender and caramelized, about 25-30 minutes, to concentrate the squash&amp;rsquo;s texture and flavor. If you can&amp;rsquo;t find kabocha, substitute with 1/2 sweet potato and 1/2 hard winter squash (delicata, butternut, acorn, calabaza, Seminole, etc).&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-5/20230312_150938.jpg"
alt="bomboloni integrali di sonora blanca"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>30-hour wholegrain &lt;em>bomboloni con lievito madre&lt;/em>, with unsifted Sonora flour.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Here goes the zen and the art of making soft and fluffy &lt;em>bomboloni&lt;/em>, which very much reminds me of making &lt;em>panettoni&lt;/em>:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Mix everything together into a stiff dough.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Bulk ferment at 75°F for 6 hours. Fold once every 30 mins, 4 times in total.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Retard in the fridge for 12 hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Divide into 10 pieces (~60g each), and shape into taut balls.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Proof at 73°F for 12 hours until tripled in size.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Heat a pot of coconut oil to 350°F-360°F; fry ~5 minutes on each side. You want both sides to be brown and crispy.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Remove from oil and let dry on a wire rack lined with paper towels.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Once cool (but still warm), coat in homemade cinnamon sugar. Fill with &lt;em>crema pasticciera&lt;/em>, if desired. They are delicious without filling, IMO.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-5/20230312_150718.jpg"
alt="bomboloni integrali di sonora blanca"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>bomboloni integrali di sonora blanca&lt;/em>: 100% wholegrain Sonora Blanca flour + caramelized kabocha purée + cinnamon sugar&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Typically, you need a strong bread flour to make these &lt;em>bomboloni&lt;/em>, but I&amp;rsquo;m quite surprised &amp;ndash; and pleased &amp;ndash; with how well these Sonora Blanca &lt;em>bomboloni integrali&lt;/em> have turned out!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The extended fermentation time give these &lt;em>bomboloni&lt;/em> a super fluffy, airy texture &amp;ndash; you won&amp;rsquo;t know it&amp;rsquo;s whole wheat!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Bomboloni&lt;/em> literally translates as &amp;ldquo;big bombs&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; a perfect name for these big round donuts and an apt moniker for the current era.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-5/20230312_151738.jpg"
alt="bomboloni integrali di sonora blanca"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>bomboloni integrali di sonora blanca&lt;/em>: yum!&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>&lt;em>This is part 5 of my &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/california-grain-adventure/">California Grain Adventure&lt;/a>. If you enjoyed this, why not check out my other &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/archives/">breadstories&lt;/a> and spread the word?&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>I made my diastatic barley malt powder from unhulled malted barley, finely ground and unsifted.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>Whole wheat levain at 50% hydration; refreshed at least twice.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:3" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>Making brown butter at home is &lt;a href="https://food52.com/recipes/7234-beurre-noisette">super easy&lt;/a>. Just melt the butter and continue to cook over medium-low heat until it turns nutty brown.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:4" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>Substitute with unrefined raw cane sugar or coconut sugar.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:4" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/section></content></item><item><title>California Dreamin' #4: Sonora Blanca</title><link>/posts/california-dreamin-4/</link><pubDate>Sat, 04 Mar 2023 21:34:34 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/california-dreamin-4/</guid><description>[California Grain Adventure #4] Sonora Blanca maxima: &lt;em>pan integral de sonora blanca&lt;/em>. 100% wholegrain. 135% hydration. Slightly sweetish, scented and flavored with aniseed and orange. &lt;em>Muy delicioso.&lt;/em></description><content>&lt;p>&lt;em>This is part 4 of my &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/california-grain-adventure/">California Grain Adventure&lt;/a>.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Every time I fly west, following the sun, I experience a lightening of spirit as the land below opens up, the checkerboards of the Midwestern plains giving way to the vast empty reach between the Rockies and the Sierra Nevada.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>If I were to pick the time when I should travel in California, it would be in the early summer. All the rest of the world at that moment is green. California alone is sheer gold. &amp;hellip; On one side the Pacific &amp;ndash; tigerish, calm, powerfully palpitant, stretching into eternity in enormous bronze-gold, foam-laced planes. On the other side, great, bare, voluptuously-contoured hills, running parallel with the train and winding serpentinely on for hours and hours of express speed; hills that look, not as though they were covered with yellow grass, but as though they were carved from massy gold. At intervals come ravines filled with a heavy green growth. Occasionally on those golden hill-surfaces appear trees.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Inez Haynes Irwin, &lt;em>The Californiacs&lt;/em> (1919)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>My favorite road in California lies between Interstate 5 and Monterrey. I used to drive along &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/California_State_Route_152">Route 152&lt;/a>, on the way from San Francisco to southern California, a dozen times a year. The land lies smoothly in carpets of green during the summer, then golds and browns for the rest of the year. Commanding it all are the oak trees spotting the hills. Today this part is still mostly clear of development and hasn&amp;rsquo;t been overrun by greed or ambition.&lt;/p>
&lt;div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
&lt;iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/ms9MupIszr8" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video">&lt;/iframe>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>It&amp;rsquo;s actually kind of odd, now that I think about it. I was initially drawn to California because of its Silicon Valley &amp;ndash; I went to work in tech, and realized the tech scene there was a shadow of its former dotcom self; the real innovation was in finding new ways to scam investors and keeping the ball rolling. California&amp;rsquo;s natural beauty was just one of &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->accidental perks&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --> that I discovered along the way.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I remember going to a California Impressionist art collection a few years ago in Irvine, a master-planned city in Orange County, southern California. The Irvine Museum was located in a peculiar place &amp;ndash; on the bottom floor of a high-rise office building in Irvine&amp;rsquo;s Financial District, a short walk from UC-Irvine campus and John Wayne Airport. The office building housed the usual white-collar businesses like law firms and travel agencies; the space occupied by the &amp;ldquo;museum&amp;rdquo; had a mundane corporate feel, and could just as easily house a dozen cubicles filled with telemarketers cold-calling people on adjustable-rate mortgages. It was actually more of a gallery &amp;ndash; and not a very big one at that.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I later found out the building was originally a McDonnell Douglas Building and the museum, which used to be on the 12th floor, was &lt;a href="https://www.latimes.com/archives/la-xpm-1992-04-15-ca-248-story.html">established&lt;/a> by descendants of James Irvine who founded Irvine Ranch, the sprawling agricultural property that evolved into the City of Irvine. The Irvine family developed their ranch in the 1960s, which is to say, the city didn&amp;rsquo;t exist before then.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-4/20230304_180946.jpg"
alt="pan integral de sonora blanca"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>pan integral de sonora blanca&lt;/em>, with 100% wholegrain White Sonora flour.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>James Irvine was a canny, Belfast-born opportunist who came to California seeking gold. He failed to strike it rich in the streams and hills near Sutter&amp;rsquo;s Mill, but became wealthy selling supplies to his fellow 49ers. (What&amp;rsquo;s the saying? &amp;ldquo;Don&amp;rsquo;t dig for gold, sell shovels!&amp;quot;) In 1864, Irvine and three other San Francisco businessmen &amp;ndash; Benjamin and Thomas Flint, and Llewellyn Bixby &amp;ndash; bought 50,000 acres of &lt;em>Rancho San Joaquín&lt;/em> from José Andrés Sepúlveda, a famed &lt;em>Californio vaquero&lt;/em> who obtained the land in 1842 through a Mexican land grant and got into a dire debt crisis due to the Great Drought of the mid-1860s. (&lt;em>Rancho San Joaquín&lt;/em> included the wind-blown marshlands on the ocean that has been developed into Newport Beach, one of California&amp;rsquo;s most elite and picturesque boating and vacation spots.)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The Flints and Bixby were shrewd Yankee traders (of Maine colonial stock) with a taste for adventure and wealth. They came west during the Gold Rush of 1849, returned to the east, and came back again in 1853 on two wagons driving flocks of sheep, oxen, horses, and cows. This laid the economic foundation for fortunes of Irvine, Bixby and the Flints. A few years later, the trio acquired adjacent &lt;em>El Rancho Lomas de Santiago&lt;/em> (the Ranch of the Hills of St. James) and &lt;em>Rancho Santiago de Santa Ana&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In 1876, James Irvine bought out his partners for $150,000. His 110,000 acres lay on the eastern bank of the Santa Ana River, stretching 23 miles from the Santa Ana Mountains to the Pacific Ocean. He held the land intact against droughts, squatters and lawsuits by railroads. When he died in 1886, the romantic ranch land was passed on to his son, James Irvine II, who incorporated it into the Irvine Company. James Irvine II also added olive, orange, lemon and walnut trees to the prosperous sheep and cattle grazing business. 10 years before he died in 1947, he set up the James Irvine Foundation to hold 51% of the Irvine Company stock, primarily as a tax maneuver. The Irvine Company was a vestige of the sort of personal tycoonnery that made mulit-millionaires out of immigrants in the Gold Rush days.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-4/20230304_181355.jpg"
alt="pan integral de sonora blanca"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>pan integral de sonora blanca&lt;/em>, with 100% wholegrain White Sonora flour.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Joan Irvine Smith, the only child of James Irvine III and the great-granddaughter of the OG James Irvine, was a smart heiress. In 1957, at age 24, she replaced her mother as the major shareholder on the all-male board of the Irvine Company and the Irvine Foundation, with which she had a complicated relationship. She had seen, a good deal more clearly and realistically than what Jane Hollister Wheelwright, another descendant of one of California&amp;rsquo;s oldest ranching families, would see 4 years later: the future of the ranch, which covered 1/5 of Orange County, must not be agrarian if it were to remain under her family&amp;rsquo;s control. The rest of the Irvine board was a problem: By making small deals, selling off bits of the whole and keeping the holdings agrarian, the board was nibbling away at the family&amp;rsquo;s bread and butter. So she pressed the architect William Pereira to present a master plan. She saw the potential return in donating the land for a University of California campus, and pushed for using Irvine Company lands (a pastoral island surrounded by bustling suburbia, a freeway hop from Los Angeles) for urban development. Most importantly, she insisted on maintaining an interest in the ranch&amp;rsquo;s development. In the end, which is to say after years of internecine battles and a series of lawsuits extending three decades, she more or less prevailed.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In 1960, before the Irvine Ranch was developed, there were 719,500 people in the whole Orange County. In 2000, there were close to 3 million, most of whom would not have been there if two families &amp;ndash; the Irvines in central Orange County, and the inheritors of Richard O&amp;rsquo;Neill&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em>Rancho Santa Margarita&lt;/em> and &lt;em>Mission Viejo&lt;/em> acreage in the southern &amp;ndash; had not developed their ranches.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-4/20230304_180553.jpg"
alt="pan integral de sonora blanca"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>pan integral de sonora blanca&lt;/em>, with 100% wholegrain White Sonora flour.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>The California Club, which is on Flower Street in downtown Los Angeles, is still the heart of southern California&amp;rsquo;s old-money business establishment, the LA version of the Bohemian Club and Pacific Union Club in San Francisco. On any given day since World War II, virtually everyone lunching at the California Club has had a direct or indirect investment in the development of California, which is to say in the obliteration of the undeveloped California on exhibition at the Irvine Museum: rolling hills and rugged seascapes; desert and mesas and arroyos; frothy waves, mountains, and big blue sky; eucalyptus, sycamore, oak, and cottonwood; cockatoos, peacocks, and horses.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>California Impressionism, of course, is a stepchild of French Impressionism, adapted with varying success to a new set of atmospheric conditions and mingled (or mangled) with various other styles. Southern Californian artists basked in broad viewer approval; they painted entirely to celebrate a golden land, sharing an Arcadian vision with fellow Californians &amp;ndash; and with tourists smitten by the fantasy of sun, surf, golden hills and distant snow-capped mountains.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>What struck me the most, while viewing the Irvine collection, was that it was permeated with a tenacious (or even pernicious) mood of nostalgia for the good old days, when California&amp;rsquo;s landscape was unspoiled, and yet it evidently lacked human passions. Whatever human forms you manage to make out are dwarfed by the undeveloped landscape, and some even look like indistinct Indians.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>There is more nostalgia for me in these paintings than in actually going out to look at what used to be the ranch now that it has been developed, because I’m looking at what I looked at as a child.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Joan Irvine Smith&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Some of this wilderness was romantic, some washed with a slightly falsified golden light, in the tradition that runs from Albert Bierstadt&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;lustrous pearly mist&amp;rdquo; to Thomas Kinkade&amp;rsquo;s famous &amp;ldquo;glow.&amp;rdquo; Most of these paintings, however, reflect the way California looked to anyone who knew the place before the 1960s.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This close representation of a familiar yet vanished landscape gives the Irvine collection its amusing effect, that of a short-term memory misfire: These paintings hang in a newly built city, Irvine (population &amp;gt;300,000, with a University of California campus enrolling some 36,000 students), that was some 60 years ago a mirror image of the paintings themselves &amp;ndash; bean fields and grazing &amp;ndash; but by no means all of the cattle and sheep operations amassed by the great-grandfather of the founder of the Irvine Museum.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-4/20230304_180652.jpg"
alt="pan integral de sonora blanca"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>pan integral de sonora blanca&lt;/em>, with 100% wholegrain White Sonora flour.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>Orange County&amp;rsquo;s middle-class promise didn&amp;rsquo;t pan out for all who came, but the population boom did wonders to the bottom line of the Irvine Company.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The company&amp;rsquo;s commercial portfolio grew and grew with new development and upgrades. The Irvine Company-owned land in Orange County has become the country&amp;rsquo;s best-selling spot for new homes, the high-end market in particular drawing continued interest from homebuilders year on year. (Orange County is one of the most expensive counties to live in the US, with a &lt;a href="https://www.redfin.com/county/332/CA/Orange-County/housing-market">median home price of $940K&lt;/a> in January 2023; its residents include founders of Kingston, Broadcom, and Pimco.) In Orange County, the company owns large parts of the 5,000-acre Irvine Spectrum Center, Fashion Island, Newport Center, half of Irvine&amp;rsquo;s 185-acre University Research Park, Jamboree Center, MacArthur Court and the Resort at Pelican Hill.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Headquartered in Newport Beach, home to some of the richest neighborhoods in the country, the privately held Irvine Company is the largest owner of offices in California and one of the two largest apartments owners in the state. Along with Orange County, San Diego and Silicon Valley, the Irvine Company has sizable holdings in Los Angeles and owns three trophy skyscrapers in Chicago. It also owns the MetLife Building at 200 Park Ave in Manhattan. The company&amp;rsquo;s holdings total ~120 million sqft, including more than 500 offices buildings and 40 retail centers, plus ~160 apartment communities with nearly 60,000 units, two golf clubs, five marinas, and three resorts.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Donald Bren, the current chairman and sole shareholder of the Irvine Company, is the wealthiest person in Orange County with a net worth of ~$17 billion, ranking No.1 among US real estate executives and No.112 on the 2022 Forbes Billionaires List.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Bren got his start as a homebuilder in 1958. In 1977, he joined a group of investors to acquire control of the Irvine Company. In 1983, he bought out many of his partners for $518 million and became the majority owner of the Irvine Company. In 1991, he paid &lt;a href="https://www.latimes.com/archives/la-xpm-1991-06-19-mn-986-story.html">$256 million&lt;/a> to heiresses Joan Irvine Smith and her mother, Athalie R. Clarke, for their shares. In 1996, he became sole owner of the Irvine Company.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It was with these proceeds of looking exclusively, and to a famous degree, forward that Joan Irvine Smith built her collection of &lt;em>plein air&lt;/em> art.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;I can look at these paintings and look back. I can see California as it was and as we will never see it again,&amp;rdquo; she told &lt;em>Art in California&lt;/em>. Hers is an extreme example of the conundrum that to one degree or another confronts any Californian who profited from the boom years: If we could still see California as it was, how many of us could now afford to &amp;ldquo;see&amp;rdquo; it?&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-4/20230304_184754.jpg"
alt="pan integral de sonora blanca"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>pan integral de sonora blanca&lt;/em>, with 100% wholegrain White Sonora flour.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h3 id="pan-de-sonora">&lt;em>Pan de Sonora&lt;/em>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>In the spirit of Joan Irvine Smith, why don&amp;rsquo;t we look forward by forgetting what the Sonora Blanca wheat was traditionally used for and starting to explore its potential in new applications?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/california-dreamin-3">mentioned&lt;/a>, a lot of bakers shun Sonora in breadmaking by default because of its commercial classification as a &amp;ldquo;soft&amp;rdquo; wheat. As a result, Sonora&amp;rsquo;s potential has been limited to tortillas, biscuits, pastries, cookies, and cakes &amp;ndash; the flat, dense stuff.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Contrary to popular belief, my preferred application for Sonora is in sourdough breads.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Making &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/desert-dynamo">a lofty loaf of bread&lt;/a> out of 100% Sonora is possible, but requires a little tango:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Diastatic malt increases the conversion of starches to sugar, boosting the Maillard reaction of the crust. Ascorbic acid (vitamin C)&amp;hellip;tightens the gluten network and gives the bread a better rise.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>The resulting bread will turn out just as airy and lofty as the breads made from hard wheat &amp;ndash; and taste far more flavorful.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Additionally, making bread with weak wheat inspires you to think and be creative, instead of just autopiloting &amp;ndash; or staying in your comfort zone where your unrealized dream is buried.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Baking a good loaf of bread is about knowing &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/about">who you are&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-4/20230304_184924.jpg"
alt="pan integral de sonora blanca"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>pan integral de sonora blanca&lt;/em>, with 100% wholegrain Sonora Blanca flour.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>For this loaf:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>total Sonora Blanca milled: 400g (100%)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>total dough hydration: 538g (135%)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Just for fun, I hand-bolted the 400g wholegrain Sonora flour into 80% (320g) flour and 20% (80g) coarse bran &amp;amp; midds. (Midds are less coarse bits of bran and germ, plus not-so-fine flour particles).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I applied 60g of the bran &amp;amp; midds to the levain and the remaining 20g to a porridge.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="bran-levain">Bran levain&lt;/h4>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Sonora Blanca, bran &amp;amp; midds&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>60g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>water&lt;/td>
&lt;td>66.7%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>40g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sourdough starter&lt;/td>
&lt;td>25%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>15g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Build the levain 6-7 hours before making the final dough, refreshing it every 3 hours or so.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="toasted-bran-porridge">Toasted bran porridge&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>Wheat midds actually contain higher levels of fiber, protein and minerals than the parent grain and have less starch and calorie. However, they are usually considered an &amp;ldquo;unwanted&amp;rdquo; by-product of the wheat flour milling industry and used as animal feed. Since I&amp;rsquo;m milling my own grains, I get to keep and enjoy all of it.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Sonora Blanca, bran &amp;amp; midds&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>20g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>whole milk&lt;/td>
&lt;td>250%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>50g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Process:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Toast the dry bran mix in a 300F oven (or in a skillet on the stovetop) for 3-4 minutes, until a slight toasty aroma hits your nose. This step is optional but will enhance the flavor enormously. Just be careful not to go overboard &amp;ndash; it will burn in a flash.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Put the bran mix in a small pot and pour in milk; bring to a full boil, whisking frequently.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Reduce heat and simmer until a thick, creamy consistency. Turn off heat and let it cool off.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>The bran mix cooks fast &amp;ndash; the whole thing takes 10-15 minutes tops.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Note:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>You can make this in a microwave, too, just make sure to pause and stir frequently.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Any kind of milk will work.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>This porridge is so freakin' good that you may not be able to resist eating it right out of the pot! Feel free to whip up a big pot of bran porridge either in the evening or on a quiet morning, and keep it in the fridge for a whole week of easy, nutritious breakfasts (topped with fruits, nuts, and a drizzle of honey).&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="anise-orange-water">Anise orange water&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>Why use orange peels, instead of fresh orange juice, like in my &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/desert-dynamo">last Sonora loaf&lt;/a>? Well, a few reasons: I want to try something new; I have a ton of dried and frozen orange peels on hand; orange peels are flavorful, aromatic, and loaded with nutrients (wonderful additions to tea); orange peels actually contain almost twice as much vitamin C (and flavonoids) than the flesh of the fruit or the juice. In general, oranges with thicker peels tend to have more vitamin C, as the nutrient is concentrated in the peel and the white pith underneath.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Making the anise orange water is really simple:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Boil a handful of orange peels (fresh or dried) and a pinch of aniseeds in a pot of water for 5-10 minutes. Optional: add a stick of cinnamon and/or a few cardamom seeds and cloves for extra flavor.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Turn off heat and let cool off.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Strain with a fine-mesh sieve.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Stir in honey or sweetener of choice.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>Mine turned out a light amber-colored, aromatic, slightly sweetish tea.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>You can also use lemon peels instead of oranges. Other substitutes include grapefruit, lime, tangerine, clementine, or citrons. You can use any fruit or vegetable that has high quantity of vitamin C. If all fails, use a tablespoon of lemon juice or rosewater.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-4/20230303_235752.jpg"
alt="135% hydration wholegrain Sonora dough"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>135% hydration wholegrain Sonora dough&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;h4 id="final-dough">Final dough&lt;/h4>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Sonora Blanca flour, 80% extraction&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>320g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->diastatic barley malt powder&lt;sup id="fnref:2">&lt;a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>3g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>anise orange water, divided&lt;/td>
&lt;td>140%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>448g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>bran levain&lt;/td>
&lt;td>36%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>115g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>toasted bran porridge&lt;/td>
&lt;td>22%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>70g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sea salt (Gustus Vitae, CA)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>6g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>olive oil (California Select EVOO - Cobram Estate, CA)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>32g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Dough process:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Autolyse @ ~70% hydration&lt;/em>: Mix the flour with malt; stir in 1/2 of the anise orange water; mix until a shaggy mass; let autolyze for 30 minutes in the fridge.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Levain&lt;/em>: Squeeze in the levain; mix until combined. Let rest for 10-20 minutes at room temperature.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Double hydration&lt;/em>: Add 90% of the remaining anise orange water gradually, &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zgz0oAhgwyg">Rubaud-mixing&lt;/a> (lifting, stretching, and dropping) until thoroughly absorbed. This requires a bit patience, so take your time. If there&amp;rsquo;s one thing I&amp;rsquo;m good at, it&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em>bassinage&lt;/em>. And I usually put on some &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLlQWGGham__4sBxnwVyKbM8n91Xb9vwUG">music&lt;/a> or &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCkB8eF4ATHl4Jm1BeCZgQ9A">podcasts&lt;/a> while I do this. Hand-mixing a dough is a type of alternative physical therapy; I find it tremendously therapeutic and cathartic. Gorging the dough with soooo much water feels like a crime, TBH. I keep going until the dough tells me to stop&amp;hellip;&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Salt&lt;/em>: Mix in the salt. The dough is quite sticky. Let rest for 20 minutes at room temperature.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Bran porridge&lt;/em>: Divide the bran porridge into 3-4 portions; spread over the dough one portion at a time; mix until evenly distributed. Let rest for 20 minutes at room temperature.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Triple hydration&lt;/em>: Add the rest of the anise orange water, Rubaud-mixing until completely incorporated. Let rest for 20 minutes at room temperature.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Olive oil&lt;/em>: Drizzle in the olive oil, Rubaud-mixing until entirely combined.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Transfer the dough to a fridge (or somewhere 38F-43F) right away and ferment for 24 hours; take it out a every few hours and perform a &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6JQm2n4aVZc">coil-fold&lt;/a>. I did 4 folds in total.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>After 24 hours of bulk fermentation, shape the dough into whatever form you want. Let it warm up to room temperature for 2-3 hours before sending it into &lt;em>el horno&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>This Sonora dough went so far beyond my usual &lt;em>pan de cristal&lt;/em> hydration level &amp;ndash; and it&amp;rsquo;s supposedly a &amp;ldquo;soft&amp;rdquo; wheat!!!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>White whole wheat is always magical: the bran, germ, and midds become &amp;ldquo;invisible&amp;rdquo; after baking, and you can&amp;rsquo;t tell it&amp;rsquo;s whole wheat.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Once again, Sonora did not disappoint.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-4/20230304_180607.jpg"
alt="pan integral de sonora blanca"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>pan integral de sonora blanca&lt;/em>, with 100% wholegrain Sonora Blanca flour.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>A custardy crumb flecked with airy holes is enrobed in dramatically thin, crispy crusts.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>My &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/california-dreamin-2">134% hydration &lt;em>pan de San Joaquín&lt;/em>&lt;/a> had creamy-as-pudding center, but &amp;ndash; holy grain &amp;ndash; that peculiar creaminess was even more pronounced in this Sonora version!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Usually, whole grains (especially with weak gluten) turn bread into a dense brick, but this version is miraculous, with generous &lt;em>alveoli&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-4/20230304_181008.jpg"
alt="pan integral de sonora blanca"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>pan integral de sonora blanca&lt;/em>, with 100% wholegrain Sonora Blanca flour.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>A full-flavored wholegrain bread without the typical aesthetics of a wholegrain bread. The toasted bran porridge adds a ton of custardiness and flavor to the crumb.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Definitely not what you would typically expect from a bread made from a &amp;ldquo;soft&amp;rdquo; wheat.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The bread&amp;rsquo;s most pronounced characteristic was a subtle buttery, sweet flavor that lingered in my mouth. I think I tasted the Sonoran Desert &amp;ndash; the soil, the texture, the flavor.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-4/20230304_181059.jpg"
alt="pan integral de sonora blanca"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>pan integral de sonora blanca&lt;/em>, with 100% wholegrain Sonora Blanca flour.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The porous, chewy texture reminded me of a &lt;em>pan corriente&lt;/em> (&amp;ldquo;ordinary bread&amp;rdquo;) that I once had with hot chocolate in Morelia, Mexico.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I secretly think that labeling Sonora as a &amp;ldquo;soft&amp;rdquo; wheat does it tremendous injustice.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I cut this bread into thick slices, and seared them so that they were crisp on one side and as creamy as pudding within. I was planning to serve them to guests topped with different compositions &amp;ndash; crème fraîche, smoked anchovy and arugula, sour cherry jam &amp;ndash; but I was so drawn by the texture that most of the pieces I cooked didn&amp;rsquo;t make it out of the kitchen.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-4/20230304_181236.jpg"
alt="pan integral de sonora blanca"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>pan integral de sonora blanca&lt;/em>, with 100% wholegrain Sonora Blanca flour.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;m not sure if Sonora is a forlorn or undiscovered bread wheat, but this wheat has lofty potentials.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I can see the Sonora flour fulfilling many purposes in cooking and baking because of its unique makeup: It&amp;rsquo;s a beautiful &amp;ldquo;soft&amp;rdquo; heritage wheat with a naturally ivory color, and a subtle, creamy wheat flavor that&amp;rsquo;s almost neutral. A must-try for anyone who prizes the nuances of taste, texture, and performance found only in heritage grains.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;code>Hot take&lt;/code>: Using Sonora in cookies, cakes, and pastries severely caps its baking potential. It&amp;rsquo;s a waste. FFS, use Frederick (SWWW, 7.5%-9% protein) in such things. Spare Sonora &amp;ndash; it can do so much better.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-4/20230304_184816.jpg"
alt="pan integral de sonora blanca"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>pan integral de sonora blanca&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>&lt;em>This is part 4 of my &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/california-grain-adventure/">California Grain Adventure&lt;/a>. If you enjoyed this, why not check out my other &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/archives/">breadstories&lt;/a> and spread the word?&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>Another perk: I learned that a very important but often overlooked reason why California, instead of an East Coast city, became the tech mecca, is because in the eastern states, intellectual property created by an employee belongs to the employer, whereas in California it has historically belonged to the employee. Therefore, in software, an employee could come up with an innovative idea, take investment, and become a CEO. This attracted VCs and talented, ambitious engineers. Without this distinction, Silicon Valley &amp;ndash; if there was going to be one &amp;ndash; would likely have developed around MIT.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>I made my diastatic barley malt powder from unhulled malted barley, finely ground and unsifted.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/section></content></item><item><title>California Dreamin' #3: Sonora Blanca</title><link>/posts/california-dreamin-3/</link><pubDate>Sun, 26 Feb 2023 02:12:55 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/california-dreamin-3/</guid><description>[California Grain Adventure #3] Sonora Blanca minima: 100% wholegrain chocolate chip &lt;em>cookies de masa madre&lt;/em>, from scratch.</description><content>&lt;p>&lt;em>This is part 3 of my &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/california-grain-adventure/">California Grain Adventure&lt;/a>.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>For beauty, California is like the fresh, glowing, golden crescent moon; it is waxing steadily to a noble fullness of development.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Inez Haynes Irwin, &lt;em>The Californiacs&lt;/em> (1919)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>The California coast always looks so sunny and breathtaking, completely concealing the fact that most of the state is too dry to allow for a lot of life to thrive.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/california-dreamin-1">part 1&lt;/a>, I mentioned how California is a great exception to the rest of the US. Here&amp;rsquo;s yet another example: California is one of the few places where 4 of the 5 global climate zones (and 10 different climate subdivisions) occur in close proximity. Perhaps the only other place on the planet similar to California is central Chile, where this convergence is made even more extreme by the dramatic Andean topography.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-3/california-koppen-climates.png"
alt="Koppen climates in California"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Much of the state boasts a Mediterranean-style climate, which is rare outside of the Mediterranean Sea region. The one in California actually has 3 variations:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>cool summers and mild winters along the coast and the western slope of the Sierra Nevada;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>cool summers and mild winters, also along the coast, but with frequent summer fog;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>mild wet winters followed by hot dry summers with little or no rain for months, in the interior valley.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>With all types, most of the rain falls in winter &amp;ndash; not summer &amp;ndash; which is unusual for most of the world, where the opposite happens.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Precipitation levels also vary from year to year. Droughts come and go; extreme, multi-year statewide droughts have occurred several times throughout the past century; regional droughts have also plagued different parts of the state over the years.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Furthermore, most of California&amp;rsquo;s rain and snow fall in the northern half of the state &amp;ndash; in the Sierra Nevada Mountains, along the North Coast, and in the Cascade Range. However, most of the state&amp;rsquo;s population lives in the tremendously drier southern half.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Due to the variability in precipitation and the imbalance in population, California depends on a large network of reservoirs, dams, and aqueducts to store and transport surface water where and when people need it. According to a &lt;a href="https://lao.ca.gov/publications/report/3571">2017 report&lt;/a> from the Legislative Analyst&amp;rsquo;s Office, California has &amp;gt;20,000 miles of levees and channels, and over 1,500 dams and reservoirs. Make no mistake, California&amp;rsquo;s various flood control projects have been funded by the federal government.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Yup, &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/california-books">a great deal&lt;/a> about California does not, on its own preferred terms, add up.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>This extreme reliance of California on federal money, so seemingly at odds with the emphasis on unfettered individualism that constitutes the local core belief, was a pattern set early on, and derived in part from the very individualism it would seem to belie.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Joan Didion, &lt;em>Where I Was From&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>In southern California, water travels a great distance to get to people&amp;rsquo;s faucets: ~25% of the water used in southern California comes from the Colorado River; another 30% from the northern Sierras via the State Water Project; and the remaining 45% comes from a mix of &amp;ldquo;local&amp;rdquo; supplies, including the City of Los Angeles' eastern Sierra deliveries as well as desalination, recycling, and groundwater.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-3/california-map.png"
alt="Map of California"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Real-life California water wars (implicating everyone from local philanthropists right up to then-President Theodore Roosevelt) inspired the 1974 film noir &lt;em>Chinatown&lt;/em>, which played down the extent of the corruption involved. Perhaps it&amp;rsquo;s no surprise that later dystopian movies like &lt;em>Blade Runner&lt;/em> (1982) imagined a future Los Angeles of 2019 as a rain-soaked wasteland, after all the havoc that city officials wrought on the area&amp;rsquo;s ecosystem for personal profit.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The digital world is a lot of fun and undeniably innovative; search engines are ad vehicles and AI-powered voice assistants suck. Still, technology hasn&amp;rsquo;t been able to abstract away reality, and people seem to forget that it&amp;rsquo;s changes in the physical world that drive a lot of living standard improvements. Given how many people struggle in low-end jobs and how quickly tech expenditures are going up, claiming the internet is great smacks of &amp;ldquo;let them eat iPhones!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Competition for water is only growing and intensifying throughout California, particularly in the Central Valley.&lt;/p>
&lt;div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
&lt;iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/fWRs5B7rWYw" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video">&lt;/iframe>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>The Central Valley is very easy to ignore &amp;ndash; not in any way as glamorous as Silicon Valley or Hollywood &amp;ndash; but it&amp;rsquo;s as important to eaters (aka. all of us) as Silicon Valley is to smartphone users or Hollywood is to moviegoers.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Bordered on either side by mountains, the Central Valley stretches ~450 miles long from Redding to Bakersfield and ~50 miles wide on average, and occupies a land mass of 18,000 square miles (11.5 million acres) &amp;ndash; roughly the size of Massachusetts and Vermont combined. This valley is predominantly used for agriculture; it occupies &amp;lt;1% of US farmland, but supplies ~25% of Americans' food and accounts for 20% of the nation&amp;rsquo;s groundwater demand.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This valley contains the world&amp;rsquo;s largest patch of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/San_Joaquin_(soil)">Class 1 soil&lt;/a>, the best there is. The ~25°F temperature swing from day to night is an ideal growing range for plants. The sun shines nearly 300 days a year. The eastern half of the valley (and the western, to some extent) uses snowpack melt from the Sierra as its water source, i.e. it doesn&amp;rsquo;t have the same drought and flood problems as the Midwest. The winters are extremely mild with no snow, which offers a whole different growing season for plants that don&amp;rsquo;t adore summer heat.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The mild temperatures and winter rain support some of the highest biodiversity in the state. A few hundred different crops are grown in the valley, including those indigenous to South Asia, Southeast Asia and Mexico. Interestingly, some of that is canceled out by California&amp;rsquo;s Desert climates.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The expansive Central Valley is really two valleys: the Sacramento Valley to the north and the San Joaquin Valley to the south. The Steppe climate of the San Joaquin Valley is oppressively hot and dry like a desert, but averages enough moisture to support grasslands and other vegetation that commonly loathe the desert.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The Central Valley became widely known in the 1920s and 1930s, when farmers arrived from the eastern US, Oklahoma, Italy or Armenia and wrote home about the clean air, bountiful water and cheap land. This massive swath is now among the world&amp;rsquo;s most productive agricultural region &amp;ndash; and has helped California transformed from an agricultural backwater to one of the crown jewels of the US food system. The valley now produces almost all of the almonds, pistachios, and walnuts consumed domestically; &amp;gt;=90% of the artichokes, broccolis, carrots, celeries, garlic, grapes, plums, and tangerines; &amp;gt;=75% of the apricots, cauliflowers, lemons, strawberries, and raspberries; and &amp;gt;=40% of the cabbages, lettuces, oranges, peaches, and peppers.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The Central Valley is patently &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->John Steinbeck&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --> country. There are many fascinating places there like the &lt;a href="https://dustbowlcamp.org/history/">Weedpatch Camp&lt;/a>, the &lt;a href="https://www.bodie.com/plan/">Bodie&lt;/a> ghost town, the Japanese Internment Camp (aka. &lt;a href="https://www.nps.gov/manz/index.htm">Manzanar War Relocation Center&lt;/a>), Death Valley, Mount Whitney (the highest peak in the lower 48 states).&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>During the dry years, the people forgot about the rich years, and when the wet years returned, they lost all memory of the dry years. It was always that way.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>John Steinbeck, &lt;em>East of Eden&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Nothing much has changed in California and the Salinas Valley since 1952 when Steinbeck wrote &lt;em>East of Eden&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Farming and food production in the Central Valley are extremely vulnerable to droughts and floods. In a normal year, ~50% of the water used in the Central Valley comes from groundwater. During drought, when less water is available from rivers and canals, agriculture in the Central Valley typically depends on groundwater for over 2/3 of its water supplies.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As California enters exceptional &lt;a href="https://cww.water.ca.gov/droughtindicator">drought&lt;/a>, groundwater supplies throughout the Central Valley are being withdrawn faster than nature can replenish.&lt;/p>
&lt;div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
&lt;iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/-mSBOseNiZg" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video">&lt;/iframe>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>This is nothing new. Declines in groundwater levels have plagued the Central Valley for decades. Groundwater, according to one study, is effectively nonrenewable, because it can take centuries for aquifers to replenish once they are depleted, particularly in arid areas without significant rainfall.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Another study found that the depletion has worsened significantly since 2019, in a race to the bottom. Farmers need as much water as they can take out of the aquifers to farm the land in the hot and dry San Joaquin Valley.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>When groundwater levels keep on dropping, land surface can begin to subside.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Indeed, the overdrafting of the aquifer is causing portions of the valley floor to sink. As diminishing water levels leave spaces underground in layers of gravel, sand and clay, the ground collapses and permanently reduces the aquifer&amp;rsquo;s water-bearing capacity. In parts of the valley, the land has been sinking about 1 ft a year, damaging canals and wells.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If the groundwater disappears, so too does the food production. That means food shortages and higher food prices. By 2040, the San Joaquin Valley is projected to lose over &lt;a href="https://www.ppic.org/wp-content/uploads/water-and-the-future-of-the-san-joaquin-valley-february-2019.pdf">535,000 acres&lt;/a> of agricultural production. That&amp;rsquo;s &amp;gt;10% of the area farmed!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Meanwhile, towns in the Central Valley are beginning to run out of municipal water. Across the state, electric grids are also at risk if hydroelectric dams don&amp;rsquo;t get enough water to produce power. How are 10% of California&amp;rsquo;s car owners going to operate their Teslas?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Over the next two decades, California could lose ~10% of its water supplies. A growing number of scientists say the Golden State&amp;rsquo;s great &amp;ldquo;aridification&amp;rdquo; could permanently and profoundly change the state&amp;rsquo;s landscape and social fabric.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>What would John Steinbeck have written about the ongoing drought in California?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>What&amp;rsquo;s the flip side to the megadrought? Megaflood?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>California&amp;rsquo;s climate, already chaotic under normal conditions, is only getting weirder and wilder. Even if California does get enough rain this year to end the drought, it doesn&amp;rsquo;t change the fact that the ongoing water crisis is worsening.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It amazes me even more that the scarcest economic resources &amp;ndash; entrepreneurial ability and technical talent &amp;ndash; are spent on automating a globally abundant resource (i.e. cheap labor) and creating new variants of digital cocaine that are arguably more addictive and more harmful than cigarettes, instead of solving real-world problems.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>In California, water is now the most precious crop of all. Some farmers have realized that it makes better economic sense to sell unused water than to grow water-intensive crops like rice and almonds.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A huge transformation is happening up and down California&amp;rsquo;s Central Valley, as the agricultural labor supply shrinks and water becomes scarcer. Vast stretches of land are now fallow because there&amp;rsquo;s no water. New calculations are being made about what specific crops to grow, how much, and where. Millions of dollars are being spent on replenishing the aquifer that has been depleted for so long.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In the era of greater weather volatility, when water can be unreliable, adaptability is an asset.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-3/sonora-cwc.jpg"
alt="Sonora wheat berries"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Sonora Blanca wheat berries, from the San Joaquin Valley of California.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Which is why landrace plant varieties like the &lt;strong>Sonora Blanca&lt;/strong> wheat are important. Wheat production still requires water, but a lot less than growing rice, nuts or fruits.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/desert-dynamo">ICYMI&lt;/a>, Sonora is a heritage soft white winter wheat brought to the Americas by Spanish missionaries in the 1600s. It&amp;rsquo;s one of the &lt;a href="https://slowfoodusa.org/white-sonora-wheat/">oldest&lt;/a> varieties cultivated in North America, predating &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/red-fife/">Red Fife&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/turkey-red/">Turkey Red&lt;/a>. It&amp;rsquo;s also sometimes called Father Kino&amp;rsquo;s wheat, after Father Eusebio Francisco Kino who established Catholic missions throughout the Pimera Alta (present-day Sonora and southern Arizona) in the late 1600s.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The earliest known cultivation records document the grain&amp;rsquo;s existence in the early 1700s in the mountains of Sonora, a region in northern Mexico. That&amp;rsquo;s probably where the variety earned its name; to this day, Sonoran tortillas are more often made from soft wheat flour than maize like in the rest of Mexico.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>By the 1800s, Sonora wheat was widely planted in California and other areas in the southwestern US; it was a predominant source of flour for the western population, until the rise of industrialization after World War I, when hybridized high-yield commodity wheat replaced it. By the 1980s, Sonora was commercially dead. Luckily &amp;ndash; for those of us who care &amp;ndash; Sonora has been revived in the southwest thanks to the local-grain movement that spread like wildfire across the US.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-3/sonora-vs-joaquin.jpg"
alt="Sonora Blanca vs. Joaquin Oro"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Sonora Blanca (left) vs. Joaquin Oro (right), both grown in the San Joaquin Valley of California.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Sonora&amp;rsquo;s heritage earns it some clout by default. More importantly, the wheat has been adapting to the drought conditions in California for &lt;em>hundreds of years&lt;/em> (shall we crown it &amp;ldquo;the OG California Wheat?&amp;quot;). This adaptability has made the landrace variety popular among California grain farmers. Drought-tolerance eliminates the need for expensive irrigation. Additionally, Sonora&amp;rsquo;s lower protein content requires less input from the farmer, and lower nitrogen requirement makes it perfectly suitable for organic farming (no need to worry about the nitrogen content of the soil).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I baked with &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/desert-dynamo">Arizona-grown Sonora&lt;/a> a while ago, and named it &amp;ldquo;desert dynamo.&amp;rdquo; I still think it&amp;rsquo;s aptly named and well deserved. Everyone was telling me it was impossible to bake a lofty bread out of soft wheat alone, so I made a 100% Sonora bread just to show them it &lt;em>can&lt;/em> be done. The bread turned out so bloody marvelous it blew my expectations out of the water.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Thanks to generous friends at the California Wheat Commission, I got a chance to delve deeper into Sonora &amp;ndash; with the San Joaquin Valley terroir (grown by Eck Farms, CA).&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>Sonora actually can be planted in either fall or spring. It&amp;rsquo;s an early spring variety that does equally well as a winter wheat in milder winter climates that don&amp;rsquo;t freeze hard.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-3/sonora-backyard.jpg"
alt="Sonora growing in a 4×4 garden bed"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Sonora growing in a 4ft × 4ft garden bed.&lt;/p>&lt;p>Source: &lt;a href="https://gardenerd.com/blog/growing-white-sonora-wheat/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">Gardenerd&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>In southern California, even if you plant Sonora in October as a winter wheat, the climate there doesn&amp;rsquo;t really allow for winter wheat to behave like a winter wheat, which ordinarily grows low and wide in late fall, goes dormant in winter, then emerges and branches out in spring to maturity.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Sonora has a relatively high protein content (~12.7%), but is typically characterized as a &amp;ldquo;soft&amp;rdquo; wheat &amp;ndash; which befuddles me. The often-cited reason is that Sonora has inadequate &lt;a href="https://modernistcuisine.com/mc/gluten-how-does-it-work/">gluten-forming proteins&lt;/a>. I&amp;rsquo;ve never done individual testing of the glutenin and gliadin fractions in any wheat, nor am I interested in such, so don&amp;rsquo;t ask me. What I do know is that &lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=i6oQNo4gpeE">protein content&lt;/a> of a flour tells you little about the flour&amp;rsquo;s strength or baking performance. Some amino acids that make up the protein are usually water-soluble and contribute little to the strength of the flour, so a high-protein flour can actually have weak gluten.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-3/sonora-wheat-berries.jpg"
alt="Sonora Blanca wheat berries"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Sonora Blanca wheat berries, from the San Joaquin Valley of California.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>My &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/desert-dynamo">last bake&lt;/a> with Sonora proved to me that the flour is indeed capable of making a stretchable dough &amp;ndash; far more stretchable than a dough made with other soft wheats like Frederick (7.5%-9% protein) or even some hard wheats like &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/orange-sunshine">Warthog&lt;/a>; and apparently stretchable enough that Sonorans developed large flour tortillas, burritos and chimichangas with it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Sonoran-style flour tortillas (&lt;em>tortillas de harina estilo Sonora&lt;/em>) are works of art; they are stretched paper thin and cooked on a hot griddle, producing small blisters that give them a smoky flavor. Check out &lt;a href="https://www.latimes.com/food/la-fo-patricia-escarcega-sonoratown-review-20190424-story.html">Sonoratown&lt;/a>&amp;rsquo;s glorious flour tortillas in downtown Los Angeles, if you haven&amp;rsquo;t. They are freshly made daily, with &lt;a href="https://cooking.nytimes.com/recipes/1019621-sonoran-style-flour-tortillas">5 ingredients&lt;/a>: salt, water, lard, baking powder and soft Sonoran wheat flour produced in San Luis Río Colorado, on the Mexico-US border. These $10 plates of Sonoran tacos are so spectacular that hundreds of Angelenos would rather spend their time lining up in front of Sonoratown than going to flashy dinners at the world-famous &lt;a href="https://la.eater.com/2019/12/18/21028471/tartine-manufactory-downtown-los-angeles-the-row-closed-why">Tartine&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
&lt;iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/js2mgjJkyGE" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video">&lt;/iframe>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>A side note: If you have ever spent some time in Arizona, you may have noticed that the most distinctive marker of Arizonan cuisine is Sonoran-style Mexican food, an approach to border cooking that differs from Tex-Mex, New Mexican, or Baja styles and is seldom found outside of Arizona. Unlike the rest of Mexico where maize is king, Sonora is a wheat-growing region where the flour tortilla gets special attention, although they still use corn tortillas for a variety of dishes. In California, you are asked if you want flour or corn tortillas with dinner. In the Sonoran-style restaurants of Arizona, it&amp;rsquo;s assumed that you want the flour version.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>Sonora wheat berries are moderately hard, and lend themselves to milling.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Similar to &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/joaquin-oro/">Joaquin Oro&lt;/a>, Sonora mills to a fine, soft wholegrain flour on the first run (on a countertop electric WonderMill set to Bread Flour).&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-3/sonora-milled.jpg"
alt="Sonora Blanca wheat berries"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Freshly milled Sonora Blanca: a smooth, velvety wholegrain flour on the first run.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Since Sonora is commercially classified as a &amp;ldquo;soft&amp;rdquo; wheat, a lot of bakers automatically pass it up in breadmaking and use it instead in scones, biscuits, pies, muffins, tortillas, cookies, and cakes.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In fact, Sonora has a hidden kick of strength (&amp;quot;&lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/desert-dynamo">desert dynamo&lt;/a>&amp;quot;) that makes it work for many purposes and many meals. You can feed your family all three meals relying on just Sonora: biscuits/scones/muffins/tortillas for breakfast, naans or breads for lunch/dinner, and cakes/cookies throughout the day.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you are new to Sonora and other heritage wheat flours, start with a familiar recipe such as chocolate chip cookies.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-3/20230224_230603.jpg"
alt="Sonora Blanca chocolate chip cookies"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Chocolate chip &lt;em>cookies de masa madre&lt;/em>, with freshly milled wholegrain Sonora Blanca flour.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>I made two batches of chocolate chip &lt;em>cookies de masa madre&lt;/em> (with sourdough) from unsifted Sonora flour. All of the flour is pre-fermented to boost the flavor and bioavailability.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="iteration-1">Iteration #1&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Formula:&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Sonora Blanca flour, 100% extraction&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>200g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->malted barley flour&lt;sup id="fnref:2">&lt;a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->, 100% extraction&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>20g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>water&lt;/td>
&lt;td>55%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>110g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sourdough discard&lt;/td>
&lt;td>20%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>40g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;em>beurre noisette&lt;/em> (brown &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->butter&lt;sup id="fnref:3">&lt;a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">3&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->), softened&lt;/td>
&lt;td>25%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>50g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>extra virgin coconut oil, softened&lt;/td>
&lt;td>25%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>50g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->&lt;em>piloncillo oscuro&lt;/em>&lt;sup id="fnref:4">&lt;a href="#fn:4" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">4&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->, softened &amp;amp; chopped&lt;/td>
&lt;td>40%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>80g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>honey&lt;/td>
&lt;td>40%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>80g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>vanilla extract&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>4g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>4g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>baking soda&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->&lt;em>chocolate caliente mexicano&lt;/em> (homemade)&lt;sup id="fnref:5">&lt;a href="#fn:5" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">5&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->&lt;/td>
&lt;td>20%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>40g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>chocolate chips (Ghirardelli bittersweet)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>90%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>180g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>&lt;code>Note&lt;/code>: I didn&amp;rsquo;t use any eggs in these cookies, because eggs have been scarce on store shelves; whatever eggs I manage to track down, they are selling at &lt;a href="https://eggspensive.net/">record high prices&lt;/a>. Government data showed US consumers were paying $4.25 on average for a dozen eggs as of last December, which was 138% more than the year before.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The process is super simple:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Make the super &lt;em>masa madre&lt;/em>: Mix together the whole wheat flour, malt, water, and sourdough into a stiff ball. Let it ferment in a warm place for 3-4 hours, or until doubled in volume. Keep an eye on it &amp;ndash; you don&amp;rsquo;t want it to overripen and get sour.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Break up the &lt;em>masa madre&lt;/em>. Add the rest of the ingredients except the chocolate chips; mix until homogeneous.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Stir in the chocolate chips; mix until evenly dispersed.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Scoop onto a baking tray, spaced about 2&amp;rdquo; apart. (Chill the dough and the scoop first for 15-20 minutes, if you prefer thicker cookies.)&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Bake for 15 minutes at 300F, or until spread out and light brown.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-3/20230224_225515.jpg"
alt="Sonora Blanca chocolate chip cookies"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Chocolate chip &lt;em>cookies de masa madre&lt;/em>, with freshly milled wholegrain Sonora Blanca flour.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Listen up!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Here are three tricks to the very best chocolate cookies:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Use fresh wholegrain flour!&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Add 10% malted barley flour.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Brown the butter to accentuate the maltiness of the flours. Do yourself a favor and get a block of high-quality butter: 83% from Wisconsin, Kerrygold, New Zealand butter, or Isigny Sainte-Mère.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>Voila!&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-3/20230224_231154.jpg"
alt="Sonora Blanca chocolate chip cookies"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Chocolate chip &lt;em>cookies de masa madre&lt;/em>, fresh from the oven. The soft chewy interior is oozing with warm chocolate.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>A thin, crispy crust enrobes a soft center oozing with melty chocolate. Heavens.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Every bite gets a rich hit of chocolate in all its creamy, nutty, and caramelized glory.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-3/20230224_230201.jpg"
alt="Sonora Blanca chocolate chip cookies"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h3 id="iteration-2">Iteration #2&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>These cookies were gone within a few hours of emerging from the oven, so I had to make a 2nd freakin' batch.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I happened to have a few gorgeous beetroots (probably from California&amp;rsquo;s San Joaquin Valley, too), so I roasted the cubed beets on a charcoal-fired BBQ grill until perfectly caramelized. Then I puréed the beets in a blender, and added some of the red gold into the cookie dough.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Sonora Blanca flour, 100% extraction&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>200g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>malted barley flour, 100% extraction&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>20g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>water&lt;/td>
&lt;td>55%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>110g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sourdough discard&lt;/td>
&lt;td>20%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>40g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>roasted beetroot purée&lt;/td>
&lt;td>50%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>extra virgin coconut oil, softened&lt;/td>
&lt;td>25%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>50g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;em>piloncillo oscuro&lt;/em>, softened &amp;amp; chopped&lt;/td>
&lt;td>40%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>80g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>honey&lt;/td>
&lt;td>40%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>80g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>vanilla extract&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>4g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>4g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>baking soda&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>chocolate chips (Ghirardelli bittersweet)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>90%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>180g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>If you haven&amp;rsquo;t noticed, I omitted the brown butter and hot chocolate mix in this batch.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-3/20230225_185243.jpg"
alt="Sonora Blanca chocolate chip cookies"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Chocolate chip cookies batch #2, with roasted beetroot purée.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>They turned out royally delicious. Actually, they reminded me of Mexican &lt;em>polvorones rojas&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-3/20230225_185711.jpg"
alt="Sonora Blanca chocolate chip cookies with beetroots"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>cookies veganos de remolacha y chocolate&lt;/em>, made from scratch with fresh wholegrain Sonora Blanca flour.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Amid global and domestic supply chain turmoils (major supermarkets in the UK have &lt;a href="https://www.cnn.com/2023/02/24/business/uk-vegetable-fruit-shortage-rationing/index.html">started rationing produce&lt;/a>), these cookies really make me wonder what would happen when California&amp;rsquo;s Central Valley falls apart&amp;hellip; What would be the new normal? Time to build out my backyard vegetable garden?&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>&lt;em>This is part 3 of my &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/california-grain-adventure/">California Grain Adventure&lt;/a>. If you enjoyed it, why not check out my other &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/archives/">breadstories&lt;/a> and spread the word?&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>A little-known fact about John Steinbeck is that he was a travel writer. His nonfiction book, &lt;em>Travels With Charley&lt;/em>, preceded other great American road trip novels by Jack Kerouac, Studs Terkel, etc. In 1962, John Steinbeck won the Nobel Prize for his body of work. The Nobel Committee wrote: &amp;ldquo;His sympathies always go out to the oppressed, the misfits, and the distressed; he likes to contrast the simple joy of life with the brutal and cynical craving for money. But in him we find the American temperament also expressed in his great feelings for the tilled soil, the wasteland, the mountains, and the ocean coast&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>I made my diastatic barley malt flour from unhulled malted barley, finely ground and unsifted.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:3" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>Making brown butter at home is &lt;a href="https://food52.com/recipes/7234-beurre-noisette">super easy&lt;/a>. You can totally veganize these cookies by substituting the butter with coconut oil.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:4" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>Substitute with unrefined raw cane sugar.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:4" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:5" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>Making a Mexican hot chocolate mix from scratch takes only a few minutes and can be adjusted to your personal taste. I used freshly ground toasted pecans &amp;amp; almonds, cocoa powder, cinnamon, cardamom, clove, tri-pepper powder (ancho, guajillo, and habanero), and coconut sugar.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:5" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/section></content></item><item><title>California Dreamin' #2: Joaquin Oro</title><link>/posts/california-dreamin-2/</link><pubDate>Tue, 21 Feb 2023 21:25:13 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/california-dreamin-2/</guid><description>[California Grain Adventure #2] &lt;em>Pan de San Joaquín&lt;/em>. One 100% wholegrain Joaquin Oro dough, 2 leavens, baked 2 ways. Total hydration cranked up to 134% to push the flour&amp;rsquo;s limits. Both turned out delightfully light and airy; exceptionally soft and chewy.</description><content>&lt;p>&lt;em>This is part 2 of my &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/california-grain-adventure/">California Grain Adventure&lt;/a>. If you missed part 1, catch up &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/california-dreamin-1/">here&lt;/a>.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Stranger, let me warn you now. If ever you start for California with the intention of seeing anything of the State, do that before you enter San Francisco. If you must land in San Francisco first, jump into a taxi, pull down the curtains, drive through the city, breaking every speed law, to &amp;ldquo;Third and Townsend,&amp;rdquo; sit in the station until a train &amp;ndash; some train, any train &amp;ndash; pulls out, and go with it. If in crossing Market Street, you raise that taxi-curtain as much as an inch, believe me, stranger, it&amp;rsquo;s all off; you&amp;rsquo;re lost. You&amp;rsquo;ll never leave San Francisco. Myself, both times I have gone to California, I have vowed to see Yosemite, the big trees, the string of beautiful old missions which dot the state, some of the quaint, languid, semi-tropical towns of the south, some of the brisk, brilliant, bustling towns of the north. But I have never really done it because I saw San Francisco first.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Inez Haynes Irwin, &lt;em>The Californiacs&lt;/em> (1919)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>NYC boasts the best bagels in the world, which New Yorkers attribute to their magical tap water. San Francisco boasts the finest sourdough in the world, which San Franciscans attribute to their special air. The unseen native inhabitants in San Francisco&amp;rsquo;s damp, foggy micro-climate, they claim, create a special &amp;ldquo;microbial terroir&amp;rdquo; that can&amp;rsquo;t be replicated anywhere else.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>And for a San Francisco sourdough to be truly &amp;ldquo;authentic,&amp;rdquo; the local history and mythology go, it has to be born in San Francisco with proper San Franciscan air, not in Oakland, Richmond, or San Jose. (BTW, everyone hates Oakland, except people who actually live there and pay half the rent of what people pay in San Francisco while still basically living in San Francisco.)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>No one has convinced more people about the unique qualities of San Francisco sourdough than Boudin Bakery, which &lt;a href="https://www.foundsf.org/index.php?title=Yeast_to_Wheat:_How_Boudin_Bakery%E2%80%99s_Yeast_Culture_Shaped_San_Francisco%E2%80%99s_Counterculture">claims&lt;/a> to have been selling the same loaf of bread made with The Original San Francisco Sourdough™ for &amp;gt;170 years. According to the Boudin Bakery museum at the ultra-touristy Fisherman&amp;rsquo;s Wharf, the company&amp;rsquo;s mother dough follows an unbroken line back to the Gold Rush in 1849. Louise Boudin even saved the starter from a burning building during the 1906 earthquake. A museum docent will readily inform you the starter is so special and irreplaceable that the Boudin mothership sends its retail stores fresh starter every 23 days. Without it, they emphasize, the sourdough produced at those stores would stop tasting like San Francisco sourdough &amp;ndash; and start tasting like Sacramento or San Diego sourdough, which is absolutely blasphemous.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Also, according to the museum, Boudin&amp;rsquo;s bread owes its special flavor to a particular strain of lactic acid bacteria that thrives &lt;em>only&lt;/em> in San Francisco&amp;rsquo;s climate. Scientists identified it here in 1970, so they named it &lt;em>Lactobacillus sanfranciscensis&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It&amp;rsquo;s a great, great story. Too bad it&amp;rsquo;s not quite true.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Scientists did identify &lt;em>Lactobacillus sanfranciscensis&lt;/em> in San Francisco. But recent studies have found it in &lt;a href="www.nytimes.com/2012/09/19/dining/for-gastronomists-a-go-to-microbiologist.html">90% of the world&amp;rsquo;s sourdough&lt;/a>, too. So from a biological standpoint, San Francisco sourdough is not all that distinctive &amp;ndash; or unique to San Francisco.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you take your precious local sourdough starter and bake with it in Los Angeles, I bet the resulting bread will taste very similar to what you make in San Francisco. Blasphemy! But likely&amp;hellip;true. Even breads made without &lt;em>Lactobacillus sanfranciscensis&lt;/em> can taste pretty darn good.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>So much for the &amp;ldquo;microbial terroir&amp;rdquo; myth. Even bakers who have been in a position to benefit from the reputation of local sourdough don&amp;rsquo;t embrace the cachet. Call a dog a dog &amp;ndash; it&amp;rsquo;s pure marketing. It sells the city, turning sourdough into another tourist attraction that San Francisco is famous for, besides the bridge and the bay.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-2/20230220_104457.jpg"
alt="Joaquin Oro pan de San Joaquín baked"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>My &lt;em>pan de San Joaquín&lt;/em>, made with home-milled 100% wholegrain Joaquin Oro flour and a non-San Francisco sourdough starter&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>There are 3 bread institutions in the San Francisco Bay Area: Acme, Semifreddi&amp;rsquo;s, and Tartine.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Acme is often credited as an OG pioneer of the San Francisco Bay Area&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Bread Revolution,&amp;rdquo; which in turn galvanized the modern &amp;ldquo;artisan bread&amp;rdquo; movement across America; to this day, Acme&amp;rsquo;s bread remains a &amp;ldquo;benchmark&amp;rdquo; for commercial handmade bread. It was a stalwart of the 1980s artisan baking scene, along with Semifreddi&amp;rsquo;s.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Newer upstarts like Tartine and Josey Baker Bread have brought on some serious competition, and challenged the status quo of what San Francisco bread is &lt;em>supposed&lt;/em> to taste like and, along the way, the status quo of home baking.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In 2006, the NY Times food columnist Mark Bittman &lt;a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2006/12/06/dining/06mini.html">wrote about&lt;/a> a NYC baker named Jim Lahey, the man behind Sullivan Street Bakery who had developed a no-knead bread recipe that consisted of only 4 steps and required just 4 ingredients &amp;ndash; flour, water, salt, and yeast. While not the OG recipe of its kind, the &amp;ldquo;no-knead&amp;rdquo; method spread like wildfire. It revolutionized the food world; its simplicity miraculously democratized breadmaking for the home baker. Lahey became a semi-god figure &amp;ndash; the Prometheus who gifted the art of breadmaking to the masses. He released a cookbook in 2009, titled &lt;em>My Bread: The Revolutionary No-Work, No-Knead Method&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A few years earlier, a transplanted New Yorker named Elizabeth Pruitt and her husband Chad Robertson moved their tiny baking operation from Point Reyes, California south to an unassuming corner of Guerrero Street, at the edge of the Mission District in San Francisco. They named it Tartine, and churned out artisan breads, viennoiseries and sandwiches. The bakery garnered praise from Alice Waters and Martha Stewart, and made the cake for a &lt;a href="https://www.sfgate.com/entertainment/article/Why-the-concert-was-canceled-3314257.php">&amp;ldquo;bohemian bourgeois&amp;rdquo;-themed birthday party&lt;/a> attended by Nancy Pelosi and Hillary Clinton. Mark Bittman &lt;a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2007/01/28/travel/28Bite.html">described&lt;/a> their shop as one of the best French-style bakeries in the country, and particularly raved about Tartine&amp;rsquo;s sandwiches, which were made on &amp;ldquo;Mr. Robertson&amp;rsquo;s exceptional bread, notable because it&amp;rsquo;s a slow-fermented yeast bread in very French style that is a welcome change from the ubiquitous sourdough.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>San Franciscans started lining up outside the shop to get a taste of what Prueitt and Robertson were baking; the queues outside Tartine became a local landmark and a symbol of a changing city. (Lines beget lines; the success of Tartine&amp;rsquo;s OG location is arguably one of the reasons that San Francisco gained a reputation as a place where people would wait in line for any sort of &amp;ldquo;cult&amp;rdquo; food item.) Tartine&amp;rsquo;s bread started to become a Veblen good, just as Prueitt and Robertson started to become food-world celebrities. In 2010, the influential &lt;em>Tartine Bread&lt;/em> was published; Robertson revealed to the world his recipe for French-style sourdough, which called for folding, shaping, scoring, and a grasp of wild yeast. The change from Lahey&amp;rsquo;s no-knead bread to Robertson&amp;rsquo;s sourdough was remarkable; home baking was about to become more technical and more precise.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The complete recipe for Basic Country Bread, the edible hero of &lt;em>Tartine Bread&lt;/em>, runs 38 pages, including photographs. It was instantly celebrated as a &amp;ldquo;masterpiece&amp;rdquo; in media, along the lines of a Martin Scorsese tracking shot or a Marcel Proust sentence.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Robertson wrote about bread in a detailed but flexible way: The prose is lean and direct; the instructions don&amp;rsquo;t just tell you what to do but explain why, what to look for, and how to make corrections, encouraging you to see his laborious artisan craft as adaptable and welcoming of interpretation. Robertson was also a laid-back surfer who radiated a particular kind of Gen X bohemianism, which inadvertently imbued breadmaking with a sort of new masculine sheen.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Seemingly, Robertson gave away the store. The bread he teaches you to make is essentially the same bread that has turned him into one of the most influential bakers in the world; it&amp;rsquo;s what causes otherwise rational adults to mob the line at Tartine Bakery. The fact is, Tartine multiplied its influence by opening up about the way they do things.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Tartine Bread&lt;/em> could have merely been aspirational, but it&amp;rsquo;s just too &lt;em>actionable&lt;/em>. The recipes work, and they inspire. All of a sudden, many of Tartine&amp;rsquo;s fans took up artisan baking at home &amp;ndash; a majority of whom happened to be guys in tech.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For tech geeks in the San Francisco Bay Area, &lt;em>Tartine Bread&lt;/em> had it all:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>a recipe that encouraged iteration and a grasp of the scientific nature of wild fermentation;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>a craft that was not frivolous or quintessentially feminine like making cupcakes; and&lt;/li>
&lt;li>a cool leader that inspires emulation.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Technologists stormed sourdough with a host of tools and techniques that built on Robertson&amp;rsquo;s artisan approach. Ken Forkish, who had quit his job at IBM to become a baker, wrote &lt;em>Flour Water Salt Yeast&lt;/em> and won a James Beard Award in 2013. Nathan Myhrvold, the former CTO of Microsoft and current CEO of patent and investment firm Intellectual Ventures, released a 5-volume cookbook called &lt;em>Modernist Bread&lt;/em> in 2017. It also won a James Beard. High-efficiency tools like $150 Brød &amp;amp; Taylor Folding Bread Proofer that offers &amp;ldquo;precision control&amp;rdquo; over temperature and humidity, or the $300 Fourneau bread oven, which &amp;ldquo;traps steam and radiates powerful heat&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;helps you achieve oven spring&amp;rdquo;, came on the market.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Overnight, Silicon Valley venture capitalists started tweeting about their fine sourdough starters; UX designers started buying $600 bannetons and taking extensive notes about each bake in apps like Evernote, Google Keep, Notion and Bear; and tender #crumbshots popped up all over breadstagram. Everyone in Silicon Valley is Very Publicly Into Sourdough All of a Sudden. People couldn&amp;rsquo;t delight more in the miracles of this alchemy than if it were neolithic times and bread was just invented yesterday. Breadmaking has become the latest form of romantic consumerism.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-2/20230220_110032.jpg"
alt="Joaquin Oro pan de San Joaquín baked"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>pan de San Joaquín&lt;/em>. home-milled unsifted Joaquin Oro flour + non-San Francisco sourdough starter + homemade pineapple yeast water poolish&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The Perfect Loaf, a sourdough bread blog launched in 2013 by Maurizio Leo, a software engineer by trade, is frequently cited as an entry point to baking for men in tech, as his approach speaks to technically-oriented individuals and, as his blog name implies, is pursuant of mastery.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Breadmaking is now seen as a sort of an &amp;ldquo;algorithm&amp;rdquo;; it&amp;rsquo;s expected to produce a certain result and if that result isn&amp;rsquo;t always what you expect, you step back and diagnose the steps along the way. Working on bread recipes has become a new form of &amp;ldquo;debugging.&amp;rdquo; That iterative procedure for optimization appeals to the engineering mind, not to mention the precision part. Breadmaking also offers various degrees of freedom &amp;ndash; it could be implemented in lots of different possible ways.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It&amp;rsquo;s a liberating escape, particularly when you work in tech for a living and can&amp;rsquo;t turn that technical side of your brain off and your work becomes so embedded in your life that it consumes you.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Like religion, romanticism also has its liminal rituals, which decouple the subjective feelings of pleasure and freedom from material goods and mass-marketed symbols, and disrupt the daily tedium and hierarchies, transporting us, through the consumption of goods and services labeled romantic, into a fantastic world in which ordinary annoyances, our own limitations and, with a little luck, even our most objectionable caprices, are temporarily interrupted. Maybe baking is an opportunity for these technologists to rehabilitate their humanity, when they are not busy creating apps that make money off everyone&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;addiction&amp;rdquo;?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Sourdough&lt;/em>, a 2017 novel by Robin Sloan, pokes fun at the obnoxious foodie culture of Silicon Valley while also ribbing the folks who are so eager to innovate it &amp;ndash; the tech guys who obsess over an ancient idea, commit to disrupting it, then get bored and move on.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The reason that Chad Robertson became a god among tech-oriented breadmaking hobbyists is perhaps more shallow than one might think: Robertson and Tartine are instrumental to this whole trend because he was in San Francisco just as this mid-2000s tech wave was taking off. Right place, right time. Right guy, right craft.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>When Robertson &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=tHUU9dcHVng">spoke&lt;/a> about the intersection of tech and bread at a Wired conference in 2015, he said as much, noting that the reason he and Prueitt even moved their bakery to San Francisco in the first place was because the burst of the dotcom bubble in the early 2000s finally made it affordable for them to do so: The median rent for a two-bedroom apartment had fallen from $3,000 a month to just under $2,000. Development had slowed, evictions and unemployment had spiked, and commercial vacancies had risen. In the Mission District, a historically working-class and Latino neighborhood, artists' spaces battled with real-estate developers.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Tartine had thrived during an economic downturn. Now it&amp;rsquo;s operating in one of the most expensive cities in the world, where a 21-year-old earning low six-figures is considered a peasant.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-2/20230220_105833.jpg"
alt="Joaquin Oro pan de San Joaquín baked"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>pan de San Joaquín&lt;/em>. home-milled unsifted Joaquin Oro flour + non-San Francisco sourdough starter + homemade pineapple yeast water poolish&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>Tartine has undergone rapid expansion since Chad Robertson personally manned the ovens at the OG store on Guerrero Street, shuttling out a limited number of loaves every evening.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In 2014, the Oakland-born and San Francisco-raised Blue Bottle, the most dominant company riding the &amp;ldquo;third wave&amp;rdquo; coffee trend, had just &lt;a href="https://valleywag.gawker.com/blue-bottle-which-raised-45-m-cut-health-benefits-fo-1663442765">raised $45 million dollars&lt;/a> in venture capital for its own expansion, and needed a bakery partner to provide food in its coffee shops. Tartine soon announced a &lt;a href="https://www.latimes.com/food/dailydish/la-dd-tartine-blue-bottle-merging-20150420-story.html">merger&lt;/a> with the company; the news turned heads in the northern California food world and beyond. Anticipating a personal windfall, Prueitt and Robertson moved into a luxurious circa 1960 house in the Castro district in 2015. Eater SF did a &lt;a href="https://sf.eater.com/2016/2/23/11098328/tartine-bakery-liz-prueitt-chad-robertson-home-kitchen#11">photo shoot&lt;/a> of their newly remodeled home kitchen, showing off their specialized kitchenware and verdant backyard.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>By February 2016 when the Eater piece went live, the Blue Bottle acquisition had &lt;a href="https://www.sfchronicle.com/restaurants/article/Blue-Bottle-and-Tartine-Bakery-nix-merger-6673950.php">fallen apart&lt;/a>. The couple put the Castro house up for sale and quietly moved out in early 2018. Still, Tartine Manufactory, a restaurant and bar concept conceived in their sleek, airy home kitchen, opened in the summer of 2016. &lt;a href="https://sf.eater.com/2016/8/17/12513334/tartine-manufactory-san-francisco-mission-photos">Eater SF&lt;/a> lauded the 5,000-sqft space as &amp;ldquo;an artisanal utopia in the Mission&amp;rdquo;; every detail was designed to represent &amp;ldquo;a new type of luxury.&amp;rdquo; Meanwhile, Tartine launched its own coffee brand, &lt;a href="https://sprudge.com/tartines-coffee-manufactory-roasting-destiny-san-francisco-107956.html">Coffee Manufactory&lt;/a>, in partnership with a former Starbucks executive who is now the Chief Operations Officer of Tartine.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>One of Tartine&amp;rsquo;s partners and investors is a real-estate private-equity firm called CIM Group, one of the largest property owners in Los Angeles and a prominent commercial landlord in Oakland, managing about $30 billion dollars in assets.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Tartine&amp;rsquo;s Coffee Manufactory planned to move into Jack London Square, a 434,000-sqft waterfront property in Oakland acquired by CIM in 2016 as part of a &lt;a href="https://www.sfchronicle.com/restaurants/article/Jack-London-Square-cooks-up-a-new-generation-of-11231529.php">$131 million deal&lt;/a> for long-term development. CIM billed the Coffee Manufactory as an anchor tenant &amp;ndash; a business that could attract customers and other businesses, increasing the overall value and cachet of the area. The developer was curating the neighborhood with buildings and tenants.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Tartine was a particularly appealing anchor tenant. The food was great, and most of it could be made off-site, requiring a fairly modest square footage for retail sites. And Tartine had a history: the flagship location, with its artistic staff and communal ambiance, radiated the sort of authenticity that a real-estate developer could only dream of cultivating. Year on year, Tartine’s brand had become cooler, airier, and more transportable.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Anna Wiener, &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href="https://www.newyorker.com/news/letter-from-silicon-valley/when-baking-and-real-estate-collide">When Baking and Real Estate Collide&lt;/a>&amp;rdquo;, &lt;em>The New Yorker&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Images of Tartine&amp;rsquo;s pastries and its OG Guerrero Street bakery started to pop up in &lt;a href="hhttps://www.buzzfeed.com/michellerial/morning-bun">Apple commercials and product demos&lt;/a>. Sweetgreen, the East Coast fast-casual salad chain that was now proliferating along the West Coast, started to offer &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href="https://sf.eater.com/2017/8/30/16227094/sweetgreen-tartine-manufactory-salad-bowl-san-francisco-bay">The Tartine Bowl&lt;/a>&amp;rdquo;, plucked from Prueitt&amp;rsquo;s recently published book &lt;em>Tartine All Day&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Tartine&amp;rsquo;s brand became another recognizable symbol of &lt;a href="https://archive.is/mmUwT">gentrification&lt;/a>; the opening of a Tartine seemed to hint that a neighborhood was on the cusp of it. The process of bringing intense, aggressive real-estate development to upper-middle-class neighborhoods, to cater to an even more affluent stratum, is gentrification on steroids.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In January 2019, Tartine opened &lt;a href="https://sf.eater.com/2019/1/22/18193239/manufactory-food-hall-sfo-tartine-cala-kamine-san-francisco-international-airport">the Manufactory Food Hall&lt;/a> in San Francisco International Airport.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>That spring, Tartine opened a splashy &lt;a href="https://la.eater.com/2019/1/28/18200748/manufactory-row-tartine-chris-bianco-los-angeles-photos-inside">new 40,000-sqft Tartine Manufactory&lt;/a> &amp;ndash; three times the size of its first Manufactory in San Francisco &amp;ndash; in the Row, a huge, newly developed compound in Downtown Los Angeles (DTLA). &lt;em>Food &amp;amp; Wine&lt;/em> published a feature on Robertson and Prueitt, with the headline &amp;ldquo;With L.A. Opening, Tartine Positions Itself for World Domination.&amp;rdquo; F*ck yeah, Silicon Valley-style.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>CIM invested in Tartine&amp;rsquo;s 5 new locations in Los Angeles (&lt;a href="https://la.eater.com/2019/1/10/18177207/tartine-silver-lake-sunset-coming-expansion-news">Silver Lake&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://la.eater.com/2019/7/29/20746164/tartine-hollywood-bakery-san-francisco-opening-sycamore-news">West Hollywood&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://la.eater.com/2019/9/6/20853090/tartine-bakery-santa-monica-expansion-opening-funeral-home">Santa Monica&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://www.thebrassy.com/blog/west-adams-tartine-is-a-welcome-neighborhood-addition">West Adams&lt;/a>, and &lt;a href="https://la.eater.com/2022/2/1/22912646/tartine-pasadena-new-cafe-opening-restaurant-los-angeles-morning-am-intel-news">Pasadena&lt;/a>). For any Angeleno who&amp;rsquo;s ever wondered just how all these Tartines landed in the Southland in the first place, here&amp;rsquo;s an answer.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In July 2019, Tartine opened its 3rd San Francisco location, in a CIM-affiliated property in the Inner Sunset neighborhood.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In September 2019, Tartine opened its 5th Bay Area location in &lt;a href="https://sf.eater.com/2019/9/16/20868239/tartine-berkeley-bakery-open-graduate-hotel">Berkeley&lt;/a>. The café is tucked into a sunroom at Berkeley&amp;rsquo;s Graduate Hotel (fka. the Hotel Durant), a chain hotel owned by Adventurous Journeys Capital, a self-described &amp;ldquo;vertically integrated real estate investment manager focused on developing and operating transformative real estate assets in spaces often overlooked or undervalued by traditional investment firms.&amp;rdquo; Tartine&amp;rsquo;s new presence at the hotel came as part of a ~$50 million transformation from the Hotel Durant to the Graduate Hotel.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Customers who walk into any of Tartine&amp;rsquo;s locations may never feel or realize they are entering part of a real-estate empire.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>How much of Tartine is owned by CIM and how deeply these two companies are intertwined has never been publicly disclosed. The daughter of a co-founder of CIM is now Tartine&amp;rsquo;s VP of Brand.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-2/20230220_190301.jpg"
alt="Joaquin Oro pan de San Joaquín baked"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>100% wholegrain &lt;em>pan de San Joaquín&lt;/em>, gleaming in the wintry sun.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Today, Tartine operates 3 locations in the San Francisco Bay Area, 5 in Los Angeles, and 6 licensed locations in Seoul (one of which is located at &lt;a href="https://tartinebakery.com/seoul/dosan">Kinfolk Dosan&lt;/a>, a cultural space created by Kinfolk, an aspirational lifestyle magazine). How can a craft bakery still be artisanal if it has 6 overseas branches?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Tartine&amp;rsquo;s workers in San Francisco watched investment flow into the new locations and increasingly felt neglected. They suspected they were the actual engine that propelled Tartine into an empire, but now they couldn&amp;rsquo;t even get a $1/hour raise. There was a lot of confusion about the company&amp;rsquo;s investors &amp;ndash; who were they, and how much power did they wield? Money to pay invoices wasn&amp;rsquo;t there.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Tartine was expanding, but the OG Mission location was falling apart. In November 2019, the San Francisco Department of Public Health &lt;a href="https://sf.eater.com/2019/11/23/20979306/tartine-rats-rodents-dph-mission">briefly shut down&lt;/a> Tartine&amp;rsquo;s Guerrero Street location, after inspectors say that its operators failed to deal with a persistent rodent infestation in the space.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Workers noticed cultural changes. Shift wine was eliminated, and management introduced a monthly music playlist. Some were dissatisfied with wages, raises, and scheduling. Employees wanted certain benefits, such as paid time off separate from state-mandated sick leave, and raises larger than the annual increases mandated by the city. All this looked feasible to them, given the company’s expansion. When they brought these requests to Tartine’s newly created human-resources department, they were confused to find that it was run out of offices leased from CIM affiliates, in Los Angeles.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Anna Wiener, &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href="https://www.newyorker.com/news/letter-from-silicon-valley/when-baking-and-real-estate-collide">When Baking and Real Estate Collide&lt;/a>&amp;rdquo;, &lt;em>The New Yorker&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>As Tartine expanded rapidly in the last 6-7 years, operational difficulties grew with it. Money was allocated to ventures that didn&amp;rsquo;t pan out. The whole enterprise seemed stretched thin. There seemed to be a fundamental disconnect between perception and reality. New investment was focused on new ventures, but Tartine&amp;rsquo;s expansion relied on the strength of its brand.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Bar Tartine closed in 2016 and had never turned a profit (since it opened in 2005 just a couple of blocks away from the OG Tartine Bakery). The planned Coffee Manufactory retail space in Jack London Square never opened.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In December 2019, Tartine&amp;rsquo;s massive DTLA Manufactory shuttered &amp;ndash; 11 months after it opened. It was a shocking closure. The store laid off its remaining workers 10 days before Christmas.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Tartine’s market, retail baking and takeaway spaces, and multiple restaurants all closed this week after just 11 months of business and a build-out rumored to have run into the tens of millions of dollars. All of the Row is struggling to find sustained weeknight retail traffic right now, but the loss of anchor tenant Tartine has hit the development’s brand particularly hard. There simply were not enough $72 mug buyers around to keep the place afloat, and that seems to say something about Tartine’s visibility and draw, and about the Row overall — not to mention the cost of goods inside. &amp;hellip;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Simply put: Tartine didn’t find a good way to consistently speak to Angelenos, and in a city where driving four miles to have dinner can mean sitting in your car for an hour, answering the “why” of the place not only proved tricky, it likely proved its undoing. &amp;hellip; More than anything, it struggled to define its place at the Row, in Downtown, in a city brimming with home bakers and panaderias and other local bread legends like Friends &amp;amp; Family, Clark Street, and Bub &amp;amp; Grandma’s.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Eater LA, &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href="https://la.eater.com/2019/12/18/21028471/tartine-manufactory-downtown-los-angeles-the-row-closed-why">Tartine&amp;rsquo;s Big DTLA Manufactory Closed After Just One Year. What Happened?&lt;/a>&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Tartine took on a new investor, Monogram Capital Partners, another private-equity firm &amp;ldquo;focused exclusively on consumer and retail companies.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Meanwhile, Chad Robertson started to show up in &lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/BlundstoneUS/videos/live-in-my-blundstones-chad-robertson/2553319681570138/">sponsored content&lt;/a> for &lt;a href="https://www.blundstone.com/limb-chad-robertson">Blundstone boots&lt;/a> on social media. He and Prueitt divorced in 2020.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Given the PE industry&amp;rsquo;s typical M.O. (i.e. the decade-long pyramiding of real estate and overleveraging on ever lower interest rates), I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be surprised if Tartine is sinking deeper and deeper into debt &amp;ndash; or might eventually end up like &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/aquaboogie-di-dolce">Dean &amp;amp; DeLuca&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In February 2020, a few short weeks before the Covid lockdown, 141 of Tartine&amp;rsquo;s &amp;gt;200 San Francisco Bay Area employees signed a letter, announcing their decision to unionize with the International Longshore and Warehouse Union. It came as a huge surprise, especially at a world-renowned bakery that boasts about ​&amp;quot;production at a human scale&amp;quot; and has been a training ground for young bakers from around the globe.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Tartine&amp;rsquo;s management declined to recognize the union, and &lt;a href="https://sf.eater.com/2020/2/11/21133479/tartine-union-management-sam-singer">hired Sam Singer&lt;/a>, a longtime San Francisco crisis communications expert known for his work with controversial companies like Chevron&amp;rsquo;s Richmond oil refinery. After letting him go amid criticism, they then hired a Las Vegas-based firm called Quest Consulting to quash the unionizing effort. Quest&amp;rsquo;s founder, Lupe Cruz, has earned himself a &lt;a href="https://www.pressdemocrat.com/article/news/union-organizers-and-workers-decry-union-busting-consulting-firms-hired-b/">reputation&lt;/a> among labor organizers as &amp;ldquo;a notorious union-buster who specializes in influencing Latino-dominated workforces.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In March 2021, over a year after voting and following a thorny, protracted dispute over 24 challenged ballots, the National Labor Relations Board announced that Tartine&amp;rsquo;s workers in San Francisco had officially unionized. In May 2022, the Tartine Union began negotiations for its first wage and healthcare contract, which &lt;a href="https://sf.eater.com/2022/8/23/23318336/tartine-bakery-union-negotiations">stalled&lt;/a> a few months later.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-2/20230220_105911.jpg"
alt="Joaquin Oro pan de San Joaquín baked"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>pan de San Joaquín&lt;/em>. home-milled unsifted Joaquin Oro flour + non-San Francisco sourdough starter + homemade pineapple yeast water poolish&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>A single person at the right place comes up with a &amp;ldquo;unique&amp;rdquo; recipe at the right time can have the outsized effect of influencing a whole new generation of bakers, and even become a cult figure.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Nothing is more powerful than an idea whose time has come.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Victor Hugo&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>No single part of Tartine&amp;rsquo;s technique or bread is new or original to me. I&amp;rsquo;ve eaten there several times; nothing about it has blown my mind. Maybe it was groundbreaking a decade ago to the culinarily ignorant masses who grew up on industrial wheatish pulp?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>That one guy who lives in San Francisco at the right time with the right trade shouldn&amp;rsquo;t get all the credit for this bread renaissance &amp;ndash; East Coast journalists began to protest. People (mostly women) have been baking bread at home for thousands of years before Robertson and Prueitt opened Tartine.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Apparently, &amp;ldquo;nerds&amp;rdquo; over-engineering breadbaking, turning this homegrown, down-to-earth craft into something more technical and complicated than it should be, and &amp;ldquo;pushing&amp;rdquo; women out in the process is &lt;a href="https://www.eater.com/2018/11/19/18099127/bread-silicon-valley-sourdough-tech-bros-tartine-chad-robertson">a huge problem&lt;/a>. The gendering of baking has become a hot topic.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;hellip;one of my favorite things about JavaScript is when we discover things 20 years after other languages, besides like the concept of baking your own bread at home instead of purchasing it from the store, we act like we invented fat arrow functions, classes, immutable data, restructuring statements, functional programming &amp;ndash; like, it&amp;rsquo;s like truly wild to witness.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&amp;hellip;this baking bread thing seems to have come out of like nowhere and it&amp;rsquo;s interesting to see. &amp;hellip; I was going to make fun of the parallels between baking bread &amp;ndash; like baking bread from a recipe and implementing an algorithm of code, but I think that the real interesting and problematic parallel is the rhetoric with which JavaScript developers talk about bread. It&amp;rsquo;s super elitist and it&amp;rsquo;s mostly dudes.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>why are there no women in tech baking bread? And I feel like &amp;ndash; this is in all seriousness, I feel this pressure now to stop this in its tracks. &amp;hellip; I&amp;rsquo;m worried about fucking bread. Like, you think I&amp;rsquo;d have enough emotional labor as a woman in tech to have to deal with baking bread &amp;ndash; I don&amp;rsquo;t know.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Jenn Schiffer, &lt;a href="https://www.deconstructconf.com/2017/jenn-schiffer-how-to-be-a-real-developer">Deconstruct Conf 2017&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>People in and around San Francisco making sourdough is such a surprising and novel phenomenon that it needs to be picked apart &amp;ndash; because (&lt;em>gasp&lt;/em>!) they happen to be men who work in tech and ruin whatever they lay their hands on for the sake of fashion and &amp;ldquo;disruption.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Perhaps the pseudo-celebrity status of Chad Robertson, the ubiquity of Instagram shots that emphasize only the visual aesthetic of breads, etc. speak to humans' shallowness and egotism more than anything else.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Who cares about some JavaScript developer in San Francisco who bakes bread at home and runs a blog about it? If anything, it&amp;rsquo;s those who follow them keenly on social media that affirm their authority and turn them into some bread gods. Why are you so desperate for external validation?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A lot of people think that to be a real developer/baker, you need to be prolific on social media. If you don&amp;rsquo;t argue about your trade on Twitter, GitHub or Instagram, you don&amp;rsquo;t &lt;em>feel like&lt;/em> you are a real developer/baker. Yeah sure. Only if you &lt;em>choose&lt;/em> to play this game and be stuck in this rat race.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-2/20230220_104703.jpg"
alt="Joaquin Oro pan de San Joaquín baked"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>pan de San Joaquín&lt;/em>. home-milled unsifted Joaquin Oro flour + non-San Francisco sourdough starter + homemade pineapple yeast water poolish&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>I don&amp;rsquo;t think the scientific approach to bread is a futile endeavor. Why can&amp;rsquo;t the scientific and the intuitive approaches co-exist?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The foundation of bread is super simple and those basic principles are still unchanged. I disagree that it&amp;rsquo;s total hubris to be attempting to innovate and move the art forward. Some folks are actually making significant innovations in breadmaking, and innovation is not an &amp;ldquo;American sickness&amp;rdquo; that needs to be cured. (In fact, I would argue that America needs more innovation &amp;ndash; especially in manufacturing and engineering &amp;ndash; that will tangibly improve the standard of living.) Breads produced with some of the new artisan methods today are actually really good &amp;ndash; in ways that their predecessors simply were not. Just because something has been around for thousands of years doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean there aren&amp;rsquo;t many new discoveries to be had. Hell, it wasn&amp;rsquo;t until a couple of decades ago that people picked up on the fact that you &lt;em>don&amp;rsquo;t&lt;/em> have to knead the dough to make great bread. Sometimes little things like this go undiscovered because no one bothered to look.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Only very recently in history has certain technology become available to us that has allowed us to exert super precise control over the baking environment (e.g. ambient temperatures, steam, etc.) and ingredients (e.g. varieties of grain, grinds, flour blends, strains of yeast). Bread keeps getting better and better because some bakers continue to tinker endlessly with these variables. New scientific analysis could herald a &amp;ldquo;golden age of fermentation.&amp;rdquo; Sure, not everyone cares about these things. For most people, bread is bread.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As a baker, you should remove ego from your &lt;em>mise en place&lt;/em>, rethink your take on baking, and do some researching and discovering for new techniques and skills. There&amp;rsquo;s always room for improvement. And maybe, just maybe, you could find some new excitement, or get your mind blown, and impart that joy and passion through your baking. Every person that eats your bakes deserves that.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I haven&amp;rsquo;t been baking my whole life. My mom never baked bread, and I didn&amp;rsquo;t eat much bread growing up. I actually loathed baking for most of my life &amp;ndash; kneading or using a dough mixer (another thing you have to wash) is absolutely tedious, and handling raw ingredients like eggs is totally disgusting. I didn&amp;rsquo;t have &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/harpys-lovesong/">my first taste of artisan sourdough bread&lt;/a> until 2014. In fact, I didn&amp;rsquo;t discover breadmaking until ~2019, well after the &amp;ldquo;tech bros&amp;rdquo; had invaded the sourdough trend and maybe even moved on, and after &lt;a href="https://www.newyorker.com/culture/culture-desk/bread-makes-a-comeback">&lt;em>The New Yorker&lt;/em> declared&lt;/a> a comeback for bread and greeted it as the giddy limit of fake trendspotting.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I was initially drawn to breadmaking because of the science behind it &amp;ndash; the microbiology and cellular gastronomy &amp;ndash; more than the intuitive part. To me, sourdough brought bread back from the dead. Now I&amp;rsquo;m more enthused about transforming different grains into good bread. It&amp;rsquo;s not about making disruptive breads, but making breads that I really like.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;Tech bros invading sourdough&amp;rdquo; is not some panic-inducing mass-epidemic of nerds suddenly swarming every supermarket by the thousands for artisan flours and baking tools. ~4 years in, I&amp;rsquo;m still the only person I know who makes bread on a regular basis. Many types of people all over the world are getting more interested in breadmaking and trying it out, but it&amp;rsquo;s still pretty rare for someone to commit to it at the same level as myself.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As a side note, I think the fact that producing some common food item at home is now seen as &amp;ldquo;novel&amp;rdquo; speaks volumes about how removed we postmodern humans are from our food. Tovala and DoorDash are good examples.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-2/20230220_191147.jpg"
alt="Joaquin Oro pan de San Joaquín"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>100% wholegrain &lt;em>pan de San Joaquín&lt;/em>, gleaming in the wintry sun.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>My second experiment with Joaquin Oro (shared by friends at the California Wheat Commission) pushes the limits of dough hydration. Gorging the Joaquin Oro grown in water-scarce California with an absurd amount of water is quite the California conundrum.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="total">Total&lt;/h4>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Joaquin Oro, 100% extraction (Eck Farms, CA)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>530g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>H₂O&lt;/td>
&lt;td>134%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>710g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>whole wheat poolish&lt;/td>
&lt;td>52%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>275g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>whole wheat levain&lt;/td>
&lt;td>15%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>80g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>azuki bean purée&lt;/td>
&lt;td>7.1%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>37.5g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sea salt (Gustus Vitae, CA)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1.4%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>7.5g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>olive oil (Awake - Brightland, CA)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5.7%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>30g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>tallow (home-rendered), softened&lt;/td>
&lt;td>7.1%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>37.5g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>I used two leavens at different hydration levels in this dough.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="yeast-water-poolish">Yeast water poolish&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>I pre-fermented ~24% of total flour in an overnight poolish, with homemade pineapple &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/yeast-water/">yeast water&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Joaquin Oro, 100% extraction (Eck Farms, CA)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>125g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>pineapple yeast water (homemade)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>120%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>150g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>You could substitute the yeast water with 1%-2% dry yeast + 120% plain H₂O.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I let the poolish ferment for 12 hours at ~70°F. When ripe, the poolish should be brimming with bubbles and double in volume.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Poolish modifies gluten, weakening it somewhat, so the dough stretches better as it ferments. For a strong-flour dough, a poolish will help bread rise taller.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="levain">Levain&lt;/h4>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Joaquin Oro, 100% extraction (Eck Farms, CA)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>40g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>H₂O&lt;/td>
&lt;td>50%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>20g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sourdough starter&lt;/td>
&lt;td>50%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>20g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>I let the levain ripen at ~75°F for 1 hour, and then retarded it in the fridge overnight.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>When ripe, my levain smelt and tasted like a tart yogurt &amp;ndash; or perhaps more like crème fraîche that made me salivate and excited to eat more.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="final-dough">Final dough&lt;/h4>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Joaquin Oro, 100% extraction (Eck Farms, CA)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>365g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>H₂O, divided&lt;/td>
&lt;td>148%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>540g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>whole wheat poolish&lt;/td>
&lt;td>75%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>275g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>whole wheat levain&lt;/td>
&lt;td>22%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>80g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>azuki bean purée&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>37.5g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sea salt (Gustus Vitae, CA)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>7g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>olive oil (Awake - Brightland, CA)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>8%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>30g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>tallow (home-rendered), softened&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>37.5g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>The process is built upon my previous &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/aquaboogie-van-wheatsworth/">wholegrain &lt;em>pan de cristal&lt;/em> loaves&lt;/a>:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Autolyse the flour at 80% hydration for 2 hours in the fridge.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Add the poolish, levain, and azuki bean purée. Mix until well incorporated.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Double hydration: Slowly drizzle in 2/3 of the remaining water, and &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zgz0oAhgwyg">Rubaud-mix&lt;/a> until thoroughly absorbed. This requires a bit of patience, so take your time. Cover the dough and let it rest for 20 minutes at room temperature.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Add the salt, and mix well.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Triple hydration: Slowly add the rest of the water, while &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zgz0oAhgwyg">Rubaud-mixing&lt;/a> until completely combined. Let the dough rest for another 20 minutes at room temperature.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Gently mix in the olive oil and softened tallow. Let the dough rest and relax for 30 minutes.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Bulk ferment the dough at ~70°F for 4 hours, performing a coil-fold every 30 minutes during the first 2.5 hours. Folding a super-high-hydration dough like this kinda feels like handling water.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Transfer the dough into a fridge and retard for 12 hours.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Take the dough out of the fridge; divide it into two or leave it whole as a large loaf. Let it rest at room temperature for 2-3 hours (no shaping necessary).&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Bake as usual: 25-30 minutes at 350°F.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>I divided the dough into two approximately equal portions, baked one in the toaster oven, and kept the other one in the fridge for another 8 hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="bake-1">Bake #1&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>The 1st piece turned out great &amp;ndash; exactly what I had expected from a hard red spring wheat.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-2/20230220_111326.jpg"
alt="Joaquin Oro pan de San Joaquín baked"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The tallow has imparted some savory aroma to the bread.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-2/20230220_104549.jpg"
alt="Joaquin Oro pan de San Joaquín baked"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>toaster oven-baked &lt;em>pan de San Joaquín&lt;/em>. home-milled 100% wholegrain Joaquin Oro flour + non-San Francisco sourdough starter + homemade pineapple yeast water poolish&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The crumb is delightfully light and airy, almost like gossamer; it&amp;rsquo;s exceptionally soft and chewy.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-2/20230220_111631.jpg"
alt="Joaquin Oro pan de San Joaquín baked"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The crust is so thin and crisp that it&amp;rsquo;s almost non-existent.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Sure, it doesn&amp;rsquo;t have Tartine bread&amp;rsquo;s shell of blistered mahogany, but the interior is so chewy and preternaturally moist that it shimmers in the light.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-2/20230220_111504.jpg"
alt="Joaquin Oro pan de San Joaquín baked"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The delicate, nutty flavor of whole wheat Joaquin Oro shines through &amp;ndash; perceptibly different from Turkey Red to me.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I like this &lt;em>pan de San Joaquín&lt;/em> toasted; topped with &lt;em>salsa roja&lt;/em>, crunchy lettuce and thinly-sliced Vadalia onions (for a pleasing texture contrast), and crumbled &lt;em>queso fresco&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-2/20230220_112031.jpg"
alt="Joaquin Oro pan de San Joaquín baked"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>toaster oven-baked &lt;em>pan de San Joaquín&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;h4 id="bake-2">Bake #2&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>Instead of baking the 20-hour retarded piece in an oven, I brought it to a Mardi Gras BBQ thingy and cooked it in a cast-iron skillet on a charcoal-fired grill. Who says February is a month to simply be endured &amp;ndash; a penance to pay before late winter yields to spring?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Magic happens when meat meets charcoal smoke. What about breads?&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-2/20230220_190227.jpg"
alt="Joaquin Oro pan de San Joaquín baked"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>I tossed a handful of black walnut and pistachio shells into the grill towards the end. Nut shells release a great smokey aroma when they burn, due to the oils that naturally occur in the shells. They burn pretty easily and add a marvelous boost of smoky sweetness to food.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-2/20230220_190435.jpg"
alt="Joaquin Oro pan de San Joaquín baked"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>20-hour retarded 100% wholegrain &lt;em>pan de San Joaquín&lt;/em>. cooked on a charcoal-fired BBQ grill. smoked with black walnut and pistachio shells.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>This grilled &lt;em>pan de San Joaquín&lt;/em> delivers an exciting punch of smoky char in first bite.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The crumb is wonderfully airy and springy like the first one, and the subtle tang of the bread becomes more pronounced with each successive bite, finishing on a question mark instead of an exclamation point.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-2/20230220_191648.jpg"
alt="Joaquin Oro pan de San Joaquín baked"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Custardy and glistening.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I like this smoky &lt;em>pan de San Joaquín&lt;/em> fresh or toasted; perfect for dunking in garlicky cioppino.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-2/20230220_190539.jpg"
alt="Joaquin Oro pan de San Joaquín baked"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>smoked wholegrain &lt;em>pan de San Joaquín&lt;/em>, glistening on a BBQ grill in the sun.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>TL;DR&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Joaquin Oro is an excellent bread wheat for sourdough baking.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>You don&amp;rsquo;t need a San Francisco sourdough starter to make excellent bread.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>&lt;em>This is part 2 of my &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/california-grain-adventure/">California Grain Adventure&lt;/a>. If you enjoyed it, why not check out my other &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/archives/">breadstories&lt;/a> or spread the word?&lt;/em>&lt;/p></content></item><item><title>California Dreamin' #1: Joaquin Oro</title><link>/posts/california-dreamin-1/</link><pubDate>Mon, 13 Feb 2023 02:15:44 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/california-dreamin-1/</guid><description>[California Grain Adventure #1] Strawberry rosehip &lt;em>pain d&amp;rsquo;épices au levain&lt;/em>, made with freshly milled Joaquin Oro grown in the San Joaquin Valley of California. Gently sweetened with a homemade spice-infused syrup.</description><content>&lt;p>&lt;em>This is part 1 of my &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/california-grain-adventure/">California Grain Adventure&lt;/a>.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I first got to know California as an undergraduate student on the East Coast, during academic conference trips to the sun-baked campus of the University of California, Davis (UC Davis) where I met my besties; and later as a part-time L-Alien (or Angeleno).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If the rest of America were academic articles, then California would be something like blog posts. The former are often plodding and obtuse, and frequently more concerned with avoiding errors than trying to communicate incisive ideas; the latter may be fuzzy, loosely-defined, or outright mistaken, but tolerable so long as they introduce fresh ideas.&lt;/p>
&lt;div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
&lt;iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/wq-S8CIU7VA" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video">&lt;/iframe>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>To say California is unlike the other 49 states in the US is an understatement. Not just that the Golden State has waaaay more sculpted, sun-bronzed, rich techies with a higher propensity to consume expensive artisan coffees. To this day, I still feel a distinct difference whenever I go to California or do business in the state.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For example:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>California&amp;rsquo;s economy is massive, but two industries dominate popular imagination and exert impact on a global scale: Tech in Silicon Valley/San Francisco, and entertainment in Hollywood/Los Angeles. Far less than 1% of all new startups and movie stars actually break out every year, but those who do achieve exponential success.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>In a country of immigrants, California seems to be &lt;em>the&lt;/em> state of immigrants. Not just that California&amp;rsquo;s population is the most diverse in the US, with no race or ethnic group constituting a majority. About a century and a half ago, California was flooded with serial migrants who came from the East Coast and were willing to decamp once more in search of gold or fame. Does this make California the most American of all states?&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Thinking back, I realize California embodies more of the &amp;ldquo;top line&amp;rdquo; mindset while New York is dominated by the &amp;ldquo;bottom line&amp;rdquo; mindset. In California, venture capital and movie studios try to pick a few outsized winners that makes their losses irrelevant. New York is complicated, obviously finance-driven, and exemplified by the prevalence of insurance in particular.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Insurers apply the law of large numbers to predict the probability and cost of &amp;ldquo;tail events.&amp;rdquo; The insurance business is about collecting a steady stream of revenue (on the liabilities side) without making catastrophic mistakes that wipe out the assets, i.e. picking up nickels in front of a steamroller. Naturally, insurers spend 80% of their time on &amp;ldquo;the losers.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In contrast, venture capital focuses on maximizing &lt;a href="https://medium.com/@quantvc/power-laws-in-venture-capital-why-the-long-tail-matters-22e057c6fa34">fat tails&lt;/a>, by &amp;ldquo;investing in maybe 7 or 8 promising companies from which you think you can get a 10x return&amp;rdquo; (Peter Thiel). Successful VCs spend 80% of their time on a tiny handful of big &amp;ldquo;winners.&amp;rdquo; Their return curves look more like highly skewed power law distributions (&amp;ldquo;the 80/20 curve&amp;rdquo;).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Finding home runs and avoiding catastrophes are very different activities and require different mindsets. Maybe that distinction partly explains why California and New York feel so vastly different.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Subsequently, winner-take-all effects and blockbuster dynamics have continually permeated the Golden State.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="california-optimism">California optimism&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>For nearly a century, California offered ordinary people better lives than they could lead perhaps anywhere else in the world. Sunsets in California are always so singularly beautiful on TV and in movies. No doubt, California is the land of sunny optimism; the Conference Board&amp;rsquo;s California Consumer Confidence Index averaged 113 in the 5 years before Covid, hotter than national baselines.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>I think people who grew up in California have more tolerance for apocalyptic notions. However, mixed up with this tolerance for apocalyptic notions in which the world is going to end dramatically is this belief that the world can’t help but get better and better. It’s really hard for me to believe that everything doesn’t improve, because thinking like that was just so much a part of being in California.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Joan Didion&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Optimism is a valuable form of human capital. Just look at &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->Japan vs. China&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>People want optimism. They don&amp;rsquo;t want to learn that it&amp;rsquo;s almost impossible to make it, that few do, and that even worse it takes years of hard work and dedication and a ton of luck &amp;ndash; and that today even the most talented don&amp;rsquo;t always succeed.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Every now and then, you detect a faint strain of melancholy, a sort of &lt;em>ennui&lt;/em>, that permeates Californians' creative output. You hear it in &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=uU0BOyQRjWM">The Beach Boys&lt;/a> (a rock band instrumental in popularizing a particular California culture of sun, sand, and surfing in the 1960s) and &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=QOOiY0bgrlU">Red Hot Chili Peppers&lt;/a>; see it in &lt;a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt3783958/">&lt;em>La La Land&lt;/em>&lt;/a> (where Los Angeles in the winter and summer scenes looks identical) and &lt;a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt4687880/">&lt;em>Goliath&lt;/em>&lt;/a>; &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/california-books">read it&lt;/a> in Philip K. Dick, Joan Didion, Jack Kerouac, John Steinbeck, etc. What do people have to worry about in the land of sunny beaches and beautiful weather?&lt;/p>
&lt;div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
&lt;iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/w_zz0JNhujE" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video">&lt;/iframe>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>As a matter of fact, California&amp;rsquo;s net migration has been negative in the last two decades, losing about a million more people than it gained through migration. Instead of moving from Oklahoma to California (à la John Steinbeck&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em>The Grapes of Wrath&lt;/em>), traffic has been reversing the other way. This trend has become even more evident in the last few months; when rent is $4k-$5k, making six figures in an industry experiencing mass layoffs is not a comfy situation.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>While tech and entertainment are monstrous sectors with far-reaching impact (even reindeer herders in the arctic forests of Karelia watch Hollywood movies and use Instagram, for instance), altogether they generate only ~10% of the state&amp;rsquo;s GDP (though one could argue for a bigger share under different definitions). The two big blockbuster industries may not have that big of an impact on the daily lives of most Californians.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Maybe that helps to explain a bit of the melancholy in the culture &amp;ndash; a golden age for all has &lt;a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20220517070336/https://isteve.blogspot.com/2009/06/benjamin-schwarzs-laments-end-of.html">passed&lt;/a> and those who were once ahead have tried to lock in their gains.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>You can check out any time you like&lt;/p>
&lt;p>But you can never leave&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&amp;ndash; Eagles, &amp;ldquo;Hotel California&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Maybe the California Dream is more elusive than we believe.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Maybe nothing exemplifies this better than wheat, whose golden age ended ~130 years ago.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="california-wheat">California wheat&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Today, California is a leading producer in &lt;a href="https://asmith.ucdavis.edu/news/we-grow-that">pretty much everything&lt;/a> except for, curiously, the major grains like wheat and corn.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Wheat was brought to California from Mexico; it was first grown by padres during the &amp;ldquo;mission period&amp;rdquo; in the 18th century and later by settlers.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>California became the nation&amp;rsquo;s second largest wheat producer (after Minnesota) in the second half of the 19th century, thanks to the Gold Rush and the associated increased demand for food. Wheat production in California hit a peak in the late 1880s; soon thereafter, it declined as rapidly as it rose, mainly due to soil exhaustion and low farm prices.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>With increasing acreage of irrigated land and better transportation to markets in the eastern US, California began a massive agricultural shift &amp;ndash; diversifying away from grains and towards the more lucrative &lt;a href="https://www.ams.usda.gov/services/grants/scbgp/specialty-crop">specialty crops&lt;/a> like vegetables, fruit, and nuts.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>By 1913, California&amp;rsquo;s wheat-planting area had shrunk to 380,000 acres (from some 3 million acres just three decades earlier). Throughout the 20th century, the wheat acreage fluctuated widely, ranging from a minimum of 270,000 acres in 1966 to a maximum of 1,345,000 acres in 1981. In recent years, the wheat acreage has stabilized somewhat, averaging about half a million acres since the year &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->2000&lt;sup id="fnref:2">&lt;a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->; wheat production averages ~40 million bushels annually. (In comparison, Kansas plants ~7 million acres of wheat annually on average and produces over 300 million bushels.)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Wheat didn&amp;rsquo;t disappear from California; it still is an important rotational crop for many growers, and California&amp;rsquo;s wheat industry is a bit unique.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-1/california-wheat-map.png"
alt="California wheat-producing areas"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>California wheat-producing areas&lt;/p>&lt;p>Source: &lt;a href="http://californiawheat.org/california-wheat/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">California Wheat Commission&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>While Kansas specializes in &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/hard-red-winter-wheat/">hard red winter wheat&lt;/a>, North Dakota in &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/hard-red-spring-wheat/">hard red spring wheat&lt;/a> and durum, and Washington in &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/soft-white-winter-wheat/">soft white wheat&lt;/a>, California grows all of the US wheat classes except soft red, i.e. you can find hard red, hard white, soft white, and durum wheat grown across the state. The two main types of wheat grown in California are &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->hard red winter wheat&lt;sup id="fnref:3">&lt;a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">3&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --> and durum wheat, mainly used for milling.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Given the vast expanse of the state, most of California&amp;rsquo;s wheat production is localized in specific regions. The majority of wheat is grown in the San Joaquin Valley, where Fresno, Kern, Kings and Tulare counties dominate production. (Yolo County in the Sacramento Valley completes the list of the top 5 counties with the largest area harvested.) Eternal sunshine, coupled with a warm and dry climate, produces big plump kernels with low moisture content, consistent kernel size distribution, and high test weight.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-1/TR-vs-Joaquin-Oro.jpg"
alt="Tukey Red (Kansas) vs. Joaquin Oro (California)"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Kernel size comparison: Tukey Red (grown in Kansas) vs. Joaquin Oro (grown in California)&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>It&amp;rsquo;s no surprise that California&amp;rsquo;s wheat yield has been among the highest in the nation. California also happens to have the largest milling capacity in the US, thanks to having the most mills in one state.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Artisan bakers and organic farmers are leading the revival of whole grains and local grain economies. While wheat breeding programs often focus on refined flour markets, UC Davis recently started an organic wheat breeding program to focus on unique wheat varieties for artisan breadmaking and local grain markets. The awesome team (a shout-out to Claudia Carter and Teng Vang) at the California Wheat Commission &amp;ndash; the coolest wheat commission in the country, by the way &amp;ndash; sent me a few of such varieties to experiment with.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-1/cwc-wheats.jpg"
alt="California wheat: Joaquin Oro (HRSW), Sonora Blanca (SWWW), and Desert Gold (durum)."/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>California wheat: Joaquin Oro (HRSW), Sonora Blanca (SWWW), and Desert Gold (durum).&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>The first California-grown wheat that I experimented with was &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/breadford-von-regrainton">Glenn&lt;/a>, a modern hard red spring variety grown by Kenter Canyon Farms along the south side of the Santa Clara River.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This week, I got to play with &lt;strong>Joaquin Oro&lt;/strong>, another California-grown hard red spring wheat. It&amp;rsquo;s a modern cultivar selected from the OG Joaquin variety for morphological, agronomic and quality traits; bred and developed by WestBred to thrive in the wheat-growing areas of the San Joaquin Valley; and released by UC Davis in 2011. Protein content ~14%.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Historically, Joaquin Oro has been the highest-quality bread wheat variety grown in California. It&amp;rsquo;s also one of the highest-rated whole wheat flours by the California Wheat Commission test lab.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-1/joaquin-oro-berries.jpg"
alt="Joaquin Oro wheat berries, from California."/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Plump and vibrant Joaquin Oro wheat berries, grown in the San Joaquin Valley of California.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>This Joaquin Oro was grown by Jon Eck of Eck Farms in Merced County, California. Jon&amp;rsquo;s parents are lifelong farmers, growing primarily almonds and sweet potatoes &amp;ndash; two of the traditional cash crops in the San Joaquin Valley. Jon decided to try growing grain as a rotational crop at the suggestion of a baker friend. John tells of his experience and learning on the excellent &lt;a href="https://www.thesourdoughpodcast.com/episodes/2021/9/27/jon-eck-california-wheat-grower">Sourdough Podcast&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The first thing I noticed with Joaquin Oro was how easily the wheat berries milled to a fine texture on the first run, on a countertop electric WonderMill set to Bread Flour.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The wholegrain Joaquin Oro flour has a finer, smoother texture (and visibly smaller bran particle size) than freshly milled Turkey Red &amp;ndash; and almost boasts of a Unifine feel.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Maybe this is what a French miller would classify as &lt;em>blé tendre&lt;/em> (&amp;ldquo;soft wheat&amp;rdquo;), a bread wheat that shows little &lt;em>résistance&lt;/em> to milling (i.e. requires less force than &lt;em>le blé résistant&lt;/em> to shear the starchy endosperm of the grain).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Despite being categorized as a &amp;ldquo;hard&amp;rdquo; wheat in the US commercial wheat classification system due to its high protein content, Joaquin Oro actually mills quite easily &amp;ndash; like a low-protein wheat. I am amazed.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-1/joaquin-oro-milled.jpg"
alt="Freshly milled Joaquin Oro"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Freshly milled Joaquin Oro.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>My first experiment with Joaquin Oro is inspired by my &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/dulce-locura/">&lt;em>pain d&amp;rsquo;épices au levain&lt;/em>&lt;/a>, in light of the upcoming Valentine&amp;rsquo;s Day. It incorporates strawberries, rosehips, spiced syrup, and dark chocolate. 🌹🍓🍫&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I decided to bolt the freshly milled Joaquin Oro to remove some of the coarsest bran bits and midds, to lighten the load a bit on the gluten in the flour, which shall hold together a boatloat of add-ins. The extracted bits will be used, instead of flour, to dust the workbench and the dough later, so nothing is wasted.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Joaquin Oro, 88% extraction (Eck Farms, CA)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>400g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>strawberry rosehip purée (homemade)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>36%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>145g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;em>sirop d&amp;rsquo;épices&lt;/em> (55% in autolyse + 25% in &lt;em>bassinage&lt;/em>)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>80%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>320g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Joaquin Oro whole wheat levain&lt;/td>
&lt;td>40%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>160g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sea salt (Gustus Vitae, CA)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>8g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>olive oil (Awake - Brightland, CA)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>20g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>dark chocolate, chopped (74% Guatamala Lachuá - Mutari Chocolate, CA)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>20%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>80g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Did you know California is America&amp;rsquo;s largest producer of strawberries? And wild rose (&lt;em>Rosa californica&lt;/em>) grows throughout the coast and foothills of the state?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you are a forager and happen to have collected some wild rosehips and strawberries from Nature&amp;rsquo;s grocery store, you are a hell of &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->a lucky bastard&lt;sup id="fnref:4">&lt;a href="#fn:4" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">4&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->. Otherwise, grab some dried rosehips and good-tasting strawberries from somewhere.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>To make the strawberry rosehip purée 🍓🌹 at home: Boil the rosehips in just enough water until soft; push the pulp through a fine-mesh sieve to remove the seeds and irritating hairs; run the resulting pulp and juice with strawberries (fresh or frozen) in a blender into a smooth purée. Use as much rosehips or strawberries as you like.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Pro tip: Make your own &lt;em>sirop d&amp;rsquo;épices&lt;/em> (spiced syrup), too.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Then proceed as documented in the &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/dulce-locura/">&lt;em>pain d&amp;rsquo;épices au levain&lt;/em>&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>TL;DR, give the dough an overnight bulk fermentation in the fridge, after a series of coil-folds in the initial 4.5 hours; shape; final proof 3-4 hours; bake off.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-1/20230212_195754.jpg"
alt="Pain d&amp;#39;épices au levain, made with freshly milled Joaquin Oro."/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>Pain d&amp;rsquo;épices au levain&lt;/em>, made with freshly milled Joaquin Oro.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Joaquin Oro delivers a nuanced flavor profile. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem to have as much bitterness as many red wheat varieties; instead it&amp;rsquo;s imbued with nutty, malty notes. This pairs exquisitely with the rich fruitiness and faint tartness of rosehips and strawberries. Homemade &lt;em>sirop d&amp;rsquo;épices&lt;/em> cranks up the sweetness and adds a wonderful touch of spice notes.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Joaquin Oro also performs excellently in baking. The dough felt quite elastic during the initial fermentation, and became very pillowy and delicate after overnight cold retard; it showed a pretty decent rise in the oven.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-1/20230212_195908.jpg"
alt="Pain d&amp;#39;épices au levain, made with freshly milled Joaquin Oro."/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>Pain d&amp;rsquo;épices au levain&lt;/em>, made with freshly milled Joaquin Oro.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The crust of this bread turned out crisp and thin; the crumb tender and springy.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The chewy texture reminded me of a traditional stottie cake in Northumberland, northern England. Irresistible.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Go make this bread and share with your sweetheart, Valentine&amp;rsquo;s Day or not, and enjoy it with a good slather of chocolate cheese fudge &amp;ndash; while everyone is getting worked up about Joe Rogan again or Kansas City Chiefs winning another Super Bowl after being underdogs for half a century.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>&lt;em>This is part 1 of my &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/california-grain-adventure/">California Grain Adventure&lt;/a>. If you enjoyed it, why not check out more &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/archives/">breadstories&lt;/a> or spread the word?&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>The current &lt;a href="https://www3.nhk.or.jp/nhkworld/en/news/20230131_12/">unemployment rate in Japan&lt;/a> is 2.5%. Japanese millennials get to enjoy a fairly tight labor market, which means they ought to choose which company to work for. But few of them have an interest in switching employers or jobs, because they rank perfect stability above high wages. This risk aversion is usually attributed to lingering fears of the previous downturn. The country that lost a decade &amp;ndash; or two &amp;ndash; has fostered a generation of youth highly averse to risk-taking. Optimism is &lt;a href="https://archive.is/vqIPO">in very short supply&lt;/a> in Japan. On the other hand, surveys show the Chinese are much more optimistic about the future. Take Cixin Liu&amp;rsquo;s sci-fi series, &lt;em>Three Body Problem&lt;/em>, for an example. The novel is driven by a fundamentally optimistic vision: It asks why aliens should not be 10,000x more advanced than humans, instead of portraying a typical alien civilization that&amp;rsquo;s only 50%-70% more advanced than humans.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>USDA/NASS historical data.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:3" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>Most varieties grown in California are genetically spring wheat (planted in the spring and harvested in late summer or early fall). However, since the majority of California wheat-growing regions have very mild winters, spring wheat can be sown in the fall or early winter like winter wheat. Wheat market classifications are typically based on the season of production rather than growth habit, which is why California&amp;rsquo;s red wheat production is referred to as hard red winter wheat.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:4" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>According to an academic study titled &amp;ldquo;Morphological and Chemical Characteristics of Fruits of Selected Rosa sp,&amp;rdquo; &lt;em>R. californica&lt;/em> contains 863 mg vitamin C per 100 g of fruit. 4 other species were studied: &lt;em>R. villosa&lt;/em> (706 mg), &lt;em>R. rugosa&lt;/em> (974 mg), &lt;em>R. spinosissima&lt;/em> (845 mg), and &lt;em>R. × damascena&lt;/em> (932 mg). Google claims oranges provide 53 mg vitamin C per 100 g. On average, rosehips tend to have at least an order of magnitude more vitamin C then oranges; &lt;em>R. californica&lt;/em> has about 16x more.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:4" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/section></content></item><item><title>Breadford von Regrainton</title><link>/posts/breadford-von-regrainton/</link><pubDate>Mon, 09 Dec 2019 16:41:45 -0800</pubDate><guid>/posts/breadford-von-regrainton/</guid><description>A hearty re-grained bread, made with spent grains and Glenn whole wheat flour.</description><content>&lt;p>I picked up a bag of Glenn wheat berries from Kenter Canyon Farms at the Atwater Village Farmers' Market in Los Angeles. It cost ~$2/lb, not cheap but not ridiculously overpriced either. The Glenn wheat was grown on Kenter Canyon Farms in Ventura County, along the south side of the Santa Clara River.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/files/Glenn.pdf">Glenn&lt;/a> is a modern HRSW developed by a NDSU breeding program to provide better scab resistance and higher yield. It was released by the North Dakota Agricultural Experiment Station in the spring of 2005. It has a fairly high protein content of 13%-14%. I have seen quite a few local and regional mills across the country label Glenn as a &amp;ldquo;heritage&amp;rdquo; wheat &amp;ndash; very curious.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I had long wanted to bake a &lt;em>treberbrot&lt;/em>, a hearty German bread made with the addition of spent grains from brewing beers. The spent grain adds some sweetness, texture and a lot of fiber to the bread.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/regrainton/201912082109.jpg"
alt="Breadford von Regrainton"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Breadford von Regrainton, a hearty re-grained bread that re-uses a lot of brewer&amp;rsquo;s spent grains.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>First, I milled the Glenn wheat berries, and &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/joeliath/">sifted&lt;/a> half into a 80% extraction flour, leaving the other half wholegrain (100% extraction).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Next, I built a levain with&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>sifted-out wheat bran; and&lt;/li>
&lt;li>a smooth purée of spent grains (from brewing Berliner Weiss) and &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fvtmBuTyu1c">boiled jackfruit seeds&lt;/a>.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>To make the dough stronger, I decided to use a 2-dough lamination method.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Dough #1:&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>80% extraction wheat flour (Glenn - Kenter Canyon Farms, CA)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>h&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->2&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->o&lt;/td>
&lt;td>85%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>bran levain&lt;/td>
&lt;td>40%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>This will be the stronger half of the dough that lifts the whole bread. You can totally swap water for beer here.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Dough #2:&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>whole wheat flour (Glenn - Kenter Canyon Farms, CA)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>h&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->2&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->o&lt;/td>
&lt;td>70%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>spent grain purée&lt;/td>
&lt;td>60%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>bran levain&lt;/td>
&lt;td>20%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>toasted flaxseeds&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>I mixed 1 part spent grains to 1 part water, and puréed the mixture in a blender. Then I autolyzed the flour, along with the flaxseeds, in this thick grainy smoothie diluted with water.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>With all of the wheat bran added back to the dough through the levain, this bread retains its whole-wheat integrity.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Add-ins:&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>spent grains&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sunflower seeds&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>roasted papaya seeds, ground&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>raisins&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.taste.com.au/quick-easy/articles/want-use-up-seeds/f45slcr4">Roasted papaya seeds&lt;/a> have a dark cocoa brown color and smell deeply aromatic. They taste like peppercorns.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I did 4 folds with each dough during the first 3 hours. Then I combined both doughs by gently stretching them out into big rectangles and placing dough #2 on top of dough #1. I sprinkled the add-ins during lamination.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The dough was bulk-fermented for 5 hours in total at room temperature, shaped into a taut boule (dusted with grated coconut), and then retarded at 40°F for 10 hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Next day, I let the dough warm up for a few hours until ~100% risen. I baked it on a shitty pizza pan in my ghetto toaster oven.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/regrainton/201912082113.jpg"
alt="Breadford von Regrainton"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>It grew so big during baking that it nearly filled up every cubic inch of the toaster oven!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The crust came out crispy and thin. The crumb is so freakin' airy.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/regrainton/201912082135.jpg"
alt="Breadford von Regrainton"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The taste is deeply flavorful with a mild tang and a subtle sweetness from spent grains and raisins.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/regrainton/201912091249.jpg"
alt="Breadford von Regrainton"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Superbly delightful.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>NGL, it tasted even better the next day.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/regrainton/201912091255.jpg"
alt="Breadford von Regrainton"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>A later variation:&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/regrainton/201912301643.jpg"
alt="Breadford von Regrainton"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Breadford von Regrainton v2.0, an incredibly flavorful re-grained bread that rises from dead spent grains.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Can&amp;rsquo;t believe it&amp;rsquo;s already December. Where did the year go?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In review, 2019 has been my Year of Fermentation. I read Sandor Katz&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em>The Art of Fermentation&lt;/em> and René Redzepi&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em>The Noma Guide to Fermentation.&lt;/em> I got into sourdough breadmaking (and bread chemistry) seriously for the firs time. I experimented audaciously with literally anything I could get my hands on: vegetables, beans, grains, milk, fish&amp;hellip; From lactic acid bacteria (LAB), I ventured into fungi &amp;ndash; koji (&lt;em>Aspergillus oryzae&lt;/em>) and tempeh (&lt;em>Rhizopus oligosporus&lt;/em>). It&amp;rsquo;s been a very memorable year and an unbelievably fulfilling one.&lt;/p></content></item></channel></rss>