<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>pan de cristal on HERESY LEVAIN</title><link>/tags/pan-de-cristal/</link><description>Latest experiments in pan de cristal from HERESY LEVAIN</description><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2023 HERESY LEVAIN 🍞 CC BY-NC-SA 4.0</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 02 Apr 2023 22:55:42 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/pan-de-cristal/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>levure de bière #1.2: California ale yeast</title><link>/posts/byb-1-2/</link><pubDate>Sun, 02 Apr 2023 22:55:42 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/byb-1-2/</guid><description>A high-hydration whole-wheat bread leavened exclusively with WLP001 California ale yeast &lt;em>barm&lt;/em>. The crumb turned out much lighter and airier than the poolish version, more like sourdough breads. The taste was similarly clean and wheat-emphatic, without the slightest tang of acidity, reminiscent of Triscuit Original whole wheat crackers or Anchor Brewing&amp;rsquo;s Summer Wheat.</description><content>&lt;p>&lt;em>Beer = liquid bread. Want to stay updated on my &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/craft-beer-yeast">craft beer yeast bread-plays&lt;/a>? Subscribe to the &lt;a href="https://tinyletter.com/breadbuster">newsletter&lt;/a>!&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>As mentioned in my &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-1/">last breadpost&lt;/a>, &lt;strong>barm&lt;/strong> is simply a thick yeasty froth or scum formed on the top of a fermenting liquid, like beer or wine.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The original method of making yeast bread in Britain was a by-product of ale-making. When traditional ale is made, a yeasty froth appears on top of the fermenting liquid (the wort). This used to be scooped off, washed, and then added to bread dough as a leaven. Bread made this way is sweet, light, and fluffy, and the leavening yeast used to be called &amp;ldquo;barm&amp;rdquo;. Its unpredictability gives us the word &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->&amp;ldquo;barmy&amp;rdquo;&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Barm first appeared in written records before the 12th century. It came from Middle English &lt;em>berme&lt;/em>, which came from Old English &lt;em>beorma&lt;/em>; it&amp;rsquo;s akin to Middle Low German &lt;em>berm&lt;/em> (yeast), Latin &lt;em>fermentum&lt;/em> (yeast), &lt;em>fervēre&lt;/em> (to boil), and Old Irish &lt;em>berbaid&lt;/em> (he boils). The word has been in use more loosely since the 13th century in reference to the foam or &amp;ldquo;head&amp;rdquo; of a pint of beer.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Using barm to leaven bread appears to be an ancient method developed by Gaelic peoples in the mists of time (no wonder Scottish bakers were the last in Britain to ditch baking with barm), and was quite different from that used in Europe, i.e. leaven bread with a sourdough or leaven (called &amp;ldquo;levain&amp;rdquo; in French). When the Romans first conquered Gaul (modern-day France), they were astonished by the light sweet bread made by the Celtic inhabitants. Barm bread survived with the Celtic peoples in Britain, Scotland and Éire, but was not common in Europe &amp;ndash; in fact, it was even condemned during the Enlightenment as &amp;ldquo;unwholesome&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-2/20230402_111008.jpg"
alt="WLP001 whole-wheat barm bread"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>whole-wheat barm bread, leavened exclusively with White Labs' WLP001 California ale yeast.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>In England, noblemen&amp;rsquo;s bread &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Manchet">manchet&lt;/a>&amp;rdquo; was always made with barm, whereas the commoners' bread &amp;ldquo;maslin&amp;rdquo; was usually leavened with a sourdough. Barm bread survived until World War II &amp;ndash; and even later in northern England largely as &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Barm_cake">barm cakes&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In the 19th century, the barm process was refined and industrialized; &amp;ldquo;yeast&amp;rdquo; began to be manufactured on a large scale, and used worldwide as &lt;em>the&lt;/em> method to leaven bread.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Curiously, the old method of making a sponge, i.e. a thick batter of flour and water with the barm, was still used with the new industrially-produced yeast, and was re-introduced to Europe from Vienna where the first yeast factories were established. Viennese bakers who emigrated to France around 1840 initiated the production of Viennese breads and other luxury bakery products in Paris using such technique. This became popular in France as a &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href="https://bakerpedia.com/processes/poolish/">poolish&lt;/a>&amp;rdquo; (an Old English version of &amp;ldquo;Polish&amp;rdquo;, as this method was first developed in Poland); bakers switched from using combinations of yeast and sourdough (&lt;em>sur levain&lt;/em>) to yeast alone for making crusty bread such as baguettes at bakeshops.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-2/20230402_111040.jpg"
alt="WLP001 whole-wheat barm bread"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>whole-wheat barm bread, leavened exclusively with White Labs' WLP001 California ale yeast.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>At the beginning of the 20th century, barm was no longer universally held in high esteem.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A 1902 domestic science book, &lt;em>&lt;a href="https://chestofbooks.com/food/science/Handbook-Of-Household-Science/Yeasts-Part-2.html">Hand-Book Of Household Science&lt;/a>&lt;/em> by Juniata L. Shepperd, considered acidity in barm bread a defect:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>There is another variety of patent yeast known as &amp;ldquo;flour barm.&amp;rdquo; This is extensively used in Scotland. The chief peculiarity of bread from this is its decidedly acid taste, thought to be due principally to lactic acid. Much salt is used in making this bread, and it has not the flavor of what, in some other countries, is called the best bread.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>A decade later, James Grant wrote in &lt;em>&lt;a href="https://archive.org/stream/grantsbreadchem00granrich/grantsbreadchem00granrich_djvu.txt">The Chemistry Of Breadmaking&lt;/a>&lt;/em> (1912):&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Bread prepared by the aid of barms is generally of poor volume and colour, rather liable to be holey, with dull bloom and texture somewhat variable, but the flavour as a rule is good. Barms are suitable for working strong, harsh flours by long, slow processes.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Hmmmm. The artisanal, open-crumb, slightly tangy, naturally leavened bread &lt;em>en vogue&lt;/em> all over the US today was not beloved in Europe a century ago.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-2/20230402_111157.jpg"
alt="WLP001 whole-wheat barm bread"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>whole-wheat barm bread, leavened exclusively with White Labs' WLP001 California ale yeast.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Interestingly, the old barm method survived the invasions of Romans, Saxons and Normans. Which makes sense because it produced the sweetest, lightest bread in the right hands. Like other ancient breads, barm bread was highly digestible and nutritious because the ferments were never single strains like they are today, and included lactic acid bacteria which also gave the bread a marvelous flavor.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Barm bread has recently enjoyed some revival because it&amp;rsquo;s a characteristic ancient bread of Britain, a true heritage. Today some British bakers still add ale to bread dough to give it the ancient flavor, which sets the British bread culture apart from others. It&amp;rsquo;s a shame that the process was &lt;a href="https://sourdough.com/blog/enzyme-bread-tech">bastardized by industrialization&lt;/a> to produce modern unwholesome yeast breads.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="how-to-get-barm">how to get barm&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>So how do you get barm? There are several ways.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Option #1: You can always ask your neighborhood &lt;strong>craft brewers&lt;/strong> or &lt;strong>home-brewing friends&lt;/strong> for some spare barm. It can be an interesting educational process, as apparently an ancient law declares that the brewer is bound to accede to your request. Your first task, though, is to convince the brewer that you mean to create bread with the barm and not a rival beer!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Option #2: &lt;a href="http://www.danlepard.com/">Dan Lepard&lt;/a>, an Australian-British baking celeb, has a famous &lt;strong>shortcut for a quick barm&lt;/strong> in his book &lt;em>&lt;a href="https://www.thehandmadeloaf.com/">The Handmade Loaf&lt;/a>&lt;/em>, intended for people who don&amp;rsquo;t have malts and hops lying around the kitchen.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Basically, it involves gelatinizing 1 part of white flour with 5 parts of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brewing#Bottle_conditioning">bottle-conditioned&lt;/a> ale (heated to 158°F/70°C), letting it cool off to room temperature, and then inoculating with 0.4 part of leaven or yeast culture.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I haven&amp;rsquo;t tried his recipe, because there seems to be some weird contradiction. I bet a lot of people assume that the live yeast in the beer has something to do with making the bread rise. Nope, it doesn&amp;rsquo;t. Heating a fresh bottle of beer to &amp;gt;104°F (40°C) kills the live yeast in it, long before it reaches 158°F/70° where you&amp;rsquo;re supposed to whisk in the flour.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>You use bottle-conditioned beer for the same reasons you use freshly milled organic flour &amp;ndash; a bottle-conditioned beer has more flavor than one without. If you don&amp;rsquo;t understand these reasons, the recipe will still work.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I believe the purpose of heating the beer is to cook off some of the alcohol, which retards the action of yeast. Lepard was effectively using the beer as a flavoring, and then re-introducing yeasts via a leaven; however lovely the results may be, it&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em>not&lt;/em> a genuine barm bread. Lepard also says this is a perfect replica of the complex barm of the old times for the home bakers. Meh. I&amp;rsquo;m not satisfied with this method nor do I care for shortcuts. I want to make a barm from scratch.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Which leads me to option #3: &lt;strong>DIY from scratch&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-2/20230402_110840.jpg"
alt="WLP001 whole-wheat barm bread"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>whole-wheat barm bread, leavened exclusively with White Labs' WLP001 California ale yeast.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;h4 id="historic-barm">historic barm&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>William Jago&amp;rsquo;s 1911 classic, &lt;em>&lt;a href="https://archive.org/details/technologyofbrea00jagorich">The Technology of Bread-Making&lt;/a>&lt;/em>, gives three variations:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>compound barm (malt and hops);&lt;/li>
&lt;li>virgin barm (spontaneous fermentation with flour and water only); and&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Parisian barm (malt and flour).&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;Compound barm&amp;rdquo; is essentially unboiled wort, made with malt, hops and water, and then inoculated with an existing culture.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;Virgin barm&amp;rdquo;, containing only water and flour, differs from a sourdough starter in that it&amp;rsquo;s made with boiling water, i.e. the flour is gelatinized. Virgin barm should be left alone to ferment spontaneously, but even in 1911 bakers added &amp;ldquo;store&amp;rdquo; (an existing culture) to speed up the process.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;Parisian barm&amp;rdquo; includes malt again, together with scalded flour, but no hops. Virgin barm differed from Parisian only in being self-fermented.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;m interested in creating a barm that will increase the biodiversity of yeasts and maximize the aroma/flavor of the bread.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-2/20230402_112234.jpg"
alt="WLP001 whole-wheat barm bread"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>whole-wheat barm bread, leavened exclusively with White Labs' WLP001 California ale yeast.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;h4 id="19th-century-parisian-barm">19th-century Parisian barm&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>John Kirkland, in his 1927 book &lt;em>The Baker’s ABC&lt;/em>, wrote about barm:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;hellip;since bakers, or others for them, began to make a fermenting agent for themselves, about 1800, that has been described as bar, while the word yeast has been retained for the brewery product, as well for the more modern article sold in more solid form. Barm contains yeast cells, generally as a variety of species, as well as some of the liquor in which the yeast has been grown. Barms are of many kinds and all degrees of “strength”; that is, a particular lot may contain few or many yeast cells and much or little of the acids, peptones, alcohols, &amp;amp;c., which have resulted from earlier fermentations. Probably the earliest barm made, as distinguished from leavens &amp;ndash; was that from malt and hops as the baker in the first instance merely copied the brewer or the distiller.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This barm was known as compound or comp or patents. Some makers used a quantity of flour in the mixture, some did not. In Scotland, where barms were first made and where they continue in favour, the compound barm was displaced by a kind made with &lt;strong>scalded flour and malt&lt;/strong>. To this was given the name of &amp;ldquo;Parisian&amp;rdquo;, although no precise evidence to show that it was copied from the practice of Parisian bakers. Another sort which may contain a little malt , but may be all scalded and raw flour, is called “Virgin barm”.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>If there is such a thing as a &amp;ldquo;Parisian barm&amp;rdquo;, then I first learned this &amp;ldquo;scalded flour and malt&amp;rdquo; method from &lt;em>Russian&lt;/em> bakers, not Parisians.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Parisian barm was introduced from Paris to Scotland in the late 19th century. It&amp;rsquo;s essentially a scientific modification of the techniques of ancient Egypt and modern France.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>William Jago&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em>&lt;a href="https://archive.org/details/technologyofbrea00jagorich">The Technology of Bread-Making&lt;/a>&lt;/em>, mentioned above, does offer a recipe for &amp;ldquo;Parisian barm&amp;rdquo;, supplied by a Mr. J. Meikle, who was apparently a well-known baker and bread writer familiar with the Scottish baking trade. Meikle&amp;rsquo;s descriptions show an evolution of baking practice beginning with, and developing away from, beer-brewing techniques.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-2/1910-Parisian-barm.png"
alt="Meikle&amp;#39;s Parisian barm recipe"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Mr. J. Meikle&amp;rsquo;s Parisian barm recipe&lt;/p>&lt;p>Source: &lt;a href="https://archive.org/details/technologyofbrea00jagorich/page/238/mode/2up" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">The Technology of Bread-Making (1911) by William Jago&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>This is very similar to the &lt;em>opara&lt;/em> (yeasted scald-sponge) method I&amp;rsquo;ve always relied on to make complex Baltic rye breads.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>&lt;a href="https://www.gutenberg.org/files/53627/53627-h/53627-h.htm">The Bread and Biscuit Baker&amp;rsquo;s and Sugar-Boiler&amp;rsquo;s Assistant&lt;/a>&lt;/em> (1890) by Robert Wells gives a Parisian barm recipe using hops:&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-2/1890-Parisian-barm.png"
alt="Robert Wells&amp;#39; Parisian barm recipe"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Robert Wells' Parisian barm recipe&lt;/p>&lt;p>Source: &lt;a href="https://www.gutenberg.org/files/53627/53627-h/53627-h.htm" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">&lt;em>The Bread and Biscuit Baker&amp;rsquo;s and Sugar-Boiler&amp;rsquo;s Assistant&lt;/em> (1890)&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Why does Wells include hops in Parisian barm and Jago doesn&amp;rsquo;t? I speculate there might be a few reasons:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Barm made with hops is able to &amp;ldquo;overcome the power of foreign ferments longer than that made without hops, because the bitter of the hops is not suited to bacterial growth&amp;rdquo;, according to Shepperd&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em>&lt;a href="http://chestofbooks.com/food/science/Handbook-Of-Household-Science/Yeasts-Part-2.html%20">Hand-Book Of Household Science&lt;/a>&lt;/em> (1902). However, &amp;ldquo;one can use but little of a yeast made with hops without injuring the flavor of the bread, and a weak yeast acts so slowly as to cause disastrous results, it is better to make yeast oftener without hops, and use plenty of it in bread making.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Since barm without hops didn&amp;rsquo;t keep as well, maybe some bakers just continued using hops to prevent barm spoilage while others didn&amp;rsquo;t. Pasteurisation arrived in the late 1870s and fewer hops were needed as a preservative. It certainly shows that disputes over what is or isn&amp;rsquo;t a poolish, a sourdough, a barm, etc. predate internet bread-geek forums.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Hopstalgia, i.e. carryover from tradition or reverence for the old days, when barm used to be made from malt and hops as the baker copied the brewer/distiller. As mentioned above, one of the reasons that bakers moved away from beer yeast in the first place was because the hops made it unpleasantly bitter. The older generations who had grown up eating hoppy barm bread most likely developed an acquired taste and nostalgia for it. Compound barm (malt and hops), for example, was considered by many of the older bakers to be &amp;ldquo;&lt;em>the&lt;/em> barm for flavour in bread&amp;rdquo;, according to Jago&amp;rsquo;s 1911 &lt;a href="https://archive.org/details/technologyofbrea00jagorich">book&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;h4 id="my-21-century-barm">my 21-century barm&lt;/h4>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Turkey Red wheat flour, 100% extraction&lt;/td>
&lt;td>90.6%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>125g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->diastatic barley malt&lt;sup id="fnref:2">&lt;a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->(sun-dried Chevallier)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>9.4%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>13g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>hot water (180-185°F)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>181%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>250g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>liquid yeast (WLP001 - White Labs, CA)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1.8%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2.5g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Step 1: gelatinize the flour&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Put the whole wheat flour in a bowl; add hot water in 2-3 increments, stirring constantly.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Step 2: saccharify the scald&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Add the malt at the end (to prevent malt enzymes from being destroyed) and mix again. Cover and hold at 150-155°F for 6 hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The scald becomes sweet/saccharified, since the diastatic malt contains amylase that converts starch into simple sugars. Saccharifying literally means &amp;ldquo;to convert into sugar.&amp;rdquo; Or, in more scientific words, saccharifying is the process of converting a sugar derivative or complex carbohydrate into a simple soluble fermentable sugar by hydrolysis.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-2/20230331_082732.jpg"
alt="The barm, after 6 hours of saccharification and before fermentation."/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>The barm, after 6 hours of saccharification and before fermentation.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Why scald the flour first?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In order for the scald (&amp;ldquo;mash&amp;rdquo; in brewing) to be successful, we need heat and water to gelatinize the starch granules, essentially opening up their inner depths to expose the starch chains.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>However, heat and water alone don&amp;rsquo;t break down starch into simpler sugars &amp;ndash; not on their own, anyway. In order to do that, we need enzymes. Malted barley, particularly pale (diastatic) malt, is packed with natural enzymes that can break down these long starch chains into much shorter fermentables that can be metabolized by yeasts.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>To the plant, starch serves as a reserve of energy that the embryo plant can use when it starts to germinate. In late summer to early fall, the seed falls off the stalk. If it immediately starts to grow after hitting the ground, it would grow too much before winter and not survive the cold. This also means that the seed comes off the stalk in a storage form known as starch, which is very hardy and doesn&amp;rsquo;t degrade nearly as quickly as sugar. So the seed will just sit in a field until the time is right for it to start growing. Then, when that time comes, many complex biological and chemical changes start to kick in, converting the starches into readily available sugars for the growing plant. Enzymes in the seed will activate, start degrading the cell walls, and break down the long chemical chains of starch into the short chains of maltose (a simple sugar). The growing plant can utilize this maltose until its stalk has poked above the surface of the ground, starting to produce its own sugar through photosynthesis.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Malting mimics this natural process, so we can activate those enzymes that will convert the starch into sweet, tasty maltose that yeast loves to eat.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Certain enzymes are produced during the malting process; the two major ones are α-amylase and β-amylase.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A-amylase basically liquefies starch and turns it into a carbohydrate stew. It also chops up the starch at 1-4 links. Every time it cuts the chain, a reducing end and a non-reducing end are formed on the chain. Β-amylase can work only on the non-reducing end. It will lop off 2 molecules of the carb stew and blend with one water molecule, producing maltose. B-amylase also can lop off 3 molecules of starch, mixing with one water molecule producing maltriose. Maltriose is the sugar that yeast use during lagering phase.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>After α-amylase and β-amylase can reduce the chain no further, α-limit and β-limit dextrins are formed. β-limit dextrin can chop the starch down to a 1-6 link. Once, the enzyme gets to a branch, they&amp;rsquo;re done. Enzymes such as dextrinase and maltase are de-branching enzymes, typically destroyed during the kilning of modern malts. There are a limited amount left in minimally modified pilsner malt. De-branching enzymes help α-amylase and β-amylase produce many non-reducing ends. The more the non-reducing ends, the more β-amylase has to work with &amp;ndash; and faster.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Brewers typically boil their wort after mashing to sanitize it and to boost hop utilization (among other things), which denatures all the enzymes. Since I don&amp;rsquo;t nuke the saccarified scald like brewers (leaving it a &amp;ldquo;raw ale&amp;rdquo;), I get to keep the valuable secondary enzymes in play for more starch conversion to take place.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Secondary enzymes, compared to their amylase cousins, aren&amp;rsquo;t very active under thermophilic conditions. However, they do become more active during mesophilic fermentation and give us a &amp;ldquo;secondary conversion&amp;rdquo; in beerspeak. This secondary conversion actually increases the amount of fermentable sugars by as much as 15%, which is a huge boost to plant efficiency.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Like a beer mash, there are many kinds of sugars in saccharified scald:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>fructose, glucose, and sucrose: ~30%&lt;/li>
&lt;li>maltose: ~45%, which, like trehalose, is made from 2 glucose molecules, but with a different bond between them.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>maltotriose: ~20%, which is 3 glucose molecules, with the exact same bond between them as in maltose.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>The increased concentration of sugar could lead to caramelization, which makes the beer less fermentable (among other things). Since I&amp;rsquo;m not after alcohol production, this is not a problem. In fact, the extra sugar might even enhance the flavor profile.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Again, I used &lt;a href="https://www.whitelabs.com/yeast-single?id=101&amp;amp;type=YEAST">WLP001 California ale yeast&lt;/a> in this barm. WLP001 has an attenuation rate of 73%-85%.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-1/20230321_143837.jpg"
alt="WLP001 California Ale Yeast"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>A homebrew pouch of WLP001 California Ale Yeast, from White Labs.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>In brewing, attenuation refers to the conversion of sugars into alcohol and carbon dioxide by the fermentation process; the greater the attenuation, the more sugar has been converted into alcohol. A more attenuated beer is drier and more alcoholic than a less attenuated beer made from the same wort. High-attenuating yeast indicates that the particular strain ferments more of the sugars available in a wort relative to other yeast strains. This results in a drier finish in the finished beer.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A 50% attenuation rate means that 50% of the sugars have been converted into alcohol and CO₂ by yeast. A 100% attenuation means all of the sugars have been consumed by yeast.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Beer fermented with normal brewer&amp;rsquo;s yeast will never have 100% attenuation. A 100% fermentable sugar solution will only attenuate to the level that the yeast can tolerate the alcohol or lack of nutrients; whereas in a wort that contains 30% non-fermentables; a yeast that can go to 80% attenuation will stop at 70% attenuation because there is nothing left to ferment. This is important because it can help predict the final gravity and alcohol content of a beer. A yeast with low attenuation will leave a beer with more sugar and more body than a yeast with high attenuation. This can also be very helpful when selecting a yeast strain for a recipe.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>You should let the yeast know what it is to ferment. It&amp;rsquo;s actually a living thing.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&amp;ndash; Yves Benoit, head brewmaster at Brouwerij De Brabandere&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Fermentability of a wort is based on much more than temperature of the mash. The composition of the grist (e.g. total diastatic power) can have a much bigger effect than temperature alone. Unfermentable sugars have the greatest impact on your attenuation than any other factors. You can turn a dry stout into a sweet one by adding just lactose. Usually, the more the non-fermentables in the mash (crystal malt, partially kilned malt, etc), the lower the attenuation. Manipulating temperatures is a tool for overcoming the limitations of the grist.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In &lt;a href="https://books.google.com/books/about/Brewing_with_Wheat.html?id=jc2QAwAAQBAJ">&lt;em>Brewing with Wheat&lt;/em>&lt;/a>, Stan Hieronymus mentions how brewers change their mash profile for each batch of grain, knowing that while it all may be wheat, the wheat from one particular farmer is different than the wheat from another. This is exactly like baking bread with different wheat varieties from different farms!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Step 3: inoculate with yeast&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Let the scald cool off gradually to ~75°F. Add &lt;strong>2.5g of WLP001&lt;/strong> (~100 drops); stir vigorously and mix thoroughly.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Ferment at &lt;strong>70°F-73°F&lt;/strong> (high end of WLP001&amp;rsquo;s recommended temperature range of 64°F-73°F) to bring out the yeast&amp;rsquo;s character. After &lt;strong>12 hours&lt;/strong>, the barm doubled in volume and started to fall and pull away from the sides of the bowl. It was ready.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-2/20230331_204415.jpg"
alt="WLP001 barm, after 12 hours of fermentation"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>WLP001 barm, after 12 hours of fermentation at 70°F-73°F.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Given the liquid yeast contains about 2.5 billion cells per mL and 2.5g has roughly 6.25 billion cells, the inoculation rate in the barm is about 16 million cells per gram.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Despite lower inoculation, I could tell the yeast was having much more fun in this saccharified scald loaded with nutrients than in the previous &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-1/">straight poolish&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Mr. J. Meikle was certainly spot on:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Parisian barm while fermenting behaves like a thin ferment made with distillers' yeast, sugar and a handful of flour, only the bells and gas bubbles are larger and brighter.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;h4 id="final-dough">final dough&lt;/h4>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Turkey Red wheat, 100% extraction&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>375g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>water&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>375g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>barm&lt;/td>
&lt;td>104%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>390.5g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sea salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>7.5g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>olive oil&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>20g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>The mixing process is the same as the &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-1/">straight poolish verison&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I let the dough ferment at &lt;strong>70-73°F&lt;/strong> for &lt;strong>8 hours&lt;/strong>, followed by another &lt;strong>14 hours&lt;/strong> at &lt;strong>60-63°F&lt;/strong>. The dough had nearly doubled in volume after 22 hours. That&amp;rsquo;s when I baked it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I just tipped the dough out onto a baking sheet; no shaping or slashing. I baked it at 350°F for 25 minutes.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-2/20230402_094542.jpg"
alt="WLP001 whole-wheat barm bread"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>WLP001 whole-wheat barm bread, baked.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Again, the bread smelled like buttery biscuits and toasted crackers during baking.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The bread felt much lighter in my hand than the &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-1/">poolish version&lt;/a>. The crumb turned out more like my usual sourdough &lt;em>pan de cristal&lt;/em> &amp;ndash; airy and open, with bigger, more irregular holes.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-2/20230402_095350.jpg"
alt="WLP001 whole-wheat barm bread"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>WLP001 whole-wheat barm bread, sliced.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Mr. J. Meikle was spot on again:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>The barm has the strength, without the &amp;ldquo;rampness,&amp;rdquo; of compound, and the mildness without the weakness of Virgin.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>The bread had a springy and chewy texture, and a nutty, slightly salty flavor that&amp;rsquo;s noticeably more complex than the &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-1/">straight poolish verison&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I tasted the same &lt;strong>clean, robust wheat flavor&lt;/strong> without a trace of tanginess, like eating Triscuit® Original whole wheat crackers (America&amp;rsquo;s favorite shredded wheat snacks), the opposite of sourdough breads.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I don&amp;rsquo;t think I&amp;rsquo;ve ever tasted a bread with such a dominating wheat flavor.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-2/20230402_110354.jpg"
alt="WLP001 whole-wheat barm bread"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>WLP001 whole-wheat barm bread, sliced.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Just like how WLP001 accentuates hop flavors in beers, I think the yeast accentuates wheat flavors in breads. The flavor of Turkey Red seems 5x-10x amplified in this WLP001 bread than in any of my sourdough breads.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The closest beer comparison I could think of is probably &lt;a href="https://www.anchorbrewing.com/blog/american-wheat-beers-heritage-and-history/">&lt;strong>American wheat beer&lt;/strong>&lt;/a>, something like &lt;a href="https://www.anchorbrewing.com/beer/summer_beer">Anchor Brewing&amp;rsquo;s Summer® Wheat&lt;/a>, the first American wheat beer brewed since Prohibition and released in the summer of 1984: medium-bodied, wheat-emphatic, clean and balanced; a smooth, crisp, and slightly bready mouthfeel.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-2/20230402_110548.jpg"
alt="WLP001 whole-wheat barm bread"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>WLP001 whole-wheat barm bread, sliced.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Adding 2% salt to the final dough was a good idea &amp;ndash; the extra salt opened up the taste buds.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The bread tasted great with a sharp cheddar and good mustard like Alstertor beer mustard, which IMO is the Charlize Theron of mustards: smooth, but not without an edge.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>There&amp;rsquo;s nothing like sitting down at the end of a day with a glass of your own fresh ale and a loaf of fresh homemade bread. The only thing to add might be homemade cheese or prosciutto!&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-2/20230402_112353.jpg"
alt="WLP001 whole-wheat barm bread"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>WLP001 whole-wheat barm bread, sliced.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>&lt;code>Note&lt;/code>:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I don&amp;rsquo;t think retarding beer yeast doughs at lower temperatures, as you would with sourdough breads, contributes much in terms of flavor or texture. It only makes scheduling easier.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Special thanks to White Labs, especially Erik Fowler in San Diego, CA and Bert Sheffield in Asheville, NC.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>How is this barm related to the adjective &lt;em>barmy&lt;/em>? When it first emerged in the language in the early 1500s, the adjective &lt;em>barmy&lt;/em> meant precisely that: full of froth, foam, or barm. But before long a figurative meaning had developed, so that by the early 17th century people who were just as excitably lively or as bubbly as a pint of beer&amp;rsquo;s foaming barm were being described in equivalent terms. From there, the more recent use of barmy to mean &amp;ldquo;unhinged&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;deranged&amp;rdquo;, or generally &amp;ldquo;not thinking straight&amp;rdquo; emerged &amp;ndash; the latter of which, at least, could always be blamed on consuming a bit too much barm.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>I malted a batch of heritage Chevallier barley at home myself and sun-dried them before grinding into a flour, to ensure the malt remained as pale as possible.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/section></content></item><item><title>levure de bière #1.1: California ale yeast</title><link>/posts/byb-1-1/</link><pubDate>Thu, 30 Mar 2023 19:55:42 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/byb-1-1/</guid><description>A very high hydration &lt;em>pan de cristal&lt;/em> leavened exclusively with White Labs' WLP001 California Ale Yeast. A 48-hour whole-wheat &lt;em>poolish&lt;/em> was used in the final dough, which went through another 24 hours of fermentation. This bread had a very clean wheaty character and neutral aroma &amp;amp; flavor &amp;ndash; a perfect baseline for my upcoming experiments.</description><content>&lt;p>Happy Thirsty Thursday! I will be going on a &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/craft-beer-yeast">bread-baking adventure with craft beer yeasts&lt;/a> over the next few weeks/months. (You can stay updated on my experiments through a &lt;a href="https://tinyletter.com/breadbuster">newsletter&lt;/a>.)&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Just a glass of beer, a piece of dry bread &amp;ndash; and in one moment the brain is stronger, the mind is clearer and the will is firm!&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Fyodor Dostoyevsky, &lt;em>Crime and Punishment&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;m not a big drinker. I enjoy &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->craft beers and spirits&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --> every now and then, but I &lt;a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/02/07/dining/drinks/wine-millennials.html">don&amp;rsquo;t drink often enough&lt;/a> to even think about brewing them at home. While many people were driven to drink more during the Covid lockdown, I went the other way. I do have tanks of Russian &lt;em>&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kvass">kvass&lt;/a>&lt;/em> and Romanian &lt;em>&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bor%C8%99_(bran)">borș&lt;/a>&lt;/em> brewing in house all the time.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For some time now, I&amp;rsquo;ve been fascinated by the centuries-old relationship between beer and bread &amp;ndash; it&amp;rsquo;s absolutely gripping, and the more I learn, the more gripping it gets. Today, for instance, I was learning about the old, strong relationship in Europe between bakers and brewers. Ages ago, breweries and bakeries lived side-by-side harmoniously. Brewers happily went about their noble work &amp;ndash; mashing, sparging, and fermenting. One blessed by-product of the brewing process was a foam that formed frothily on top of the fermenting liquor. The dusty baker next door would welcome consignments of this malty foam &amp;ndash; known as &amp;ldquo;barm&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; and utilize the natural yeasts in it to leaven his dough. It made perfect sense, and as historical records have shown, ale and bread were the staple diet in the old days.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;As we brew, so we bake.&amp;rdquo; - an old adage&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Previously, I had thought that before commercial yeasts were developed, all bakers used sourdough to make their bread. Nope! Up until the 19th century, village bakers either depended on village brewers for their yeast (&amp;ldquo;barm&amp;rdquo;) in order to leaven their bread, or they literally brewed up their own &amp;ldquo;barm&amp;rdquo; for baking.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-1/20230330_132800.jpg"
alt="pan de cristal with WLP001 yeast poolish"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>pan de cristal&lt;/em> with WLP001 yeast poolish&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Andreas Krennmair&amp;rsquo;s book, &lt;em>Vienna Lager&lt;/em>, has an interesting take on how the relationship between brewers and bakers changed in the 19th century when brewers switched from ales to lagers:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Industrialisation had a profound effect on other breweries in and around Vienna: because of the quick success of Anton Dreher&amp;rsquo;s beer and brewing methods, all other breweries switched to bottom fermentation just within a few years. This rapid change had an unintended implication for another craft that had previously been reliant on breweries: baking. In the centuries before, bakers had been reliant on fresh beer yeast, which brewers always had available in abundance. When brewers started switching to bottom fermentation, the yeast given to bakers also changed its properties: &amp;hellip;the yeast suddenly contained hop bittering compounds and hop resins that turned these yeast darker and bitter-tasting, making it unsuitable for baking. &amp;hellip;so the Viennese baker&amp;rsquo;s guild announced in 1845 that they would award a prize to the person who could produce a leaven that was suitable to replace the much sought-after top-fermenting beer yeast.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Coincidentally, the 1800s were the golden age of the hop industry; hop acreage reached its peak in 1878.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>By the end of the century, yeast specifically cultivated for breadmaking had become commercially available in blocks, and later in dry, granulated forms. Slowly &amp;ndash; and sadly &amp;ndash; the close bond between breweries and bakeries faded away.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-1/20230330_132906.jpg"
alt="pan de cristal with WLP001 yeast poolish"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>pan de cristal&lt;/em> with WLP001 yeast poolish&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.toastale.com/">Toast Ale&lt;/a>, a London-based craft brewery, makes beer from waste bread. In the &lt;a href="https://www.willhawkes.net/blog/2023/3/20/march2023newsletter">March 2023 edition&lt;/a> of Will Hawkes&amp;rsquo;s newsletter &lt;em>London Beer City&lt;/em>, Toast&amp;rsquo;s founder talked about the company&amp;rsquo;s funding (some from Heineken), marketing strategy (&amp;ldquo;buyer personas&amp;rdquo;) and business model:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>While the impact of bread on the flavour of the beer is limited (typically, bread replaces 25 percent of the malted barley), I’ve always thought the implied message of Toast, that you can make great beer out of old bread, was a difficult one for the brewing industry. What happened to the ‘finest malt and hops’?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&amp;hellip;those who drink Toast’s beers are at ease with the idea of surplus bread being used to make it. In common with most people, I suspect, they don’t really care about malt and hops. They just want something nice to drink.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>The idea of making bread with breweries' by-products has intrigued me for a long time. I&amp;rsquo;ve baked and enjoyed &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/breadford-von-regrainton/">breads infused with brewer&amp;rsquo;s spent grains&lt;/a>, as well as ones leavened with &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/yeast-water/">wild yeasts captured from fruits&lt;/a>. But how about baking bread with brewer&amp;rsquo;s yeast?&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="bakers-yeast-vs-brewers-yeast">baker&amp;rsquo;s yeast vs. brewer&amp;rsquo;s yeast&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>In the mid-19th century, when bakers ditched breweries' barms &lt;em>en masse&lt;/em> and started looking for new sources of yeast, for a few years a new trade of &amp;ldquo;barm-brewers&amp;rdquo; sprang up who specialized in propagating yeast for bakers.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-1/1860-barm.png"
alt="a paper given to the Royal Scottish Society of Arts in 1860"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>A paper given to the Royal Scottish Society of Arts in 1860, describing the various modes of leavening bread.&lt;/p>&lt;p>Source: &lt;a href="https://books.google.ie/books?id=ueM0AAAAMAAJ&amp;amp;pg=PA235" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">Transactions of the Royal Scottish Society of Arts, Volume 5&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>This in turn was displaced by the introduction of compressed blocks of yeast known as &amp;ldquo;fresh yeast&amp;rdquo; today. As &lt;a href="https://dafteejit.com/2020/03/the-history-of-modern-baking-yeast/">Andreas Krennmair writes&lt;/a>, the process of making compressed yeast was invented by a brewer, who used brewer&amp;rsquo;s yeast. This has inspired Lars Marius Garshol to ponder, &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href="https://www.garshol.priv.no/blog/411.html">Does bread yeast exist?&lt;/a>&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In fact, most forms of brewer&amp;rsquo;s yeast and baker&amp;rsquo;s yeast currently on the market all come from the same species of yeast called &lt;em>&lt;code>Saccharomyces cerevisiae&lt;/code>&lt;/em>. The yeast derives its name from the Latinized Greek meaning &amp;ldquo;sugar fungus&amp;rdquo;, because it converts sugars into CO₂ and ethanol during aerobic fermentation &amp;ndash; which makes beer alcoholic and inflates a lump of dough into a fluffy loaf of bread.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>All &lt;em>S. cerevisiae&lt;/em> strains share a common natural history. Some, through artificial selection, are better adapted for certain processes, while others have more than one use.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Before the arrival of industrial yeasts, baker&amp;rsquo;s yeast used to be much more diverse, but what we call &amp;ldquo;bread yeast&amp;rdquo; today is simply particular strains of &lt;em>S. cerevisiae&lt;/em> monocultures that have been selected by yeast manufacturers primarily for their ability to rapidly metabolize wheat starch, produce large quantities of CO₂ while fermenting the dough, and make bread light. The quick-rising yeast now available in stores is an improved strain developed using modern genetic methods. Professional bakers use commercial yeasts that produce a fast and strong rise and a clean taste (less flavor and depth) in the finished loaf of bread.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Modern bread yeast manufacturers narrowly focus their yeast development on two issues:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>gas production.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>speed of rising.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>Variants are produced with these goals in mind, to suit different technical requirements of the baking industry.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For example, instant yeasts (aka. fast-rising, rapid-rise, quick-rise, and bread machine yeast), are manufactured to dissolve more quickly than active dry yeasts; they can be mixed directly into flour and other dry ingredients, without the need to &amp;ldquo;proof&amp;rdquo; the yeast in warm water first. Lesaffre, one of the world&amp;rsquo;s largest yeast producers, has formulated &lt;a href="https://lesaffre.ae/en/our-products/professional-products/saf-instant-gold-500g/">Saf-Instant® Gold dry yeast&lt;/a> specifically for sweet doughs (with &amp;gt;=5% sugar/weight of flour) like Hawaiian rolls and &lt;em>panettoni&lt;/em>, as well as &lt;a href="https://lesaffrebaking.com/product/saf-instant-red/">Saf-Instant® Red&lt;/a> that excels in sugarless doughs.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-1/20230330_132311.jpg"
alt="pan de cristal with WLP001 yeast poolish"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>pan de cristal&lt;/em> with WLP001 yeast poolish&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>A number of people claim that baker&amp;rsquo;s yeast brews good beers (since most bread yeasts are &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->phenolic&lt;sup id="fnref:2">&lt;a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A 2018 paper published in the &lt;em>Journal of the Institute of Brewing&lt;/em>, titled &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1002/jib.503">evaluation of &lt;em>Saccharomyces cerevisiae&lt;/em> strains isolated from non-brewing environments in beer production&lt;/a>&amp;rdquo;, tested 12 novel &lt;em>S. cerevisiae&lt;/em> strains isolated from grape must, bakery, wine, and apple stillage in the production of beer. The researchers found that&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>The most suitable strain for beer production, based on fermentative ability and volatile profile, was a baker&amp;rsquo;s yeast&amp;hellip;. Interestingly, some esters were above the sensory threshold.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Another example: The Finnish farmhouse ale &lt;em>sahti&lt;/em> is fermented with baking strains, rather than &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->brewing strains&lt;sup id="fnref:3">&lt;a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">3&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->, of &lt;em>S. cerevisiae&lt;/em>. A 2020 paper, titled &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1002/jib.608">sourdough derived strains of &lt;em>Saccharomyces cerevisiae&lt;/em> and their potential for farmhouse ale brewing&lt;/a>&amp;rdquo;, concludes&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>sourdough isolates of &lt;em>S. cerevisiae&lt;/em> are suitable for &lt;em>sahti&lt;/em> production, but could also be applied to other beer styles as a way to differentiate products.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>However, I haven&amp;rsquo;t heard the other way round, i.e. brewer&amp;rsquo;s yeast makes good bread.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Manufacturers of beer and wine yeasts all describe multiple varieties of yeasts, each producing a slightly differently flavored product. In the case of wine, some yeasts are tied to specific cultivars of grapes. The importance of yeast strains in producing different varieties of beer is illustrated by White Labs' assortment of beer yeasts:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.whitelabs.com/yeast-single?id=169&amp;amp;type=YEAST">WLP566&lt;/a> Belgian Saison II Ale Yeast: &amp;ldquo;a moderate phenol producer with clove-like flavor and aromatic notes present in the finished beer&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.whitelabs.com/yeast-single?id=174&amp;amp;type=YEAST">WLP590&lt;/a> French Saison Ale Yeast: &amp;ldquo;produces flavors and aromas of pear, apple and cracked pepper&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.whitelabs.com/yeast-single?id=267&amp;amp;type=YEAST">WLP077&lt;/a> Tropicale Yeast Blend: &amp;ldquo;a balance of tropical flavors and aromas, such as passionfruit, grapefruit, and mango&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Wouldn&amp;rsquo;t it be lovely to be able to make a bread that produces a &amp;ldquo;clove-like&amp;rdquo; aroma and flavor when it&amp;rsquo;s toasted? Or a loaf with a slight hint of smoky tomato that might make it ideal for &lt;em>bruschetta&lt;/em>?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>What if breads in a bakery might, for the first time, be differentiated by subtleties of aroma? Imagine a boule with a hint of plum and thyme under an overtone of apple &amp;ndash; next to a boule made with the same recipe but a different yeast and thus yielding a hazelnut aroma.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-1/20230330_132413.jpg"
alt="pan de cristal with WLP001 yeast poolish"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>pan de cristal&lt;/em> with WLP001 yeast poolish&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Beer is, after all, liquid bread. Like brewers, I&amp;rsquo;m constantly on the lookout for special flours and yeasts to make that unique, satisfying loaf.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I keep thinking about experimenting with combinations of different yeast strains in a dough to see how they might enhance a bread&amp;rsquo;s flavor and aroma. The yeast monoculture practice be damned.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>What does it take to make a good loaf of bread with brewer&amp;rsquo;s yeast? Is it possible in the modern era? I want to find out.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>There is a vast catalog of yeast strains used by brewers and wine makers that I want to experiment with, and it&amp;rsquo;s never been easier to collaborate with people over the internet.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="california-ale-yeast">California ale yeast&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>The first craft beer yeast I decided to experiment is &lt;a href="https://www.whitelabs.com/yeast-single?id=101&amp;amp;type=YEAST">WLP001&lt;/a> California Ale Yeast®, which is White Labs' OG yeast strain, first produced in 1995.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-1/20230321_143837.jpg"
alt="WLP001 California Ale Yeast"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>A homebrew pouch of WLP001 California Ale Yeast, from White Labs.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>This &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->&amp;ldquo;Chico&amp;rdquo;&lt;sup id="fnref:4">&lt;a href="#fn:4" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">4&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --> strain (named after the &lt;em>châteaux&lt;/em> of Sierra Nevada Brewing Company) is probably the most widely used beer strain on the West Coast, if not in the entire country. It&amp;rsquo;s a driving force behind IPA 2.0, aka. the yeast that launched 1,000 beers.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>WLP001 is famous for its clean flavors and hardy fermentations and is known for its use in hoppy beers. It accentuates hop flavors and aromas and attenuates well, even for high-gravity beers. A higher-than-average attenuation leads to drier beers as well as medium flocculation to leave a clean and crisp beer. With a healthy pitch and yeast, WLP001 is also quick at reabsorbing diacetyl.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>The yeast has a very beery aroma right out of the package.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A &amp;ldquo;clean-fermenting&amp;rdquo; strain with a neutral flavor and aroma profile (instead of a &amp;ldquo;fruity&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;estery&amp;rdquo; strain) would be an interesting baseline for comparisons with other yeasts.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Another reason for starting with WLP001 is that a clean fermenter showcases a brewer&amp;rsquo;s recipe formulation (e.g. choice of malts, hops, brewing temperatures, and fermentation temperatures) more than other strains. Since I&amp;rsquo;ve made &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/pan-de-cristal/">these kinds of breads&lt;/a> many times, it&amp;rsquo;d be fairly easy for me to tell how the ale yeast differs from sourdough.&lt;/p>
&lt;h5 id="wlp001-poolish">WLP001 poolish&lt;/h5>
&lt;p>Many researchers have reported that the dough fermentation by &lt;em>S. cerevisiae&lt;/em> promoted an increase in the contents of phenolic compounds due to the structural breakdown of cell wall, leading to the liberation of phenolic compounds and/or metabolization of phenolics by yeast.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>On the other hand, thermal processing may have negative effects on these bioactive compounds, likely caused by oxidation, isomerization, and interaction with wheat proteins.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>One technical challenge of baking with yeast is making the yeast&amp;rsquo;s distinct character shine through.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Maybe a poolish (a preferment with 25% of total flour) with super low yeast inoculation would help? A poolish particularly elevates the bread&amp;rsquo;s creamy, slightly nutty character and crisp, thin crust. (Yum.)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>So I made a loose preferment that used roughly equal parts of whole wheat flour and water by weight with a tiny bit of California ale yeast &amp;ndash; and no salt.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Turkey Red wheat flour, 100% extraction&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>125g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>water&lt;/td>
&lt;td>120%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>150g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>ale yeast (WLP001 - White Labs, CA)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2.5g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>I mixed the whole wheat flour and water together in a &lt;strong>shallow, wide-open bowl&lt;/strong>. I prefer it to tall, narrow fermenters because high hydrostatic pressure and CO₂ levels tend to inhibit ester formation.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-1/20230326_145734.jpg"
alt="WLP001 yeast poolish, before fermentation"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>WLP001 yeast poolish, before fermentation.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>I added ~100 drops of WLP001, which totaled ~2.5g. I whipped it vigorously into the mixture.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>White Labs' homebrew yeasts typically have a concentration of &amp;gt;=100 billion cells per 40 mL, i.e. 2.5 billion cells per mL. Assume 2.5g of the liquid yeast contains roughly 6.25 billion cells, the inoculation rate in the poolish is about 22-23 million cells per gram.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>These [West Coast] yeasts have a potential ester profile. If you play with fermentation temperature, you can really influence the character of the beer.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Richard Norgrove, Bear Republic Brewing Company (Healdsburg, California)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>WLP001 has a fermentation temperature range of 64°F-73°F. I loosely covered up the poolish (leaving an air gap) and let it ferment at the high side of the recommended temperatures (&lt;strong>70°F-73°F&lt;/strong>), in order to bring out the yeast&amp;rsquo;s character. I checked on it every few hours and gave it a stir to aerate the mixture.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-1/20230326_145753.jpg"
alt="WLP001 yeast poolish, before fermentation"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>WLP001 yeast poolish, before fermentation.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>I provided WLP001 all the time it needed to propagate, and let the poolish tell me when it was done. It ended up going for &lt;strong>48 hours&lt;/strong>. This was to ensure vigorous and complete fermentation before the poolish was mixed into the final dough.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-1/20230328_153644.jpg"
alt="WLP001 yeast poolish, after 48 hours of fermentation"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>WLP001 yeast poolish, after 48 hours of fermentation.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Clean strains usually ferment more slowly than fruitier strains and flocculate at a medium rate, remaining in suspension long enough to condition the beer properly.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>When ripe, the poolish doubled in volume. It was brimming with almost uniform micro-bubbles, instead of the bigger, more irregular bubbles you get with sourdough or bread yeast.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-1/20230328_153717.jpg"
alt="WLP001 yeast poolish, after 48 hours of fermentation"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>WLP001 yeast poolish, after 48 hours of fermentation.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Upon initial mixing, the mixture had a mild toasty wheat aroma from freshly milled Turkey Red wheat. The toasty wheat aroma was replaced by a slight yeasty twang after 12 hours, so I assume that&amp;rsquo;s when the yeast started working. After 48 hours, the yeasty aroma was completely gone. The smell was very clean &amp;ndash; maybe with a hint of fresh beer.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-1/20230328_153656.jpg"
alt="WLP001 yeast poolish, after 48 hours of fermentation"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>WLP001 yeast poolish, after 48 hours of fermentation.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>A quick search on home-brewing forums show that &lt;a href="https://www.homebrewtalk.com/threads/wlp001-peach-flavor.211921/">peach esters&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://www.homebrewtalk.com/threads/wlp001-flocculation-and-clearing.242072/">slow flocculation&lt;/a> seem to be the two major complaints people have with WLP001. Neither is a problem for my bread.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="final-dough">final dough&lt;/h4>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Turkey Red wheat, 80% extraction&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>375g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>water&lt;/td>
&lt;td>105%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>395g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>WLP001 poolish&lt;/td>
&lt;td>74%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>277.5g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sea salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>4g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>olive oil&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>20g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>I decided &lt;em>not&lt;/em> to use a levain (sourdough), in order to have a more clean aroma/flavor profile of the ale yeast. So, this dough was leavened purely by a poolish with WLP001.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-1/20230328_221805.jpg"
alt="WLP001 yeast poolish dough"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>WLP001 yeast poolish dough&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The process is similar to the &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/california-dreamin-2/">&lt;em>pan de San Joaquín&lt;/em>&lt;/a>:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Autolyze the flour at 70% hydration for 2 hours in the fridge.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Add the poolish. Mix until well incorporated.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Double hydration: Slowly drizzle in the remaining water, and &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zgz0oAhgwyg">Rubaud-mix&lt;/a> until thoroughly absorbed. Cover the dough and let it rest for 20 minutes at room temperature.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Mix in the salt. Let the dough rest for a few minutes.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Gently mix in the olive oil. Let the dough rest and relax for 30 minutes.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Bulk ferment the dough at &lt;strong>~73°F&lt;/strong> for &lt;strong>8 hours&lt;/strong>, performing a coil-fold every 45 minutes during the first 3 hours.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Transfer the dough to a cooler place &lt;strong>~65°F&lt;/strong> and leave (loosely covered) for another &lt;strong>16 hours&lt;/strong>.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Divide into 2 pieces. No shaping or slashing necessary. Bake as usual: 25-30 minutes at 350°F.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;h4 id="total">total&lt;/h4>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Turkey Red wheat, 80% extraction&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>500g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>H₂O&lt;/td>
&lt;td>109%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>545g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>liquid ale yeast (WLP001)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>0.5%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2.5g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sea salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>0.8%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>4g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>olive oil&lt;/td>
&lt;td>4%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>20g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;h4 id="tasting">tasting&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>The bread smelled like buttery biscuits and toasted crackers during baking.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-1/20230330_132240.jpg"
alt="pan de cristal with WLP001 yeast poolish"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>pan de cristal&lt;/em> with WLP001 yeast poolish, crumb shot&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The crumb had almost uniform micro-bubbles &amp;ndash; just like the poolish &amp;ndash; rather than the bigger, irregular air holes you get with sourdough or bread yeast.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-1/20230329_233127.jpg"
alt="pan de cristal with WLP001 yeast poolish"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>It had a very clean wheat flavor &amp;ndash; something I hadn&amp;rsquo;t noticed in a sourdough bread and it really stood out to me in this bread. It reminded me of eating Triscuits, with a slight hint of dankness.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I think this clean and neutral bread would be a good baseline for my upcoming craft beer yeast experiments.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-1/20230329_233251.jpg"
alt="pan de cristal with WLP001 yeast poolish"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The crust turned a beautiful mahogany color that I hadn&amp;rsquo;t seen before with sourdough breads.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-1/20230330_133023.jpg"
alt="pan de cristal with WLP001 yeast poolish"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>pan de cristal&lt;/em> with WLP001 yeast poolish, crust shot&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Overall, I would say the yeast struggled in this dough, probably because it had no nutrients. Which gives me &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/byb-1-2/">an interesting idea&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-1/20230330_132603.jpg"
alt="pan de cristal with WLP001 yeast poolish"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>pan de cristal&lt;/em> with WLP001 yeast poolish&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>&lt;em>This is my 1st &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/craft-beer-yeast">&lt;em>pain maison à la levure de bière&lt;/em>&lt;/a>. Special thanks to White Labs, especially Erik Fowler (Head of Education &amp;amp; Craft Hospitality) in San Diego, CA and Bert Sheffield (R&amp;amp;D Chef) in Asheville, NC.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>Tom Acitelli, author and journalist who writes about wine, beer and spirits, has written some interesting books about America&amp;rsquo;s craft brewing &amp;amp; distilling revolution: &lt;em>The Audacity of Hops: The History of America&amp;rsquo;s Craft Beer Revolution&lt;/em> (2013), &lt;em>American Wine: A Coming-of-Age Story&lt;/em> (2015), and &lt;em>Whiskey Business: How Small-Batch Distillers Are Transforming American Spirits&lt;/em> (2017).&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>A phenol is a hydroxylated aromatic ring, a compound with a 6-membered carbon ring bonded directly to a hydroxyl group (-OH). These are the same class of compounds used in some antiseptics, and some consumers describe their flavor and aroma as medicinal. The health benefits of phenolic acids are primarily due to their antioxidant properties, but these acids also show anti-ulcer, anti-diabetic, anti-cancer, anti-inflammatory, anti-aging, anti-microbial, cardioprotective, hepatoprotective and neuroprotective activities.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:3" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>Ale strains of &lt;em>S. cerevisiae&lt;/em> are &amp;ldquo;top-fermenting&amp;rdquo; (I prefer &amp;ldquo;top-harvesting&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;warmish-fermenting&amp;rdquo; for clearer communication) yeasts. They are relatively hydrophobic, such that upon flocculating or clumping together, they tend to connect to the CO₂ produced and float to the surface of the fermenter contents. As a result, brewers were able to collect the yeast and create more colonies for future beers. On the other hand, lagers are made with &lt;em>S. pastorianus&lt;/em> strains, which are &amp;ldquo;bottom-fermenting&amp;rdquo; (or &amp;ldquo;bottom-harvesting&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;cold-fermenting&amp;rdquo;, to be more specific) and widely thought to have originated from a natural hybridization event that occurred between a &lt;em>S. cerevisiae&lt;/em> strain and a non-&lt;em>S. cerevisiae&lt;/em> strain, probably a &lt;em>S. bayanus&lt;/em> strain. From this perspective, ales are considered closer to the ancient beer type than lagers.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:4" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;Chico&amp;rdquo; refers to Chico, California, the first location of Sierra Nevada Brewing Company&amp;rsquo;s OG taproom, where the strain is sourced. In 1979, two home brewers established the Sierra Nevada Brewing Company to expand their beloved hobby into a business. The pair&amp;rsquo;s first beer release was the famed Pale Ale, the beer that proved beers with an aggressively hopped backbone could be successful. Although labeled as a pale ale, it was really the &amp;ldquo;OG IPA&amp;rdquo; as it highlighted hops that no other beers had done before. Sierra Nevada brewers nicknamed this strain of yeast &amp;ldquo;Chico&amp;rdquo;, after the brewery&amp;rsquo;s hometown.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:4" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/section></content></item><item><title>California Dreamin' #7: Desert Gold</title><link>/posts/california-dreamin-7/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Mar 2023 02:31:32 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/california-dreamin-7/</guid><description>[California Grain Adventure #7] &lt;em>Pane Ricco&lt;/em>, a luxuriously high-hydration bread with 100% wholegrain Desert Gold durum, sour cream, cracked black pepper, and salty addictive cheeses.</description><content>&lt;p>&lt;em>This is part 7 of my &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/california-grain-adventure/">California Grain Adventure&lt;/a>.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>The West begins where the average annual rainfall drops below twenty inches.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Bernard DeVoto&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>The Imperial Valley in southern California is often cited as a great example of modern desert agriculture.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>From what I&amp;rsquo;ve seen, the Imperial Valley is a place of jarring contrasts. Half of the valley remains in its natural state, aka. a bone-dry desert with some breathtaking sand dunes; the other half exemplifies a modern engineering marvel &amp;ndash; mile after mile of green fields lined by irrigation canals and sometimes shrouded by showers of water from sprinklers.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-7/california-imperial-valley.jpg"
alt="Map of Imperial Valley, California"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Imperial Valley is one of the oldest farming communities in the Colorado River basin. It lies in the Colorado Desert section of the Sonoran Desert, with overwhelming heat and meager average rainfall (about 3&amp;quot; or 76 mm per year). Dirt was carried here over millions of years by the Colorado River, as it carved the Grand Canyon ever deeper.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Thanks to irrigation &amp;ndash; that is, thanks to the US Bureau of Reclamation &amp;ndash; states such as California, Arizona, and Idaho became populous and wealthy; millions settled in regions where nature, left alone, would have countenanced thousands at best; great valleys and hemispherical basins metamorphosed from desert blonde to semi-tropical green.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Agriculture is the economic backbone of the Imperial Valley due to irrigation, which is supplied entirely from the Colorado River via the All-American Canal. Thousands of acres of prime farmland have transformed the desert into one of the most productive farming regions in California with an annual crop production of over $1 billion. Evidently, agriculture accounts for nearly half of all local employment.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-7/SaltonSeaArielFromSouth.jpg"
alt="Aerial view of Imperial Valley and Salton Sea"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Aerial view of the Imperial Valley and Salton Sea from the south.&lt;/p>&lt;p>Source: &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Imperial_Valley,_California#/media/File:SaltonSeaArielFromSouth.jpg" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">Samboy&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Unlike the Central Valley in the north which draws its water from rain and snow in the Sierra Mountains or pumps it from shrinking underground aquifers, the Imperial Valley has only one source of water: the Colorado River, 80 miles to the east.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The most basic principle governing water use in the western US is &amp;ldquo;first in time, first in right.&amp;rdquo; These lush fields in the Imperial Valley owe their existence to fortune-seeking land speculators and engineers who arrived early and, starting in 1901, dug the first canal to ship water here from the Colorado River. (Prior to the 20th century, this patch was mostly unsettled.) Since most of the Imperial Valley actually lies below sea level &amp;ndash; and well below the canal&amp;rsquo;s starting point on the Colorado River near Yuma, Arizona &amp;ndash; water is able to flow there by gravity alone.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Thanks to the stunning wealth that irrigation farming had produced, California came rolling out of the 1920s like Jay Gatsby in his alabaster phaeton. Agriculture was California; there were no sprawling defense and aerospace industries, no Silicon Valley.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The Salton Sea was an unfortunate consequence of the engineering failure that marked the construction of the original canal. The current canal, built during the New Deal and named the &lt;a href="https://www.iid.com/water/water-transportation-system/colorado-river-facilities/all-american-canal">All-American Canal&lt;/a>, began delivering water to the Imperial Valley in 1940; two years later, it became the sole water source for Imperial Valley&amp;rsquo;s residents and farmlands.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-7/ImperialValleyfromBC.jpg"
alt="The Imperial Valley from the highway between Tijuana and Mexicali"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Looking north at the Imperial Valley, from the highway between Tijuana and Mexicali.&lt;/p>&lt;p>Source: &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Imperial_Valley,_California#/media/File:ImperialValleyfromBC.jpg" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">CharismaticDespot&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Water delivered to the Imperial Irrigation District (IID) each year by the All-American Canal &amp;ndash; through a vast system of canals, dams, and pipelines &amp;ndash; is enough to cover the entire irrigated land, roughly 500,000 acres, with 5 feet of water.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Imported water and a long growing season allow two crop cycles each year; the Imperial Valley now supplies over 2/3 of winter fruits and vegetables, cotton, and grain for domestic and international markets. The valley also produces most of the lamb and sheep in the US. (This raises a bunch of uncomfortable questions: What&amp;rsquo;s the rest of America doing? Why is the whole nation dependent on a few hundred farms concentrated in an irrigated desert for its food? How did this situation come to be? What happened to Eliot Coleman&amp;rsquo;s four-season farming revolution? &amp;hellip; )&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>Alfalfa is the king crop produced in the Imperial Valley. 1 out of every 3 farmed acres in the valley is dedicated to growing alfalfa, which dries into a high-protein hay commonly used as food for livestock. It&amp;rsquo;s also one of the thirstiest drop; its deep roots sucking up water in a region scorched by a 22-year drought.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Another contradiction of California: How does irrigating alfalfa in 120°F temperatures in the dead of July make any sense at all?&lt;/p>
&lt;div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
&lt;iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/AYBZISNYk8I" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video">&lt;/iframe>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>The Imperial Valley&amp;rsquo;s alfalfa industry is not only one of the largest water users in the basin, but also one of the most powerful.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Large-scale production of water-gorging, low-value crops like alfalfa during a megadrought is possible only because the Imperial Valley is the single biggest controller of rights to Colorado River water and the IID farmers have access to cheap (subsidized) water.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Due to these massive irrigation projects, south of the canal, the Colorado River no longer flows above ground at all for much of the year into Mexico.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The Colorado River, which supplies freshwater to more than 40 million people in the southwestern US and northern Mexico, has been in rapid decline. Reduced snowpack, drought conditions and higher average temperatures have all reduced the river&amp;rsquo;s flow in recent decades. The two biggest reservoirs along the river, Lake Mead and Lake Powell, are each creeping towards a &amp;ldquo;dead pool,&amp;rdquo; an ominous sign that the Colorado River could stop flowing entirely.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Agriculture accounts for ~80% of total water consumption in the Colorado River basin, with roughly half of that going towards the production of alfalfa hay, according to a 2020 &lt;a href="https://core.ac.uk/download/pdf/323061602.pdf">study&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
&lt;iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/g-pygL1-yzM" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video">&lt;/iframe>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>What has all this irrigation amounted to?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Massive industrial storehouses line the area, packed with thousands upon thousands of stacks of alfalfa bales ready to be fed to dairy cows &amp;ndash; but not cows in California&amp;rsquo;s Central Valley or Montana&amp;rsquo;s rangelands. Instead, the alfalfa will be fed to cows across the Pacific &amp;ndash; in China, Japan and Korea, and farther away in Saudi Arabia, the United Arab Emirates, etc. An increasing percentage of the alfalfa produced here is exported.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Growers say the reasons boil down to simple economics. The market for alfalfa hay in southern California has shrunk over the years as dairies have closed or moved elsewhere, while demand for dairy products has grown exponentially in other parts of the world. Meanwhile, it costs little to freight goods on the back haul to China, because the US runs a persistently high trade deficit with China; containers from Asia arrive full but often return empty. Some claim it&amp;rsquo;s actually cheaper to ship hay to China than to haul the same load by truck to dairy farms 400 miles north in the San Joaquin Valley.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Brokers regularly fly in from overseas, some staying at a local golf course and country club. Chinese buyers are wined and dined across the border in Mexicali, which has a long-established Chinese community.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>According to a 2015 &lt;a href="https://pacinst.org/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/CA-Ag-Water-Use.pdf">analysis&lt;/a> by the Pacific Institute, alfalfa production in California uses around 5 acre-feet (6,167 cubic meters) of water. In comparison, sugar beets use roughly 3 acre-feet (3,700 cubic meters), and grains as little as 1 acre-foot (1,233 cubic meters).&lt;/p>
&lt;div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
&lt;iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/EE4uMOtqIc8" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video">&lt;/iframe>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>The top water-using activity in California is growing alfalfa. Farmers in Imperial County currently draw more water from the Colorado River than all of Arizona and Nevada combined. An alfalfa farmer can grow alfalfa 10-12 times a year and sell it for $260-$280/ton. These are not the hardworking family farmers of yesteryear. They are giant agribusiness corporations pulling in $1.8 billion from selling 7 million tons of alfalfa every year in California, according to a University of California, Davis study by Daniel Geisseler and William R. Horwath.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This business has been extremely profitable because alfalfa farmers get 3.4 million acre-feet (1 acre foot =325,851 gallons) of water every year for only $35-$60 per acre-foot. The water you get for your house costs you $800 per acre-foot today, and it could be double that in 10 years' time. You could supply the water needs of 40 million people with that 3.4 million acre-feet. It&amp;rsquo;s likely that enough water for greater Los Angeles is being used to raise irrigated pasture for livestock.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Feeding irrigated grass to cows is as wasteful a use of water as you can conceive. Pasture is hydrologically inefficient in the extreme, and, metabolically speaking, so are cows: You need 7-8 feet of water in the hot deserts to keep grass alive, which means that you need ~50,000 pounds of water to raise 1 pound of cow. (Feeding alfalfa to cows requires even more water, but at least alfalfa fixes nitrogen in the soil.)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If the livestock industry earned California any real money, and if cows (unlike avocados or artichokes) couldn&amp;rsquo;t be raised on rainfall in 35 other states, then giving more water to cows than to humans in the nation&amp;rsquo;s richest and most populous state &amp;ndash; a semi-desert state at the mercy of a precarious water supply &amp;ndash; might make a grain or two of sense.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>During the last few years, companies from Saudi Arabia and the United Arab Emirates have established farming operations on thousands of acres around the Imperial Valley and the adjacent Palo Verde Valley.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Saudi Arabian companies are pumping up groundwater from beneath land they have purchased and are using it to grow alfalfa for export to the Middle East. They have no plan for replacing this scarce and finite groundwater that accumulated over thousands of years.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As a matter of fact, foreign corporations have increased purchases of farmland in the US, particularly in the southwest where longstanding laws on water rights give land owners unlimited access to the valuable water underneath the soil.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Why don&amp;rsquo;t they grow their own alfalfa? Because they are short of water and it&amp;rsquo;s so much cheaper to buy from the US.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Growing water-intensive crops in the US and exporting them to water-scarce countries is a form of geo-economic arbitrage, a natural consequence of the globalization of everything. Essentially, water is exported out of the US in the form of crops like alfalfa, rice, or almonds. Guess who is currently one of the largest net exporters of virtual water in the world?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This trend has been accelerating for decades, despite concerns that this &amp;ldquo;virtual water trading&amp;rdquo; is unsustainable in the long term, especially in drought-plagued areas such as California. If California is &lt;em>really&lt;/em> short of water, why are we shipping it to Asia?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>What this means is, ultimately, the US is not in control of its own farmland &amp;ndash; or food production.&lt;/p>
&lt;div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
&lt;iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/QPEN0o5pbA4" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video">&lt;/iframe>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>Some argue the Imperial Valley is doing good by growing food and feeding the country, and point the finger at some desert metropolises such as Las Vegas, which boasts some 50 million visitors each year and wastes way more &lt;a href="https://www.latimes.com/environment/story/2023-01-29/colorado-river-in-crisis-cracking-down-on-grass">water from Colorado River&lt;/a> with its gushing fountains. The truth is, Las Vegas and Reno represent 95% of Nevada&amp;rsquo;s economy but use 10% of its water &amp;ndash; alfalfa growers use most of the rest.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Water overuse is a prisoner&amp;rsquo;s dilemma and a tragedy of the commons. If free-market mechanisms &amp;ndash; which much of western ag publicly applauds and privately abhors &amp;ndash; were actually allowed to work, the West&amp;rsquo;s water &amp;ldquo;shortage&amp;rdquo; would be exposed for what it is: the sort of shortage you expect when inexhaustible demand chases an almost free good. (If someone were selling Porsches for $3,000 apiece, there would be a shortage of those, too.) California has a shortage of water because it has a surfeit of cows &amp;ndash; it&amp;rsquo;s really almost as simple as that.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If history is any guide, the odds that we can sustain a &amp;ldquo;civilization&amp;rdquo; in deserts would have to be regarded as low. Only one desert civilization, out of dozens that grew up in antiquity, has survived uninterrupted into modern times. And Egypt&amp;rsquo;s approach to irrigation was fundamentally different from all the rest.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-7/imperial-valley-google-maps-review.png"
alt="Review of Imperial Valley, California"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>A user review for Imperial County, California (posted on Google Maps)&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h3 id="pane-ricco">pane ricco&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>It just struck me that I should make a &lt;em>pane ricco&lt;/em> (rich bread). I named it as such because in the western US, it&amp;rsquo;s often said that water flows uphill toward money. And it literally does. Water leaps 3,000 feet across the Tehachapi Mountains in gigantic siphons to slay the thirst of Los Angeles, as it&amp;rsquo;s shoved 1,000 feet out of Colorado River canyons to hydrate Phoenix and Palm Springs and the irrigated lands around them. Water is wealth in the West.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-7/20230324_174201.jpg"
alt="pane ricco with Desert Gold durum"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>handmade &lt;em>pane ricco&lt;/em> with wholegrain Desert Gold durum flour&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>This durum dough uses as much water and milk derivatives as it could handle, which, by the West Coast&amp;rsquo;s definition, is rich.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Desert Gold durum flour, 100% extraction&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>400g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>water, divided&lt;/td>
&lt;td>125%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>500g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>whole-milk sour cream&lt;/td>
&lt;td>20%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>80g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>whole durum levain (60% hydration)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>30%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>120g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sea salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>4g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>olive oil&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>40g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>black peppercorns, crushed&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>4g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->cheeses, finely grated&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>40g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>The process is pretty much the same as &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/california-dreamin-4">&lt;em>pan integral de sonora blanca&lt;/em>&lt;/a>. Basically, keep going with &lt;em>bassinage&lt;/em> until the dough became so fragile that it might break down anytime.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I baked the bread on a BBQ grill (again!).&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-7/20230324_174619.jpg"
alt="pane ricco with Desert Gold durum"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>handmade &lt;em>pane ricco&lt;/em> with wholegrain Desert Gold durum flour&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The classic flavor combination of &lt;em>cacio e pepe&lt;/em> never disappoints.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The crust is beautifully caramelized; firm and crisp, with a distinct smokey char.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-7/20230324_173604.jpg"
alt="pane ricco with Desert Gold durum"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>handmade &lt;em>pane ricco&lt;/em> with wholegrain Desert Gold durum flour&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The crumb is light, fluffy, and airy, with distinct honeycomb layers.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-7/20230324_173653.jpg"
alt="pane ricco with Desert Gold durum"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>handmade &lt;em>pane ricco&lt;/em> with wholegrain Desert Gold durum flour&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The texture is soft and tender, yet springy and chewy. The taste reminds me of roasted chickpeas. Black peppercorns provide a interesting texture contrast, and lend a mild spiced kick to the flavor of the crumb. The combination with salty addictive cheeses is mouthwatering.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-7/20230324_175617.jpg"
alt="pane ricco with Desert Gold durum"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>handmade &lt;em>pane ricco&lt;/em> with wholegrain Desert Gold durum flour&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>And this bread toasts like a dream.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="gnocchi">Gnocchi&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>I made a plate of plump sourdough &lt;em>gnocchi&lt;/em> as well, with Desert Gold durum, &lt;em>masa harina&lt;/em>, and Yukon Gold potatoes.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-7/20230324_102531.jpg"
alt="handmade sourdough gnocchi with Desert Gold durum"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>handmade sourdough gnocchi with Yukon Gold potatoes, wholegrain Desert Gold durum flour, and &lt;em>masa harina&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Formula:&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Desert Gold durum flour, 100% extraction&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>50g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;em>masa harina&lt;/em>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>50g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Yukon Gold potatoes, roasted &amp;amp; riced&lt;/td>
&lt;td>80%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>400g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>butter, softened&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>50g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sourdough discard&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>50g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>These fork-sized orbs were sauced with garlicky sun-dried tomatoes, topped with fresh basil leaves and shaved parmigiano-reggiano.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I could eat this every day and be happy.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-7/20230324_194435.jpg"
alt="handmade potato gnocchi with Desert Gold durum sauced"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>handmade sourdough gnocchi, served with sun-dried tomatoes, fresh basil, and shaved parmigiano-reggiano&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>&lt;code>Note&lt;/code>:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Kamut (khorasan) wheat is actually very close to durum, just a larger grain size. If you can&amp;rsquo;t get durum, try kamut.&lt;/p>
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>I used equal amounts of Parmigiano-Reggiano Stravecchio (aged for 5 years), Gruyère Vieux (aged for 18 months), and Pecorino Romano (aged for 12 months).&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/section></content></item><item><title>Aquaboogie di Dolce</title><link>/posts/aquaboogie-di-dolce/</link><pubDate>Sun, 21 Aug 2022 23:32:41 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/aquaboogie-di-dolce/</guid><description>An absurdly high-hydration summer panettone, made with 85% extraction Turkey Red and 100% extraction einkorn.</description><content>&lt;p>I just found out that Dean &amp;amp; DeLuca, one of America&amp;rsquo;s fanciest gourmet grocery store chains whose name is synonymous with NYC luxury, &lt;a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20200401042156/https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2020-04-01/dean-deluca-files-for-bankruptcy-protection-from-creditors">filed for Chapter 11 bankruptcy protection&lt;/a> from creditors in April 2020. It had &amp;ldquo;liabilities of as much as $500 million and assets of no more than $50 million.&amp;rdquo; The chain&amp;rsquo;s owner, Thailand&amp;rsquo;s Pace Development Corp., defaulted on a total of THB ฿9.5Bn (USD ~$315 million) of debt in 2019.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Turns out, it was Dean &amp;amp; DeLuca&amp;rsquo;s vendors &amp;ndash; bakeries and patisseries that supplied many of the store&amp;rsquo;s pricey gourmet products &amp;ndash; who were the first to sound the death knell of the retail chain. &lt;a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2019/07/10/dining/dean-and-deluca-closes-stores.html">The NY Times&lt;/a> reported that 4+ NYC vendors, including Bien Cuit and Fulton Fish Market, were &amp;ldquo;owed hundreds of thousands of dollars.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Such a shame the iconic brand ended up in shambles.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I popped into Dean &amp;amp; DeLuca&amp;rsquo;s flagship location in NYC&amp;rsquo;s SoHo a few times when I lived in the city. Tourists are notoriously obsessed with shops in SoHo. Lol. I haven&amp;rsquo;t bothered to keep up with NYC news since I moved away years ago. I had no idea Dean &amp;amp; DeLuca opened stores in Tokyo, Bangkok, Singapore, Seoul, Dubai, Doha, Bahrain, etc. TBH, high-end stores like Dean &amp;amp; DeLuca are best for dumpster-diving.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>For many customers who stepped inside Dean &amp;amp; DeLuca over its nearly 42-year history, the visit was more about getting a glimpse of a posh world far beyond their pay grade, where a polished Thanksgiving of perfectly roasted turkey and decadent chocolate cakes could be had for the price of all the money in your bank account. Purchasing something at the stores &amp;ndash; no matter how small &amp;ndash; was a treat that made someone feel like one of the many celebrities who readily raved about shopping trips to Dean &amp;amp; DeLuca in the press. Until Whole Foods and Eataly came along, Dean &amp;amp; Deluca existed in a class of its own. &amp;hellip;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Dean &amp;amp; DeLuca enjoyed a cache well into the late-aughts that was regularly documented in pop culture. In a violent scene in &lt;em>American Psycho&lt;/em>, a book about a 1980s Wall Street serial killer, main character Patrick Bateman name drops Italian sea salt purchased from Dean &amp;amp; DeLuca. Characters in shows like &lt;em>Will &amp;amp; Grace&lt;/em> regularly mentioned the store, reminding viewers of their expensive New York tastes. A version of the company’s stylish coffee house was cemented into the memory of &lt;em>Felicity&lt;/em> viewers, whose main character works as a barista at a Dean &amp;amp; DeLuca cafe. Perhaps most indicative of the special-occasion nature of a trip to Dean &amp;amp; DeLuca is a scene in &lt;em>The Devil Wears Prada&lt;/em> where boyfriend Nate (played by Adrian Grenier) brings home a celebratory bag of food from the luxury store for girlfriend Andrea (played by Anne Hathaway), remarking that “they charge, like, five dollars a strawberry there.”&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Brenna Houck, &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href="https://www.eater.com/2019/7/16/20695333/dean-and-deluca-stores-closing-debt-fancy-food-market-rise-and-fall">Dean &amp;amp; DeLuca Sold America Luxury but Couldn’t Pay Its Own Bills&lt;/a>&amp;rdquo;, Eater&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>NGL, it was at the Dean &amp;amp; DeLuca in SoHo where I had &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->my first taste&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --> of panettone years ago. It was a fancy-schmancy panettone from Italy.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I haven&amp;rsquo;t eaten many artisan panettoni, and I&amp;rsquo;ve tried making it myself a few times. Each and every panettone is a quest for achieving a crumb that&amp;rsquo;s simultaneously moist, light, decadent, and ethereal.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Why not make a panettone, during the sweltering summer? Turns out &lt;em>&lt;a href="https://www.dissapore.com/spesa/panettone-estivo-2022-sette-grandi-lievitati-per-lestate/">panettoni estivi&lt;/a>&lt;/em> already became a &amp;ldquo;trend&amp;rdquo; last year. Never short the hedonism of US consumers.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I looked up panettone recipes by Carol Field, Roy Schvartzapel, Piergiorgio Giorilli, Iginio Massari, Ezio Marinato, Gino Fabbri, Giambattista Montanari, and Michel Suas to figure out the pattern across the maestros' methods. Then I decided to try something of my own.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I wanted this summer panettone to be lighter and fresher than a winter holiday version, so I used less butter, less sugar and no eggs. No, I definitely don&amp;rsquo;t want this one to be as brazenly buttery as Roy Schvartzapel&amp;rsquo;s luxury panettone.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="impasto-1">Impasto #1&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The &lt;em>lievito madre&lt;/em> is too much work, so I used &lt;a href="https://theflavorbells.com/yeast-water/">homemade fruit yeast water&lt;/a> instead.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>85% extraction wheat flour (Turkey Red - Stutzman Farms, OH)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>plum yeast water (homemade)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>50%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>ginger-turmeric syrup (homemade)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>20%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sugar (Louisiana cane sugar - Three Brothers Farm, LA)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>unsalted butter (Spesiell Kremen - Nordic Creamery, WI)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>15%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>To make the ginger-turmeric syrup, mix fresh ginger, turmeric, water, sugar, and spices (coriander, cumin, peppercorn, cinnamon, etc.) in a pot. Bring to a boil. Reduce heat and simmer until a syrupy consistency is reached. Let cool and then strain.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Process (by hand):&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Combine the flour with the yeast water and the syrup, and let autolyze for 30 mins.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Mix in the sugar.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Add the softened butter, in 4 increments. Mix in thoroughly.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Slap &amp;amp; fold until a very soft, smooth and strong dough is formed (with ~80% gluten development).&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Ferment for 12 hours at ~72°F (longer at lower temperatures).&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>At the end of fermentation, the first dough should triple in volume.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="impasto-2">Impasto #2&lt;/h3>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>100% extraction einkorn flour (Stutzman Farms, OH)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>impasto #1&lt;/td>
&lt;td>900%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>diastatic malt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>h₂o&lt;/td>
&lt;td>250%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>honey (Champion Hill Farm, MI)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>30%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;em>pasta di arancia&lt;/em> (homemade)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>125%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>pawpaw purée (wild)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>40%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>unsalted butter (Spesiell Kremen - Nordic Creamery, WI)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>70%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>dried fruits (mangoes, pineapples, apples)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>30%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>dried petals (safflowers, hibiscus, marigolds)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sprouted quinoa&lt;/td>
&lt;td>222%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>To make &lt;em>pasta di arancia&lt;/em>, mix together peeled (and de-seeded) navel oranges, mandarins, tangelos, lemons, ginger, turmeric, honey, sugar, and orange zest in a blender until you get a creamy paste. The proportion of each ingredient depends on your personal preferences. You should make a big batch &amp;ndash; it can be kept in a sterilized glass jar in the fridge for a few weeks or in the freezer for a few months.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I soaked the dried fruits and flower petals in some dessert wine (Silver Dick - Wenwood Farm Winery, MO) overnight.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I also soaked some quinoa in double the amount of water overnight and let the seeds sprout. The wet sprouted quinoa came up to be 222% of final flour weight.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Process (by hand):&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>To impasto #1, add all the flour, malt, salt and 1/3 of the water. Mix for a few minutes.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Add the honey and mix in completely.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Add the &lt;em>pasta di arancia&lt;/em> and pawpaw purée. Slap &amp;amp; fold until just combined.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Let rest for 15 mins.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Add the butter in 4 increments. Mix until the butter is completely incorporated into the dough and the gluten has reached full development.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Let rest for 10 mins.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Add the rest of the water very slowly, mixing in completely before continuing. Adding water after butter is like lightening an emulsion; it made me think of making mayonnaise. &amp;mdash;-&amp;gt; TBH, no panettone recipe I&amp;rsquo;ve seen calls for this much water. I went with my gut and gorged the dough with as much water as I felt it could handle. Ludicrously, after a whopping 250% hydration, I felt the dough could handle even more h₂o&amp;hellip;(another experiment for next time?) It held together really well and didn&amp;rsquo;t break down at all. The dough started to feel as puffy and jiggly as a &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/aquaboogie">&lt;em>pan de cristal&lt;/em>&lt;/a>!&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Let rest for 10 mins.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Stretch the dough out into a thin rectangle, and laminate with the add-ins (soaked fruits, petals and quinoa).&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Bulk-ferment at ~80°F for 1 hour, folding every 20 mins.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Shape the dough and place into a baking mold. &amp;lt;&amp;mdash;- I thought about baking the dough flat out like I do with the &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/aquaboogie">&lt;em>pan de cristal&lt;/em>&lt;/a>. Not this time, because I was still hoping to make a &amp;ldquo;panettone,&amp;rdquo; which should be a tall loaf. I shaped the dough into a log and placed it into a loaf pan, so it would rise up to a proper height.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Proof for 4-6 hours at ~80°F (or ~12 hours at 72°F).&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>The dough should rise up 2x like a giant cotton candy before baking.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I baked it in my toaster oven at 350-325°F for 50 mins.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>After baking, I tipped the panettone over on its side and let it cool off like that for 24 hours, instead of doing the fancy upside-down hanging. NGL, the hanging method is definitely far more effective at helping the panettone&amp;rsquo;s delicate crumb maintain its elongated structure.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/aquaboogie-di-dolce/202208211156.jpg"
alt="Aquaboogie di Dolce"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Despite the improper cooling, the panettone has turned out decent (not a devastating failure).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The crumb feels superbly moist and delicate; it tastes boldly fruity and pleasantly sweet. We devoured half of the loaf in one sitting.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you think about how much sugar, honey, and butter go into each panettone, how is it possible this thing doesn&amp;rsquo;t have a rich taste and a fluffy texture? They all help to elevate the crumb.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/aquaboogie-di-dolce/202208211153.jpg"
alt="Aquaboogie di Dolce"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Aquaboogie di Dolce, an absurdly high-hydration summer panettone.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Honey (sugar) softens the crumb, while fats lubricate the dough and help the flour particles move alongside each other more smoothly, making the dough more flexible and stretchable. In breads with a high percentage of whole grains, a little honey brings out more of the grain&amp;rsquo;s flavor and balances out its earthiness.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Generic supermarket butter is ~80% fat; the remaining 20% is mostly water and some proteins. Fats do more than providing a smoother mouthfeel and a richer sensory experience. When an enriched dough is placed in a hot oven, the butter melts. As a result, the water content in the butter turns into steam. It&amp;rsquo;s that steam being trapped by the gluten in the dough that lifts the croissant off into honeycomb ecstasy. Meanwhile, the fat molecules become a bit more mobile and they will re-organize themselves slightly. Since fats don&amp;rsquo;t like to sit in water, they will actually surround the air bubbles in bread. This way the fat stabilizes the air bubbles. Consequently, enriched breads tend to have a lot of small air bubbles. Since the fats remain in place after baking (they cool down and solidify again), they will remain around these air bubbles. That acts like a protective layer and helps keep the bread fresh.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Both sugar and fat prevent the gluten from forming long, chewy strands and help produce a more tender bread, but they should be added only towards the end of mixing/kneading after the gluten network is mostly developed. Any type of sugar and fat will probably work just as well.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/aquaboogie-di-dolce/202208211201.jpg"
alt="Aquaboogie di Dolce"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>This panettone is an absolutely fantastic substrate for the iconic Cuban &lt;em>medianoche&lt;/em> &amp;ndash; sweet, salty, and deeply satisfying. Yes, I use Italian panettone to make Cuban &lt;em>medianoche&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>2022/12/18&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I got to sample a slice of Olivieri 1882&amp;rsquo;s latest &lt;em>panettone all&amp;rsquo;aceto balsamico&lt;/em> at a holiday party. It was lavishly soft, airy, and decadent; laced with balsamic cream and studded with balsamic-vinegar infused raisin.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The packaging says it uses Carandini&amp;rsquo;s Balsamic Vinegar of Modena IGP. Olivieri&amp;rsquo;s website describes it as follows:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Carandini, one of Modena&amp;rsquo;s oldest families, has been producing hand-crafted balsamic vinegars using traditional family methods since 1641. Their hero expression, the Emilio Balsamic Vinegar of Modena, is a premium, high-density vinegar that contains 60% grape must and strikes a delicate balance between sweet and sour. Exuding a mahogany color and rich perfume, the versatile product lends a subtle acidity and fragrant sweetness to Olivieri&amp;rsquo;s staple Panettone recipe.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>FYI, Carandini&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em>Aceto Balsamico di Modena IGP&lt;/em> (Balsamic Vinegar of Modena) is not a true &lt;em>Aceto Balsamico Tradizionale&lt;/em>, i.e. made from a reduction of pressed Trebbiano and Lambrusco grape that&amp;rsquo;s aged for a minimum of 12 years in a series of wooden barrels of successively smaller sizes. True balsamic vinegar is rich, glossy, deep brown in color, and has a complex flavor that balances the natural sweetness and sourness of cooked grape juice with hints of wood from the casks.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Aceto Balsamico di Modena&lt;/em> is a commercial-grade cheaper imitation of the traditional balsamic vinegar. They can be made from as little as 20% grape must (and not necessarily from Modena or Reggio Emilia), with the addition of wine vinegar, coloring, caramel, and sometimes thickeners like guar gum or corn starch to artificially simulate the sweetness and thickness of the naturally aged &lt;em>Aceto Balsamico Tradizionale di Modena&lt;/em>. IGP status requires a minimum aging period of 2 months (not necessarily in wooden barrels), rising to 3 years when labeled as &lt;em>invecchiato&lt;/em> (aged).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;60% grape must&amp;rdquo; = 40% wine vinegar. Since Carandini&amp;rsquo;s Balsamic Vinegar of Modena has IGP in its label, it&amp;rsquo;s most likely produced in Modena. (For some reason, I&amp;rsquo;ve yet to come across a bottle of balsamic vinegar that&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em>not&lt;/em> made in Modena.)&lt;/p>
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>Dean &amp;amp; DeLuca reminded me of Southern Season, a gourmet specialty food retailer in the Carolinas where I got to taste many fine cheeses and chocolates from around the world. Southern Season filed for Chapter 11 bankruptcy in 2016. It had liabilities of ~$18.9 million compared to ~$9.8 million in assets &amp;ndash; not as outrageous as Dean &amp;amp; DeLuca&amp;rsquo;s debt-to-asset ratio.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/section></content></item><item><title>Aquaboogie van Wheatsworth</title><link>/posts/aquaboogie-van-wheatsworth/</link><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jul 2021 23:01:38 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/aquaboogie-van-wheatsworth/</guid><description>A series of heretically high-hydration wholegrain &lt;em>pan de cristal&lt;/em> experiments.</description><content>&lt;p>I have been experimenting with wholegrain &lt;em>pan de cristal&lt;/em>. Impossible? &amp;ldquo;Water makes the baker rich.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="100-turkey-red">100% Turkey Red&lt;/h4>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>whole wheat flour (Turkey Red - Stephens Land &amp;amp; Cattle, KS)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>cold &lt;em>aqua&lt;/em> (autolyse 75% + bassinage 45% + salt 10%)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>130%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>whole wheat levain&lt;/td>
&lt;td>40%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>olive oil (Peranzana)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>20%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>The process is pretty much the same as in the &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/aquaboogie">80% extraction version&lt;/a> &amp;ndash; except that I gorged with dough a lot more water during &lt;em>bassinage&lt;/em> and olive oil after.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/aquaboogie-van-wheatsworth/202107121516.jpg"
alt="Aquaboogie van Wheatsworth"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/aquaboogie-van-wheatsworth/202107121521.jpg"
alt="Aquaboogie van Wheatsworth"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/aquaboogie-van-wheatsworth/202107121523.jpg"
alt="Aquaboogie van Wheatsworth"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>100% whole wheat &amp;lsquo;pan de cristal&amp;rsquo;, made with unbolted Turkey Red.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>A very light and airy crumb. Reminded me of my &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/the-wheatwalker">first Turkey Red bread&lt;/a>, but this one is much more chewy and &amp;ldquo;spongy.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="70-turkey-red--30-triticale">70% Turkey Red + 30% triticale&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>Triticale (&lt;em>Tricosecate&lt;/em>) is a man-made cross of wheat (&lt;em>Triticum&lt;/em>) and rye (&lt;em>Secale&lt;/em>), exhibiting characteristics of both grains, i.e. triticale contains the complex flavor and nuance of rye, mellowed by the easier behavior of wheat. It has been around for well over a century. It was &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/files/Stace-Triticale-1987.pdf">first bred in labs&lt;/a> in the late 1800s in Scotland and Germany, in order to combine the yield potential and grain quality of wheat with the disease and environmental tolerance of rye.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In &lt;em>Star Trek&lt;/em> episode &amp;ldquo;The Trouble with Tribbles&amp;rdquo;, the protection of a grain developed from triticale is the central focus. This grain was a genetically-engineered hybrid of wheat and rye with four distinct lobes per kernel, hence the name &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href="https://memory-alpha.fandom.com/wiki/Quadrotriticale">quadro-triticale&lt;/a>.&amp;rdquo; Mr. Spock attributes the ancestry of the root grain, triticale, to 20th-century Canada.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Indeed, in 1953 the University of Manitoba in western Canada began the first intensive triticale breeding program in North America, working mostly with durum wheat-rye crosses. Early efforts concentrated on developing a high-yield, drought-tolerant human food crop species suitable for marginal wheat-producing areas.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It was only after the 1970s that farmers started to grow this grain on a commercial scale &amp;ndash; mostly for forage or fodder. Over the years, triticale&amp;rsquo;s popularity has surged and ebbed. Farmers tend to either love the crop and continually plant it, or give it a go once and decide they like other grains better. Triticale has recently &lt;a href="https://hayandforage.com/article-2178-a-call-to-triticale.html">resurfaced&lt;/a> as a choice grain for high-protein feed.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In the vast potpourri of hybrid grains that have been developed so far, at least this one has been around for well over a century and has had more research than some other stuff that has been engineered in the last ~5 years.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Triticale is mostly grown in Europe (Poland, Germany, Belarus, France and Russia), but you can find it easily in North America and Australia these days.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In an attempt to better understand the idiosyncrasies of this grain, I ferreted out as much information as possible on the internet. What I&amp;rsquo;ve learned:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Triticale actually has a higher protein content than wheat and, at the same time, a lower gluten content than wheat due to genetic inheritance from rye. The latter trait has deprived the grain of superstardom in the breadmaking fraternity. A suggested solution: blend &amp;lt;=30% triticale flour into a wheat dough.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Unlike rye, triticale actually has a very poor ability to absorb water. Start with low hydration (~60%) if making a 100% triticale bread, and don&amp;rsquo;t expect a tall, fluffy loaf.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Triticale appears to benefit from the LAB fermentation process of a natural leaven. This helps to make the protein more soluble and improves the viscosity of the dough itself.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>A triticale dough also benefits from minimal handling, i.e. &amp;ldquo;no knead&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;folding&amp;rdquo;, because it has a low mixing tolerance.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>Triticale seems to be a good candidate for blending, rather than using it totally on its own.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>whole wheat flour (Turkey Red - Stephens Land &amp;amp; Cattle, KS)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>70%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>whole triticale flour (Sunflower Acres, CO)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>30%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>cold &lt;em>aqua&lt;/em> (autolyse 75% + bassinage 45% + salt 5%)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>125%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>whole triticale levain&lt;/td>
&lt;td>40%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>olive oil (Peranzana)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>20%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>The 70% wheat 30% triticale flour blend yielded a spongy bread with honeycomb crumb.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/aquaboogie-van-wheatsworth/202107181604.jpg"
alt="Aquaboogie van Wheatsworth"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/aquaboogie-van-wheatsworth/202107181605.jpg"
alt="Aquaboogie van Wheatsworth"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/aquaboogie-van-wheatsworth/202107181606.jpg"
alt="Aquaboogie van Wheatsworth"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>100% wholegrain &amp;lsquo;pan de cristal&amp;rsquo;, made with 70% unbolted Turkey Red and 30% unbolted triticale.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Compared to the 100% Turkey Red &lt;em>pan de cristal&lt;/em>, this 30% triticale version has a milder flavor and a less open but more moist crumb. Tasty in a different way.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="50-turkey-red--50-spelt">50% Turkey Red + 50% spelt&lt;/h4>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>whole wheat flour (Turkey Red - Stephens Land &amp;amp; Cattle, KS)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>50%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>whole spelt flour (Oberkülmer - Tom &amp;amp; Mary Klein, OH)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>50%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>cold &lt;em>aqua&lt;/em> (autolyse 75% + bassinage 45% + salt 10%)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>130%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>caramelized onion purée&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>whole spelt levain&lt;/td>
&lt;td>40%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>olive oil (from garlic confit)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>20%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>fermented jalapeños&lt;/td>
&lt;td>15%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>wild garlic leaves&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>shredded cheese&lt;/td>
&lt;td>20%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>The jalapeños and garlic went in the dough during coil-folds.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I piled heaps and heaps of cheeses (from Hemme Brothers Creamery, MO) on top of the dough, just before it went into the oven:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>aged cheddar&lt;/li>
&lt;li>applewood smoked cheddar&lt;/li>
&lt;li>sour cream &amp;amp; onion cheddar curds&lt;/li>
&lt;li>garlic dill cheddar curds&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Indulgent like those cheese slippers at Fervere Bakery in Kansas City.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/aquaboogie-van-wheatsworth/202107231506.jpg"
alt="Aquaboogie van Wheatsworth"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>100% wholegrain &amp;lsquo;pan de cristal&amp;rsquo;, made with 50% unbolted Turkey Red and 50% unbolted Oberkülmer spelt.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The golden crispy cheese-laden crust is the crown jewel.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/aquaboogie-van-wheatsworth/202107231523.jpg"
alt="Aquaboogie van Wheatsworth"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/aquaboogie-van-wheatsworth/202107241008.jpg"
alt="Aquaboogie van Wheatsworth"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The crumb is juicy, bold and spicy.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/aquaboogie-van-wheatsworth/202107241010.jpg"
alt="Aquaboogie van Wheatsworth"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/aquaboogie-van-wheatsworth/202107241018.jpg"
alt="Aquaboogie van Wheatsworth"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>100% wholegrain &amp;lsquo;pan de cristal&amp;rsquo;, made with 50% unbolted Turkey Red and 50% unbolted Oberkülmer spelt.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>After these experiments, I doubt I will miss making lower-hydration wheat breads again. If I&amp;rsquo;ve learned anything about my baking, it&amp;rsquo;s this: why &amp;ldquo;do&amp;rdquo; when I can &amp;ldquo;overdo&amp;rdquo;? The &lt;em>pan de cristal&lt;/em> is a game-changer.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Only those who will risk going too far can possibly find out how far one can go.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>T.S. Eliot&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote></content></item><item><title>Aquaboogie</title><link>/posts/aquaboogie/</link><pubDate>Wed, 05 May 2021 23:10:46 -0600</pubDate><guid>/posts/aquaboogie/</guid><description>&lt;em>Pan de Cristal&lt;/em>, an elusive gem. A whopping 110% hydration plus 15% oil results in an extremely wet formless mixture which, after proper mixing, transforms into a marvelously glossy and almost fluid blob of a dough that spreads willingly &amp;ndash; and yields elastic translucent crumbs and a terrain of air bubbles.</description><content>&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;ve been playing with &lt;em>pan de cristal&lt;/em>, using freshly milled whole wheat flour bolted down to 80% extraction.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Pan de cristal&lt;/em> (called &lt;em>pa de vidre&lt;/em> in Catalan) is a Spanish &amp;ldquo;glass bread&amp;rdquo; invented in ~2004 by Barcelonian baker Jordi Nomen. It&amp;rsquo;s characterized by high hydration and double fermentation, which causes a very hollow and alveolate crumb that&amp;rsquo;s almost non-existent. &lt;em>Pan de cristal&lt;/em> is now a registered trademark &lt;a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/913153046">owned by its creator&lt;/a>. Nomen&amp;rsquo;s next bakery, Concept Pa, has developed a more extreme variety called &lt;em>&lt;a href="http://www.pandecristal.com/products/diamond-crystal-bread-r/">pan de cristal® diamante&lt;/a>&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Claudio Perrando, a German-Panamanian baker who rose to international stardom over the last decade through the internet, seems to be the most famous ambassador of &lt;em>pan de cristal.&lt;/em> His version has translucent crumb and such MASSIVE holes that it undoubtedly wins the competition for the Bread with the Fewest Calories per Cubic Centimeter. He sells his recipes online. I&amp;rsquo;ve never bought his recipes, but from what I can tell, he uses an over-ripe poolish and a long autolyse (with high-gluten super-fine flour) to add more extensibility to the dough. He does a 3-4h warm bulk-fermentation and a 1h final proof.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>80% extraction wheat flour (Turkey Red - Aspen Moon Farm, CO)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>cold &lt;em>aqua&lt;/em> (autolyse 75% + bassinage 30% + salt mixing 5%)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>110%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>rye levain&lt;/td>
&lt;td>35%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>olive oil&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->10%-20%&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Autolyze the flour with 75% of the &lt;em>aqua&lt;/em> for 1-2 hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Add the levain and mix until gluten development.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Add the next 30% &lt;em>aqua&lt;/em> in 4 increments &lt;em>à la bassinage&lt;/em>. Make sure each addition of water is well absorbed before adding more.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Let rest for 15-20 mins, and mix in the salt with the last 5% &lt;em>aqua&lt;/em>. The dough will noticeably tighten after absorbing the salt.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Let rest for 30 mins before mixing in the oil. The dough should be super airy and jiggly.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Perform 5 coil folds, at 45-min intervals. Sprinkle any add-ins at each fold, e.g., cinnamon sugar, chocolate chips, herbs.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Bulk ferment at 75F for 3h and retard in the fridge overnight. (Or straight to the fridge for 36-48h after the first 2 folds at room temperature.)&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/aquaboogie/202205050812.jpg"
alt="80% extraction pan de cristal"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/aquaboogie/202205050813.jpg"
alt="80% extraction pan de cristal"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Next day, take it out of the fridge, divide and rest 2-3h. No shaping necessary.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Bake at 375°F for the first 20 mins, until the crust is brown and blistered. Bake for another 10-15 mins at 350F until cooked through.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/aquaboogie/202205051301.jpg"
alt="80% extraction pan de cristal"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Pan de cristal, made with 80% extraction Turkey Red.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>A whopping 110% hydration plus 15% oil results in an extremely wet formless mixture which, after proper mixing, transforms into a gorgeously glossy and almost fluid blob of a dough that spreads willingly, and yields elastic translucent crumbs and a terrain of air bubbles.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/aquaboogie/202205051305.jpg"
alt="80% extraction pan de cristal"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Crispy. Chewy. Bubbly. Wheaty. With flecks and sheen in the crumb like Italian terrazzo floors.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This bread makes fantastic and ginormous sandwiches as the way Roman Gods intended. Also an excellent delivery vessel for tomatoes and Iberian ham.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/aquaboogie/202205051307.jpg"
alt="80% extraction pan de cristal"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>BTW, I make &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/aquaboogie-van-wheatsworth/">wholegrain versions&lt;/a>, too.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>This is also the base recipe I use for my scandalous &lt;em>schiacciata toscana&lt;/em>. It&amp;rsquo;s supposedly a Florentine flat bread that is characteristically closer to a &lt;em>pizza bianca&lt;/em> than anything else, made famous by All&amp;rsquo;antico Vinaio (rumored to be the greatest sandwich shop in the world).&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>The Florentine &lt;em>schiacciata all&amp;rsquo;olio&lt;/em> uses a goodly amount of olive oil and large grain salt, and the best is cooked in a wood burning oven. It should be crispy but not hard, oily but not greasy.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>If making &lt;em>schiacciata&lt;/em>, flip the dough onto a rectangular baking sheet. Use fingers to gently dent and push the dough outwards towards all four corners, preserving the air bubbles inside, until the dough is about 3/4&amp;quot; (2 cm) at its thickest part. Make random dimples 2&amp;quot; (5 cm) apart that puncture all the way through the dough to the pan. This will prevent the dough from doming too much while baking and help create even thickness for sandwiches. Drizzle olive oil all over the surface of the dough.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The best way to appreciate the unique flavor of Turkey Red &lt;em>pan de cristal&lt;/em> is to add a touch of salted butter and/or honey and eat while still slightly warm. When the bread starts to stale, toast it and dunk it into a warm, funky dip like a &lt;em>bagna càuda&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;ve experimented with increasing the amount of oil to ~20% of flour weight, and had great results.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/section></content></item></channel></rss>