<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>quinoa on HERESY LEVAIN</title><link>/tags/quinoa/</link><description>Latest experiments in quinoa from HERESY LEVAIN</description><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2023 HERESY LEVAIN 🍞 CC BY-NC-SA 4.0</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 21 Aug 2022 23:32:41 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/quinoa/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Aquaboogie di Dolce</title><link>/posts/aquaboogie-di-dolce/</link><pubDate>Sun, 21 Aug 2022 23:32:41 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/aquaboogie-di-dolce/</guid><description>An absurdly high-hydration summer panettone, made with 85% extraction Turkey Red and 100% extraction einkorn.</description><content>&lt;p>I just found out that Dean &amp;amp; DeLuca, one of America&amp;rsquo;s fanciest gourmet grocery store chains whose name is synonymous with NYC luxury, &lt;a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20200401042156/https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2020-04-01/dean-deluca-files-for-bankruptcy-protection-from-creditors">filed for Chapter 11 bankruptcy protection&lt;/a> from creditors in April 2020. It had &amp;ldquo;liabilities of as much as $500 million and assets of no more than $50 million.&amp;rdquo; The chain&amp;rsquo;s owner, Thailand&amp;rsquo;s Pace Development Corp., defaulted on a total of THB ฿9.5Bn (USD ~$315 million) of debt in 2019.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Turns out, it was Dean &amp;amp; DeLuca&amp;rsquo;s vendors &amp;ndash; bakeries and patisseries that supplied many of the store&amp;rsquo;s pricey gourmet products &amp;ndash; who were the first to sound the death knell of the retail chain. &lt;a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2019/07/10/dining/dean-and-deluca-closes-stores.html">The NY Times&lt;/a> reported that 4+ NYC vendors, including Bien Cuit and Fulton Fish Market, were &amp;ldquo;owed hundreds of thousands of dollars.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Such a shame the iconic brand ended up in shambles.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I popped into Dean &amp;amp; DeLuca&amp;rsquo;s flagship location in NYC&amp;rsquo;s SoHo a few times when I lived in the city. Tourists are notoriously obsessed with shops in SoHo. Lol. I haven&amp;rsquo;t bothered to keep up with NYC news since I moved away years ago. I had no idea Dean &amp;amp; DeLuca opened stores in Tokyo, Bangkok, Singapore, Seoul, Dubai, Doha, Bahrain, etc. TBH, high-end stores like Dean &amp;amp; DeLuca are best for dumpster-diving.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>For many customers who stepped inside Dean &amp;amp; DeLuca over its nearly 42-year history, the visit was more about getting a glimpse of a posh world far beyond their pay grade, where a polished Thanksgiving of perfectly roasted turkey and decadent chocolate cakes could be had for the price of all the money in your bank account. Purchasing something at the stores &amp;ndash; no matter how small &amp;ndash; was a treat that made someone feel like one of the many celebrities who readily raved about shopping trips to Dean &amp;amp; DeLuca in the press. Until Whole Foods and Eataly came along, Dean &amp;amp; Deluca existed in a class of its own. &amp;hellip;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Dean &amp;amp; DeLuca enjoyed a cache well into the late-aughts that was regularly documented in pop culture. In a violent scene in &lt;em>American Psycho&lt;/em>, a book about a 1980s Wall Street serial killer, main character Patrick Bateman name drops Italian sea salt purchased from Dean &amp;amp; DeLuca. Characters in shows like &lt;em>Will &amp;amp; Grace&lt;/em> regularly mentioned the store, reminding viewers of their expensive New York tastes. A version of the company’s stylish coffee house was cemented into the memory of &lt;em>Felicity&lt;/em> viewers, whose main character works as a barista at a Dean &amp;amp; DeLuca cafe. Perhaps most indicative of the special-occasion nature of a trip to Dean &amp;amp; DeLuca is a scene in &lt;em>The Devil Wears Prada&lt;/em> where boyfriend Nate (played by Adrian Grenier) brings home a celebratory bag of food from the luxury store for girlfriend Andrea (played by Anne Hathaway), remarking that “they charge, like, five dollars a strawberry there.”&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Brenna Houck, &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href="https://www.eater.com/2019/7/16/20695333/dean-and-deluca-stores-closing-debt-fancy-food-market-rise-and-fall">Dean &amp;amp; DeLuca Sold America Luxury but Couldn’t Pay Its Own Bills&lt;/a>&amp;rdquo;, Eater&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>NGL, it was at the Dean &amp;amp; DeLuca in SoHo where I had &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->my first taste&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --> of panettone years ago. It was a fancy-schmancy panettone from Italy.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I haven&amp;rsquo;t eaten many artisan panettoni, and I&amp;rsquo;ve tried making it myself a few times. Each and every panettone is a quest for achieving a crumb that&amp;rsquo;s simultaneously moist, light, decadent, and ethereal.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Why not make a panettone, during the sweltering summer? Turns out &lt;em>&lt;a href="https://www.dissapore.com/spesa/panettone-estivo-2022-sette-grandi-lievitati-per-lestate/">panettoni estivi&lt;/a>&lt;/em> already became a &amp;ldquo;trend&amp;rdquo; last year. Never short the hedonism of US consumers.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I looked up panettone recipes by Carol Field, Roy Schvartzapel, Piergiorgio Giorilli, Iginio Massari, Ezio Marinato, Gino Fabbri, Giambattista Montanari, and Michel Suas to figure out the pattern across the maestros' methods. Then I decided to try something of my own.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I wanted this summer panettone to be lighter and fresher than a winter holiday version, so I used less butter, less sugar and no eggs. No, I definitely don&amp;rsquo;t want this one to be as brazenly buttery as Roy Schvartzapel&amp;rsquo;s luxury panettone.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="impasto-1">Impasto #1&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The &lt;em>lievito madre&lt;/em> is too much work, so I used &lt;a href="https://theflavorbells.com/yeast-water/">homemade fruit yeast water&lt;/a> instead.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>85% extraction wheat flour (Turkey Red - Stutzman Farms, OH)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>plum yeast water (homemade)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>50%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>ginger-turmeric syrup (homemade)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>20%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sugar (Louisiana cane sugar - Three Brothers Farm, LA)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>unsalted butter (Spesiell Kremen - Nordic Creamery, WI)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>15%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>To make the ginger-turmeric syrup, mix fresh ginger, turmeric, water, sugar, and spices (coriander, cumin, peppercorn, cinnamon, etc.) in a pot. Bring to a boil. Reduce heat and simmer until a syrupy consistency is reached. Let cool and then strain.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Process (by hand):&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Combine the flour with the yeast water and the syrup, and let autolyze for 30 mins.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Mix in the sugar.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Add the softened butter, in 4 increments. Mix in thoroughly.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Slap &amp;amp; fold until a very soft, smooth and strong dough is formed (with ~80% gluten development).&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Ferment for 12 hours at ~72°F (longer at lower temperatures).&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>At the end of fermentation, the first dough should triple in volume.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="impasto-2">Impasto #2&lt;/h3>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>100% extraction einkorn flour (Stutzman Farms, OH)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>impasto #1&lt;/td>
&lt;td>900%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>diastatic malt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>h₂o&lt;/td>
&lt;td>250%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>honey (Champion Hill Farm, MI)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>30%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;em>pasta di arancia&lt;/em> (homemade)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>125%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>pawpaw purée (wild)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>40%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>unsalted butter (Spesiell Kremen - Nordic Creamery, WI)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>70%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>dried fruits (mangoes, pineapples, apples)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>30%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>dried petals (safflowers, hibiscus, marigolds)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sprouted quinoa&lt;/td>
&lt;td>222%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>To make &lt;em>pasta di arancia&lt;/em>, mix together peeled (and de-seeded) navel oranges, mandarins, tangelos, lemons, ginger, turmeric, honey, sugar, and orange zest in a blender until you get a creamy paste. The proportion of each ingredient depends on your personal preferences. You should make a big batch &amp;ndash; it can be kept in a sterilized glass jar in the fridge for a few weeks or in the freezer for a few months.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I soaked the dried fruits and flower petals in some dessert wine (Silver Dick - Wenwood Farm Winery, MO) overnight.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I also soaked some quinoa in double the amount of water overnight and let the seeds sprout. The wet sprouted quinoa came up to be 222% of final flour weight.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Process (by hand):&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>To impasto #1, add all the flour, malt, salt and 1/3 of the water. Mix for a few minutes.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Add the honey and mix in completely.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Add the &lt;em>pasta di arancia&lt;/em> and pawpaw purée. Slap &amp;amp; fold until just combined.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Let rest for 15 mins.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Add the butter in 4 increments. Mix until the butter is completely incorporated into the dough and the gluten has reached full development.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Let rest for 10 mins.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Add the rest of the water very slowly, mixing in completely before continuing. Adding water after butter is like lightening an emulsion; it made me think of making mayonnaise. &amp;mdash;-&amp;gt; TBH, no panettone recipe I&amp;rsquo;ve seen calls for this much water. I went with my gut and gorged the dough with as much water as I felt it could handle. Ludicrously, after a whopping 250% hydration, I felt the dough could handle even more h₂o&amp;hellip;(another experiment for next time?) It held together really well and didn&amp;rsquo;t break down at all. The dough started to feel as puffy and jiggly as a &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/aquaboogie">&lt;em>pan de cristal&lt;/em>&lt;/a>!&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Let rest for 10 mins.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Stretch the dough out into a thin rectangle, and laminate with the add-ins (soaked fruits, petals and quinoa).&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Bulk-ferment at ~80°F for 1 hour, folding every 20 mins.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Shape the dough and place into a baking mold. &amp;lt;&amp;mdash;- I thought about baking the dough flat out like I do with the &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/aquaboogie">&lt;em>pan de cristal&lt;/em>&lt;/a>. Not this time, because I was still hoping to make a &amp;ldquo;panettone,&amp;rdquo; which should be a tall loaf. I shaped the dough into a log and placed it into a loaf pan, so it would rise up to a proper height.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Proof for 4-6 hours at ~80°F (or ~12 hours at 72°F).&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>The dough should rise up 2x like a giant cotton candy before baking.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I baked it in my toaster oven at 350-325°F for 50 mins.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>After baking, I tipped the panettone over on its side and let it cool off like that for 24 hours, instead of doing the fancy upside-down hanging. NGL, the hanging method is definitely far more effective at helping the panettone&amp;rsquo;s delicate crumb maintain its elongated structure.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/aquaboogie-di-dolce/202208211156.jpg"
alt="Aquaboogie di Dolce"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Despite the improper cooling, the panettone has turned out decent (not a devastating failure).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The crumb feels superbly moist and delicate; it tastes boldly fruity and pleasantly sweet. We devoured half of the loaf in one sitting.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you think about how much sugar, honey, and butter go into each panettone, how is it possible this thing doesn&amp;rsquo;t have a rich taste and a fluffy texture? They all help to elevate the crumb.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/aquaboogie-di-dolce/202208211153.jpg"
alt="Aquaboogie di Dolce"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Aquaboogie di Dolce, an absurdly high-hydration summer panettone.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Honey (sugar) softens the crumb, while fats lubricate the dough and help the flour particles move alongside each other more smoothly, making the dough more flexible and stretchable. In breads with a high percentage of whole grains, a little honey brings out more of the grain&amp;rsquo;s flavor and balances out its earthiness.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Generic supermarket butter is ~80% fat; the remaining 20% is mostly water and some proteins. Fats do more than providing a smoother mouthfeel and a richer sensory experience. When an enriched dough is placed in a hot oven, the butter melts. As a result, the water content in the butter turns into steam. It&amp;rsquo;s that steam being trapped by the gluten in the dough that lifts the croissant off into honeycomb ecstasy. Meanwhile, the fat molecules become a bit more mobile and they will re-organize themselves slightly. Since fats don&amp;rsquo;t like to sit in water, they will actually surround the air bubbles in bread. This way the fat stabilizes the air bubbles. Consequently, enriched breads tend to have a lot of small air bubbles. Since the fats remain in place after baking (they cool down and solidify again), they will remain around these air bubbles. That acts like a protective layer and helps keep the bread fresh.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Both sugar and fat prevent the gluten from forming long, chewy strands and help produce a more tender bread, but they should be added only towards the end of mixing/kneading after the gluten network is mostly developed. Any type of sugar and fat will probably work just as well.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/aquaboogie-di-dolce/202208211201.jpg"
alt="Aquaboogie di Dolce"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>This panettone is an absolutely fantastic substrate for the iconic Cuban &lt;em>medianoche&lt;/em> &amp;ndash; sweet, salty, and deeply satisfying. Yes, I use Italian panettone to make Cuban &lt;em>medianoche&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>2022/12/18&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I got to sample a slice of Olivieri 1882&amp;rsquo;s latest &lt;em>panettone all&amp;rsquo;aceto balsamico&lt;/em> at a holiday party. It was lavishly soft, airy, and decadent; laced with balsamic cream and studded with balsamic-vinegar infused raisin.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The packaging says it uses Carandini&amp;rsquo;s Balsamic Vinegar of Modena IGP. Olivieri&amp;rsquo;s website describes it as follows:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Carandini, one of Modena&amp;rsquo;s oldest families, has been producing hand-crafted balsamic vinegars using traditional family methods since 1641. Their hero expression, the Emilio Balsamic Vinegar of Modena, is a premium, high-density vinegar that contains 60% grape must and strikes a delicate balance between sweet and sour. Exuding a mahogany color and rich perfume, the versatile product lends a subtle acidity and fragrant sweetness to Olivieri&amp;rsquo;s staple Panettone recipe.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>FYI, Carandini&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em>Aceto Balsamico di Modena IGP&lt;/em> (Balsamic Vinegar of Modena) is not a true &lt;em>Aceto Balsamico Tradizionale&lt;/em>, i.e. made from a reduction of pressed Trebbiano and Lambrusco grape that&amp;rsquo;s aged for a minimum of 12 years in a series of wooden barrels of successively smaller sizes. True balsamic vinegar is rich, glossy, deep brown in color, and has a complex flavor that balances the natural sweetness and sourness of cooked grape juice with hints of wood from the casks.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Aceto Balsamico di Modena&lt;/em> is a commercial-grade cheaper imitation of the traditional balsamic vinegar. They can be made from as little as 20% grape must (and not necessarily from Modena or Reggio Emilia), with the addition of wine vinegar, coloring, caramel, and sometimes thickeners like guar gum or corn starch to artificially simulate the sweetness and thickness of the naturally aged &lt;em>Aceto Balsamico Tradizionale di Modena&lt;/em>. IGP status requires a minimum aging period of 2 months (not necessarily in wooden barrels), rising to 3 years when labeled as &lt;em>invecchiato&lt;/em> (aged).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;60% grape must&amp;rdquo; = 40% wine vinegar. Since Carandini&amp;rsquo;s Balsamic Vinegar of Modena has IGP in its label, it&amp;rsquo;s most likely produced in Modena. (For some reason, I&amp;rsquo;ve yet to come across a bottle of balsamic vinegar that&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em>not&lt;/em> made in Modena.)&lt;/p>
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>Dean &amp;amp; DeLuca reminded me of Southern Season, a gourmet specialty food retailer in the Carolinas where I got to taste many fine cheeses and chocolates from around the world. Southern Season filed for Chapter 11 bankruptcy in 2016. It had liabilities of ~$18.9 million compared to ~$9.8 million in assets &amp;ndash; not as outrageous as Dean &amp;amp; DeLuca&amp;rsquo;s debt-to-asset ratio.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/section></content></item></channel></rss>