<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>wisconsin on HERESY LEVAIN</title><link>/tags/wisconsin/</link><description>Latest experiments in wisconsin from HERESY LEVAIN</description><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2023 HERESY LEVAIN 🍞 CC BY-NC-SA 4.0</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 13 Oct 2021 22:33:41 -0600</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/wisconsin/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Squirrels Hoard</title><link>/posts/squirrels-hoard/</link><pubDate>Wed, 13 Oct 2021 22:33:41 -0600</pubDate><guid>/posts/squirrels-hoard/</guid><description>A forager&amp;rsquo;s bread, loaded with wild acorns, black walnuts, and hickory nuts.</description><content>&lt;p>Last few weeks I went on multiple wild food foraging expeditions. It was a blast. Came back with a boatload of pawpaws, acorns, hickory nuts, and black walnuts.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Acorns are not delicious right off the tree, which is likely what started the modern misconception that they are inedible. Acorns are definitely edible. They just require a process called &amp;ldquo;leaching&amp;rdquo; to remove the bitter tannins and become palatable, and all it takes is water and time. The internet has a ton of information on how to do that.&lt;/p>
&lt;div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
&lt;iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/4zyI6vn9Azg" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video">&lt;/iframe>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>Black walnuts are a pain in the butt to process. So I took the whole load to a local hulling station, and paid a small fee (60¢/lb) to have the black walnuts dehulled and cleaned. Just got a big sack of clean and dry whole black walnuts back. All I needed to do was crack the black walnuts and hickory nuts on my vintage metal nut cracker, and pick out the nut meat. A tedious yet meditative activity.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Once the acorns were done leaching and the nuts shelled, I wanted to make a bread to celebrate the beautiful season.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I came up with a Midwest Blend of heritage wheat flours:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>50% Red Fife (Anarchy Acres, WI): a HRSW first grown in Canada in 1842 by farmer David Fife; aka. the OG Canadian Wheat&lt;/li>
&lt;li>30% Turkey Red (Ben Penner Farms, MN): a beautiful HRWW, as &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/the-wheatwalker/">previously demonstrated&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>20% Goldcoin (Anarchy Acres, WI): a SWWW with &amp;lt;10% protein&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>After reading up on acorns, I decided to infuse them into the dough in 3 different ways:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>roasted acorn flour: dehydrate leached acorn meal, grind into a fine flour, and roast slowly in an oven until dark brown and caramelized (but not burnt)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>acorn levain: build a levain with leached wet acorn meal&lt;/li>
&lt;li>cream of acorn: cook leached acorn meal into a porridge, with flaxseeds, poppyseeds, chia seeds, and sunflower seeds&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>So, yeah, a boatload of acorns in this bread. Because, why not?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Formula for the dough:&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>88% extraction Midwest Blend heritage flour&lt;/td>
&lt;td>75%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>roasted acorn flour&lt;/td>
&lt;td>25%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>acorn levain&lt;/td>
&lt;td>40%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>cream of acorn&lt;/td>
&lt;td>30%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>h₂o&lt;/td>
&lt;td>83%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1.5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>hickory nuts, toasted&lt;/td>
&lt;td>7%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>black walnuts, toasted&lt;/td>
&lt;td>7%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>No autolyse. Simply mix everything together and cold-ferment for 44 hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/squirrels-hoard/202110121749.jpg"
alt="forager&amp;#39;s bread"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/squirrels-hoard/202110121750.jpg"
alt="forager&amp;#39;s bread"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/squirrels-hoard/202110121751.jpg"
alt="forager&amp;#39;s bread"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The baked bread took on a beautiful chocolate color with a purplish hue.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/squirrels-hoard/202110121132.jpg"
alt="forager&amp;#39;s bread"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The sweet nutty aroma was absolutely wonderful &amp;ndash; it reminded me of hazelnuts (or even nutella).&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/squirrels-hoard/202110121956.jpg"
alt="forager&amp;#39;s bread"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/squirrels-hoard/202110121957.jpg"
alt="forager&amp;#39;s bread"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The crumb was very moist, tender and custardy, yet still springy like a sponge cake.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It tasted totally different than how it smelt. The bold earthiness of the wild nuts dominated the flavor profile.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/squirrels-hoard/202110121131.jpg"
alt="forager&amp;#39;s bread"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Squirrels Hoard, a forager&amp;rsquo;s dream.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Only a mild sweet nutty flavor from the acorn, and a subtle hint of tang.&lt;/p></content></item></channel></rss>