<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>imperial valley on HERESY LEVAIN</title><link>/tags/imperial-valley/</link><description>Latest experiments in imperial valley from HERESY LEVAIN</description><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2023 HERESY LEVAIN 🍞 CC BY-NC-SA 4.0</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 25 Mar 2023 02:31:32 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/imperial-valley/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>California Dreamin' #7: Desert Gold</title><link>/posts/california-dreamin-7/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Mar 2023 02:31:32 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/california-dreamin-7/</guid><description>[California Grain Adventure #7] &lt;em>Pane Ricco&lt;/em>, a luxuriously high-hydration bread with 100% wholegrain Desert Gold durum, sour cream, cracked black pepper, and salty addictive cheeses.</description><content>&lt;p>&lt;em>This is part 7 of my &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/california-grain-adventure/">California Grain Adventure&lt;/a>.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>The West begins where the average annual rainfall drops below twenty inches.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Bernard DeVoto&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>The Imperial Valley in southern California is often cited as a great example of modern desert agriculture.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>From what I&amp;rsquo;ve seen, the Imperial Valley is a place of jarring contrasts. Half of the valley remains in its natural state, aka. a bone-dry desert with some breathtaking sand dunes; the other half exemplifies a modern engineering marvel &amp;ndash; mile after mile of green fields lined by irrigation canals and sometimes shrouded by showers of water from sprinklers.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-7/california-imperial-valley.jpg"
alt="Map of Imperial Valley, California"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Imperial Valley is one of the oldest farming communities in the Colorado River basin. It lies in the Colorado Desert section of the Sonoran Desert, with overwhelming heat and meager average rainfall (about 3&amp;quot; or 76 mm per year). Dirt was carried here over millions of years by the Colorado River, as it carved the Grand Canyon ever deeper.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Thanks to irrigation &amp;ndash; that is, thanks to the US Bureau of Reclamation &amp;ndash; states such as California, Arizona, and Idaho became populous and wealthy; millions settled in regions where nature, left alone, would have countenanced thousands at best; great valleys and hemispherical basins metamorphosed from desert blonde to semi-tropical green.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Agriculture is the economic backbone of the Imperial Valley due to irrigation, which is supplied entirely from the Colorado River via the All-American Canal. Thousands of acres of prime farmland have transformed the desert into one of the most productive farming regions in California with an annual crop production of over $1 billion. Evidently, agriculture accounts for nearly half of all local employment.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-7/SaltonSeaArielFromSouth.jpg"
alt="Aerial view of Imperial Valley and Salton Sea"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Aerial view of the Imperial Valley and Salton Sea from the south.&lt;/p>&lt;p>Source: &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Imperial_Valley,_California#/media/File:SaltonSeaArielFromSouth.jpg" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">Samboy&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Unlike the Central Valley in the north which draws its water from rain and snow in the Sierra Mountains or pumps it from shrinking underground aquifers, the Imperial Valley has only one source of water: the Colorado River, 80 miles to the east.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The most basic principle governing water use in the western US is &amp;ldquo;first in time, first in right.&amp;rdquo; These lush fields in the Imperial Valley owe their existence to fortune-seeking land speculators and engineers who arrived early and, starting in 1901, dug the first canal to ship water here from the Colorado River. (Prior to the 20th century, this patch was mostly unsettled.) Since most of the Imperial Valley actually lies below sea level &amp;ndash; and well below the canal&amp;rsquo;s starting point on the Colorado River near Yuma, Arizona &amp;ndash; water is able to flow there by gravity alone.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Thanks to the stunning wealth that irrigation farming had produced, California came rolling out of the 1920s like Jay Gatsby in his alabaster phaeton. Agriculture was California; there were no sprawling defense and aerospace industries, no Silicon Valley.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The Salton Sea was an unfortunate consequence of the engineering failure that marked the construction of the original canal. The current canal, built during the New Deal and named the &lt;a href="https://www.iid.com/water/water-transportation-system/colorado-river-facilities/all-american-canal">All-American Canal&lt;/a>, began delivering water to the Imperial Valley in 1940; two years later, it became the sole water source for Imperial Valley&amp;rsquo;s residents and farmlands.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-7/ImperialValleyfromBC.jpg"
alt="The Imperial Valley from the highway between Tijuana and Mexicali"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Looking north at the Imperial Valley, from the highway between Tijuana and Mexicali.&lt;/p>&lt;p>Source: &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Imperial_Valley,_California#/media/File:ImperialValleyfromBC.jpg" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">CharismaticDespot&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Water delivered to the Imperial Irrigation District (IID) each year by the All-American Canal &amp;ndash; through a vast system of canals, dams, and pipelines &amp;ndash; is enough to cover the entire irrigated land, roughly 500,000 acres, with 5 feet of water.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Imported water and a long growing season allow two crop cycles each year; the Imperial Valley now supplies over 2/3 of winter fruits and vegetables, cotton, and grain for domestic and international markets. The valley also produces most of the lamb and sheep in the US. (This raises a bunch of uncomfortable questions: What&amp;rsquo;s the rest of America doing? Why is the whole nation dependent on a few hundred farms concentrated in an irrigated desert for its food? How did this situation come to be? What happened to Eliot Coleman&amp;rsquo;s four-season farming revolution? &amp;hellip; )&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>Alfalfa is the king crop produced in the Imperial Valley. 1 out of every 3 farmed acres in the valley is dedicated to growing alfalfa, which dries into a high-protein hay commonly used as food for livestock. It&amp;rsquo;s also one of the thirstiest drop; its deep roots sucking up water in a region scorched by a 22-year drought.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Another contradiction of California: How does irrigating alfalfa in 120°F temperatures in the dead of July make any sense at all?&lt;/p>
&lt;div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
&lt;iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/AYBZISNYk8I" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video">&lt;/iframe>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>The Imperial Valley&amp;rsquo;s alfalfa industry is not only one of the largest water users in the basin, but also one of the most powerful.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Large-scale production of water-gorging, low-value crops like alfalfa during a megadrought is possible only because the Imperial Valley is the single biggest controller of rights to Colorado River water and the IID farmers have access to cheap (subsidized) water.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Due to these massive irrigation projects, south of the canal, the Colorado River no longer flows above ground at all for much of the year into Mexico.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The Colorado River, which supplies freshwater to more than 40 million people in the southwestern US and northern Mexico, has been in rapid decline. Reduced snowpack, drought conditions and higher average temperatures have all reduced the river&amp;rsquo;s flow in recent decades. The two biggest reservoirs along the river, Lake Mead and Lake Powell, are each creeping towards a &amp;ldquo;dead pool,&amp;rdquo; an ominous sign that the Colorado River could stop flowing entirely.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Agriculture accounts for ~80% of total water consumption in the Colorado River basin, with roughly half of that going towards the production of alfalfa hay, according to a 2020 &lt;a href="https://core.ac.uk/download/pdf/323061602.pdf">study&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
&lt;iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/g-pygL1-yzM" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video">&lt;/iframe>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>What has all this irrigation amounted to?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Massive industrial storehouses line the area, packed with thousands upon thousands of stacks of alfalfa bales ready to be fed to dairy cows &amp;ndash; but not cows in California&amp;rsquo;s Central Valley or Montana&amp;rsquo;s rangelands. Instead, the alfalfa will be fed to cows across the Pacific &amp;ndash; in China, Japan and Korea, and farther away in Saudi Arabia, the United Arab Emirates, etc. An increasing percentage of the alfalfa produced here is exported.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Growers say the reasons boil down to simple economics. The market for alfalfa hay in southern California has shrunk over the years as dairies have closed or moved elsewhere, while demand for dairy products has grown exponentially in other parts of the world. Meanwhile, it costs little to freight goods on the back haul to China, because the US runs a persistently high trade deficit with China; containers from Asia arrive full but often return empty. Some claim it&amp;rsquo;s actually cheaper to ship hay to China than to haul the same load by truck to dairy farms 400 miles north in the San Joaquin Valley.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Brokers regularly fly in from overseas, some staying at a local golf course and country club. Chinese buyers are wined and dined across the border in Mexicali, which has a long-established Chinese community.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>According to a 2015 &lt;a href="https://pacinst.org/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/CA-Ag-Water-Use.pdf">analysis&lt;/a> by the Pacific Institute, alfalfa production in California uses around 5 acre-feet (6,167 cubic meters) of water. In comparison, sugar beets use roughly 3 acre-feet (3,700 cubic meters), and grains as little as 1 acre-foot (1,233 cubic meters).&lt;/p>
&lt;div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
&lt;iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/EE4uMOtqIc8" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video">&lt;/iframe>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>The top water-using activity in California is growing alfalfa. Farmers in Imperial County currently draw more water from the Colorado River than all of Arizona and Nevada combined. An alfalfa farmer can grow alfalfa 10-12 times a year and sell it for $260-$280/ton. These are not the hardworking family farmers of yesteryear. They are giant agribusiness corporations pulling in $1.8 billion from selling 7 million tons of alfalfa every year in California, according to a University of California, Davis study by Daniel Geisseler and William R. Horwath.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This business has been extremely profitable because alfalfa farmers get 3.4 million acre-feet (1 acre foot =325,851 gallons) of water every year for only $35-$60 per acre-foot. The water you get for your house costs you $800 per acre-foot today, and it could be double that in 10 years' time. You could supply the water needs of 40 million people with that 3.4 million acre-feet. It&amp;rsquo;s likely that enough water for greater Los Angeles is being used to raise irrigated pasture for livestock.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Feeding irrigated grass to cows is as wasteful a use of water as you can conceive. Pasture is hydrologically inefficient in the extreme, and, metabolically speaking, so are cows: You need 7-8 feet of water in the hot deserts to keep grass alive, which means that you need ~50,000 pounds of water to raise 1 pound of cow. (Feeding alfalfa to cows requires even more water, but at least alfalfa fixes nitrogen in the soil.)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If the livestock industry earned California any real money, and if cows (unlike avocados or artichokes) couldn&amp;rsquo;t be raised on rainfall in 35 other states, then giving more water to cows than to humans in the nation&amp;rsquo;s richest and most populous state &amp;ndash; a semi-desert state at the mercy of a precarious water supply &amp;ndash; might make a grain or two of sense.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>During the last few years, companies from Saudi Arabia and the United Arab Emirates have established farming operations on thousands of acres around the Imperial Valley and the adjacent Palo Verde Valley.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Saudi Arabian companies are pumping up groundwater from beneath land they have purchased and are using it to grow alfalfa for export to the Middle East. They have no plan for replacing this scarce and finite groundwater that accumulated over thousands of years.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As a matter of fact, foreign corporations have increased purchases of farmland in the US, particularly in the southwest where longstanding laws on water rights give land owners unlimited access to the valuable water underneath the soil.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Why don&amp;rsquo;t they grow their own alfalfa? Because they are short of water and it&amp;rsquo;s so much cheaper to buy from the US.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Growing water-intensive crops in the US and exporting them to water-scarce countries is a form of geo-economic arbitrage, a natural consequence of the globalization of everything. Essentially, water is exported out of the US in the form of crops like alfalfa, rice, or almonds. Guess who is currently one of the largest net exporters of virtual water in the world?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This trend has been accelerating for decades, despite concerns that this &amp;ldquo;virtual water trading&amp;rdquo; is unsustainable in the long term, especially in drought-plagued areas such as California. If California is &lt;em>really&lt;/em> short of water, why are we shipping it to Asia?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>What this means is, ultimately, the US is not in control of its own farmland &amp;ndash; or food production.&lt;/p>
&lt;div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
&lt;iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/QPEN0o5pbA4" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video">&lt;/iframe>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>Some argue the Imperial Valley is doing good by growing food and feeding the country, and point the finger at some desert metropolises such as Las Vegas, which boasts some 50 million visitors each year and wastes way more &lt;a href="https://www.latimes.com/environment/story/2023-01-29/colorado-river-in-crisis-cracking-down-on-grass">water from Colorado River&lt;/a> with its gushing fountains. The truth is, Las Vegas and Reno represent 95% of Nevada&amp;rsquo;s economy but use 10% of its water &amp;ndash; alfalfa growers use most of the rest.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Water overuse is a prisoner&amp;rsquo;s dilemma and a tragedy of the commons. If free-market mechanisms &amp;ndash; which much of western ag publicly applauds and privately abhors &amp;ndash; were actually allowed to work, the West&amp;rsquo;s water &amp;ldquo;shortage&amp;rdquo; would be exposed for what it is: the sort of shortage you expect when inexhaustible demand chases an almost free good. (If someone were selling Porsches for $3,000 apiece, there would be a shortage of those, too.) California has a shortage of water because it has a surfeit of cows &amp;ndash; it&amp;rsquo;s really almost as simple as that.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If history is any guide, the odds that we can sustain a &amp;ldquo;civilization&amp;rdquo; in deserts would have to be regarded as low. Only one desert civilization, out of dozens that grew up in antiquity, has survived uninterrupted into modern times. And Egypt&amp;rsquo;s approach to irrigation was fundamentally different from all the rest.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-7/imperial-valley-google-maps-review.png"
alt="Review of Imperial Valley, California"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>A user review for Imperial County, California (posted on Google Maps)&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h3 id="pane-ricco">pane ricco&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>It just struck me that I should make a &lt;em>pane ricco&lt;/em> (rich bread). I named it as such because in the western US, it&amp;rsquo;s often said that water flows uphill toward money. And it literally does. Water leaps 3,000 feet across the Tehachapi Mountains in gigantic siphons to slay the thirst of Los Angeles, as it&amp;rsquo;s shoved 1,000 feet out of Colorado River canyons to hydrate Phoenix and Palm Springs and the irrigated lands around them. Water is wealth in the West.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-7/20230324_174201.jpg"
alt="pane ricco with Desert Gold durum"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>handmade &lt;em>pane ricco&lt;/em> with wholegrain Desert Gold durum flour&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>This durum dough uses as much water and milk derivatives as it could handle, which, by the West Coast&amp;rsquo;s definition, is rich.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Desert Gold durum flour, 100% extraction&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>400g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>water, divided&lt;/td>
&lt;td>125%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>500g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>whole-milk sour cream&lt;/td>
&lt;td>20%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>80g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>whole durum levain (60% hydration)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>30%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>120g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sea salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>4g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>olive oil&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>40g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>black peppercorns, crushed&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>4g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->cheeses, finely grated&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>40g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>The process is pretty much the same as &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/california-dreamin-4">&lt;em>pan integral de sonora blanca&lt;/em>&lt;/a>. Basically, keep going with &lt;em>bassinage&lt;/em> until the dough became so fragile that it might break down anytime.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I baked the bread on a BBQ grill (again!).&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-7/20230324_174619.jpg"
alt="pane ricco with Desert Gold durum"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>handmade &lt;em>pane ricco&lt;/em> with wholegrain Desert Gold durum flour&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The classic flavor combination of &lt;em>cacio e pepe&lt;/em> never disappoints.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The crust is beautifully caramelized; firm and crisp, with a distinct smokey char.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-7/20230324_173604.jpg"
alt="pane ricco with Desert Gold durum"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>handmade &lt;em>pane ricco&lt;/em> with wholegrain Desert Gold durum flour&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The crumb is light, fluffy, and airy, with distinct honeycomb layers.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-7/20230324_173653.jpg"
alt="pane ricco with Desert Gold durum"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>handmade &lt;em>pane ricco&lt;/em> with wholegrain Desert Gold durum flour&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The texture is soft and tender, yet springy and chewy. The taste reminds me of roasted chickpeas. Black peppercorns provide a interesting texture contrast, and lend a mild spiced kick to the flavor of the crumb. The combination with salty addictive cheeses is mouthwatering.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-7/20230324_175617.jpg"
alt="pane ricco with Desert Gold durum"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>handmade &lt;em>pane ricco&lt;/em> with wholegrain Desert Gold durum flour&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>And this bread toasts like a dream.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="gnocchi">Gnocchi&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>I made a plate of plump sourdough &lt;em>gnocchi&lt;/em> as well, with Desert Gold durum, &lt;em>masa harina&lt;/em>, and Yukon Gold potatoes.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-7/20230324_102531.jpg"
alt="handmade sourdough gnocchi with Desert Gold durum"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>handmade sourdough gnocchi with Yukon Gold potatoes, wholegrain Desert Gold durum flour, and &lt;em>masa harina&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Formula:&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Desert Gold durum flour, 100% extraction&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>50g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;em>masa harina&lt;/em>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>50g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Yukon Gold potatoes, roasted &amp;amp; riced&lt;/td>
&lt;td>80%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>400g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>butter, softened&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>50g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sourdough discard&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>50g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>These fork-sized orbs were sauced with garlicky sun-dried tomatoes, topped with fresh basil leaves and shaved parmigiano-reggiano.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I could eat this every day and be happy.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-7/20230324_194435.jpg"
alt="handmade potato gnocchi with Desert Gold durum sauced"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>handmade sourdough gnocchi, served with sun-dried tomatoes, fresh basil, and shaved parmigiano-reggiano&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>&lt;code>Note&lt;/code>:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Kamut (khorasan) wheat is actually very close to durum, just a larger grain size. If you can&amp;rsquo;t get durum, try kamut.&lt;/p>
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>I used equal amounts of Parmigiano-Reggiano Stravecchio (aged for 5 years), Gruyère Vieux (aged for 18 months), and Pecorino Romano (aged for 12 months).&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/section></content></item></channel></rss>