<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>brettanomyces on HERESY LEVAIN</title><link>/tags/brettanomyces/</link><description>Latest experiments in brettanomyces from HERESY LEVAIN</description><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2023 HERESY LEVAIN 🍞 CC BY-NC-SA 4.0</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 16 Apr 2023 15:55:25 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/brettanomyces/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>levure de bière #3: Lactobacillus + Kveiks + Brettanomyces</title><link>/posts/byb-3/</link><pubDate>Sun, 16 Apr 2023 15:55:25 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/byb-3/</guid><description>&lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em> reincarnated as a wholegrain bread. A mightily aromatic and tasty scald with craft malts. Sequential mixed-fermentation with cultures from Imperial Yeast: A44 Kveiking, W25 Lacto Brevis, and W15 Suburban Brett.</description><content>&lt;p>&lt;em>Beer = liquid bread. Want to stay updated on my &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/craft-beer-yeast">craft beer yeast bread-plays&lt;/a>? Subscribe to the &lt;a href="https://tinyletter.com/breadbuster">newsletter&lt;/a>!&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>One of my all-time favorite beer styles is &lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em> (German: &lt;em>Berliner Weiße&lt;/em>), a deliciously tart wheat beer that originated in the region around Berlin, Germany and developed gradually from the 17th to the 20th century. A popular story has it that in 1809, Napoleon and his troops celebrated their Prussian victory with &lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em>; the soldiers described the beer as sweet and tart, strong and effervescent, and dubbed it &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->&amp;ldquo;the Champagne of the North.&amp;quot;&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em> is defined by its mouth-watering sour tang &amp;ndash; slightly less sour than a &lt;em>gueuze&lt;/em>, and not as funky or vinous. A great &lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em> is complex but straightforward, acidic but infinitely enjoyable. It&amp;rsquo;s malty but dry, crisp, refreshing, and light &amp;ndash; rarely with oakiness, hoppiness, tannins, or acetic flavors.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Whereas &lt;em>weissbier&lt;/em> makes the drinker monosyllabic, reserved, and retiring, the Bavarian brewings open his heart and let loose his tongue.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Henry Vizetelly&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>The origins of &lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em> are hazy at best. Along with its sour cousin, Leipziger &lt;em>gose&lt;/em>, the wheat ale hearkens back to a time when brewers in northern Germany lived by their own rules. Literally. The area evaded the Bavarian &amp;ldquo;beer purity&amp;rdquo; laws known as &lt;em>Reinheitsgebot&lt;/em> for centuries, allowing brewers to create funky, sour ales that resemble Belgian styles more than those of the Rhineland.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Weisse&lt;/em> in German means &amp;ldquo;wheat&amp;rdquo;, and &lt;em>weissbier&lt;/em> is usually translated into English as &amp;ldquo;wheat beer&amp;rdquo;, which includes a faulty assumption that there is usually a heavy component of wheat in the malt bill. Like the famous &lt;em>witbiers&lt;/em> (&amp;ldquo;white beers&amp;rdquo;) of Belgium, &lt;em>weisse&lt;/em> also means &amp;ldquo;white.&amp;rdquo; That is, &lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em> is traditionally brewed from air-dried rather than kiln-dried malt.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-3/Friedies-berliner-weisse.jpg"
alt="Friedies Berliner Weisse"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Friedies &lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em>&lt;/p>&lt;p>Source: &lt;a href="https://friediesbrauhaus.blog/berliner-weisse-das-ergebnis/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">Friedies Brauhaus&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>There are several competing theories surrounding the development of the style. One theory holds that the French Huguenot refugees, who fled to Berlin in the 17th and early 18th centuries, developed the beer after migrating through Flanders and picking up techniques from brewers of Flanders brown and red ales. There is little hard evidence supporting this theory, although the Landré family, who were prominent &lt;em>weissbier&lt;/em> brewers and had factories at &lt;em>Stralauer Straße&lt;/em> 36/37 and &lt;em>Münzstraße&lt;/em> 3, were French-born Huguenots. But the Landrés didn&amp;rsquo;t come to Berlin until &lt;a href="https://www.hugenottenmuseum-berlin.de/sammlung/objekt-des-monats/jubilaeumskelch-der-weissbierbrauerei-landre-1885">the second half of the 18th century&lt;/a>, and Charles Fréderic Edouard Landré didn&amp;rsquo;t acquire the wheat beer brewery at &lt;em>Stralauer Straße&lt;/em> 36/37, which was founded in 1780, until 1835. It seems rather late, given the brewing of &lt;em>weissbier&lt;/em> in northern Germany predates the 1600s.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Another theory points to an improvement of a beer called &lt;em>Halberstädter Broihan&lt;/em>, a &lt;em>weissbier&lt;/em> that was first developed by the brewer Cord Broihan in the 16th century and became incredibly popular across northern Germany for several centuries. A Hanover native, Broihan returned to his homeland in 1526 after a stay in Hamburg, and tried to copy the then-popular Hamburg beer, but failed. So he invented a wheat beer that soon became fashionable. Berlin brewers succeeded in further developing the recipe and brewing a wheat beer that tasted better and was more digestible. The &lt;em>Berlinische Weitzenbier&lt;/em> was born; it was praised by the Berlin doctor J. S. Elsholz as early as 1642. It was officially mentioned for the first time in a 1680 document.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The Bohemian military leader and statesman Albrecht von Wallenstein reportedly appreciated the white beer. However, during the turmoil of the Thirty Years' War (1618-1648), wheat was in short supply. The situation in the &lt;em>Mark Brandenburg&lt;/em> was so dire that Wallenstein complained bitterly in a letter to his subordinate Arnim von Boitzenburg, &amp;ldquo;&amp;hellip;&lt;em>dahero denn nicht weiß, wie den Durst löschen muss, dieweil ich das Gerstenbier nicht trinken kann&lt;/em>&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo; (&amp;rdquo;&amp;hellip;so I don&amp;rsquo;t know how to quench my thirst, since I can&amp;rsquo;t drink the barley beer&amp;hellip;&amp;quot;)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>19th-century Berliners no longer had this problem. By the late 18th century, &lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em> seemed to have emerged as a distinct style of its own, and became available at all times and practically everywhere. &lt;a href="https://barclayperkins.blogspot.com/2015/03/berliner-weissbier-breweries-in-1890s.html">Specialty &lt;em>weissbier&lt;/em> breweries&lt;/a> such as Landré on &lt;em>Stralauer Straße&lt;/em>, Breithaupt on &lt;em>Palisadenstraße&lt;/em>, and &lt;a href="https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wei%C3%9Fbierbrauerei_Willner">Willner&lt;/a> in Pankow brewed excellent beer.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>From the late 1850s to 1870s, however, &lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em> fell out of favor &amp;ndash; so much so that an English publisher named Henry Vizetelly predicted in 1859, &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->&amp;ldquo;Ten years hence and guide-books will describe [&lt;em>weissbier&lt;/em>] with the same reverence as the Colosseum in Rome, or the Palace of the Doges in Venice. Ten years later there will be a case in the Berlin Museum containing the mysterious goblets, representing a &amp;lsquo;white or a half white,&amp;rsquo; and the so-called &amp;lsquo;cool blonde.'&amp;quot;&lt;sup id="fnref:2">&lt;a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A revival did ensue. In 1879, Vizetelly paid homage to the &amp;ldquo;&lt;em>kühle blonde&lt;/em>&amp;rdquo; in &lt;em>Berlin Under the New Empire&lt;/em>, describing in detail its place in a Berliner&amp;rsquo;s life.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>In front of everyone stood a gigantic tumbler which could have been fitted with ease upon any ordinary head, and which contained a liquid pale and clear as Rhine wine, surmounted by a huge crown of froth not unlike a prize cauliflower. This was the famous &amp;ldquo;weiss,&amp;rdquo; the mere mention of which suffices to send a Berliner into raptures and into the mysteries of which I was about to be initiated. &amp;hellip; [Berlin was] the city where the &lt;em>kühle blonde&lt;/em> is obtained in the greatest perfection and where &lt;em>bier-stuben&lt;/em> offering no other beverage to their frequenters abound. The beer is drunk by preference when it is of a certain age, and in perfection it should be largely impregnated with carbonic acid gas and have acquired a peculiar sharp, dry, and by no means disagreeable flavor.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>The modern &lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em> developed relatively late, towards the end of the 19th century. Shortly after the turn of the 20th century, &lt;em>weißbier-stuben&lt;/em> (wheat beer bars) mushroomed all over Berlin. At the height of its popularity, &lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em> was the most popular alcoholic drink in Berlin, with &lt;a href="https://barclayperkins.blogspot.com/2015/03/berliner-weissbier-breweries-in-1890s.html">dozens of breweries&lt;/a> producing it.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-3/Crabtree-berliner-weisse.jpg"
alt="Crabtree Berliner Weisse"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em> by Crabtree Brewing Company (Colorado, US)&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>History suggests that wheat beers brewed around Berlin were not originally sour (i.e. not any different from those brewed in Hamburg or Nürnberg), but rather light and easy to drink compared to the heavier &lt;em>braunbier&lt;/em> (brown beer). Most of the &lt;em>weissbiers&lt;/em> were about 3% ABV and used a mash of at least 50% wheat. Interestingly, the wort was not boiled and the amount of hops used was minimal. The hops were typically not added in the kettle, but blended into the mash as a separate boiled infusion to increase the mash temperature.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Since the wort wasn&amp;rsquo;t sterilized, you can easily imagine the enormous diversity of microorganisms that survived into the cooled wort. Thus, it was crucial to start the fermentation as quickly as possible to suppress most of the spoilage microorganisms. Even so, heat-tolerant lactic acid bacteria (LAB) survived and synergistically fermented the worts into beers with a dry and lightly acidic character. This was not true spontaneous fermentation as carried out in &lt;em>lambics&lt;/em> &amp;ndash; yeast was pitched, but carried both yeast and bacteria from previous fermentations.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A. F. Zimmermann wrote in &lt;em>Der Bier-Brauer als Meister in seinem Fache&lt;/em> (1842), &amp;ldquo;all wheat beers, especially in the summer, easily turn sour and sometimes even sour during the brewing process.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Other microorganisms survived wort production, too; malts have plenty of their own LAB, for instance. Fermentation took place in wood, which is porous and thus difficult to sanitize.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Therefore, there are 3 production stages where acidification could have taken place:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>During mashing: if the mash stood too long, especially at room temperatures&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>During fermentation: primarily caused by yeast cross-contaminations&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>During storage: mainly caused by microflora in the storage vessels&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>The result was a range of beers with vastly differing levels of acidity. Although acidity was not uncommon in beers of the 17th-18th centuries, the variability of the beer meant that it often failed to meet consumers&amp;rsquo; expectations.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Both J. G. Krünitz (in &lt;em>Oekonomische Encyklopädie&lt;/em>, published in 1773) and &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->Johann Samuel Halle&lt;sup id="fnref:3">&lt;a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">3&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --> described the brewing process used in the second half of the 18th century, both indicating production was brewery-specific. For example, Halle offered a recipe made with equal parts of barley and wheat malts, while Krünitz provided one with 2/3 wheat and 1/3 barley. Such differences continued until only two breweries made the beer at the beginning of the 21st century &amp;ndash; and until they merged, &lt;em>Berliner Kindl&lt;/em> and &lt;em>Schultheiss&lt;/em> followed very different brewing processes.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Krünitz also wrote about how some of the distinctive features of the style&amp;rsquo;s brewing methods had already appeared by the 1770s:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>A decoction method, in which Berlin brewers pulled off the thinnest portion of a mash from the top, brought it to a boil, and then added hops to the decoction. The remaining wort was never boiled. This was an important technique. LAB is very sensitive to hops and could easily be killed by over-hopping. This is not a problem &amp;ndash; in fact, a blessing &amp;ndash; when brewing most styles. But &lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em> relies on &lt;em>lactobacilli&lt;/em> to acquire its trademark sour note. Over the years, brewers have used several techniques to get around this problem. To this day, the brewers of &lt;em>Berliner Kindl Weisse&lt;/em> split the wort, leave half raw, and add hops to only the other half.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Some of the wort was drawn off before cooling and pitched with yeast. By the time the rest of the wort had cooled, this yeasted portion would already be fermenting, and pitched into the main body of wort.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>Franz Schönfeld pointed out in his 1902 book, &lt;em>Die Herstellung obergähriger Biere&lt;/em>:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>In the early decades of the 19th century, &lt;em>Berlin Weissbier&lt;/em> brewers regularly refreshed their yeast with fresh &lt;em>Bitterbier&lt;/em> yeast brought in from &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cottbus">Cottbus&lt;/a>. If they kept re-pitching harvested yeast, their beer would get too sour.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Only in the 1830s or 1840s did brewers begin using mixed cultures that could be safely re-pitched without needing to be periodically refreshed.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>After World War II, the style started to wane again. Even though it&amp;rsquo;s protected under &lt;em>appellation d&amp;rsquo;origine contrôlée&lt;/em> (AOC) within Europe &amp;ndash; no beer produced outside Berlin can carry the name &amp;ndash; &lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em> no longer enjoys the popularity that it once did in its home city. The Berlin tradition has sadly slipped through the cracks and remained in a very mournful state, hanging on by a thin thread.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-3/450-berliner-weisse.jpg"
alt="450 North Brewing Slushy Blueberry Dessert Berliner Weisse"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Slushy Blueberry Dessert &lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em> by 450 North Brewing (Indiana, US)&lt;/p>&lt;p>Source: &lt;a href="https://www.craftbeerjoe.com" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">Craft Beer Joe&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The consolidated &lt;em>Berliner-Kindl-Schultheiss-Brauerei&lt;/em> (now part of the massive Radeberger Gruppe), the last brewery in Berlin producing &lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em>, and therefore the last brewery on Earth that may use the appellation, does not even feature the historic beer during its brewery tours. The ubiquitous brand it produces, &lt;em>Berliner Kindl Weisse&lt;/em>, has such a sharp, one-dimensional, lactic sourness that it&amp;rsquo;s hard to drink without those colorful sugar syrups.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The few commercial breweries that still produce &lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em> no longer use a yeast/bacterial blend to co-ferment the beer; the bacterial fermentation is conducted separately from the yeast fermentation, and the beer is blended to achieve a pre-defined acidity. Beers produced this way are very pale, slightly hazy, and effervescent, with a light tang. They are refreshing oddities, but show little complexity.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>Like any beer style that has been around for more than 5 minutes, &lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em> has gone through several transformations, adapting to technological, political and social changes along the way.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>One of my biggest qualms about beers labeled as &lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em> on the market is that they are often too light and &lt;a href="https://barclayperkins.blogspot.com/2017/10/how-sour-was-berliner-weisse.html">not sour enough&lt;/a> for me. I&amp;rsquo;d like to amp up the flavor.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Here&amp;rsquo;s my journey of making a &lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em>-inspired bread from scratch, in the melting pot that is America.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Size: one 9&amp;rdquo; x 4&amp;quot; loaf&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-3/20230415_143916.jpg"
alt="Berliner Weisse bread sliced"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em> bread, sliced.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;h3 id="scald-2h--100-105f-2h--109-114f-4h--150-155f">Scald (2h @ 100-105°F, 2h @ 109-114°F, 4h @ 150-155°F)&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>These days, everyone tells you that &lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em> is brewed with 50% wheat malt and 50% pilsener malt.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>From the beginning, Berlin&amp;rsquo;s brewers sought to keep the beer as white as possible, and used air-dried or lightly kilned wheat. The grist varied throughout history:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://barclayperkins.blogspot.com/2022/06/lets-breew-1834-berliner-weisse.html">75% smoked wheat + 25% lager&lt;/a> in 1834&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://barclayperkins.blogspot.com/2022/06/brewing-berliner-weisse-in-1840s.html">83.3% wheat + 16.7% barley&lt;/a> in 1842&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://barclayperkins.blogspot.com/2022/06/another-way-of-mashing-berliner-weisse.html">87.5% wheat + 12.5% barley&lt;/a> in 1845&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://barclayperkins.blogspot.com/2022/06/lets-brew-wednesday-1907-berliner.html">75% wheat + 25% lager&lt;/a> in 1907&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Benedikt Koch has an interesting &lt;a href="https://wilder-wald.com/2017/12/08/historic-berliner-weisse-homebrew-recipe/">recipe&lt;/a> for a historically accurate version; it uses 70% wheat malt and 30% pilsner malt to create &amp;ldquo;enough mouthfeel and doughiness from the wheat.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>My focus wasn&amp;rsquo;t on historic accuracy, but on how to play yeasts, bacteria, and grains off each other to create a balanced, tasty bread that has a similar flavor profile to &lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Total dry malts: 200g&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;em>Ölandsvete&lt;/em> wheat malt (Root Shoot Malting, Colorado)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>70%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>140g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->diastatic barley malt&lt;sup id="fnref:4">&lt;a href="#fn:4" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">4&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->(sun-dried Chevallier)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>20%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>40g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>honey malt (Root Shoot Malting, Colorado)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>rye malt (Root Shoot Malting, Colorado)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>boiled water (from cooking pasta), cooled off to ~120°F&lt;/td>
&lt;td>140%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>280g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Process&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Grind the malts, individually or collectively, into a flour. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t have to be super fine.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Place all the malt flours in a bowl or small saucepan; pour the hot pasta water (aka. liquid gold) in 2-3 increments, stirring constantly. It should have the consistency of a slightly thick porridge.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Hold the mash at&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>100-105°F for 2 hour (to help phytase break down phytin molecules and release phytic acid which lowers the mash pH);&lt;/li>
&lt;li>109-114°F for 2 hours (to help maximize the release of ferulic acid, which is a precursor to 4-vinyl-guaiacol, a molecule that&amp;rsquo;s credited with giving off a clove-like aroma);&lt;/li>
&lt;li>raise the temperature to 150-155°F and hold for 4 hours (to saccharify).&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>The mash tasted mightily malty and sweet after 8 hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Total: 480g (to be split into 400g and 80g)&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-3/20230413_151535.jpg"
alt="craft malts from Root Shoot Malting"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>craft malts from Root Shoot Malting (Colorado): Bono rye, &lt;em>Ölandsvete&lt;/em> wheat, and honey malt.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;h3 id="thermophilic-sour-lactobacillus-brevis-24h--100-95f">Thermophilic sour: &lt;em>Lactobacillus brevis&lt;/em> (24h @ 100-95°F)&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Breweries are split between their methods in souring &lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em>. On one side, there are kettle-soured proponents; on the other, you have the staunch traditionalists.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Kettle souring allows for a quick turn-around and eliminates a brewery&amp;rsquo;s concern for cross-contamination. Souring bacteria need a special cleaning procedure, so some brewers prefer the kettle sour technique to lower this risk. Most American breweries use this technique for brewing &lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em>, because it&amp;rsquo;s fast, simple, and consistent.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The traditional brewing method is to co-ferment with &lt;em>lactobacilli&lt;/em> and yeast to make a more expressive flavor profile. This takes longer and requires dedicated sour beer fermenters.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I do what works for me in my home lab. And I&amp;rsquo;m going to combine the method that Krünitz mentioned in his 1773 book with Otto Francke&amp;rsquo;s method of souring patented in 1908.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Important Question for Breweries which produce Acid Beers of the Type of Berlin &amp;ldquo;Weiss&amp;rdquo; Beer. O. Francke (&lt;em>Wochensch. Brau.&lt;/em>, 1907, 24, 621-624). — &amp;ldquo;Weiss&amp;rdquo; beer is prepared by fermenting wort with yeast and lactic acid bacteria. It is a very difficult matter, however, to acclimatise a mixture of lactic acid bacteria and pure yeast in constant proportions. The author recommends a process (which has been employed for two years with very satisfactory results) in which the lactic acid and yeast fermentations are carried out separately. The wort, as it runs off from the spent grains, is subjected to the action of pure culture lactic acid bacteria until the required degree of acidity is attained. The wort is then boiled, cooled, and fermented with pure culture yeast. The beer thus prepared has a pleasant acid taste, and does not require the aid of certain non-slime forming pediococci (see this Journal, 1907, 13, 626-630) to impart a pleasant flavour to it. If a mature, vinous &amp;ldquo;Weiss&amp;rdquo; beer is required, it is only necessary to treat the lactic acid-containing wort with ordinary bacteria-containing &amp;ldquo;Weiss&amp;rdquo; beer yeast. The presence of the lactic acid protects the fermenting wort against the attack of dangerous pediococci, and the beer acquires a sound, vinous taste. The beer prepared by the first method (i.e., that in which the lactic acid fermentation is followed by a pure yeast fermentation) only requires a short period of storage before it is ready for consumption. For the lactic acidification, the author employs distillery culture lactic acid bacillus &lt;em>Delbrücki&lt;/em>, and for the alcoholic fermentation, top-fermentation pure yeast, Race B (high attenuating).&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;em>Journal of the Institute of Brewing&lt;/em>, Volume 14, Issue 2, 1908, pages 196-197&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>I drew off 80g of the scald and inoculated with yeast (see &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/byb-3/#barm-kveiks-8h--100-95f">barm&lt;/a>), while souring the rest 400g.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Let the saccharified scald cool off to ~110°F.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>saccharified scald&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>400g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Lacto Brevis (Imperial Yeast, Oregon)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>8g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>I could let the scald ferment spontaneously over the course of a few days to develop a harmony of lactic acid, like Berliners did a few hundred years ago. But I opted to lacto-ferment the scald with a thermophilic culture, e.g. &lt;em>Lactobacillus delbrückii subsp. bulgaricus&lt;/em>, to build a particular aroma and tart-sweet taste. I have a homemade thermophilic starter (containing multiple wild &lt;em>Lactobacillus&lt;/em> strains) that easily achieves this goal, or I can take a shortcut by using a Bulgarian yogurt that contains &amp;ldquo;live and active cultures.&amp;rdquo; (IIRC, the &lt;a href="https://www.poilane.com/en/products/poilane-the-secrets-of-the-world-famous-bread-bakery-par-apollonia-poilane">&lt;em>Poilâne&lt;/em>&lt;/a> book has a recipe for a 2-day levain that uses yogurt.)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This time, I wanted to try acidifying the scald with a strain of &lt;em>Lactobacillus brevis&lt;/em> from &lt;a href="https://www.imperialyeast.com/organic-yeast-strains/yeast-types/wild-sour/lacto-brevis/">Imperial Yeast&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Lacto Brevis is a great strain for souring wort in the kettle or fermenter, prior to adding yeast for fermentation.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>I recall reading somewhere that &lt;em>Lactobacillus brevis&lt;/em> typically produces more lactic acid than strains like &lt;em>Lactobacillus delbrückii&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Thermophilic cultures love and thrive off heat. Unless you plan to ferment outdoors in the thick of summer in Arizona, you generally need some setup (yogurt maker or crockpot) to keep the heat consistent.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Other LAB strains you could consider, instead of &lt;em>Lactobacillus brevis&lt;/em>:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;em>Lactobacillus delbrückii&lt;/em>: The species name &lt;em>delbrückii&lt;/em> came from Max Delbrück, a Berlin native and a founder of microbiology, who characterized bacteria in the sour beers of Berlin in the 1930s.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;em>Lactobacillus helveticus&lt;/em>: a primary culture used in the manufacturing of hard and extra-hard Italian and Swiss cheeses.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;em>Lactobacillus acidophilus&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;em>Lactobacillus lactis&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;em>Lactobacillus plantarum&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;em>Lactobacillus paracasei&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;em>Streptococcus salivarius subsp. thermophilus&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;em>Pediococcus pentosaceus&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Regardless of which strain you use, any of them, to an extent, has a positive effect on the aroma and taste of the bread.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I added 9.6g of &lt;a href="https://www.imperialyeast.com/organic-yeast-strains/yeast-types/wild-sour/lacto-brevis/">Lacto Brevis&lt;/a> to the scald as an inoculation medium, and mixed it in evenly. Then I covered the mixture with a plastic wrap, pressing down to remove as much oxygen as possible. Keep in mind that liquid yeast cultures from different labs have different concentrations; adjust inoculation percentage accordingly.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I typically hold the thermophilic stage at 110-120°F, but Imperial Yeast recommends a temperature range of 100-85°F for Lacto Brevis (&lt;a href="https://www.whitelabs.com/news-update-detail?id=45&amp;amp;type=NEWS">White Labs&lt;/a> has also shown that &lt;em>Lactobacillus brevis&lt;/em> struggles with lactic acid production at &amp;gt;107°F), so I left the scald to sour for 24 hours at 100-95°F.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>After 24 hours, the scald showed little activity, which is probably a good sign. Pure cultures of &lt;em>Lactobacillus&lt;/em> &lt;a href="https://www.milkthefunk.com/wiki/Lactobacillus">cannot fully ferment wort&lt;/a>. If it starts bubbling and producing CO₂ visibly, then it&amp;rsquo;s likely cross-contaminated with yeast. Thomas Hübbe, in his 2016 master thesis &amp;ldquo;effect of mixed cultures on microbiological development in &lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em>&amp;rdquo;, supports that &lt;em>Lactobacillus&lt;/em> attenuates &amp;lt;10% of the sugars in wort.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The scald smelled neutral (no funky, phenolic aroma), and tasted mildly tart and sweet. I thought that was a sweet spot &amp;ndash; I didn&amp;rsquo;t want the thermophilic souring to go too far or have a very low pH that could disrupt the yeast&amp;rsquo;s fermentation. The scald will develop its maximal character later from other cultures.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Total: 408g&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="barm-kveiks-8h--100-95f">Barm: Kveiks (8h @ 100-95°F)&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>About 2/3 of the way through the thermophilic sour, I made a barm with a blend of kveik ale yeasts.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>saccharified scald&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>80g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>A44 Kveiking (Imperial Yeast, Oregon)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>0.5%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>0.4g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>I used Imperial Yeast&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href="https://www.imperialyeast.com/organic-yeast-strains/yeast-types/ale/kveiking/">A44 Kveiking&lt;/a>, a blend of 3 kveik strains that &amp;ldquo;thrives in hot fermentations when big complex ester profiles are desired&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;can produce an insane amount of pineapple, guava and other exotic tropical fruit aromas.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Typically, one would use a neutral German or European ale yeast to ferment a &lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em>, so the resulting flavors won&amp;rsquo;t contradict each other. But this Kveiking&amp;rsquo;s ester profile happens to match the tropical tart sweetness of Root Shoot&amp;rsquo;s honey malt. It would be really nice if the former could accentuate the latter.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>The Kveiking blend also works well when fermenting kettle soured worts for a strong tropical fruit character.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>As with other kveiks, a little bit goes a long way. A low pitch rate (e.g. on the dangerous edge of underpitching), coupled with a continuously high fermentation temperature, can drive these aromatics even higher.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Kveiking has an attenuation rate of 75-85% and low flocculation. Imperial Yeast recommends a temperature range of 97-75°F for Kveiking. So I mixed in 0.4g of the liquid yeast (adjust the inoculation percentage accordingly based on concentration), gave it a vigorous mix, and let the barm ferment at 100-95°F (same temperatures as Lacto Brevis) for 8 hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The barm already doubled in volume after 6 hours. The surface was very bubbly. I stirred it back down, and let it ripen for another 2 hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>When fully ripe, the barm smelled faintly beery and mildly alcoholic, with some fruity notes. It tasted explosively flavorful, like a pineapple-based tropical fruit punch infused with guava, persimmon, and cinnamon apple!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Maybe the intrigue of &lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em> comes from what the yeast does in an acidic environment: It comes up with some fun cider, &lt;em>sauvignon blanc&lt;/em>, passion fruit, funky tropical-ness &amp;ndash; which makes this style &lt;em>uber&lt;/em> interesting.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Total: 80.4g&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="mesophilic-sour-3h--95-85f-3h--85-75f">Mesophilic sour (3h @ 95-85°F, 3h @ 85-75°F)&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Once the barm and the thermophilic sour were both done with their respective fermentation, I proceeded to the mesophilic phase.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Step 1&lt;/strong>: 3h @ 95-85°F&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I dropped 40% (32g) of the ripened barm to the surface of the thermophilic sour, did &lt;em>not&lt;/em> mix at all, and just left it to open-ferment at falling temperatures from 95°F to 85°F for 3 hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In this temperature range, &lt;em>Lactobacillus brevis&lt;/em> continues to work, acidifying the scald further. The barm begins yeast fermentation of the soured scald.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>After 2 hours, I began to notice some very active bubbling (CO₂) on the surface where the barm was dropped.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Step 2&lt;/strong>: 3h @ 85-75°F&lt;/p>
&lt;p>After 3 hours, I added the remainder of the barm, gave it a thorough mix, and left it to open-ferment at 85-75°F for another 3 hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In this temperature range, yeast fermentation continues. &lt;em>Lactobacillus brevis&lt;/em> should show reduced activity or even become dormant in this temperature range.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Total: 488.4g&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="complex-sour-brettanomyces-bruxellensis-24h--70-60f">Complex sour: &lt;em>Brettanomyces bruxellensis&lt;/em> (24h @ 70-60°F)&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>It was not until the second half of the 20th century that brewing scientists identified &lt;em>Brettanomyces&lt;/em> in &lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em>. F. J. Methner&amp;rsquo;s 1987 thesis on &lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em> showed that the mixed pitching cultures contained &lt;em>Brettanomyces&lt;/em> and a second variety passed on through brewery equipment. The slow-acting strains affected flavor and aroma only in bottles that were cellared for a long time.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Over the last few years, a number of people (e.g. &lt;a href="https://escarpmentlabs.com/en-us/blogs/resources/tales-from-the-lab">Richard Preiss&lt;/a> of Escarpment Labs) have isolated &lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em> &lt;em>Brettanomyces&lt;/em> strains out of old bottles and even kept some of them alive. Brewing with &lt;a href="https://schneeeule.berlin/en/portfolio/marlene-en/">historical strains&lt;/a> must be fun!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Funk and &lt;em>Brettanomyces&lt;/em>-derived flavors are not required in modern &lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em>. Since I&amp;rsquo;m a hopeless fan of funk, I had to seek out some &lt;em>Brettanomyces&lt;/em> and added a little bit during the tertiary fermentation to accentuate the bread&amp;rsquo;s complexity. IMO, the main function of &lt;em>Brettanomyces&lt;/em> in &lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em> is to transform lactic and acetic acid to ethyl lactate and ethyl acetate.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-3/Brettanomyces-wheel.jpg"
alt="Brettanomyces aroma/flavor wheel"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Brettanomyces aroma/flavor wheel, showing the major metabolic pathways, enzymes, and metabolites produced by different &lt;em>Brettanomyces&lt;/em> strains during beer fermentation. The data suggest that &lt;em>Brettanomyces&lt;/em>, especially &lt;em>B. bruxellensis&lt;/em>, is capable of producing large amounts of acetate and medium-chain fatty acid esters including ethyl acetate, ethyl lactate, isoamyl acetate and phenethyl acetate, which are mainly found in lambic beers and American coolship ales.&lt;/p>&lt;p>Source: &lt;a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1002/jib.580" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">&amp;lsquo;Molecular and biochemical aspects of &lt;em>Brettanomyces&lt;/em> in brewing&amp;rsquo; (2019)&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Keep in mind, though, too much &lt;em>Brettanomyces&lt;/em> can throw a &lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em> off balance, and detract from its inherent thirst-quenching character. Great funky beers/breads are balanced and fresh-tasting.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>mesophilic sour&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>488.4g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>W15 Suburban Brett (Imperial Yeast, Oregon)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>I added 5g (about 1% of total scald weight thus far) of Imperial Yeast&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href="https://www.imperialyeast.com/organic-yeast-strains/yeast-types/wild-sour/suburban-brett/">Suburban Brett&lt;/a> to the finished mesophilic sour. This &lt;em>Brettanomyces bruxellensis&lt;/em> strain is said to produce &amp;ldquo;complex and balanced aromas of sour cherry, dried fruit and balanced by a unique tropical fruit profile.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>According to &lt;a href="https://www.milkthefunk.com/wiki/Brettanomyces">Milk The Funk wiki page on Brettanomyces&lt;/a>:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>If pitched into a beer that has already been fermented by &lt;em>Saccharomyces&lt;/em> or if co-pitched with &lt;em>Saccharomyces&lt;/em>, a wider range of flavors including the funkier flavors can be produced by changing some of the flavor compounds produced during the &lt;em>Saccharomyces&lt;/em> fermentation into other flavor compounds, although &lt;em>Brettanomyces&lt;/em> can also produce funky phenols on its own (&lt;em>de novo&lt;/em>) without phenolic precursors produced from &lt;em>Saccharomyces&lt;/em>. A small cell count of &lt;em>Brettanomyces&lt;/em> is plenty for creating these flavors if pitched after and co-pitched with &lt;em>Saccharomyces&lt;/em>, and normally a starter is not necessary unless pitching &lt;em>Brettanomyces&lt;/em> as the primary fermenter.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Imperial Yeast recommends a temperature range of 74-64°F for this &lt;em>Brettanomyces bruxellensis&lt;/em> strain, so I let it ferment (loosely covered) at 70-60°F for 24 hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>At these cooler temperatures, kveiks slow down and sit quietly in the background (e.g. lower attenuation and less fruity esters), while &lt;em>Brettanomyces&lt;/em> shines.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>When done, the mash became incredibly lively. It had an intensely fruity aroma and flavor that reminded me of pineapple, guava, passion fruit, tamarind, and even the Swedish mesophilic yogurt, &lt;em>filmjölk&lt;/em>! Not one-dimensionally sour, but deeply tropical with a complex sweet tartness. Unbelievably tasty.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Brettanomyces&lt;/em> certainly contributed a different touch of tartness than &lt;em>Lactobacillus brevis&lt;/em>; they complemented each other well in this barm. &lt;em>Brettanomyces&lt;/em> can be funky / fruity and tart, but not sour.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Total: 493.4g&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-3/20230414_135809.jpg"
alt="complex sour after 60&amp;#43; hours"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>the complex sour: incredibly lively, aromatic, and tasty!&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>By now, the scald has gone through &lt;strong>all of the fermentation phases&lt;/strong> that would normally take place in an 18th- or 19th-century &lt;em>weissbierbrauerei&lt;/em>:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>155-150°F: saccharification&lt;/li>
&lt;li>100-95°F: thermophilic LAB fermentation&lt;/li>
&lt;li>95-85°F: mesophilic LAB and &lt;em>Saccharomyces&lt;/em> yeast fermentation&lt;/li>
&lt;li>85-75°F: &lt;em>Saccharomyces&lt;/em> yeast fermentation&lt;/li>
&lt;li>70-60°F: &lt;em>Brettanomyces&lt;/em> yeast fermentation&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-3/20230414_135906.jpg"
alt="complex sour"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>The 62-hour sour, after going through all of the fermentation phases that would normally take place in an 18th- or 19th-century &lt;em>weissbierbrauerei&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;h3 id="final-dough--35h--68f">Final dough (3.5h @ ~68°F)&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Total wholegrain flour: 350g&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Turkey Red wheat flour, 100% extraction&lt;/td>
&lt;td>80%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>280g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>oat flour, 100% extraction&lt;/td>
&lt;td>20%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>70g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sour (all)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>141%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>493.4g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>water&lt;/td>
&lt;td>34%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>120g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sea salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>3.5g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>I prefer my bread to have just a hint of natural sweetness, rather than plenty sweet. Add malt syrup or honey, if desired.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I basically mixed everything together into a smooth, cohesive, and soft dough (adjust hydration as necessary). I let it sit at room temperature (~68°F) for 20 minutes to autolyze, before giving it a few rounds of stretching and folding. The gluten was somewhat weak, but it&amp;rsquo;s okay.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I fermented the dough at room temperature (~68°F) for 90 minutes. It expanded by ~50% and felt very puffy.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Then I degassed the dough and shaped it into a log (form into a &lt;em>boule&lt;/em> or &lt;em>bâtard&lt;/em> if desired), and placed it in a 9&amp;quot; x 4&amp;quot; loaf pan for final proof.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>After another 90 minutes at ~68°F, the dough rose by ~50% and formed a domed surface with a few cracks. I sprayed the dough with water and baked it for 45 minutes in my ghetto toaster oven (first 15 minutes at 375°F; then 30 minutes at 325°F).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>After baking, I let the bread cool off and cure for 12 hours before cutting.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-3/20230415_144616.jpg"
alt="Berliner Weisse bread sliced"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em> reincarnated as bread, with &lt;em>Lactobacillus&lt;/em>, &lt;em>kveiks&lt;/em>, and &lt;em>Brettanomyces&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;h3 id="tasting">Tasting&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Who knew a surprise was awaiting me when I sliced into this bread?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The &lt;strong>aroma&lt;/strong> was very interesting and inviting, like a zesty Granny Smith apple with a hint of raisin and cinnamon.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-3/20230415_144016.jpg"
alt="Berliner Weisse bread sliced"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em> bread, crumbshot&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The &lt;strong>color&lt;/strong> of the crumb was somewhere between soft yellow orange and luscious grapefruit (probably due to the bran and germ in unsifted whole red wheat flour).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The &lt;strong>texture&lt;/strong> was comparable to that of my regular sourdough breads. The crust was very thin and crisp; the crumb tight and soft. Mouth-filling, biscuity, and wheaty. Not ethereally fluffy, but still light on the palate.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The &lt;strong>flavor&lt;/strong> was mellow yet deeply layered. It started off with a delicate apple pie; continued to a medley of fruits (banana, orange, raisins, cinnamon apple, strawberries, apricot, peach, lychee, passion fruit&amp;hellip;) that somehow reminded me of banana nut muffins or blueberry streusel cakes; and then transitioned perfectly to a mild wheat sweetness with a little slightly clove-ish undertone.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-3/20230415_145258.jpg"
alt="Berliner Weisse bread sliced"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em> bread, crumbshot&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The finish was mildly tangy (reminiscent of pineapple), and a little &amp;ldquo;dry&amp;rdquo; after I swallowed. There was a wheaty aftertaste. The touch of smooth, rounded acidity left my mouth watering and wanting another bite. Whole wheat seemed to have played off the tartness that defines &lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It was subtly tart and well balanced, not unduly sour or puckering. You can tell the nice balance of lactic acid in this bread by its lack of sharp bitterness or a salty-type quality.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Wheat-forward, apple-esque, and unexpectedly nuanced.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-3/20230415_145623.jpg"
alt="Berliner Weisse bread sliced"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em> bread, crumbshot&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Like a &lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em> that&amp;rsquo;s light, zippy, zingy, and drinkable, this bread was very pleasant to eat on its own.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A little sweet, a little sour, and a whole lot of complex fruity notes. It&amp;rsquo;s the perfect buddy to soak in that summer social sun with. I&amp;rsquo;m amazed by the harmonious balance of sweetness and acidity, the marvelous self-conducted symphony by different yeasts and bacteria.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The slices paired exquisitely with raspberry jam and goat cheese for breakfast; with leftover Easter ham (or a hot bratwurst) and some sauerkraut for lunch/dinner.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-3/20230415_144042.jpg"
alt="Berliner Weisse bread sliced"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em> bread, crumbshot&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>When toasted, this bread took on a slightly different flavor profile: more subtle, less cinnamony, more fruity. It smelled more like freeze-dried apple slices, fruit punch, and Jolly Rancher; and tasted more like field-fresh apples.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>One things for sure &amp;ndash; this bread was too easy to enjoy. The whole loaf disappeared in record time (I invited 4 tasters, each of whom gobbled up a few slices; nobody believed this bread had no fruit in it). Simple and elegant, delicious and refreshing. I can see how the mystique of &lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em> has defied convention and beguiled invaders and imbibers for centuries.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I would think this bread tastes best 24 hours after baking.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-3/20230415_145911.jpg"
alt="Berliner Weisse bread sliced"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em> bread, crumbshot&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;h3 id="post-baking-thoughts">Post-baking thoughts&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>I have learned a lot more about yeasts through this experiment. Yeast is going to be the new hops.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Once again, it&amp;rsquo;s crazy to think that a bread with such complex flavors was made from just some humble grains, without any modern high-tech add-ins.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I should have doubled the recipe and made more than 1 loaf. This is a bread I will definitely make again (it was so worth it, and I could easily adapt the timing to my own WFH schedule). I may even top-crop some cultures from the barm for future batches.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Fruity sweetness&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In the 19th century, Germans started to find &lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em> a little too tart and added sweeteners to soften its acidity. Originally, they added &lt;em>kümmel&lt;/em> (a caraway-based liqueur), but today it&amp;rsquo;s common to add a shot of &lt;em>schuss&lt;/em>, or syrup, directly to the glass before it&amp;rsquo;s filled with beer. In Berlin, when you order a &lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em>, the waiter will often ask, &amp;ldquo;&lt;em>rot oder grün&lt;/em>?&amp;rdquo; (&amp;ldquo;red or green?&amp;quot;)&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-3/berliner-weiss.jpg"
alt="Berliner Weiße mit Schuß"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>Berliner Weiße mit Schuß&lt;/em>: Berliner Weisse with red &lt;em>himbeersirup&lt;/em> (raspberry syrup) or green &lt;em>waldmeistersirup&lt;/em> (woodruff syrup)&lt;/p>&lt;p>Source: &lt;a href="https://willkommen-in-germany.tumblr.com/post/161499667736/berliner-weisse-mit-schu%C3%9F-berlins-traditional" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">Willkommen in Deutschland&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The colors refer to the type of syrup you&amp;rsquo;d like to add to the beer. Red is usually a sweet raspberry syrup known as &lt;em>himbeersirup&lt;/em>. Green is a more traditional grassy herbal syrup made from &lt;em>waldmeister&lt;/em> (woodruff).&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;A great favourite with the ladies is the frothy Berlin white beer, drunk out of large bowl-shaped glass, and with a liqueur-glass of raspberry syrup added to it.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Dundee Evening Telegraph (Wednesday 01 November 1905, page 6)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>While Germans commonly add syrups to their &lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em> to balance its funky sourness, Americans put their own twists on the style by adding different combinations of fruits. I don&amp;rsquo;t think this bread needed any extra fruitiness (it&amp;rsquo;s not a fruit juice), but I may experiment with adding ~10% of wild pawpaw purée in a future iteration.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>&lt;strong>Lactobacillus brevis&lt;/strong>&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>According to &lt;a href="https://wilder-wald.com/2017/12/08/historic-berliner-weisse-homebrew-recipe/">Benedikt Koch&amp;rsquo;s research&lt;/a>, the main &lt;em>Lactobacillus&lt;/em> strain found in &lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em> was &lt;em>Lactobacillus brevis&lt;/em>. I did not know this at all before making this bread. I used Lacto Brevis because that was what I had on hand at the moment, other than my homemade thermophilic starter. Other hop-tolerant &lt;em>Lactobacillus&lt;/em> strains, such as &lt;em>L. lindnerii&lt;/em>, &lt;em>L. casei&lt;/em>, &lt;em>L. coryniformis&lt;/em> and &lt;em>L. plantarum&lt;/em>, have also been found in &lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I found a wealth of information on &lt;em>Lactobacillus brevis&lt;/em> in a 2003 paper called &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/14623377/">beer spoilage bacteria and hop resistance&lt;/a>.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Additionally, I read that a &amp;ldquo;symbiosis&amp;rdquo; between yeast and &lt;em>Lactobacillus&lt;/em> only seems to work when the &lt;em>Lactobacillus&lt;/em> is &lt;em>L. brevis&lt;/em>. This rod-shaped &lt;em>Lactobacillus&lt;/em> strain seems to leave the simpler sugars to the yeast, which keeps the yeast somewhat fitter in a hostile, acidic environment. There is little information on how this works in beer literature. In sourdough literature, however, it&amp;rsquo;s mentioned and researched several times.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Malts and thiols&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>How much of the bread&amp;rsquo;s bright, tropical-fruit aromas and flavors are contributed by malts and yeasts, respectively?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Currently, hops high in bound thiols (e.g. Saaz and Calypso) and genetically-modified &amp;ldquo;thiolized&amp;rdquo; yeasts are the go-to tools that brewers are employing to maximally unleash previously inaccessible tropical aromas into their beers. However, a few scientists and brewers are &lt;a href="https://brewingindustryguide.com/what-malt-can-do-for-your-thiols/">discovering&lt;/a> malts may be the most powerful player in this realm.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-3/20230415_150238.jpg"
alt="Berliner Weisse bread sliced"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em> reincarnated as bread, with &lt;em>Lactobacillus&lt;/em>, &lt;em>kveiks&lt;/em>, and &lt;em>Brettanomyces&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>🍻 Special thanks to&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Rory @ &lt;a href="https://www.imperialyeast.com/">Imperial Yeast&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Craig Miller @ &lt;a href="https://www.rootshootmalting.com">Root Shoot Malting&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>See &lt;em>The Simon &amp;amp; Schuster Pocket Guide to Beer&lt;/em> (1997) by Michael Jackson, p.65.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>See &lt;em>Bentley&amp;rsquo;s Miscellany&lt;/em>, Vol. 46, by Richard Bentley, et al. (London: Richard Bentley, 1859), 418.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:3" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>See &lt;em>Die Berliner Weisse: Ein Stück Berliner Geschichte&lt;/em> (&amp;ldquo;Berliner Weisse: A Piece of Berlin History&amp;rdquo;), by Gerolf Annemüller, Hans-J. Manger, and Peter Lietz (Berlin: VLBFachbücher, 2001), 34.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:4" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>I malted a batch of heritage Chevallier barley at home (slightly undermodified) and sun-dried them before grinding into a flour, to ensure the malt remained as pale as possible.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:4" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/section></content></item></channel></rss>