<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>hard red winter wheat on HERESY LEVAIN</title><link>/tags/hard-red-winter-wheat/</link><description>Latest experiments in hard red winter wheat from HERESY LEVAIN</description><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2023 HERESY LEVAIN 🍞 CC BY-NC-SA 4.0</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 08 Dec 2022 21:39:07 -0600</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/hard-red-winter-wheat/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Dulce Locura</title><link>/posts/dulce-locura/</link><pubDate>Thu, 08 Dec 2022 21:39:07 -0600</pubDate><guid>/posts/dulce-locura/</guid><description>A sweet potato &lt;em>pain d&amp;rsquo;épices&lt;/em>, made in an un-French way. Gently sweetened by a homemade spice-infused simple syrup. The crumb was tender and springy, the sweetish flavor in harmony with the chocolate and spices; the crust was crispy and fabulous. Irresistible and toothsome.</description><content>&lt;p>The US is still a superlulz &lt;a href="https://www.investopedia.com/terms/j/jit.asp">JIT&lt;/a> la la land. One bullet is &lt;a href="https://www.npr.org/2022/12/04/1140647869/power-substations-north-carolina-gunfire-vandalism">all it takes&lt;/a> to shut down the power grid for days&amp;hellip;possibly weeks. It reminded me of Juan Zarate&amp;rsquo;s memoir, &lt;em>Treasury&amp;rsquo;s War.&lt;/em> Unlike Europe, Uncle Sam is blessed with extraordinary energy abundance. Still, it feels like a first-world country with third-world infrastructure. As much as it sucks for the people affected, we are all living in an age of energy vulnerability.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I have been to various parts of North freakin' Carolina a number of times. Charlotte, like any other financial center, is the most boring. The Research Triangle (Raleigh, Durham, and Chapel Hill) in the heart of Piedmont is more fun. Of course, nothing beats Asheville &amp;ndash; a hipster mecca. Best memories are licking my fingers after eating N&amp;rsquo;Asheville &amp;ldquo;Mount St. Hell No&amp;rdquo; spicy crispy fried chicken at &lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=JE5SyITVOTE">Rocky&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a>, and getting caught in a rainstorm in Wilmington on the riverwalk and roaming the beaches like a drowned rat.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It wasn&amp;rsquo;t until recently that I learned North Carolina is the #1 producer of sweet potatoes in the US.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Last week I stumbled across a &lt;a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/Breadit/comments/udoyzj/pain_depices_au_levain_naturally_leavened_french/">reddit&lt;/a> on &lt;em>pain d&amp;rsquo;épices au levain&lt;/em>, got sidetracked, and went down a rabbit hole. I still have a ton of sweet potatoes left over from the Gobble Gobble Day. Why not create a &lt;em>pain d&amp;rsquo;épices&lt;/em> of my own, you know, heresy style? Maybe with a North Carolina character? Forgive me, France.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="homemade-spiced-syrup">Homemade spiced syrup&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>First off, I made a simple &lt;em>sirop d&amp;rsquo;épices&lt;/em> in the Instant Pot:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>60g aged orange peels&lt;/li>
&lt;li>30g fresh ginger&lt;/li>
&lt;li>1 whole star anise&lt;/li>
&lt;li>1 piece 4&amp;quot; cinnamon stick&lt;/li>
&lt;li>5 cloves&lt;/li>
&lt;li>2 allspice berries&lt;/li>
&lt;li>10 cardamom seeds&lt;/li>
&lt;li>200g sugar&lt;/li>
&lt;li>200g raisin water (soak 150g raisins in 250g water for a few hours, and squeeze out the liquid)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>200g h₂o&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Pressure-cooked for 1 minute, followed by 30 minutes of natural release. Then I left it overnight, to allow the aromatics to meld together further. The sweet orangey aroma wafted through the house. Next morning, I strained the whole mixture through a through a fine-mesh sieve, and filled up 2 big jars with the thin brown goodness.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This homemade syrup packs quite a punch with its fragrant combination of spices. Delightfully sweet with a deep orange flavor, and chock full of bold, brisk notes.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;code>Pro tip&lt;/code>: Instead of throwing away the leftover aromatic pulp from straining, blend it finely into a sweet fruit paste. Use it as a delicious spread on toasts, or thin it a little and use as a marinade/sauce/glaze in savory dishes.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="tar-heel-blend">Tar Heel Blend&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>I decided to mix up my own Tar Heel Blend wheat flour, instead of using my go-to workhorse Turkey Red.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>60% Appalachian White (Fish Pond Branch Farms, NC): a HWWW with a mild creamy taste and ~12% protein&lt;/li>
&lt;li>20% NuEast (Fish Pond Branch Farms, NC): a HRWW with a delicate nutty flavor and ~10% protein&lt;/li>
&lt;li>20% Sungold spelt (Red Tail Grains, NC): a modern cultivar of spelt with ~12% protein&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Much like Missouri, the eastern US is not hospitable to growing bread wheat, because the area&amp;rsquo;s humidity increases the incidence of disease in the fields and affects yield and quality of the grain. Historically, North Carolina has grown almost exclusively soft wheats (lower protein, better for crackers, biscuits, etc). But, in response to a growing demand from the resurgence of artisan bakeries, two modern high-yielding cultivars of hard winter wheat, Appalachian White and NuEast, were bred by NC State researchers and &lt;a href="https://www.ars.usda.gov/news-events/news/research-news/2009/ars-releases-first-hard-winter-wheat-varieties-for-eastern-us-production/">released in 2009&lt;/a> to farmers as high-quality bread wheats suited for production in the Carolinas.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="levain">Levain&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>Kick the levain into high gear with 2 feedings, 10 hours apart:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Build #1:&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>stiff WW starter&lt;/td>
&lt;td>25%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>WW flour (freshly milled Tar Heel Blend)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>h₂o&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Build #2:&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>build #1&lt;/td>
&lt;td>225%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>WW flour (freshly milled Tar Heel Blend)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>h₂o&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>I let it ferment (for ~18 hours at 65F) until it got loose and bubbly.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="final-dough">Final dough&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>While the levain is fermenting, cook the sweet potatoes.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you want your sweet potatoes sweeter, cook them &lt;a href="https://www.seriouseats.com/the-best-mashed-sweet-potatoes-recipe">low and slow&lt;/a>, so that the enzyme will have more time to break down more starch and convert it to more maltose.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I heated a pot of plain water in an Instant Pot to ~160F, and threw a few whole Carolina Ruby sweet potatoes directly into it. I covered up the pot, and let the spuds rest in the warm water bath overnight. You want to hold the sweet spuds in that 135F-170F (57C-77C) sweet spot for an extended period of time, to activate their endogenous enzymes that bring out their natural sweetness. After a few hours, you can take the sweet spuds out of the water bath, roast and mash them.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Tar Heel Blend, 85% extraction&lt;/td>
&lt;td>80%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>whole rye flour (Wren&amp;rsquo;s Abruzzi rye - Carolina Ground, NC)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>20%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>roasted sweet potatoes, mashed (Carolina Ruby)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>37.5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;em>sirop d&amp;rsquo;épices&lt;/em> (50% in autolyse + 25% &lt;em>eau de bassinage&lt;/em>)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>75%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>ripe levain&lt;/td>
&lt;td>42.5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sea salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1.5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>dark chocolate, chopped (80% Patanemo - Escazú Chocolates, NC)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>12%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>I squished up the flour with 1/2 of the spiced syrupy water and the cooled sweet potato, and autolyzed for 2 hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>After the autolyse, I squeezed all of the levain into the dough, while adding 1/2 of the remaining sweet water in several increments. Gave it a few rounds of slap &amp;amp; fold until it reached a semi-homogeneous texture, to make sure everything was evenly incorproated.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>After a 20-minute rest, I squished in the salt and the rest of the sweet water. The dough looked and felt like a sticky mess.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I did a coil-fold every 20 minutes for the first hour.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>At the 2h mark, I added the chocolate pieces, and gave the dough another coil-fold so that all of the chocolate bits were completely enveloped.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I did two more coil-folds at the 3h and 4h marks, respectively, to make sure the chocolate goodies were totally distributed throughout the dough.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The dough started to feel puffy. I decided to stop turning it, and let it ferment, unmolested, in the sunroom overnight (~43F).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Next morning, the dough had doubled in volume. I let it warm up on the kitchen counter for 2 hours. Then I shaped it into a boule and placed it in a proofing bowl, seam-side down.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>When the surface of the dough reached ~60F, I dumped it out onto a baking tray lined with parchment paper, and baked it in the toaster oven. 350F for the first 20 minutes, and 325F for 20 more minutes.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I let the bread cool for 4 hours before slicing.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The bread surrounding the little nuggets of chocolate was not bland at all! It was ever so gently sweetened by the simple syrup, like everything was magically pulled together.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The crumb was tender and springy, the sweetish flavor in harmony with the chocolate and spices; the crust was crispy and fabulous. Another winner for my repertoire!&lt;/p></content></item><item><title>Aquaboogie di Dolce</title><link>/posts/aquaboogie-di-dolce/</link><pubDate>Sun, 21 Aug 2022 23:32:41 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/aquaboogie-di-dolce/</guid><description>An absurdly high-hydration summer panettone, made with 85% extraction Turkey Red and 100% extraction einkorn.</description><content>&lt;p>I just found out that Dean &amp;amp; DeLuca, one of America&amp;rsquo;s fanciest gourmet grocery store chains whose name is synonymous with NYC luxury, &lt;a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20200401042156/https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2020-04-01/dean-deluca-files-for-bankruptcy-protection-from-creditors">filed for Chapter 11 bankruptcy protection&lt;/a> from creditors in April 2020. It had &amp;ldquo;liabilities of as much as $500 million and assets of no more than $50 million.&amp;rdquo; The chain&amp;rsquo;s owner, Thailand&amp;rsquo;s Pace Development Corp., defaulted on a total of THB ฿9.5Bn (USD ~$315 million) of debt in 2019.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Turns out, it was Dean &amp;amp; DeLuca&amp;rsquo;s vendors &amp;ndash; bakeries and patisseries that supplied many of the store&amp;rsquo;s pricey gourmet products &amp;ndash; who were the first to sound the death knell of the retail chain. &lt;a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2019/07/10/dining/dean-and-deluca-closes-stores.html">The NY Times&lt;/a> reported that 4+ NYC vendors, including Bien Cuit and Fulton Fish Market, were &amp;ldquo;owed hundreds of thousands of dollars.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Such a shame the iconic brand ended up in shambles.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I popped into Dean &amp;amp; DeLuca&amp;rsquo;s flagship location in NYC&amp;rsquo;s SoHo a few times when I lived in the city. Tourists are notoriously obsessed with shops in SoHo. Lol. I haven&amp;rsquo;t bothered to keep up with NYC news since I moved away years ago. I had no idea Dean &amp;amp; DeLuca opened stores in Tokyo, Bangkok, Singapore, Seoul, Dubai, Doha, Bahrain, etc. TBH, high-end stores like Dean &amp;amp; DeLuca are best for dumpster-diving.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>For many customers who stepped inside Dean &amp;amp; DeLuca over its nearly 42-year history, the visit was more about getting a glimpse of a posh world far beyond their pay grade, where a polished Thanksgiving of perfectly roasted turkey and decadent chocolate cakes could be had for the price of all the money in your bank account. Purchasing something at the stores &amp;ndash; no matter how small &amp;ndash; was a treat that made someone feel like one of the many celebrities who readily raved about shopping trips to Dean &amp;amp; DeLuca in the press. Until Whole Foods and Eataly came along, Dean &amp;amp; Deluca existed in a class of its own. &amp;hellip;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Dean &amp;amp; DeLuca enjoyed a cache well into the late-aughts that was regularly documented in pop culture. In a violent scene in &lt;em>American Psycho&lt;/em>, a book about a 1980s Wall Street serial killer, main character Patrick Bateman name drops Italian sea salt purchased from Dean &amp;amp; DeLuca. Characters in shows like &lt;em>Will &amp;amp; Grace&lt;/em> regularly mentioned the store, reminding viewers of their expensive New York tastes. A version of the company’s stylish coffee house was cemented into the memory of &lt;em>Felicity&lt;/em> viewers, whose main character works as a barista at a Dean &amp;amp; DeLuca cafe. Perhaps most indicative of the special-occasion nature of a trip to Dean &amp;amp; DeLuca is a scene in &lt;em>The Devil Wears Prada&lt;/em> where boyfriend Nate (played by Adrian Grenier) brings home a celebratory bag of food from the luxury store for girlfriend Andrea (played by Anne Hathaway), remarking that “they charge, like, five dollars a strawberry there.”&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Brenna Houck, &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href="https://www.eater.com/2019/7/16/20695333/dean-and-deluca-stores-closing-debt-fancy-food-market-rise-and-fall">Dean &amp;amp; DeLuca Sold America Luxury but Couldn’t Pay Its Own Bills&lt;/a>&amp;rdquo;, Eater&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>NGL, it was at the Dean &amp;amp; DeLuca in SoHo where I had &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->my first taste&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --> of panettone years ago. It was a fancy-schmancy panettone from Italy.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I haven&amp;rsquo;t eaten many artisan panettoni, and I&amp;rsquo;ve tried making it myself a few times. Each and every panettone is a quest for achieving a crumb that&amp;rsquo;s simultaneously moist, light, decadent, and ethereal.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Why not make a panettone, during the sweltering summer? Turns out &lt;em>&lt;a href="https://www.dissapore.com/spesa/panettone-estivo-2022-sette-grandi-lievitati-per-lestate/">panettoni estivi&lt;/a>&lt;/em> already became a &amp;ldquo;trend&amp;rdquo; last year. Never short the hedonism of US consumers.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I looked up panettone recipes by Carol Field, Roy Schvartzapel, Piergiorgio Giorilli, Iginio Massari, Ezio Marinato, Gino Fabbri, Giambattista Montanari, and Michel Suas to figure out the pattern across the maestros' methods. Then I decided to try something of my own.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I wanted this summer panettone to be lighter and fresher than a winter holiday version, so I used less butter, less sugar and no eggs. No, I definitely don&amp;rsquo;t want this one to be as brazenly buttery as Roy Schvartzapel&amp;rsquo;s luxury panettone.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="impasto-1">Impasto #1&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The &lt;em>lievito madre&lt;/em> is too much work, so I used &lt;a href="https://theflavorbells.com/yeast-water/">homemade fruit yeast water&lt;/a> instead.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>85% extraction wheat flour (Turkey Red - Stutzman Farms, OH)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>plum yeast water (homemade)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>50%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>ginger-turmeric syrup (homemade)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>20%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sugar (Louisiana cane sugar - Three Brothers Farm, LA)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>unsalted butter (Spesiell Kremen - Nordic Creamery, WI)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>15%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>To make the ginger-turmeric syrup, mix fresh ginger, turmeric, water, sugar, and spices (coriander, cumin, peppercorn, cinnamon, etc.) in a pot. Bring to a boil. Reduce heat and simmer until a syrupy consistency is reached. Let cool and then strain.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Process (by hand):&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Combine the flour with the yeast water and the syrup, and let autolyze for 30 mins.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Mix in the sugar.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Add the softened butter, in 4 increments. Mix in thoroughly.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Slap &amp;amp; fold until a very soft, smooth and strong dough is formed (with ~80% gluten development).&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Ferment for 12 hours at ~72°F (longer at lower temperatures).&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>At the end of fermentation, the first dough should triple in volume.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="impasto-2">Impasto #2&lt;/h3>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>100% extraction einkorn flour (Stutzman Farms, OH)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>impasto #1&lt;/td>
&lt;td>900%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>diastatic malt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>h₂o&lt;/td>
&lt;td>250%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>honey (Champion Hill Farm, MI)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>30%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;em>pasta di arancia&lt;/em> (homemade)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>125%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>pawpaw purée (wild)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>40%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>unsalted butter (Spesiell Kremen - Nordic Creamery, WI)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>70%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>dried fruits (mangoes, pineapples, apples)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>30%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>dried petals (safflowers, hibiscus, marigolds)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sprouted quinoa&lt;/td>
&lt;td>222%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>To make &lt;em>pasta di arancia&lt;/em>, mix together peeled (and de-seeded) navel oranges, mandarins, tangelos, lemons, ginger, turmeric, honey, sugar, and orange zest in a blender until you get a creamy paste. The proportion of each ingredient depends on your personal preferences. You should make a big batch &amp;ndash; it can be kept in a sterilized glass jar in the fridge for a few weeks or in the freezer for a few months.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I soaked the dried fruits and flower petals in some dessert wine (Silver Dick - Wenwood Farm Winery, MO) overnight.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I also soaked some quinoa in double the amount of water overnight and let the seeds sprout. The wet sprouted quinoa came up to be 222% of final flour weight.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Process (by hand):&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>To impasto #1, add all the flour, malt, salt and 1/3 of the water. Mix for a few minutes.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Add the honey and mix in completely.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Add the &lt;em>pasta di arancia&lt;/em> and pawpaw purée. Slap &amp;amp; fold until just combined.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Let rest for 15 mins.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Add the butter in 4 increments. Mix until the butter is completely incorporated into the dough and the gluten has reached full development.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Let rest for 10 mins.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Add the rest of the water very slowly, mixing in completely before continuing. Adding water after butter is like lightening an emulsion; it made me think of making mayonnaise. &amp;mdash;-&amp;gt; TBH, no panettone recipe I&amp;rsquo;ve seen calls for this much water. I went with my gut and gorged the dough with as much water as I felt it could handle. Ludicrously, after a whopping 250% hydration, I felt the dough could handle even more h₂o&amp;hellip;(another experiment for next time?) It held together really well and didn&amp;rsquo;t break down at all. The dough started to feel as puffy and jiggly as a &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/aquaboogie">&lt;em>pan de cristal&lt;/em>&lt;/a>!&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Let rest for 10 mins.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Stretch the dough out into a thin rectangle, and laminate with the add-ins (soaked fruits, petals and quinoa).&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Bulk-ferment at ~80°F for 1 hour, folding every 20 mins.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Shape the dough and place into a baking mold. &amp;lt;&amp;mdash;- I thought about baking the dough flat out like I do with the &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/aquaboogie">&lt;em>pan de cristal&lt;/em>&lt;/a>. Not this time, because I was still hoping to make a &amp;ldquo;panettone,&amp;rdquo; which should be a tall loaf. I shaped the dough into a log and placed it into a loaf pan, so it would rise up to a proper height.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Proof for 4-6 hours at ~80°F (or ~12 hours at 72°F).&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>The dough should rise up 2x like a giant cotton candy before baking.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I baked it in my toaster oven at 350-325°F for 50 mins.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>After baking, I tipped the panettone over on its side and let it cool off like that for 24 hours, instead of doing the fancy upside-down hanging. NGL, the hanging method is definitely far more effective at helping the panettone&amp;rsquo;s delicate crumb maintain its elongated structure.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/aquaboogie-di-dolce/202208211156.jpg"
alt="Aquaboogie di Dolce"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Despite the improper cooling, the panettone has turned out decent (not a devastating failure).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The crumb feels superbly moist and delicate; it tastes boldly fruity and pleasantly sweet. We devoured half of the loaf in one sitting.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you think about how much sugar, honey, and butter go into each panettone, how is it possible this thing doesn&amp;rsquo;t have a rich taste and a fluffy texture? They all help to elevate the crumb.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/aquaboogie-di-dolce/202208211153.jpg"
alt="Aquaboogie di Dolce"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Aquaboogie di Dolce, an absurdly high-hydration summer panettone.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Honey (sugar) softens the crumb, while fats lubricate the dough and help the flour particles move alongside each other more smoothly, making the dough more flexible and stretchable. In breads with a high percentage of whole grains, a little honey brings out more of the grain&amp;rsquo;s flavor and balances out its earthiness.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Generic supermarket butter is ~80% fat; the remaining 20% is mostly water and some proteins. Fats do more than providing a smoother mouthfeel and a richer sensory experience. When an enriched dough is placed in a hot oven, the butter melts. As a result, the water content in the butter turns into steam. It&amp;rsquo;s that steam being trapped by the gluten in the dough that lifts the croissant off into honeycomb ecstasy. Meanwhile, the fat molecules become a bit more mobile and they will re-organize themselves slightly. Since fats don&amp;rsquo;t like to sit in water, they will actually surround the air bubbles in bread. This way the fat stabilizes the air bubbles. Consequently, enriched breads tend to have a lot of small air bubbles. Since the fats remain in place after baking (they cool down and solidify again), they will remain around these air bubbles. That acts like a protective layer and helps keep the bread fresh.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Both sugar and fat prevent the gluten from forming long, chewy strands and help produce a more tender bread, but they should be added only towards the end of mixing/kneading after the gluten network is mostly developed. Any type of sugar and fat will probably work just as well.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/aquaboogie-di-dolce/202208211201.jpg"
alt="Aquaboogie di Dolce"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>This panettone is an absolutely fantastic substrate for the iconic Cuban &lt;em>medianoche&lt;/em> &amp;ndash; sweet, salty, and deeply satisfying. Yes, I use Italian panettone to make Cuban &lt;em>medianoche&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>2022/12/18&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I got to sample a slice of Olivieri 1882&amp;rsquo;s latest &lt;em>panettone all&amp;rsquo;aceto balsamico&lt;/em> at a holiday party. It was lavishly soft, airy, and decadent; laced with balsamic cream and studded with balsamic-vinegar infused raisin.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The packaging says it uses Carandini&amp;rsquo;s Balsamic Vinegar of Modena IGP. Olivieri&amp;rsquo;s website describes it as follows:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Carandini, one of Modena&amp;rsquo;s oldest families, has been producing hand-crafted balsamic vinegars using traditional family methods since 1641. Their hero expression, the Emilio Balsamic Vinegar of Modena, is a premium, high-density vinegar that contains 60% grape must and strikes a delicate balance between sweet and sour. Exuding a mahogany color and rich perfume, the versatile product lends a subtle acidity and fragrant sweetness to Olivieri&amp;rsquo;s staple Panettone recipe.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>FYI, Carandini&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em>Aceto Balsamico di Modena IGP&lt;/em> (Balsamic Vinegar of Modena) is not a true &lt;em>Aceto Balsamico Tradizionale&lt;/em>, i.e. made from a reduction of pressed Trebbiano and Lambrusco grape that&amp;rsquo;s aged for a minimum of 12 years in a series of wooden barrels of successively smaller sizes. True balsamic vinegar is rich, glossy, deep brown in color, and has a complex flavor that balances the natural sweetness and sourness of cooked grape juice with hints of wood from the casks.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Aceto Balsamico di Modena&lt;/em> is a commercial-grade cheaper imitation of the traditional balsamic vinegar. They can be made from as little as 20% grape must (and not necessarily from Modena or Reggio Emilia), with the addition of wine vinegar, coloring, caramel, and sometimes thickeners like guar gum or corn starch to artificially simulate the sweetness and thickness of the naturally aged &lt;em>Aceto Balsamico Tradizionale di Modena&lt;/em>. IGP status requires a minimum aging period of 2 months (not necessarily in wooden barrels), rising to 3 years when labeled as &lt;em>invecchiato&lt;/em> (aged).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;60% grape must&amp;rdquo; = 40% wine vinegar. Since Carandini&amp;rsquo;s Balsamic Vinegar of Modena has IGP in its label, it&amp;rsquo;s most likely produced in Modena. (For some reason, I&amp;rsquo;ve yet to come across a bottle of balsamic vinegar that&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em>not&lt;/em> made in Modena.)&lt;/p>
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>Dean &amp;amp; DeLuca reminded me of Southern Season, a gourmet specialty food retailer in the Carolinas where I got to taste many fine cheeses and chocolates from around the world. Southern Season filed for Chapter 11 bankruptcy in 2016. It had liabilities of ~$18.9 million compared to ~$9.8 million in assets &amp;ndash; not as outrageous as Dean &amp;amp; DeLuca&amp;rsquo;s debt-to-asset ratio.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/section></content></item><item><title>Kornerstone</title><link>/posts/kornerstone/</link><pubDate>Sun, 19 Jun 2022 19:32:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>/posts/kornerstone/</guid><description>An old-school Jewish deli rye, made with a hefty amount of single-grind wholegrain Danko rye flour and two kinds of heritage wheat flours. Infused with caramelized onions, spent brewer&amp;rsquo;s grains, and poppy seeds.</description><content>&lt;p>Charles Bukowski&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em>Ham on Rye&lt;/em> is one of my favorite books. I consider it one of his best works and surely one of the greatest novels in all literature.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A ham on rye sandwich is about the simplest thing an American can eat. Ditto Bukowski&amp;rsquo;s writings are as simple as you get.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The leading rye-producing states in the US are the Dakotas, Nebraska, Minnesota, and Georgia. &amp;lt;50% of the rye grown in the US is harvested for grain, with the rest used as pasture/hay or as a cover crop. ~50% of the amount harvested for grain is fed to livestock or exported, and the remainder is used for distilling, food, and seed. In the Midwest, rye is primarily grown for grain, but occasionally for hay/pasture.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For generations, ham on rye was the proletarian sandwich of choice in the Midwest (pastrami on rye in New York). Rye bread was part of the sacred Midwestern German-American trinity: sauerkraut, dill pickles and chewy rye with caraway seeds. Mothers in America made sandwiches for their kids to take to school, and a ham on rye was what kids would eat. It&amp;rsquo;s boring, but flavorful and filling.&lt;/p>
&lt;div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
&lt;iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/SPkZbJAP7Zc" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video">&lt;/iframe>
&lt;/div>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;Who the hell invented the sandwich? They should write a book about him.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>a fat guy at The Golden Horn in the movie &lt;em>&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SPkZbJAP7Zc">Barfly&lt;/a>&lt;/em> (1987)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;Hamming it up&amp;rdquo; means to overdo something, especially in acting. Bukowski&amp;rsquo;s book has little to do with the sandwich. I interpret the &amp;ldquo;ham&amp;rdquo; as a metaphor for the neon (pretense, not kosher), which he contrasted with the plain humble staple &amp;ldquo;rye,&amp;rdquo; to squeeze all of the pretense out of his life.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="the-rye-pyramid">The rye pyramid&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>In my mind, there are generally 3 categories of rye breads, based on the percentage of rye they have.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Brick ryes&lt;/strong> (&amp;gt;=66% rye): these breads are dense and brick-like; made completely or mostly from rye (rye flour, soaked rye, or cracked rye); leavened with rye levain; very sticky, must be mixed with a paddle; soft, despite the lack of wheat flour.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;em>walliserbrot&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;em>roggenbrot&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;em>gersterbrot&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;em>vollkornbrot&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;em>pumpernickel&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;em>borodinsky&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;em>rugbrød&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;em>rupjmaize&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;em>ruisleipä&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Intermediate ryes&lt;/strong> (30%-65% rye): these breads have a solid backbone of wheat, with varying degrees of rye, making them something akin to farmers' breads but with more rye and less wheat; they are distinctly chewy and flavorful.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;em>kornbroyt&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;em>pain de seigle&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;em>pain de méteil&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Rye-flavored breads&lt;/strong> (&amp;lt;30% rye): the bulk of the flour in these breads is wheat; the wheat provides structure, while the rye adds flavor.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;em>landbrot&lt;/em> (country bread)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;em>bauernbrot&lt;/em> (farmer&amp;rsquo;s bread)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>In this category, there is a sub-group of enriched, flavored ryes (usually &amp;lt;15% rye) that became quite popular in America in the last century or so:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>American &lt;em>pumpernickel&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Jewish deli rye&lt;/li>
&lt;li>marbled rye (the combination of American &lt;em>pumpernickel&lt;/em> and Jewish deli rye)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>onion rye&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>There is another sub-group of lean ryes (&amp;lt;10%) such as the San Francisco Sourdough that add rye for some rustic nuance but I don&amp;rsquo;t consider them to be rye breads.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="the-american-bastardization-of-rye">The American bastardization of rye&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>As a matter of fact, the so-called Jewish rye bread found in a contemporary Jewish bakery or delicatessen is &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/attack-of-the-ryeclops">an American invention&lt;/a> &amp;ndash; an American bastardization of a European rye. It&amp;rsquo;s a light, mild rye loaf made with a large amount of wheat flour and seasoned with caraway seeds, lacking the intensity of Minsk rye and Bavarian rye. It was popularized by Jewish delicatessens, but it&amp;rsquo;s not specific to the Jewish tradition, unlike &lt;em>challah&lt;/em> or &lt;em>matzah&lt;/em>. IMO, it&amp;rsquo;s as Jewish as General Tso&amp;rsquo;s chicken is Chinese.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Rye is the main cereal crop in those areas of Eastern Europe most densely populated by Jews and was correspondingly cheap, especially compared with wheat. Rye has been a staple ingredient of vodkas for centuries.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Over there, the most common type of rye bread &amp;ndash; the one with the highest proportion of rye &amp;ndash; was called &lt;em>razeve broyt&lt;/em>, literally &amp;ldquo;black bread.&amp;rdquo; It was usually prepared at home, and consisted of as much rye flour as the bread could bear. The Yiddish writer and scholar Hirsh Abramovitch, who was born in 1881, described making such bread from single-grind rye flour, as follows:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>The whole kernel was used &amp;ndash; the bran, the starch, the germ, and everything else. Some flour and warm water were mixed together in a kneading trough and left to stand overnight, covered with a tablecloth which was covered in turn with a fur coat or a pillow. The warmth made the mixture start to ferment. Sometime before dawn, the sourdough was kneaded by hand for about three-quarters of an hour, while more flour and water were added. Once everything was thoroughly mixed, the trough was covered up again and left to stand somewhere warm for four or five hours until the mixture had risen, when it would be formed into loaves of between fifteen and twenty-five pounds. &amp;hellip; The loaves would sit in the oven for four to six hours, depending on their size. Women who didn&amp;rsquo;t want the tops of their loaves to be black would sift rye flour in a thick sieve, mix the sifted flour with water, and smear it on the tops of the loaves before putting them into the oven. &amp;hellip; They called this mixture &lt;em>kharmushke&lt;/em>; it gave the bread a &amp;ldquo;Jewish look,&amp;rdquo; in contrast to gentile bread, which was &amp;ldquo;as black as coal.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Michael Wex, &lt;em>Rhapsody in Schmaltz&lt;/em> (2016)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>This doesn&amp;rsquo;t even remotely resemble the wheaty light rye served in most Jewish delis today. Although people in the old days may have guts of iron rather than abs of steel, eating these dense rye bricks (allegedly 2 lbs. a day on average!) was hardly a lifestyle choice. &lt;em>Razeve broyt&lt;/em> was the food of poverty &amp;ndash; the most fundamental food that was available to everyone. The poorest people would stretch their rye flour by grating potatoes into it, and unwillingly eat the bread &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ea6OET3Zi20">dry&lt;/a>.&amp;rdquo; White bread was considered a luxury, and many Jews started switching to the lighter, more wheaty bread as soon as they could afford it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As a matter of historical fact, wherever in Europe Jews settled, they adopted the local breads and slightly modified them to reflect the strictures of &lt;em>kashrut&lt;/em>. Therefore, the dark, sweet-sour ryes of Lithuania are every bit as Jewish as the light caraway-flecked ryes of southern Poland and Ukraine. The rye breads that managed to survive the journey to America, with the thousands of Jewish immigrants at the beginning of the 20th century, were those that best lent themselves to American conditions, namely, lower-percentage ryes that took advantage of the cheaper, easier-to-handle, and more abundant wheat that Eastern European Jewish bakers found when they arrived. The high-percentage ryes that represented the taste of home for Jews from Lithuania, Belarus and northern Poland had morphed into something new and uniquely American by the end of World War II. To mask the change, immigrant bakers loaded their breads with caraway seeds, which lent baked goods a fleeting flavor of anise/licorice.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="the-regression-of-jewish-deli-rye">The regression of Jewish deli rye&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The Jewish rye that caught on in the US &amp;ndash; the iconic bookends for pastrami &amp;ndash; probably began as some variation on the &lt;em>kornbroyt&lt;/em>. The OG unadulterated &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->&lt;em>kornbroyt&lt;/em>&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --> originated in central Europe, where &amp;ldquo;korn&amp;rdquo; is not maize/corn, but &lt;a href="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/%D7%A7%D7%90%D6%B8%D7%A8%D7%9F#Yiddish">Old High German&lt;/a> for &amp;ldquo;grain,&amp;rdquo; which in bread almost always refers to rye, and &amp;ldquo;broyt&amp;rdquo; is derived from Old High German &amp;ldquo;brōt,&amp;rdquo; meaning a loaf of bread. &lt;em>Kornbroyt&lt;/em> (literally &amp;ldquo;rye bread,&amp;rdquo; but nowadays often referred to as &amp;ldquo;Jewish corn rye&amp;rdquo;) is traditionally a heavy sourdough loaf built on a solid backbone of wheat, 30%-60% rye, and no maize/corn at all. It&amp;rsquo;s akin to farmer&amp;rsquo;s breads but with less wheat; it has a distinct chewiness and depth of flavor. As in &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/attack-of-the-ryeclops">Scandinavian &lt;em>smørrebrød&lt;/em>&lt;/a>, the peppery earthiness of rye pairs marvelously with rich and savory fillings like chopped livers, pastrami, and kosher salami.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Obviously, &lt;em>kornbroyt&lt;/em> was one of the building blocks of the Jewish-American bread microcosm. In the early Jewish deli rye inspired by the &lt;em>kornbroyt&lt;/em>, 30%-40% of the total flour was either medium rye (~85% extraction) or white rye (65%-70% extraction, with the bran and germ removed), and the rest was wheat flour. The blend lets the rye shine through without taking over. The whiter the rye, the milder the flavor &amp;ndash; sometimes just a hint of rye.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>By mid-20th century, an even lighter (~20% rye), mildly tangy, &amp;ldquo;shissel&amp;rdquo; (Yiddish for caraway, also spelt &amp;ldquo;sissel&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;cissel&amp;rdquo;) rye bread had swept across the US like wildfire. It&amp;rsquo;s fluffier, whiter, and less crusty than the old-fashioned 40% version, but closer to American-style white bread. It&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Jewish&amp;rdquo; because one could routinely find it on the shelves of the bakeries and delis that anchored Jewish settlements in major US cities and wherever else they established communities.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This &amp;ldquo;Jewish deli rye&amp;rdquo; became the American default, towering over other American rye breads such as sweet earthy &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->&lt;a href="https://www.allneedfulthings.net/NT_Breads/Old_Milwaukee_Rye.html">Old Milwaukee Rye&lt;/a>&lt;sup id="fnref:2">&lt;a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->, austere &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->Dakota rye&lt;sup id="fnref:3">&lt;a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">3&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->, and &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->Boston brown bread&lt;sup id="fnref:4">&lt;a href="#fn:4" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">4&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->, all of which use at least &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/joeliath/">1/3 rye&lt;/a>. Its popularity probably contributed to people&amp;rsquo;s biggest misconception about rye bread: rye = caraway. Rye has &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/attack-of-the-ryeclops">so many faces, possibilities, and flavor elements&lt;/a> that to denigrate it to that one astringent note is to do it a tremendous injustice. People who think they don&amp;rsquo;t like rye probably just don&amp;rsquo;t like caraway.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Unfortunately, in today&amp;rsquo;s delis, a 20% rye begrudgingly tossed with a tiny amount of &lt;em>shissel&lt;/em> is considered the standard of good deli rye &amp;ndash; and even such a loaf is hard to find these days. The Jewish deli rye at Zingerman&amp;rsquo;s, reputedly &lt;a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120305231242/http://www.saveur.com/article/Travels/best-rye-breads-in-america">America&amp;rsquo;s very best deli rye&lt;/a>, contains ~25% rye. By contrast, most commercial Jewish rye breads have &amp;lt;= 5% rye and rarely come with any &lt;em>shissel&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The shift came about during the post-WWII years, when white flour became cheaper, and easier to work with, than rye flour. The modern &amp;ldquo;rye&amp;rdquo; bread didn&amp;rsquo;t just lack in flavor and quality compared to traditional Jewish rye loaves: It was cheaper and lasted longer. In the 1960s-70s, industrial bakeries, such as Levy&amp;rsquo;s in Brooklyn, hooked many &lt;a href="https://forward.com/culture/482193/levys-jewish-rye-you-dont-have-to-be-jewish-model-joseph-attean-native/">conspicuously non-Jewish&lt;/a> New Yorkers on the taste of a packaged rye bread (pasteurized for a longer shelf life), with the &lt;a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2014/01/12/business/judy-protas-writer-of-slogan-for-levys-real-jewish-rye-dies-at-91.html?_r=0">viral slogan&lt;/a> &amp;ldquo;You don&amp;rsquo;t have to be Jewish to love Levy&amp;rsquo;s Real Jewish Rye.&amp;rdquo; That was a watershed moment. As independent Jewish bakeries failed to beat their larger, industrial competition, quality rye bread disappeared from delis.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/kornerstone/Levys-jewish-rye-walmart.png"
alt="Levy&amp;#39;s Real Jewish Rye"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Levy&amp;rsquo;s Real Jewish Rye (from Walmart)&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Over the past 40-50 years, according to Stan Ginsberg and Norm Berg in their book &lt;em>Inside the Jewish Bakery&lt;/em>, the flavor and texture of commercial rye bread have been drastically watered down as baking companies went national &amp;ndash; and Americanized with it. Rye bread became paler and lighter in texture, with less and less rye flour and more and more additives (oils, conditioners, and preservatives). Commercial bakeries also started using commercial dry yeast instead of sourdough; the latter takes too long (as time has become the most precious commodity) and, for a long time, wasn&amp;rsquo;t generally considered reliable or controlled enough a process for mass production &amp;ndash; probably not good for FDA and local health inspectors, either. So most commercial rye bread lacks the true rye sour starter flavor, and is no longer naturally chewy or dark. Or crusty.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The Jewish delicatessens of New York are often sacrosanct institutions. Landmarks like Katz&amp;rsquo;s, Carnegie Deli, and 2nd Ave Deli serve up lovingly spiced pastrami and corned beef, but their bread is a disgrace. There, I said it! Rye at these &amp;ldquo;legendary&amp;rdquo; NYC delis is shoddy slices of dry, thin, bland, and oftentimes stale white bread that pass for Jewish rye by default, similar to the way DiGiorno can technically be called pizza.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Orwasher&amp;rsquo;s, one of NYC&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ChZ4ZBQ1dkQ">most legendary&lt;/a> bakeries, still make 10-lb. loaves of &lt;em>shissel&lt;/em> rye daily, and customers can buy as much or as little as they need.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/kornerstone/Orwashers-community-rye_2022-06-17.png"
alt="Orwasher&amp;#39;s community rye in 2022"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Orwasher&amp;rsquo;s community rye in 2022, on UberEats.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The original Orwasher&amp;rsquo;s opened in 1916 on East 78th Street between 1st and 2nd Avenues, by a Hungarian immigrant named Abraham Orwasher, when a stretch of Yorkville used to be known as &amp;ldquo;Little Hungary.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Under current owner Keith Cohen, who took over in 2007, the bakery has become more internationally-focused (i.e. more French baguettes and brioches, and American-style white bread) while maintaining its mom-and-pop feel. They have paid heed to the &amp;ldquo;local movement&amp;rdquo; (who hasn&amp;rsquo;t?) by incorporating regionally-grown grains.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Cohen has pushed hard to build out the distribution arm of the business, and the bakery now churns out ~10,000 loaves a day and sells to 100+ different places around NYC. Cohen &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=yfrOH5OwKBk&amp;amp;t=270s">says&lt;/a> Orwasher&amp;rsquo;s still makes its rye bread from an OG rye sour starter that hasn&amp;rsquo;t been remade in 100+ years, but the bakery&amp;rsquo;s rye bread is no longer what it was.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Cohen published &lt;em>Orwasher&amp;rsquo;s Artisan Bread&lt;/em> in 2014. Out of curiosity, I looked it up. Bingo, the book has a recipe for the bakery&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;New York rye bread.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/kornerstone/NY_Rye_Orwashers_Artisan_Bread_2014.png"
alt="book recipe for Orwasher&amp;#39;s NY classic deli rye"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Recipe for Orwasher&amp;rsquo;s NY classic deli rye, published in &amp;lsquo;Orwasher&amp;rsquo;s Artisan Bread&amp;rsquo; (2014)&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The recipe doesn&amp;rsquo;t list any rye flour as an ingredient, but does call for a &amp;ldquo;rye biga.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The book says the bakery keeps two rye bigas: one white at 46% hydration and one dark at 133% hydration. I would guess that the dark rye biga is built with dark rye flour, which is usually a wholegrain (100% extraction) flour complete with all the bran and germ; and the white rye biga is built with all-purpose rye flour (65%-70% extraction, with the bran and germ removed).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The book specifies &amp;ldquo;white rye biga&amp;rdquo; as such wherever it&amp;rsquo;s called. Elsewhere, it lists simply &amp;ldquo;rye biga,&amp;rdquo; such as in this recipe. I&amp;rsquo;m assuming it either refers to the dark rye biga by default or they are meant to be interchangeable.&lt;/p>
&lt;pre tabindex="0">&lt;code>453.6g of dark rye biga (133% hydration) = 194.6g dark rye flour + 259g water
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;p>This means the total amount of (dark) rye present in the entire loaf is&lt;/p>
&lt;pre tabindex="0">&lt;code>194.6g / (194.6g + 1110g) = 14.9%
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/kornerstone/NY_Rye_photo_Orwashers_Artisan_Bread_2014.png"
alt="book photo for Orwasher&amp;#39;s NY classic deli rye"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Photo for Orwasher&amp;rsquo;s NY classic deli rye, published in &amp;lsquo;Orwasher&amp;rsquo;s Artisan Bread&amp;rsquo; (2014)&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>But in case it uses the white rye biga,&lt;/p>
&lt;pre tabindex="0">&lt;code>453.6g of white rye biga (46% hydration) = 310.6 white rye flour + 143g water
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;p>The total amount of (white) rye present in the entire loaf would be&lt;/p>
&lt;pre tabindex="0">&lt;code>310.6g / (310.6g + 1110g) = 21.9%
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;p>Even if this &amp;ldquo;rye biga&amp;rdquo; turns out to be a blend of the dark and the white, you know the range of rye percentages in Orwasher&amp;rsquo;s NY rye bread: &lt;code>14.9% dark rye&lt;/code> ~ &lt;code>21.9% white rye&lt;/code>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>And caraway is a skimpy 4% of the total flour weight. That will probably get even skimpier given the caraway shortage caused by Covid-related supply disruptions.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/kornerstone/Orwashers-rye-2019.png"
alt="Orwasher&amp;#39;s NY classic deli rye in 2019"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Orwasher&amp;rsquo;s NY classic deli rye in 2019&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/kornerstone/Orwashers_rye_bread_UberEats_20220617.png"
alt="Orwasher&amp;#39;s NY classic deli rye in 2022"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Orwasher&amp;rsquo;s NY classic deli rye in 2022, on UberEats.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>I guess trying to run the business as a bakery, sandwich shop and café simultaneously that serves breakfast, lunch and dinner has diluted the quality of the oldie that made it famous. Still, kudos to Orwasher&amp;rsquo;s for being able to pay Manhattan rents every month and stay in business for 100+ years.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>On weekends, Orwasher&amp;rsquo;s also makes a postmodern &amp;ldquo;corn rye&amp;rdquo; with a local spin, using local Sixpoint Brewery&amp;rsquo;s Righteous Rye Ale in the dough.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/kornerstone/Corn_Rye_Orwashers_Artisan_Bread_2014.png"
alt="book recipe for Orwasher&amp;#39;s corn rye"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Recipe for Orwasher&amp;rsquo;s corn rye, published in &amp;lsquo;Orwasher&amp;rsquo;s Artisan Bread&amp;rsquo; (2014)&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/kornerstone/Orwashers-righteous-rye_2022-06-17"
alt="Orwasher&amp;#39;s Righteous Rye bread in 2022"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Orwasher&amp;rsquo;s Righteous Rye bread in 2022, on UberEats.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>A traditionally made &lt;em>kornbroyt&lt;/em> is highly prized by Jewish bread aficionados today because 1) as George Greenstein says in his 1993 book, &lt;em>Secrets of a Jewish Baker&lt;/em>, &amp;ldquo;there are few bakeries left that haven&amp;rsquo;t compromised its real flavor, moisture, and texture&amp;rdquo;; and 2) in this hyper-Instagrammable era of openest-crumb breadporn and hypnotizing unicorn bagels, the rougher-textured, leathery-looking loaf still has the pull and tang of tradition that transcends time.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Jewish deli rye made with &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->&amp;gt;=20% of coarse rye flour&lt;sup id="fnref:5">&lt;a href="#fn:5" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">5&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --> hasn&amp;rsquo;t existed for years in NYC. Sadly, most New Yorkers don&amp;rsquo;t know the difference between good and &lt;a href="https://larissazimberoff.com/articles/2014/07/why-is-new-york-rye-bread-so-bad.html">bad rye bread&lt;/a>. They just firmly believe in the superiority of their ryes, and foolishly brag about the magic of &lt;a href="https://www.ediblemanhattan.com/food-for-thought/why-is-new-york-tap-water-good/">NYC tap water&lt;/a>, which they love to credit for bestowing everything from pizzas to bagels to coffee with the city&amp;rsquo;s unique flavor. Apparently, that holy water has done nothing to save NYC&amp;rsquo;s rye bread from condemnation.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The author Andrew Coe &lt;a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20141230123837/https://www.seriouseats.com/2014/06/rebuilding-the-jewish-bakery.html">explained&lt;/a> in a 2014 article:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;You may have never heard of Shissel Rye before &amp;ndash; it&amp;rsquo;s a bread that didn&amp;rsquo;t survive the softening and blandification of the New York rye tradition. &amp;ldquo;Shissel&amp;rdquo; means bowl in Yiddish, and maybe it&amp;rsquo;s so named because the loaf looks like an inverted bowl. From the outside, it&amp;rsquo;s easy to mistake it for a corn rye, because it has a similar leathery crust. But it&amp;rsquo;s made from wetter dough than corn rye, which gives the loaf a denser crumb and more pronounced sour twang.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Sure, there are dozens of new artisan bakeries that have tried to revive the real Deli rye bread and &lt;em>kornbroyt&lt;/em>. They are not rye bread as such, but &amp;ldquo;Old World&amp;rdquo; artisan wholegrain sourdough breads that seek to imitate &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WUxClvWBHtk">Poilâne&amp;rsquo;s legendarily crusty boules&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="heartland--jewish-soul-food-mecca">Heartland = Jewish soul food mecca&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Few have looked west and figured out &lt;a href="https://www.myjewishlearning.com/the-nosher/the-best-jewish-food-in-detroit/">the plethora of Jewish delis in Detroit&lt;/a> are some of America&amp;rsquo;s best-kept culinary secrets. That&amp;rsquo;s where the process of double-baking rye bread was pioneered and where legit Jewish rye breads are still made.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Jews have lived in Detroit for &amp;gt;200 years. The earliest Jewish immigrants were mostly German, but plenty of Hungarian, Russian, and Polish Jews settled in the Detroit-Ann Arbor-Ypsilanti area as well and brought their family recipes with them.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Many of the region&amp;rsquo;s early Jewish families opened grocery stores (Farmer Jack&amp;rsquo;s, Hiller&amp;rsquo;s, Freeman &amp;amp; Reese Grocers, etc.) and delis (Zingerman&amp;rsquo;s, the Stage Deli, etc). It was at the Stage Deli in Oak Park, in the post-WWII years when the composition of rye bread started incorporating larger and larger portions of cheaper and longer-lasting white flour, where the now-famed Detroit-style rye bread really began.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In the 1960s, Jack Goldberg, founder of the Stage Deli, was intent on serving the freshest rye bread to customers. Local bakeries delivered bread early in the morning, but most of Jack&amp;rsquo;s customers were coming in at lunch, when the rye bread they wanted was already cold. So he started ordering his rye bread partially cooked (baking halted ~80% of the way through). Just before the lunch rush, he would finish baking the bread in a steaming oven in house, so they were still warm in time for lunch. That last-minute steam gives the bread a soft, moist center and a crackly crispy crust. Additionally, forgoing the thin slicer that everyone else was using, Jack put the loaves on a deli meat slicer and cut the hot bread, fresh to order, into roughly 1&amp;quot; thick slices &amp;ndash; perfect for supporting the hulking pile of fatty meat without falling apart.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Most [sandwiches] are served on Jack Goldberg&amp;rsquo;s famous double-baked rye, a Detroit specialty. The rye in New York generally comes pre-sliced, in small disks about half an inch thick. The best deli ryes have a crisp, amber-colored crust and soft center, though these are increasingly difficult to find, especially in New York. Back when he started, Jack Goldberg pioneered the process of double-baking his rye breads. &amp;hellip; The warm loaf is cut into inch-thick slices on a diagonal. When you bite into a slice of double-baked rye, the difference in taste and texture is astounding. A thick, rustic crust greets your teeth, recalling the pleasurable chewiness of sourdough. The warm center of a double-baked rye has an airier density about it and doesn&amp;rsquo;t break apart when stressed with a Bye-Bye-Birdie (house-roasted turkey breast, chopped liver and Russian dressing). It makes New York&amp;rsquo;s rye taste like pigeon food.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>David Sax, &lt;em>Save the Deli&lt;/em> (2009)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Jack&amp;rsquo;s double-baked rye distinguished the Stage Deli from the competition. The method caught on, and soon enough every single Jewish deli across the Motor City was selling warm rye bread that held up well under pressure. Jack&amp;rsquo;s winning business formula is still used today at the Stage Deli in West Bloomfield.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The Stage Deli, along with other local joints like Steve&amp;rsquo;s Deli and the Bread Basket Deli, all use thick-cut rye that employs a decent amount of rye flour blended with the white flour, unlike most of the rye-less loaves in New York masquerading as Jewish rye.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>I first experienced double baked rye at the Bread Basket, a small chain of Detroit delicatessens, with Sy Ginsberg, the corned beef king of Michigan and much of the Midwest. As the waitress set down a sandwich of Ginsberg&amp;rsquo;s trademark corned beef in front of us, I was equally impressed with the bread. It had a darker flecked color to it, with a golden crust that reminded me of good sourdough. The crumb was warm to the touch, and the heat of the oven had released a tangy perfume of yeast. It felt like a little pillow in my hand, cradling the tender corned beef slicked with mustard. The crust had crackle and chew, the crumb was soft and doughy. It tasted like rye bread ought to.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>David Sax&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Those who grew up in eastern Missouri / southern Illinois would vividly recall the taste of &amp;ldquo;tzitzel&amp;rdquo; rye from Pratzel&amp;rsquo;s Bakery, the last Jewish-owned kosher bakery in St. Louis. This round caraway rye bread came coated in cornmeal, and was the pride of the bakery&amp;rsquo;s founders, who opened shop in ~1913, and of their successors who operated the business until 2011.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A 2011 book, &lt;em>From the Jewish Heartland: Two Centuries of Midwest Foodways&lt;/em>, by Ellen F. Steinberg and Jack H. Prost, includes a long interview with the descendants of Max Pratzel, with particular fervor about the &lt;em>tzitzel&lt;/em> rye, which also appears in many other food memories about this bakery.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.losttables.com/pratzels/pratzels.htm">Lost Tables&lt;/a>, an amazing website that chronicles lost restaurants in St. Louis, tells the story behind Pratzel&amp;rsquo;s rye:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Long before sourdough was a word associated with San Francisco, Jewish bakers were creating ryes and pumpernickel breads using sourdough starters they brought with them from Europe. When Max Pratzel came to St. Louis, he went to another Jewish baker and asked him for a small portion of his sour culture. Pratzel&amp;rsquo;s continued to grow that culture for almost 100 years and used it to make their rye bread.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Bakers used cornmeal to glide loaves in and out of the baking ovens. Nate Pratzel liked the taste of the cornmeal coated rye bread bottoms so much that he would cut them off and take them home. Eventually, it occurred to him that it might be a good idea to cover the entire loaf with cornmeal, which is how one of Pratzel&amp;rsquo;s bestseller, tzizel rye bread, was born.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Luckily, the sister site Lost Dishes has posted a &lt;a href="https://www.lostdishes.com/pratzels/tzizel.htm">recipe&lt;/a> for the &lt;em>tzitzel&lt;/em> rye, for anyone who&amp;rsquo;s interested. It&amp;rsquo;s from a &lt;a href="http://littlecreekpress.com/bookstore/manna-cafe-and-bakery-cookbooka-memoir-of-two-businesses-a-community-and-the-food-that-connected-them/">recent cookbook&lt;/a> by descendants of the Pratzel family who moved to Wisconsin, opened a bakery there, and shipped the tzizel rye bread to hungry former St. Louisans around the country. The bakery &lt;a href="https://www.northsidenews.org/manna-cafe-bakery-closes-after-15-years-nourishing-the-northside/">closed&lt;/a> in the midst of Covid, as the Pratzels were at the end of their lease and approaching their own retirement age.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Like everything else these days, Jewish deli rye &amp;ndash; like the bagel &amp;ndash; is becoming &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->an endangered species&lt;sup id="fnref:6">&lt;a href="#fn:6" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">6&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->, with fewer and fewer bakeries making it the traditional way.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="diy-old-school-deli-rye">DIY old-school deli rye&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>If you want a good deli rye, you gotta make it at home. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t take years to bake yourself a decent loaf of rye bread that tastes delicious and can stand up to corned beef. Your great-(great-etc.) grandmothers most likely didn&amp;rsquo;t apprentice at a Paris &lt;em>boulangrie&lt;/em> and still churned out great rye bread with whatever starters they had and kept going throughout some pretty challenging winters. I also highly doubt they had the luxury of building a sour culture meticulously with all kinds of grains à la Tartine, discarding &amp;gt;=90% of it, replenishing it with a new supply of flour, and letting it mature for the right number of days until it was ready to set up in loaves.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>You just have to be willing to experiment and fail a couple of times and pay attention to how it looks, feels, smells, and be willing to fiddle around and adjust the next time. Early delivery, continual improvement, and flexible adjustment, much like agile software development.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This rye I made is a variation of the old-school deli rye, closer to a &lt;em>kornbroyt&lt;/em> than a contemporary rye-flavored bread at delis.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/kornerstone/202206181714.jpg"
alt="kornerstone: Jewish deli rye"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>I used a whole lot of single-grind wholegrain rye flour: 30% of final flour weight, and 45% of total flour weight (including the levain).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Since this dough contains a relatively high percentage of whole grains, I used a 2-dough lamination method to make it stronger. It has &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/breadford-von-regrainton/">worked well&lt;/a> for me before. I was able to give it a long fermentation.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I also added some &amp;ldquo;altus,&amp;rdquo; which was originally a way for bakers to re-use bread they hadn&amp;rsquo;t sold. They would cut &amp;ldquo;old&amp;rdquo; rye bread into small pieces, soak in water until saturated and wrung out. It makes for a more tender and flavorful bread. I didn&amp;rsquo;t &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/zombie-dust/">soak my &amp;ldquo;old&amp;rdquo; rye bread&lt;/a> (you can use any type of bread); I just let it dry out a bit and ground it into crumbs in a coffee grinder.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Instead of caraway seeds, I used caramelized onions, spent brewer&amp;rsquo;s grains, and poppy seeds. If you are concerned about the opioids in poppy seeds, &lt;a href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fchem.2021.692045/full">studies&lt;/a> have shown that crushing and intensively cooking them significantly decrease their morphine content. Additionally, poppy seeds only truly develop their nutty flavor after crushing and baking.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The rye flour I used is freshly milled &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/files/danko-rye.pdf">Danko&lt;/a> (&lt;em>Dańkowskie Nowe&lt;/em> in Polish), which is a high-yielding winter rye developed in 1976 by the Poznań Plant Breeding Center in Poland, for the purpose of milling. It was bred from a lineage of northern European ryes known for their high starch content and excellent baking performance in traditional whole rye loaves. Quite a few &lt;a href="https://danko.pl/en/odmiany-categories/rye/">newer Dańkowskie varieties&lt;/a> have been developed since. Danko itself hails from Poland&amp;rsquo;s Warta River Valley and adapts well to the Mid-Atlantic climate. It has a floral aroma when freshly milled, and a good flavor balance between bready and spicy. (I haven&amp;rsquo;t been able to track down a &lt;a href="https://www.ryerevival.org/projects">Midwestern source&lt;/a> for Danko rye. If you know of any, &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/say-hi/">drop me a line&lt;/a>!)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Similar to how grape varietals and terroir influence the style and character of wines, so do varieties of rye &amp;ndash; and the soils and micro-climates they grow in. Rye whiskey derives its unique spicy and flavorful characteristics from the complexity of the grain. A traditional rye bread is definitively more flavorful than white bread. Many of the ryes that grow well in the US are old varieties brought over from Europe. There are also some newer hybrids that are being tested especially for local climate and soil conditions.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/kornerstone/202206191549.jpg"
alt="kornerstone: Jewish deli rye"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>As usual, I refreshed the levain 3 times with freshly milled wholegrain rye flour (80% hydration) over a period of 24 hours, and let it ferment at 60°F-70°F until it doubled in volume and was brimming with bubbles and a clean vinegary smell. Alternatively, you could sift the wholegrain rye into a medium rye flour and some coarse bits; use the former in the final dough, and feed the latter to the levain. You can manipulate the balance of acetic acid to lactic acid in the rye sour by changing the hydration: a dryer, more dough-like sour will contain more acetic acid and give a more vinegary flavor, while a wetter one (more like a thick paste at the start and a pancake batter once it&amp;rsquo;s developed) will tend more towards the lactic side and a yogurty/cheesy flavor.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>80% extraction wheat flour (Marquis - Anarchy Acres, WI)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>50%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>100% extraction wheat flour (Wisconsin #2 - Anarchy Acres, WI)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>15%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>100% extraction rye flour (Danko - Zeng Farm, NJ)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>30%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>old rye bread crumbs (aka. altus)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>cold water (50°F)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>92%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>rye levain (80% hydration)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>50%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>caramelized onions&lt;/td>
&lt;td>20%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>spent brewer&amp;rsquo;s grains&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Dutch blue poppy seeds, crushed (Savory Spice)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>kosher salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>America loves sweet onions! They are so popular that nowadays you can find them in any grocery store anytime of the year. I used a large Vidalia onion from a farmers' market. I cut the onion into medium-width slices, and cooked them on a George Foreman grill until brown and fragrant.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Dough #1: Autolyze the rye flour, whole wheat flour and breadcrumbs with just a little over half (~55%) of the total water. Mix thoroughly to hydrate every particle of the grain, cover, and leave for ~2 hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Dough #2: Mix together the 80% extraction wheat flour with the rest of the water. Cover and leave for ~2 hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Next, add equal portion of the levain and the salt to each dough. Mix or slap &amp;amp; fold for 5-10 mins. The wholegrain rye-wheat dough is weak and sticky, but it&amp;rsquo;s OK. The 80% extraction wheat flour dough should be strong and extensible.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Fold each dough 3 times in the next 2 hours, at 30-min intervals.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Now, the lamination: Wet your work surface with a spray bottle filled with water, to prevent the dough from sticking to it. Turn each dough out onto the damp surface, and gently spread it out as thinly and evenly as possible without tearing, into one large rectangle.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Carefully place the wholegrain rye-wheat dough on top of the other one. Try to line them up as much as possible.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Sprinkle all of the add-ins (onions, spent grains, and poppy seeds) all over the dough. Fold the dough into thirds (left-right, up-down) evenly and symmetrically to create the lamination and layer everything together.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Transfer the dough into a fridge to finish bulk fermentation overnight. I did take it out a few hours later to do another couple of coil-folds, and returned it to the fridge immediately after. Total bulk-fermentation: 2.5 hours at room temperature (~70°F) and 12 hours in the fridge (~40°F).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Next morning, take the dough out of the fridge. Mine doubled in volume overnight and felt so full of air pockets.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Pre-shape it loosely via a coil-fold. After a 30-min rest, shape the dough tightly into whatever form you desire. I shaped mine into a log, rolled it in additional onions and spent grains, and placed it in a parchment paper-lined loaf pan for final proof. You can, of course, roll the dough in a copious amount of caraway seeds or coarsely ground cornmeal.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>After 2 hours of final rise at room temperature, I baked it, as usual, in my ghetto toaster oven. The first 20 mins at 350°F, followed by another 30 mins at 300°F.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/kornerstone/202206181722.jpg"
alt="kornerstone: Jewish deli rye"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>It turned out a magnificent rye, without a fancy pizza stone or preheated Le Creuset Dutch oven.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/kornerstone/202206181715.jpg"
alt="kornerstone: Jewish deli rye"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>I waited 24 hours before cutting it. Patience is a virtue in short supply.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The crumb is highly moist and delicate. As soft as the finest goose down pillow.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/kornerstone/202206191228.jpg"
alt="kornerstone: Jewish deli rye"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>It tastes much bolder than a typical deli rye.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I like it toasted, smeared with cream cheese, and topped with olives.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>That tender crumb mingles marvelously with fatty, flaky corned beef, conjuring up a guilty pleasure so heavenly that it&amp;rsquo;s worth the heartburn.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/kornerstone/202206191239.jpg"
alt="kornerstone: Jewish deli rye"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>A real Jewish treat, before everyone became uber health-conscious, used to be a roast beef sandwich on rye with Bermuda onions and &lt;em>schmaltz&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The bread also pairs exquisitely with &lt;em>komijnekaas&lt;/em> (a classic Dutch gouda-style cheese seasoned with cumin and caraway seeds) or Veldhuizen&amp;rsquo;s caraway cheddar.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/kornerstone/202206191542.jpg"
alt="kornerstone: Jewish deli rye"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Bon appétit!&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>2022/12/31 update&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Just watched a Hallmark movie called &lt;em>Hanukkah on Rye&lt;/em>. All the sandwich breads featured in the movie looked so white that it made me think of this rye&amp;hellip; So I made another loaf &amp;ndash; with &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/attack-of-the-ryeclops">heritage Finnish rye&lt;/a>. I put some raw onions in the rye levain and added more caramelized onions to the final dough. Seriously onion-y.&lt;/p>
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>For recipes, see either &lt;em>Inside the Jewish Bakery: Recipes and Memories from the Golden Age of Jewish Baking&lt;/em> by Stanley Ginsberg and Norman Berg, or &lt;em>Secrets of a Jewish Baker&lt;/em> by George Greenstein.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>Bernard Clayton&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em>New Complete Book of Breads&lt;/em> includes a recipe for Old Milwaukee Rye, originally from Bernadine Landsberg of Milwaukee. Additionally, the 1st edition (2001-2002) of &lt;em>Home Cooking: Dickinson County Style&lt;/em> features a &lt;a href="https://cookingwithbarryandmeta.blogspot.com/2012/12/old-milwaukee-rye-bread.html">recipe&lt;/a> for Old Milwaukee Rye from Rethie Foster, who initially discovered this bread in the newspaper and it became a favorite.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:3" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>North Dakota is rye country as well as wheat country, a rich land where 19th-century Norwegian settlers come to life in Ole Edvart Rølvaag&amp;rsquo;s classic family saga, &lt;em>Giants in the Earth&lt;/em>. Dakota Harvest Bakers in Grand Forks, ND developed a quintessentially American interpretation of a traditional rye bread, for its Scandinavian-American customers who craved &amp;ldquo;bread like Nana used to make.&amp;rdquo; Stanley Ginsberg included a recipe in his 2016 book, &lt;em>The Rye Baker&lt;/em>.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:4" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>17th-century settlers in the Massachusetts Bay Colony tried to grow wheat, but the unfavorable climate and soil forced them to switch to rye.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:4" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:5" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>20% rye and 80% wheat is roughly the ratio that George Greenstein uses in his 1993 book, &lt;em>Secrets of a Jewish Baker&lt;/em>.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:5" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:6" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>See David Sax&amp;rsquo;s 2009 book, &lt;em>Save the Deli: In Search of Perfect Pastrami, Crusty Rye, and the Heart of Jewish Delicatessen&lt;/em>.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:6" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/section></content></item><item><title>Squirrels Hoard</title><link>/posts/squirrels-hoard/</link><pubDate>Wed, 13 Oct 2021 22:33:41 -0600</pubDate><guid>/posts/squirrels-hoard/</guid><description>A forager&amp;rsquo;s bread, loaded with wild acorns, black walnuts, and hickory nuts.</description><content>&lt;p>Last few weeks I went on multiple wild food foraging expeditions. It was a blast. Came back with a boatload of pawpaws, acorns, hickory nuts, and black walnuts.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Acorns are not delicious right off the tree, which is likely what started the modern misconception that they are inedible. Acorns are definitely edible. They just require a process called &amp;ldquo;leaching&amp;rdquo; to remove the bitter tannins and become palatable, and all it takes is water and time. The internet has a ton of information on how to do that.&lt;/p>
&lt;div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
&lt;iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/4zyI6vn9Azg" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video">&lt;/iframe>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>Black walnuts are a pain in the butt to process. So I took the whole load to a local hulling station, and paid a small fee (60¢/lb) to have the black walnuts dehulled and cleaned. Just got a big sack of clean and dry whole black walnuts back. All I needed to do was crack the black walnuts and hickory nuts on my vintage metal nut cracker, and pick out the nut meat. A tedious yet meditative activity.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Once the acorns were done leaching and the nuts shelled, I wanted to make a bread to celebrate the beautiful season.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I came up with a Midwest Blend of heritage wheat flours:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>50% Red Fife (Anarchy Acres, WI): a HRSW first grown in Canada in 1842 by farmer David Fife; aka. the OG Canadian Wheat&lt;/li>
&lt;li>30% Turkey Red (Ben Penner Farms, MN): a beautiful HRWW, as &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/the-wheatwalker/">previously demonstrated&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>20% Goldcoin (Anarchy Acres, WI): a SWWW with &amp;lt;10% protein&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>After reading up on acorns, I decided to infuse them into the dough in 3 different ways:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>roasted acorn flour: dehydrate leached acorn meal, grind into a fine flour, and roast slowly in an oven until dark brown and caramelized (but not burnt)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>acorn levain: build a levain with leached wet acorn meal&lt;/li>
&lt;li>cream of acorn: cook leached acorn meal into a porridge, with flaxseeds, poppyseeds, chia seeds, and sunflower seeds&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>So, yeah, a boatload of acorns in this bread. Because, why not?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Formula for the dough:&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>88% extraction Midwest Blend heritage flour&lt;/td>
&lt;td>75%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>roasted acorn flour&lt;/td>
&lt;td>25%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>acorn levain&lt;/td>
&lt;td>40%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>cream of acorn&lt;/td>
&lt;td>30%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>h₂o&lt;/td>
&lt;td>83%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1.5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>hickory nuts, toasted&lt;/td>
&lt;td>7%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>black walnuts, toasted&lt;/td>
&lt;td>7%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>No autolyse. Simply mix everything together and cold-ferment for 44 hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/squirrels-hoard/202110121749.jpg"
alt="forager&amp;#39;s bread"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/squirrels-hoard/202110121750.jpg"
alt="forager&amp;#39;s bread"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/squirrels-hoard/202110121751.jpg"
alt="forager&amp;#39;s bread"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The baked bread took on a beautiful chocolate color with a purplish hue.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/squirrels-hoard/202110121132.jpg"
alt="forager&amp;#39;s bread"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The sweet nutty aroma was absolutely wonderful &amp;ndash; it reminded me of hazelnuts (or even nutella).&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/squirrels-hoard/202110121956.jpg"
alt="forager&amp;#39;s bread"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/squirrels-hoard/202110121957.jpg"
alt="forager&amp;#39;s bread"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The crumb was very moist, tender and custardy, yet still springy like a sponge cake.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It tasted totally different than how it smelt. The bold earthiness of the wild nuts dominated the flavor profile.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/squirrels-hoard/202110121131.jpg"
alt="forager&amp;#39;s bread"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Squirrels Hoard, a forager&amp;rsquo;s dream.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Only a mild sweet nutty flavor from the acorn, and a subtle hint of tang.&lt;/p></content></item><item><title>Aquaboogie</title><link>/posts/aquaboogie/</link><pubDate>Wed, 05 May 2021 23:10:46 -0600</pubDate><guid>/posts/aquaboogie/</guid><description>&lt;em>Pan de Cristal&lt;/em>, an elusive gem. A whopping 110% hydration plus 15% oil results in an extremely wet formless mixture which, after proper mixing, transforms into a marvelously glossy and almost fluid blob of a dough that spreads willingly &amp;ndash; and yields elastic translucent crumbs and a terrain of air bubbles.</description><content>&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;ve been playing with &lt;em>pan de cristal&lt;/em>, using freshly milled whole wheat flour bolted down to 80% extraction.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Pan de cristal&lt;/em> (called &lt;em>pa de vidre&lt;/em> in Catalan) is a Spanish &amp;ldquo;glass bread&amp;rdquo; invented in ~2004 by Barcelonian baker Jordi Nomen. It&amp;rsquo;s characterized by high hydration and double fermentation, which causes a very hollow and alveolate crumb that&amp;rsquo;s almost non-existent. &lt;em>Pan de cristal&lt;/em> is now a registered trademark &lt;a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/913153046">owned by its creator&lt;/a>. Nomen&amp;rsquo;s next bakery, Concept Pa, has developed a more extreme variety called &lt;em>&lt;a href="http://www.pandecristal.com/products/diamond-crystal-bread-r/">pan de cristal® diamante&lt;/a>&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Claudio Perrando, a German-Panamanian baker who rose to international stardom over the last decade through the internet, seems to be the most famous ambassador of &lt;em>pan de cristal.&lt;/em> His version has translucent crumb and such MASSIVE holes that it undoubtedly wins the competition for the Bread with the Fewest Calories per Cubic Centimeter. He sells his recipes online. I&amp;rsquo;ve never bought his recipes, but from what I can tell, he uses an over-ripe poolish and a long autolyse (with high-gluten super-fine flour) to add more extensibility to the dough. He does a 3-4h warm bulk-fermentation and a 1h final proof.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>80% extraction wheat flour (Turkey Red - Aspen Moon Farm, CO)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>cold &lt;em>aqua&lt;/em> (autolyse 75% + bassinage 30% + salt mixing 5%)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>110%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>rye levain&lt;/td>
&lt;td>35%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>olive oil&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->10%-20%&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Autolyze the flour with 75% of the &lt;em>aqua&lt;/em> for 1-2 hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Add the levain and mix until gluten development.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Add the next 30% &lt;em>aqua&lt;/em> in 4 increments &lt;em>à la bassinage&lt;/em>. Make sure each addition of water is well absorbed before adding more.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Let rest for 15-20 mins, and mix in the salt with the last 5% &lt;em>aqua&lt;/em>. The dough will noticeably tighten after absorbing the salt.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Let rest for 30 mins before mixing in the oil. The dough should be super airy and jiggly.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Perform 5 coil folds, at 45-min intervals. Sprinkle any add-ins at each fold, e.g., cinnamon sugar, chocolate chips, herbs.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Bulk ferment at 75F for 3h and retard in the fridge overnight. (Or straight to the fridge for 36-48h after the first 2 folds at room temperature.)&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/aquaboogie/202205050812.jpg"
alt="80% extraction pan de cristal"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/aquaboogie/202205050813.jpg"
alt="80% extraction pan de cristal"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Next day, take it out of the fridge, divide and rest 2-3h. No shaping necessary.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Bake at 375°F for the first 20 mins, until the crust is brown and blistered. Bake for another 10-15 mins at 350F until cooked through.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/aquaboogie/202205051301.jpg"
alt="80% extraction pan de cristal"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Pan de cristal, made with 80% extraction Turkey Red.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>A whopping 110% hydration plus 15% oil results in an extremely wet formless mixture which, after proper mixing, transforms into a gorgeously glossy and almost fluid blob of a dough that spreads willingly, and yields elastic translucent crumbs and a terrain of air bubbles.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/aquaboogie/202205051305.jpg"
alt="80% extraction pan de cristal"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Crispy. Chewy. Bubbly. Wheaty. With flecks and sheen in the crumb like Italian terrazzo floors.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This bread makes fantastic and ginormous sandwiches as the way Roman Gods intended. Also an excellent delivery vessel for tomatoes and Iberian ham.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/aquaboogie/202205051307.jpg"
alt="80% extraction pan de cristal"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>BTW, I make &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/aquaboogie-van-wheatsworth/">wholegrain versions&lt;/a>, too.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>This is also the base recipe I use for my scandalous &lt;em>schiacciata toscana&lt;/em>. It&amp;rsquo;s supposedly a Florentine flat bread that is characteristically closer to a &lt;em>pizza bianca&lt;/em> than anything else, made famous by All&amp;rsquo;antico Vinaio (rumored to be the greatest sandwich shop in the world).&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>The Florentine &lt;em>schiacciata all&amp;rsquo;olio&lt;/em> uses a goodly amount of olive oil and large grain salt, and the best is cooked in a wood burning oven. It should be crispy but not hard, oily but not greasy.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>If making &lt;em>schiacciata&lt;/em>, flip the dough onto a rectangular baking sheet. Use fingers to gently dent and push the dough outwards towards all four corners, preserving the air bubbles inside, until the dough is about 3/4&amp;quot; (2 cm) at its thickest part. Make random dimples 2&amp;quot; (5 cm) apart that puncture all the way through the dough to the pan. This will prevent the dough from doming too much while baking and help create even thickness for sandwiches. Drizzle olive oil all over the surface of the dough.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The best way to appreciate the unique flavor of Turkey Red &lt;em>pan de cristal&lt;/em> is to add a touch of salted butter and/or honey and eat while still slightly warm. When the bread starts to stale, toast it and dunk it into a warm, funky dip like a &lt;em>bagna càuda&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;ve experimented with increasing the amount of oil to ~20% of flour weight, and had great results.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/section></content></item><item><title>Harpy's Lovesong</title><link>/posts/harpys-lovesong/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Apr 2021 19:22:12 -0600</pubDate><guid>/posts/harpys-lovesong/</guid><description>A magical multigrain bread.</description><content>&lt;p>The first time I tasted naturally leavened bread was in April 2014, in Athens, Georgia. I was hitting a low point in life. A friend brought me a loaf of multigrain bread from &lt;a href="https://www.independentbaking.com/">Independent Baking Co.&lt;/a>, a new bakery in the heart of Five Points.&lt;/p>
&lt;div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
&lt;iframe src="https://player.vimeo.com/video/82806228" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" title="vimeo video" webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen>&lt;/iframe>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>I didn&amp;rsquo;t have the faintest idea what sourdough was, but that loaf of bread &amp;ndash; dark caramel-colored crackly crusts enrobed a cream-colored nutty crumb, with a slight tang and a satisfying flavor &amp;ndash; cheered me up somehow and remained etched in my memory.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This bread is an attempt to recreate that magical warm moment.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/harpys-lovesong/202104030952.jpg"
alt="Harpy&amp;#39;s Lovesong"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;h4 id="levain">Levain&lt;/h4>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>100g freshly milled brown teff (Desert Oasis, NV)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>100g whole milk&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>stiff WW starter&lt;/td>
&lt;td>15%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>In case you didn&amp;rsquo;t know, teff is the world&amp;rsquo;s smallest &amp;ldquo;grain&amp;rdquo; (actually the seed of an Ethiopian grass) that&amp;rsquo;s mostly bran and germ.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Microwave freshly milled teff flour and milk for 2 mins, until a porridge consistency is reached. Add the starter after the mixture has cooled off completely. Leave the levain to mature for 14+ hours at ~65°F.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="soaker">Soaker&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>Soak as many varieties of grains and seeds as you would like. Total dry weight is 40% of the flour weight in the final dough.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>millet&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>quinoa&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>kaniwa&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>amaranth&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>pumpkin seeds&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>rolled oats&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>flaxseeds&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sunflower seeds&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>poppy seeds&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sesame seeds&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>water&lt;/td>
&lt;td>150%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Let the soaker stand at room temperature for 12 hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="dough">Dough&lt;/h4>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>80% extraction wheat flour (Rouge de Bordeaux - Dayspring Farms, GA)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>80%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>whole spelt flour (Sungold spelt - Grapewood Farm, VA)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>whole rye flour (Abruzzi rye - Carter Farms, NC)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>brown rice flour (Charleston Gold - Anson Mills, SC)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>water&lt;/td>
&lt;td>85%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>soaker (not drained)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>shredded coconut (for dusting)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2%-5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Cold-ferment for 24+ hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/harpys-lovesong/202104030955.jpg"
alt="Harpy&amp;#39;s Lovesong"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/harpys-lovesong/202104031001.jpg"
alt="Harpy&amp;#39;s Lovesong"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/harpys-lovesong/202104031002.jpg"
alt="Harpy&amp;#39;s Lovesong"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/harpys-lovesong/202104031029.jpg"
alt="Harpy&amp;#39;s Lovesong"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Harpy&amp;rsquo;s Lovesong, a magical multigrain bread.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure></content></item><item><title>Kyoto by Blimp</title><link>/posts/kyoto-by-blimp/</link><pubDate>Fri, 11 Dec 2020 17:41:59 -0600</pubDate><guid>/posts/kyoto-by-blimp/</guid><description>Marbled &lt;em>matcha&lt;/em> cocoa bread, made with Kyoto Uji &lt;em>matcha&lt;/em> and a blend of Southern flours. A kaleidoscope of fun flavors.</description><content>&lt;p>I love &lt;em>matcha&lt;/em> (抹茶), which is basically powdered green tea. Like anything in life, it&amp;rsquo;s an acquired taste. I hated bitter beers when I first tried them, but now I love the likes of Chimay Cinq Cents and Stone Ruination. If you&amp;rsquo;ve never had &lt;em>matcha&lt;/em> before, you will likely not love it the first time you try it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>So how is &lt;em>matcha&lt;/em> different from other green teas, you ask? Well, first of all, it differs in the preparation process. Most teas are infused with water and the leaves are strained out and discarded, whereas &lt;em>matcha&lt;/em> is actually whisked into hot water, i.e. the tea leaves are consumed directly.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Secondly, &lt;em>matcha&lt;/em> actually goes through extra processes during cultivation compared to the general category of green tea usually referred to as &lt;em>sencha&lt;/em> (煎茶, steamed, rolled, and dried green tea leaves). Once the buds of the &lt;em>Camellia sinensis&lt;/em> tea leaves start to sprout, the entire crop is kept in the shade for about a month before harvesting. This slows down the rate of photosynthesis, increasing the amount of chlorophyll in the leaves. In the end, this produces a tea leaf with a sweet flavor and bold &lt;em>umami&lt;/em>. Lastly, the steamed and then thoroughly dried tea leaves are meticulously ground on a stone mill into a fine powder. This powder form is what makes it possible to add a concentrated green tea flavor to many products.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The Chinese were the first to grow and grind green tea. However, the Japanese were the ones who invented the method of creating &lt;em>matcha&lt;/em> as we know it today.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Japanese tea cultivation started when a 12th-century monk named Myouan Eisai (明菴栄西) brought green tea seeds &amp;ndash; along with the Rinzai school of Zen Buddhism &amp;ndash; from China and planted them on Mt. Sefuri. In addition, he gave tea seeds to Myoue Shounin (明恵上人), a monk from Kousan-ji temple (高山寺) in Toganoo (栂尾), Kyoto. Shounin planted the seeds near the temple and &amp;ndash; voilà! &amp;ndash; this was the start of Uji tea. Oh, Eisai also wrote a book about tea, called Kissa Yojoki (喫茶養生記), often translated as &amp;ldquo;How to Stay Healthy by Drinking Tea.&amp;rdquo; The book begins with &amp;ldquo;Tea is the ultimate mental and medical remedy and has the ability to make one’s life more full and complete”.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For a long time, only the nobility and upper echelons of the Japanese society drank green tea. It was not until the Meiji Restoration at the end of the 19th century that the cultivation, consumption and preparation of green tea became widespread in Japan.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Modern Japan has developed the most advanced and refined industry for the cultivation of a few varieties of green tea. Furthermore, it&amp;rsquo;s the world&amp;rsquo;s second largest green tea producer after China. As green tea became more popular in the West over the last two decades, China has begun to produce more and more of its own &amp;ldquo;&lt;em>matcha&lt;/em>&amp;rdquo; under &amp;ldquo;simulated&amp;rdquo; Japanese farming conditions.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Like wine grapes, the quality and growth of green tea are greatly affected by the region&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em>terroir&lt;/em>. Being Japan&amp;rsquo;s oldest and most famous green tea region means Uji is inevitably a hot spot for tea tourism. People love to visit Kyoto tea country&amp;rsquo;s traditional tea shops and modern tea emporiums, stroll through rolling hills of tea fields, and sample a variety of teas. I know people who have travelled to Uji, Japan to taste &lt;em>matcha&lt;/em> and still feel only so-so about it. Lol.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>There is a Japanese proverb that says &amp;ldquo;good medication is bitter in taste&amp;rdquo; (良薬は口に苦し), and &lt;em>matcha&lt;/em> is one of them. Matcha has a unique, complex taste. It&amp;rsquo;s slightly bitter, with a sweet aftertaste; it&amp;rsquo;s buttery and nutty, with a seaweedy undertone.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>David&amp;rsquo;s Tea &lt;em>matcha&lt;/em> is a good place to start, although it&amp;rsquo;s likely not the best &lt;em>matcha&lt;/em> that you&amp;rsquo;ll ever have.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>One way to enjoy the mild bitterness of &lt;em>matcha&lt;/em> more is to add it to baked goods. Baking enhances the rich aroma of the &lt;em>matcha&lt;/em>, and that&amp;rsquo;s why there are gazillion forms of &lt;em>matcha&lt;/em>-flavored baked goods in Asia.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For this bread, I selected flours from below the Mason Dixon line. The American South is synonymous with sweet tea, and South Carolina remains the only US state that commercially produces tea on a large scale.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;Generally, soft wheats have a high starch yield on milling and a low protein content. They are grown in areas of high rainfall and lower soil fertility, primarily east of the Mississippi River. Low-protein southern flours are deployed to their best advantage in their growing region&amp;rsquo;s specialties-biscuits, pies, and cakes where tenderness is prized over strength. Beyond wheat&amp;rsquo;s given genetic quotient of hardness or softness, environmental conditions determine the hardness of any given crop. Not only the overall protein content but also the quality and specific amounts of each protein present can be affected by seasonal variations.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Joseph Amendola &amp;amp; Nicole Rees, &lt;em>Understanding Baking: The Art and Science of Baking&lt;/em>, 3rd edition, page 7.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Wheats grown in the South generally aren&amp;rsquo;t very strong. This bread is another reminder to pay attention to the quality and property of ingredients grown in a particular region.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="matcha-dough">Matcha dough&lt;/h4>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>88% extraction wheat flour (Rouge de Bordeaux - Dayspring Farms, GA)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;em>matcha&lt;/em>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>3%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>brewed &lt;em>genmaicha&lt;/em>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>80%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>The &lt;em>matcha&lt;/em> I used here is Marukyu-Koyamaen &lt;em>aoarashi matcha&lt;/em> (丸久小山園の抹茶青嵐). It&amp;rsquo;s an entry-grade &lt;em>matcha&lt;/em> with intense flavors &amp;ndash; better for baking than sipping.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>3% &lt;em>matcha&lt;/em> may seem too little, but &lt;em>matcha&lt;/em> is only consumed about 1-2g at a time. &lt;em>Usucha&lt;/em> (薄茶), the common &lt;em>matcha&lt;/em> preparation, usually calls for 1 tsp/2g of &lt;em>matcha&lt;/em> per 70-80ml of water.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Everyday/ceremonial (not cooking) &lt;em>matcha&lt;/em> is usually made from high-grade &lt;em>gyokuro&lt;/em> (玉露), not &lt;em>sencha&lt;/em>. But for cooking &lt;em>matcha&lt;/em>, you don&amp;rsquo;t need such high grade. You could technically make your own at home, by pulverizing some high-quality green tea leaves in a coffee grinder and sifting a few times to get a fine powder. It&amp;rsquo;s totally fine in lattes, smoothies and baked goods. Some heresy right here.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>So, wtf is &lt;em>genmaicha&lt;/em> and why did I use it instead of plain h₂o? Well, &lt;em>genmaicha&lt;/em> (玄米茶) is basically a Japanese popcorn tea: a blend of roasted puffed brown rice and &lt;em>sencha&lt;/em>. You taste green tea and popcorn at the same time &amp;ndash; the best of both worlds!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I wanted a robust green tea flavor in this bread. That&amp;rsquo;s why I brewed a pot of Ippodo&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em>genmaicha&lt;/em> and soaked the flour in the cooled tea.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Rouge de Bordeaux was the OG baguette wheat from the Bordeaux region of France. It gained popularity in the 19th century among artisan bakers who loved the smooth, mellow flavor, aroma of spices, and robust performance.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="cocoa-dough">Cocoa dough&lt;/h4>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>whole spelt flour (Sungold spelt - Grapewood Farm, VA)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>50%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>cornmeal (Bloody Butcher red corn - Five Maples Farm, VA)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>whole rye flour (Abruzzi rye - Carter Farms, NC)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>brown rice flour (Charleston Gold - Anson Mills, SC)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>whole pea flour (Sea Island red peas - Marsh Hen Mill, SC)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>roasted soybean flour (Maehara Seifun kuromame kinako - Tanba, Kyoto)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>cocoa powder (Pernigotti cacao amaro)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>h₂o&lt;/td>
&lt;td>90%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Spelt is an ancient wheat with a golden color and notes of honey and fresh hay. It&amp;rsquo;s quite versatile &amp;ndash; strong enough for bread and pasta, but delicate enough for pastry doughs, cakes and cookies.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Just mix everything together, and leave them in two separate containers in the fridge overnight. Yes, overnight autolyse.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Obviously, the green dough is going to be the stronger sibling and do most of the heavy-lifting.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Next day, I let them warm up to room temperature before adding 40% ripe levain and 2% salt. The green dough was very extensible and easy to work with. The cocoa dough, not so much.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I laminated both &lt;em>pâtes&lt;/em> together and added 10% toasted walnuts and 20% dried fruits (raisins, dates, and jujubes).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The dough went through 4 hours of bulk fermentation at room temperature with 3 folds, and had ~50% rise in volume before preshaping.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>2 hours of warm proof in a loaf pan before baking. Fantastic oven spring.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/kyoto-by-blimp/202012111150.jpg"
alt="85% extraction Turkey Red wheat bread"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Cooled overnight and sliced next morning.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The bread turned out less airy than I expected. The &lt;em>matcha&lt;/em> turned out more hydroscopic than I thought it would be, and the green &lt;em>pâte&lt;/em> was a little too taut. Next time I&amp;rsquo;ll definitely increase the hydration. The green tea flavor was noticeable but mellow.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The crumb was tender, moist, and mildly chewy. A taster said the sweet fruity aroma immediately reminded him of spiced apple cider!&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/kyoto-by-blimp/202012111327.jpg"
alt="85% extraction Turkey Red wheat bread"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>This one was a lot of fun to eat: one bite tasted tart like a granny smith apple, the next bite was reminiscent of a &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/shinsekai-ambrosia/">Lärabar&lt;/a>, yet the next brought to mind mocha, nougat, hazelnut&amp;hellip; A kaleidoscope of flavors.&lt;/p></content></item><item><title>Dr. Funkenstein</title><link>/posts/dr-funkenstein/</link><pubDate>Mon, 19 Oct 2020 20:28:06 -0600</pubDate><guid>/posts/dr-funkenstein/</guid><description>A zero-waste science experiment to salvage a batch of unbeloved Karl92 wheat, through a long fermendation. It metamorphosed into a whole wheat alveolate ecstasy that you never knew existed.</description><content>&lt;p>A few weeks ago, I got some organic Karl92 wheat from Richard, grown by a local farmer.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Karl92 is a modern high-quality HRWW variety, selected from &amp;ldquo;Karl&amp;rdquo; by R. G. Sears, leader of the Manhattan wheat program from 1982 to 2000. Karl92 has higher yield and better disease resistance than the OG variety. Protein content is ~12%.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This lot of Karl92 got invaded by wild onions while still growing in the fields, and the wheat berries picked up an oniony aroma. I thought naturally onion-scented wheat was quite interesting &amp;ndash; I wondered if it would be a great flour for a herbaceous bread. There&amp;rsquo;s a niche market for everything. If I were to market this batch of Karl92, I would label them &amp;ldquo;Funkadelic Ecstasy organic whole wheat: kissed by wild onions, ingrained with Mother Earth&amp;rsquo;s inherent magic.&amp;rdquo; Coastal foodies and food snobs would go crazy about it. No doubt. FWIW, there&amp;rsquo;s a toy company that sells squishy onions &amp;ndash; stress balls in the shape and color of a red onion and, when you squish them, they actually release onion scents to encourage further stress relief.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I also got a batch of Karl92 whole wheat flour that was milled a while ago and starting to smell musty. I know, 99% of people would just toss it in the trash. But the zero-waster in me was curious whether this batch of flour could be &lt;a href="https://ift.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1111/1541-4337.12481">salvaged through fermentation&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>So I dumped the flour (1,722g) on a BBQ grill, and let it smoke over a bunch of corn husks for a few hours. The smelly flour picked up a nutty, endearing, almost bacon-y aroma. Then I sifted the smoked flour twice: got 237g coarse bran (14%) out the first time, and 220g middlings (13%) the second time, leaving 1,265g flour (73% extraction).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I divided the 237g coarse bran into&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>200g: for levain&lt;/li>
&lt;li>37g: for dusting/coating&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>And thus began my cosmic adventure into the funky world of Karl92.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="levain-425g">Levain: 425g&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>2 builds, in 24h:&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>coarse bran&lt;/td>
&lt;td>200g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>boiling water&lt;/td>
&lt;td>200g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>diastatic barley malt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sourdough starter, stiff WW&lt;/td>
&lt;td>20g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Pour boiling water over the coarse bran in a gass bowl. Mix well. Let it sit for a few hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>You can add the malt while the bran soaker has cooled off some, but add the starter only after the bran soaker has cooled off completely to room temperature.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Based on my previous baking experiments and consumption of scientific studies, the most effective way to process the bran and improve its texture is sourdough starter + alpha amylase + xylanase, let sit for 24 hours at 24°C/75°F. (I&amp;rsquo;ve done this many times on oat hull fiber and have achieved good results. I have a friend who&amp;rsquo;s pathologically obsessed with &amp;ldquo;volume eating&amp;rdquo;, e.g., consuming large volumes of food while taking in minimal calories at the same time. Oat fiber is insanely popular among these volume-eaters, because the boatload of fiber in it increases the volume of food while adding zero net carbs or calories.)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Depending on the genotype, dry wheat bran can contain about 50% dietary fiber and 9%-25% starch. Most of that dietary fiber in bran is insoluble fiber (hemicelluloses):&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>arabinoxylans (~55%)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>celluloses (9-12%)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>lignins (3-5%)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>fructans (3-4%)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>β-glucans (2.2-2.6%).&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Most arabinoxylans are water-unextractable, but a smaller part is water-extractable. Cellulose is insoluble and resistant to many microorganisms and enzymes. Celluloses are often associated with lignins and other non-starchy polysaccharides. Together with lignin and other fibers, cellulose forms a lignocellulose, which is highly resistant towards degradation. Fructans and β-glucans are the main components of the soluble fiber.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Xylanase is an enzyme that can degrade or break down the xylans in insoluble fiber and convert them into a simple sugar (xylose), which then can be metabolized by the yeast and lactic acid bacteria. In the end, this makes insoluble fiber less capable of interfering with and diluting the gluten in grains, so the bread won&amp;rsquo;t lose much volume or taste.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Amylase is another enzyme that breaks down starches, polysaccharides, and complex carbohydrates into easier-to-absorb simple sugars.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Diastatic barley malt packs in amylase and some endogenous xylanase, while wheat bran itself also contains &lt;a href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/10.1021/jf800264a">xylanase and laccase&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Grain kernels themselves usually contain a certain amount of endogenous xylanases for re-modeling and expansion of cell walls during normal cell growth and for more drastic cell wall degradation during seed germination. Additionally, grains also contain microbial xylanases from micro-organisms populating the outer grain kernels layers.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Industrial production of xylanases is mostly manufactured via submerged fermentation of lignocellulolytic substrates such as barley husk, corn cobs, hay, wheat bran or straw.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="scalded-soaker-1100g">Scalded soaker: 1,100g&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>Soak the middlings from the second sift in hot water for 24h.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>middlings&lt;/td>
&lt;td>220g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>boiling water (4x bran weight)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>880g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>I usually give the coarse bits a prolonged, unconstrained hydration to completely satisfy their thirst, before I get the final dough going. (I ended up having to retard both the bran levain and the soaker in the fridge after the first 24 hours, due to traveling.)&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="final-dough">Final dough&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>When you incorporate the levain and the scalded soaker into the final dough, you add every part of the grain back. Not one bit is wasted. Therefore, this bread retains its whole-grain integrity.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sifted Karl92 flour&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1,265g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>scalded soaker&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1,100g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>water&lt;/td>
&lt;td>120g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>levain&lt;/td>
&lt;td>425g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>30g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>No autolyse this time. I simply amalgamated everything and left the shaggy mess in the fridge overnight, à‎ la Jim Lahey&amp;rsquo;s no-knead method.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Another reason I didn&amp;rsquo;t feel like working the dough: The gluten in the sifted Karl92 flour had deteriorated to the point where it performed almost like a pastry flour. The dough was very sticky even at such low hydration.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you must calculate the hydration percentage:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>excluding levain: 1,000g/1,485g = 67%&lt;/li>
&lt;li>including levain: 1,210g/1,700g = 71%&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>The next day, I took the dough out of the fridge and gave it a stretch &amp;amp; fold. Time and cool temperatures worked their magic on the dough &amp;ndash; it was coming together on its own without much manual coaxing.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A few hours later, I pulled the dough out again and laminated it with caramelized onions (not drained), &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->wheat berries&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->, and &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->bread spices&lt;sup id="fnref:2">&lt;a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->. I let the dough rest in the cold until bedtime and gave it a coil-fold. Afterwards, I left it undisturbed in the fridge for 72 hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The overall process was basically similar to what I did with the Turkey Red bread, but at a significantly slower pace.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s percentage&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->flour&lt;sup id="fnref:3">&lt;a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">3&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1,485g (1,265g flour + 220g middlings)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>water&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1,000g (880g + 120g)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>67%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>levain&lt;/td>
&lt;td>425g&lt;/td>
&lt;td>29%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>30g&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>onions&lt;/td>
&lt;td>80g&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5.4%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>spices&lt;/td>
&lt;td>20g&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1.3%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>wheat berries&lt;/td>
&lt;td>107g&lt;/td>
&lt;td>7.2%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>I decided to go for a 72h fermentation for a few reasons:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>to &lt;a href="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/pdf/10.1271/bbb.130027">reduce as much mycotoxin&lt;/a> as possible through prolonged lactic acid bacteria fermentation;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>to mask the musty smell/taste via developing a complex web of flavors;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>to see how long the gluten could hold together before it started to break down.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>72+ hours later, I took the dough out of the fridge and pre-shaped it loosely. The dough had risen by ~30% but felt chock full of air. It hadn&amp;rsquo;t become a soup, so I guess the gluten hadn&amp;rsquo;t collapsed. After a 1-hour bench rest, I shaped it tight (using the reserved 37g coarse bran as coating) and let it proof at room temperature until 100% risen. It took about 5 hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/dr-funkenstein/20201016_1413.jpg"
alt="Funky Karl final proof"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Funky Karl going through final proof.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/dr-funkenstein/20201016_1430.jpg"
alt="Funky Karl final proof"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Funky Karl going through final proof: a closer look.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Then I baked it as usual, in the toaster oven. The dough weighed 3,187g (7.08 lbs) before baking.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It turned out a monstrous loaf: It measured about 11&amp;quot;x9&amp;quot;x5&amp;quot; and weighed just under 6 lbs. after cooling.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Hipsters might call this a &lt;em>miche&lt;/em>, a.k.a. the &lt;a href="https://nypost.com/2017/10/03/new-yorkers-are-paying-20-for-a-loaf-of-bread/">fancy&lt;/a> Parisian way of denoting &amp;ldquo;a supersized rustic sourdough bread,&amp;rdquo; which is in fact a French slang for &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href="https://daysontheclaise.blogspot.com/2009/03/la-miche.html">butt-cheek&lt;/a>.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/dr-funkenstein/20201016_1904.jpg"
alt="Funky Karl baked"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Funky Karl making a glorious debut from the oven.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/dr-funkenstein/20201016_1909.jpg"
alt="Funky Karl baked"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The sweet aroma of freshly baked bread wafted through the whole house &amp;ndash; one of my all-time favorite smells. I let the bread sit in a brown paper bag overnight before slicing.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="crumb-reveal">Crumb reveal&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>The bread was a breeze to cut into. The knife came out clean. A very distinctive and pleasant fragrance immediately hit the nose.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/dr-funkenstein/20201017_1259.jpg"
alt="Funky Karl crumbshot"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The crumb turned out much more aerated than in the Turkey Red loaf and had some large holes; it was also much lighter and fluffier, although a bit less moist, than the TR. (High hydration level promotes bigger holes, but the high percentage of whole grain flours works against them.)&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/dr-funkenstein/20201017_1633.jpg"
alt="Funky Karl crumbshot"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>I don&amp;rsquo;t want to sound like a food snob, but I have to confess that the only words I could think of when slicing this bread were &amp;ldquo;alveolate ecstasy.&amp;rdquo; Each slice felt ethereal, almost weightless, on my hand. In any case, this was a great crumb for sandwiches and toasts.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/dr-funkenstein/20201018_1109.jpg"
alt="Funky Karl baked"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Funky Karl, an alveolate ecstasy you never knew existed.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Now, the flavor: I was struck first by the tender, airy texture &amp;ndash; so delicate on my tongue that it felt like eating cottony clouds &amp;ndash; although there was some nice chew, too.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/dr-funkenstein/20201017_1256.jpg"
alt="Funky Karl crumbshot"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/dr-funkenstein/20201017_1300.jpg"
alt="Funky Karl crumbshot"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Funky Karl crumb porn.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Like the Turkey Red loaf, there was little wheat flavor. Maybe there was, but it was easily overshadowed by a prominent combination of sourness and tanginess. I would describe it as noticeably more tangy than sour &amp;ndash; it likely contained a wider spectrum of piquancy than I could articulate &amp;ndash; and I would compare it to a sour rye bread or even a tamarind/lemon juice combination. Call it a &lt;em>pane picante integrale&lt;/em>?&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/dr-funkenstein/20201018_1103.jpg"
alt="Funky Karl crumbshot"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The brisk flavors of caramelized onions (or was it the wild onions looming in the Karl92?) and crushed spices came through and were nearly assertive enough to go &lt;em>mano a mano&lt;/em> with the lush tartness.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The wheat berries had literally melted into the crumb and were content to stay in the background.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/dr-funkenstein/20201018_2149.jpg"
alt="Funky Karl crumbshot"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The crust was thin, crispy, and chewy except for the ears which crunched. It tasted much more flavorful than the crumb, as usual, and added the nuttiness I always enjoy.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>All in all, I think the long, cold fermentation resulted in a fortified crust giving way to richly complex layers of bold, indulgent, sophisticated flavors. Lots of nutty, earthy and sweet overtones followed by a deep tanginess and a trace of pleasing bitterness. I&amp;rsquo;m a &lt;em>huge&lt;/em> fan of zing and heat, and this bread hit the spot!&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/dr-funkenstein/20201018_2151.jpg"
alt="Funky Karl crumbshot"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/dr-funkenstein/20201018_2153.jpg"
alt="Funky Karl crumbshot"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Best part: I didn&amp;rsquo;t smell or taste any mustiness in it no matter how hard I tried, nor did we feel sick at all from eating it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We devoured half of the loaf in 3 days (delicious as is, but even better toasted), and took the rest to a BBQ at the relatives yesterday. They all grew up eating pre-sliced Wonder Bread (or Bunny® Bread, which &amp;ndash; I just learned yesterday &amp;ndash; has been a household name and an &lt;a href="https://orangebeanindiana.com/2020/05/08/thats-what-i-said-the-story-of-bunny-bread/">iconic brand&lt;/a> in the Midwest for decades, no offense) and have vastly different food preferences than me.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/dr-funkenstein/20201019_1300.jpg"
alt="Funky Karl crumbshot"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Everybody loved the texture of the bread; they thought it was almost as soft and fluffy as the premium mediocre Bunny® Original 100% Whole Wheat Bread! Lol. This may sound like an insult to a coastal foodie, but in a Midwestern context it must be interpreted as the highest form of compliment &amp;ndash; because &amp;ldquo;you can&amp;rsquo;t beat the Bunny!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/dr-funkenstein/20201019_1301.jpg"
alt="Funky Karl crumbshot"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/dr-funkenstein/20201019_1303.jpg"
alt="Funky Karl crumbshot"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>However, nobody liked the pungent flavor of this bread. Someone compared it to balsamic vinegar, and someone else said it tasted as sour as Trolli sour gummy worms (&amp;ldquo;for people who can&amp;rsquo;t get enough tanginess in their life&amp;rdquo;). Still, the bread disappeared quickly &amp;ndash; maybe people just got intense carb cravings.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Oh well. That was fun.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Guess I have just found another failproof (and easier) way of making whole wheat &amp;ldquo;clouds,&amp;rdquo; besides the method I accidentally discovered while making &lt;em>panettone integrale&lt;/em>. What I have done with Karl92 over the last couple of weeks &amp;ndash; from smoking the flour to sifting to the 72h fermentation &amp;ndash; is fairly labor-intensive and time-consuming, not something I&amp;rsquo;d do often or use for production. Just a science experiment for my own curiosity.&lt;/p>
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>Spices consisted of dill seeds, caraway seeds, fennel seeds, coriander, fenugreek seeds, anise, black peppercorns, and papaya seeds; all roasted and coarsely ground just before using.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>I soaked a handful of funky Karl92 wheat berries in liquid whey, and let it ferment for a few days. Drained and incorporated the mushy berries (wet weight 107g).&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:3" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>With 220g midds added back, the total amount of flour used directly in the dough stood at 1,485g (~86% extraction).&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/section></content></item><item><title>The Wheatwalker</title><link>/posts/the-wheatwalker/</link><pubDate>Sun, 13 Sep 2020 22:50:39 -0700</pubDate><guid>/posts/the-wheatwalker/</guid><description>My first foray into baking with heirloom wheat: an experimental open-crumb wheaty bread made with locally grown and milled Turkey Red, the OG American wheat.</description><content>&lt;p>I recently took a trip to CoMo (Columbia, MO) to visit Richard Kapp&amp;rsquo;s lovely farm and &lt;a href="https://www.centralmissourigrainsforfood.com/">mill&lt;/a>. The moment Richard told me he had local Turkey Red, I was hooked. I had no idea Turkey Red could be grown in central Missouri.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Richard shared a lot of stories about local agriculture: growing hard wheats in Missouri is more challenging than selling bicycles in Alaska, because of the climate, soil, distribution, uncompetitive commercial potential, dearth of local interests, etc. The University of Missouri is far less keen on hard wheat trials and researches than Kansas and Nebraska.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Richard also gave me a nice tour of his farm, and kindly offered me a sample of his freshly milled organic Turkey Red flour (85% extraction) to try. This batch of Turkey Red was grown by Paul Lehmann, an organic farmer in Fayette (~25 miles northwest of CoMo).&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="the-og-american-wheat">The OG American wheat&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>Turkey Red is a type of hard red winter wheat brought to Kansas by Mennonite immigrants from Russia, the part now known as Ukraine, in the late 1870s. It ended up becoming the primary wheat variety grown in the Midwest for the next ~70 years. It grew especially well in Kansas and, by the early 20th century, was planted in more than 75% of the fields. (Hard red winter wheat was widely grown in the Great Plains area with Kansas as the center, and became known as &amp;ldquo;Kansas wheat.&amp;quot;)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>After World War II, as industrial farming and the &amp;ldquo;Green Revolution&amp;rdquo; started taking hold, this heritage variety faded away. Wheat began to be hybridized for yield and depend on the application of fertilizers, herbicides, pesticides, etc. The increase in productivity, in many cases, come at the cost of flavor and nutrition.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>There is speculation that the changes made during hybridization altered the protein and gluten structure of the grain, which has made modern hybrid wheat more difficult to digest and is thought to be the cause of gluten-intolerence in many people.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Unlike modern high-yielding dwarf wheat varieties, Turkey Red grows very tall, creating lots of straw and biomass for the soil. It&amp;rsquo;s a landrace variety, i.e. it contains genetic diversity making it adaptable across bio-regions. Fortunately, Turkey Red seeds were saved and this heritage wheat is making a comeback in many parts of the Midwest. It&amp;rsquo;s one of the most popular revival wheats used by US bakers, treasured for its flavor and digestibility.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>There is actually a museum in Goessel, Kansas dedicated to the Mennonite farmers who brought over Turkey Red seeds from Russia in 1874.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="master-formula">Master formula&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>Total Turkey Red flour used: 450g (440g in the dough + 10g bran for dusting)&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>total weight&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>flour&lt;/td>
&lt;td>440g&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>water&lt;/td>
&lt;td>380g&lt;/td>
&lt;td>86%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>levain&lt;/td>
&lt;td>88g&lt;/td>
&lt;td>20%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>9g&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->spent grains&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->&lt;/td>
&lt;td>45g&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>raisins&lt;/td>
&lt;td>20g&lt;/td>
&lt;td>4.5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Dusting:&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>reserved bran&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Process:&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>process&lt;/th>
&lt;th>time&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>bran soaking&lt;/td>
&lt;td>12 hours (75°F)&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>autolyse&lt;/td>
&lt;td>6 hours (60°F)&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>bulk ferment&lt;/td>
&lt;td>14 hours (44°F)&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>final proof&lt;/td>
&lt;td>3 hours (75°F)&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>bake&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1 hour&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>I used extended bran soaking, high hydration, and retarded cold fermentation in this dough to help draw out the natural flavors of heritage wheat flours.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h4 id="day-1">Day 1&lt;/h4>
&lt;h5 id="10pm">10pm&lt;/h5>
&lt;p>Sift 450g of the 85% extraction Turkey Red flour into&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>400g flour (~75% extraction)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>50g bran &amp;amp; germ
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>40g: for hot soaker&lt;/li>
&lt;li>10g: for dusting later&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Even though the 85% extraction flour has already been sifted, it still contains a fair amount of the bran and germ which can&amp;rsquo;t be milled as finely as the starch and can stand in the way of gluten formation.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Still, you want to hang on to every bit of these, because they contain important nutrients as well as a nuanced flavor from the local terroir.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Make a scalded soaker:&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>bran &amp;amp; germ&lt;/td>
&lt;td>40g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>boiling water&lt;/td>
&lt;td>160g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Mix well and let sit, covered, at room temperature for 12-18 hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h4 id="day-2">Day 2&lt;/h4>
&lt;h5 id="1pm">1pm&lt;/h5>
&lt;p>Mix together:&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sifted ~75% extraction flour&lt;/td>
&lt;td>400g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>scalded soaker&lt;/td>
&lt;td>200g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>cold water (50°F)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>200g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Mix well and autolyze at 60°F for ~6 hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;h5 id="7pm">7pm&lt;/h5>
&lt;p>After ~6 hours of cool autolyse, mix the final dough.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Add 88g of stiff whole wheat levain (60% hydration). Slap &amp;amp; fold for 5-7 mins.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Add the salt and 20g of water (&lt;em>bassinage&lt;/em>), mix and squeeze for another 5-10 mins until completely absorbed. The dough is very tacky but should start to feel some strength by the end of this mixing.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Place the worked dough in a fridge (44°F) immediately. Cold bulk-ferment for the next 14 hours. Do 3 sets of stretch &amp;amp; fold, at 30 minutes apart, during the first 2 hours. My dough felt very extensible, although not very strong.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>At the 3-hour mark, laminate the dough with spent grains (not drained) à la German &lt;em>biertreberbrot&lt;/em> and chopped raisins.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>My dough almost passed the &amp;ldquo;windowpane&amp;rdquo; test!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>At the 4-hour mark, perform a coil-fold.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Remove 10g of the dough and put in an aliquot jar for easy measuring. Place the aliquot next to the dough in the same bowl, and return both to the fridge. Leave them undisturbed overnight.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h4 id="day-3">Day 3&lt;/h4>
&lt;h5 id="9am">9am&lt;/h5>
&lt;p>Remove the dough from fridge, and pre-shape via a loose coil-fold. Both the dough and the aliquot have risen a little bit overnight.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Rest for 45-60 minutes.&lt;/p>
&lt;h5 id="10am">10am&lt;/h5>
&lt;p>Shape the dough tightly and place in a proofing vessle. I put mine in a loaf pan lined with parchment paper.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Let the dough rest for 2-3 hours at room temperature, until the aliquot portion has risen nearly 100%. Mine took ~3 hours to get there.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;code>Note&lt;/code>: Watch the dough not the clock! Move at the dough&amp;rsquo;s pace.&lt;/p>
&lt;h5 id="1pm-1">1pm&lt;/h5>
&lt;p>Time to bake!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I did 15 minutes at 375F in the toaster oven, followed by another 35 minutes at 300F.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The dough had a pretty decent oven spring. It actually rose more than I expected and emitted some intoxicating wheat aroma!&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/the-wheatwalker/20200912201813b.jpg"
alt="85% extraction Turkey Red wheat bread"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>When the bread was done baking, it sounded hollow when I firmly thumped the bottom with my fingers.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/the-wheatwalker/20200912201815.jpg"
alt="85% extraction Turkey Red wheat bread"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Should&amp;rsquo;ve slashed a little deeper, huh?&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/the-wheatwalker/20200912201817b.jpg"
alt="85% extraction Turkey Red wheat bread"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Let the bread cool.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Size of the baked bread: 8&amp;rdquo; x 5&amp;quot; x 4&amp;quot;.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h4 id="day-4">Day 4&lt;/h4>
&lt;h5 id="3pm">3pm&lt;/h5>
&lt;p>After 24 hours of cooling and curing, came the moment of truth&amp;hellip;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The crunchy crust has softened overnight and is quite easy to cut into. The knife comes out mostly clean.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/the-wheatwalker/20200913201527c.jpg"
alt="85% extraction Turkey Red wheat bread"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The crumb is fairly open. No gaping holes, but a very nice texture. Moist, tender, pillowy, and springy. I&amp;rsquo;m surprised how light it is.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/the-wheatwalker/20200913201532a.jpg"
alt="85% extraction Turkey Red wheat bread"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The crumb surrounding the raisins tastes mildly tangy but flavorful &amp;ndash; almost like a small amount of caraway seeds and cinnamon has been added. Scattered raisins give you random bursts of sweetness.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The spent grains impart a subtle malty flavor and nutty crunch every now and then when you hit a berry. In case you are wondering, it does not taste like beer at all. You just get some extra fiber from the spent grains.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/the-wheatwalker/20200913201548c.jpg"
alt="85% extraction Turkey Red wheat bread"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The crust is thin, crisp, chewy and firm, and tastes much more flavorful (sweet, cinnamony notes).&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/the-wheatwalker/20200913201547e.jpg"
alt="85% extraction Turkey Red wheat bread"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The extended hydration of bran and long autolyse really helped with gluten development. The dough needed quite a bit of coaxing at the beginning, but gradually fell into place. A cool, long fermentation helped to develop a light texture and a complex flavor.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Overall, this is a wheaty loaf that doesn&amp;rsquo;t taste dense or earthy like other almost whole wheat loaves. It has a lingering flavor that is just incredible.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This Turkey Red from CoMo is absolutely delicious. The high-quality soil these grains are grown in and the freshness of the flour contribute a rich, unmistakable nuttiness and depth of flavor to the bread.&lt;/p>
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>The spent grains were a wet mush from a local craft brewery, consisting of 1/2 white wheat malt and 1/2 pilsner malt.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/section></content></item><item><title>Orange Sunshine</title><link>/posts/orange-sunshine/</link><pubDate>Mon, 31 Aug 2020 22:42:43 -0500</pubDate><guid>/posts/orange-sunshine/</guid><description>A seedelicious bread made with 100% Warthog whole wheat flour and a bucket of orange juice.</description><content>&lt;p>The first time I ate homemade bread was in 2011 in Kansas City, when I was backpacking across the US. I had no idea that bread was something you could make at home. Prior to that, my experience with bread had been exclusively limited to the typical white mush served at school cafeterias. It was so disgustingly bland, empty, and unfulfilling &amp;ndash; not to mention it was also emblematic of everything that was wrong with America &amp;ndash; that I developed a sort of White Bread PTSD and swore I&amp;rsquo;d never eat another slice of bread after college.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Funny how the Covid lockdown has inspired/forced a lot of people to bake breads at home &amp;ndash; and even sell their homemade breads on Etsy. It has forced me to pay more attention to where I source my food from and whether they will always be available.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A number of artisan-ish bakeries across the country are selling their bread flours nicely packaged in eco-friendly brown paper bags at &amp;ldquo;pandemic special&amp;rdquo; prices, to make up for their lost business &amp;amp; revenue due to the shutdown and retain customer relationships.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Last month, King Arthur Flour rebranded itself to King Arthur Baking Company. The flour company was founded in 1790, and is America&amp;rsquo;s first flour company. They have re-aligned the company to reflect their mission &amp;ndash; &amp;ldquo;bake joy.&amp;rdquo; King Arthur is now a lifestyle company, like Lululemon, Peloton and Chipotle. I don&amp;rsquo;t buy King Arthur&amp;rsquo;s flours or care for its recipes, but I do find that rebranding &amp;ndash; particularly the timing &amp;ndash; interesting.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Literally every state has a &amp;ldquo;local&amp;rdquo; flagship producer. IL has Janie&amp;rsquo;s. NY has Farmer Ground Flour. OR has Camas Country Mill. NC has Carolina Ground. TX has Barton Springs Mill. AZ has Hayden Flour Mills. Who is MO&amp;rsquo;s local artisan flagship producer?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If I were going to bring coastal friends &amp;ldquo;Missouri-grown&amp;rdquo; non-touristy gifts, I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t know what to get &amp;ndash; other than t-ravs, provel, and maybe some local booze. I know the MO Department of Agriculture has a program called Missouri Grown, but the local goodies gift box it has put together is a joke.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Missouri always feels like a giant black hole of locally grown grains. Sure, Missouri grows a ton of soybeans, corn and soft wheat. I mean, it&amp;rsquo;s a Corn Belt state. But most of them are exported via the Mississippi River, and the rest processed into animal feed, industrial inputs, and biofuels. Only a tiny percentage stays local. The US Soybean Export Council and American Soybean Association (which has a political action committee called SoyPAC) are both headquartered in St. Louis (STL). Monsanto was founded in STL and headquartered here for over 100 years, and its new parent, Bayer AG, still established its North American HQ here. The world&amp;rsquo;s biggest grain traders &amp;ndash; Archer Daniel Midland (ADM), Bunge, and Cargill &amp;ndash; all have major operations in STL as well. (These 3, along with Louis Dreyfus, control ~90% of global grain trade and have enormous power over grain prices.) Evidently, their presence here impacts local farmers and agri-food system.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Missouri certainly doesn&amp;rsquo;t have a shortage of local producers, and the flagship local product with (inter)national recognition doesn&amp;rsquo;t have to be bread wheat &amp;ndash; South Carolina has done exceptionally well with heirloom rice renaissance, for example.&lt;/p>
&lt;div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
&lt;iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/cgpgwBXKYHI" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video">&lt;/iframe>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>I had the good fortune of living a stone&amp;rsquo;s throw away from Anson Mills in Charleston for a number of years, and got to witness its metamorphosis to the Palmetto State&amp;rsquo;s flagship artisan producer/purveyor, an explosive commercial success with international fame. Tourists from all over the world flock to Charleston, SC to visit Anson Mills and experience the antebellum culinary past. It has become a culinary tourist destination in and of itself. More incredibly, the entrepreneurs behind Anson Mills are not even SC natives. What&amp;rsquo;s the MO equivalent of Anson Mills or Carolina Gold rice, or of even San Francisco&amp;rsquo;s Tartine? My point is, MO local producers have a branding/PR problem. Tom Cruise is a globally recognizable brand. Janie&amp;rsquo;s of Illinois is a national brand. What&amp;rsquo;s the most recognizable MO brand? The only local product brand (even remotely) familiar to people from out of state or overseas might be Hammons Black Walnuts, which does have a D2C web store, but its branding and packaging leave a lot to be desired.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Kansas City (the Wheat Belt&amp;rsquo;s buckle) seems rife for a &amp;ldquo;single-origin wheat&amp;rdquo; renaissance that will help rebuild &lt;a href="https://thecounter.org/rural-kansas-depopulation-commodity-agriculture/">local economy&lt;/a> and reclaim the Wheat State&amp;rsquo;s agricultural heritage. In the late 19th and early 20th centuries, Kansas City had dozens of flour mills. Grain magnate Frank A. Theis (namesake of Theis Park) wrote in a 1938 article in The Kansas City Star, &amp;ldquo;No other industry, directly or indirectly, has been more closely identified with the growth of Kansas City.&amp;rdquo; In South Carolina and North Carolina, the cultivation of revival grains is a rapidly expanding enterprise.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I desperately wanted to find a Missouri-grown bread wheat. I went on a relentless hunt for this elusive prize, with little success. All neighboring states grow bread wheats, why not Missouri? My curiosity took me down a rabbit hole&amp;hellip; What started out as a seemingly trivial question turned into a herculean quest and then Mission Impossible.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Obviously, most people buy flours, not grains. So flour was where I started.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A bearded guitarist and baker used to sell his sourdough breads at farmers' markets and some restaurants in STL. One of his breads was &lt;em>pan bigio&lt;/em>, an Italian country loaf made with &amp;ldquo;local Cape Girardeau whole wheat flour.&amp;rdquo; I tried to find out which Cape Girardeau farm/mill that was (since I wasn&amp;rsquo;t aware there even was one), but he shut down his operations in March and went dark.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I called up the few artisan-ish bakeries in STL that pride themselves on using &amp;ldquo;locally grown and milled wheat&amp;rdquo; to ask what flours they use and where they source them from. Not only did they refuse to tell me anything, but also they got very confused and in some cases suspicious&amp;hellip; as if I had broken an unspoken cultural taboo. One of the nicer bakers directed me to the proverbial purveyors of &amp;ldquo;unique local organic artisanal products,&amp;rdquo; aka. specialty retailers that label everything with 10+ &lt;em>haute&lt;/em> adjectives and lists everything 1,000% higher than MSRP. Well, that was a very curious experience. I&amp;rsquo;m not sure whether these bakeries 1) genuinely use local ingredients as much as they claim, 2) severely lack business acumen to begin with, or 3) are simply too small-minded and uncreative.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I went back to the drawing board and started doing some research, when I found out that the band, from Delaware, Maryland, northern Virginia and southern Illinois and through Missouri to the eastern part of Kansas, is known for growing soft winter wheat. In fact, whatever wheat ends up flourishing on a commercially viable scale in Missouri is usually soft winter wheat and mostly exported, although Mizzou Cooperative Extension&amp;rsquo;s hard winter wheat trials in several locations around the state are successful. Most of the commercial bakeries here source their bread flours by truckloads from western Kansas.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>After a few days of hopeless internet research, I was on the verge of giving up. Serendipitously, a couple of small farms in central/western MO came across my radar &amp;ndash; they grow organic hard red winter wheat!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>So this is how I found 180 Farms in Sweet Springs, MO. I called up Greg Guier earlier last week week, to inquire about his organic wheat berries. Holy shit, Greg is one of the nicest and most down-to-earth people I&amp;rsquo;ve ever talked to. Some Midwesterners are just frighteningly friendly! He told me this year&amp;rsquo;s Warthog Red, a hard red winter wheat, was still being harvested and would be ready in a few days, and last year&amp;rsquo;s Darby White, a hard white winter wheat, was readily available. He said he delivers only to Kansas City, because he tried for years to set up delivery arrangements in STL but couldn&amp;rsquo;t get anyone interested.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I was going camping in the Ozarks this weekend anyway, so I took a detour and stopped by Greg&amp;rsquo;s farm to scoop up some freshly harvested Warthog wheat berries. (Heck, even swung by the Overland Park Farmer&amp;rsquo;s Market and procured some heritage Meishan pork from Odd Bird Farm in Weston, MO.) Turns out, that was a great decision.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>Warthog is a modern HRWW with a moderate protein content (10%-11%). I remember Warthog was hugely popular at the NYC Greenmarket a few years ago (thanks to GrowNYC Grains, a distributor/hub that promotes and sells local grains in the Northeast). Farmer-miller Thor Oechsner planted Warthog for the first time in 2010, loved it, and grew to become the largest Warthog producer in the Northeast. Then Janie&amp;rsquo;s Mill picked it up, too.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I did read about Warthog&amp;rsquo;s relatively low protein level for a HRWW, and kept that in mind while working with the flour. In fact, Oechsner recommended blending Warthog with a spring wheat flour to boost protein content while letting Warthog&amp;rsquo;s special flavor shine through.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Nah. I&amp;rsquo;m gonna go Warthog all the way through.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/orange-sunshine/202008311430.jpg"
alt="Orange Sunshine"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>First step: mill the Warthog wheat berries several times to get the finest grind possible.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>whole wheat flour (Warthog - 180 Farms, MO)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>rye levain&lt;/td>
&lt;td>40%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>water&lt;/td>
&lt;td>42%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>fresh orange juice&lt;/td>
&lt;td>42%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>diastatic barley malt powder&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>flaxseeds, freshly ground&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>soaker&lt;/td>
&lt;td>33%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>seed mix (for coating)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>The science behind incorporating orange juice and diastatic malt is explained in a later &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/desert-dynamo/">post&lt;/a>. TL;DR: Diastatic malt increases the conversion of starches to sugar, boosting the caramelization of the crust. Ascorbic acid (vitamin C) in orange juice tightens the gluten network and gives the bread a better rise.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Soaker:&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>quinoa&lt;/td>
&lt;td>25%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sunflower seeds&lt;/td>
&lt;td>25%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>whole flax seeds&lt;/td>
&lt;td>25%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>black sesame seeds&lt;/td>
&lt;td>25%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>orange juice&lt;/td>
&lt;td>150%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>You know my usual M.O.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/orange-sunshine/202008311432.jpg"
alt="Orange Sunshine"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The crumb doesn&amp;rsquo;t look too bad. Excuse my cutting.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/orange-sunshine/202008311437.jpg"
alt="Orange Sunshine"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Pretty darn tender and juicy.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/orange-sunshine/202008311438.jpg"
alt="Orange Sunshine"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Yum, the flavor is superb.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/orange-sunshine/202008311455.jpg"
alt="Orange Sunshine"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Orange Sunshine, a seedelicious bread made with 100% Warthog whole wheat flour and a bucket of orange juice.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>A great backpacking bread.&lt;/p></content></item><item><title>Zombie Dust</title><link>/posts/zombie-dust/</link><pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2020 12:09:53 -0500</pubDate><guid>/posts/zombie-dust/</guid><description>This unapologetically flavorful bread, made with a shameless amount of old bread, will be your only respite after the zombie apocalypse.</description><content>&lt;p>Grains used to be widely grown in the northeastern US. In 1845, wheat was grown in every country of New York. There were even four acres of wheat grown in Manhattan.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>New Jersey was one of the &amp;ldquo;bread colonies,&amp;rdquo; where wheat was an important export crop for farmers.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>During Colonial times the wheat belt in New Jersey stretched from New York City to Philadelphia. By 1750 the New Jersey colony had progressed rapidly in milling, and much of the flour marketed in New York City came from the region around New Brunswick. In the first half of the 18th century the New Jersey flouring mills were considered as the best in the country.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Harry B. Weiss, &lt;em>The Early Grist and Flouring Mills of New Jersey&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>In his book, &lt;em>The Third Plate&lt;/em>, Chef Dan Barber mentions that there was one gristmill for every seven hundred Americans in 1840.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The remains of those mills can still be seen along the banks of the Garden State&amp;rsquo;s rivers and major streams. In gristmills, grains were ground between millstones, which crushed the entire kernel (bran, germ, and endosperm) into flour. Once ground, flour had a shelf life of about 1 week. You brought your wheat to the mill or you milled it yourself. Some of the bran and germ could be sifted out, but the volatile oils in the remaining bran and germ turn rancid quickly through exposure to oxygen, reducing the shelf life of stone-ground flour. The invention of the modern roller mill in the late 1800s enabled millers to strip the bran and germ from the endosperm during milling &amp;ndash; and, in the process, remove most of the nutrients and flavors. Flour changed from a locally produced, perishable food into a high-volume, shelf-stable commodity. Many local farmers and millers were unable to compete against large-scale highly-efficient grain operations in the Midwest. By 1955, only &lt;a href="https://morrisparks.net/index.php/parks/cooper-gristmill">one&lt;/a> flour mill remained in New Jersey.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Re-localization of food supply chains has been underway across the world, to promote food sovereignty. The economics of local grains could work. There is a farmer in Ontario who makes a living selling his hand-processed grains direct to consumers. Thor Oechsner, an organic grain farmer in New York, built a mill (Farmer Ground Flour) and a bakery (Wide Awake Bakery) to ensure markets for his grains. Regional hubs and distributors like GrowNYC Grains and The Northeast Grainshed have been pivotal in connecting growers with processors and bakers, and sparking a rise in demand for local grains.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>IMHO, the success of re-localizing grains and flours largely depends on the willingness of bakers to develop a sensory approach to baking, i.e. understand the differences in gluten content, water absorption and flavor in locally-grown grains and locally-milled flours, which lack the consistency that large industrial mills achieve by blending different varieties of wheat. By foregoing strict adherence to recipes, bakers are liberated from the expectation that flour must behave consistently, regardless of the origin, farming practices and conditions in which the grain is grown. They would be able to better accommodate variability in the way locally-grown grains perform during the making of breads and pastries.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>The white flour industrial complex so completely dominates the food landscape&amp;hellip;that to wish for anything substantially different seems, well, wishful and nostalgic.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Michael Pollan, &lt;em>Cooked&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>I have been working my way through Pyotr Kropotkin&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em>Conquest of Bread&lt;/em>. It&amp;rsquo;s hard to forget that bread shortages helped ignite the French Revolution and the Arab Spring. Kropotkin&amp;rsquo;s call for &amp;ldquo;well-being for all&amp;rdquo; has inspired me to think about how to repurpose old bread into new meals, essentially &amp;ldquo;paying it forward&amp;rdquo; so that nothing is wasted and someone could always have a loaf of bread.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>German bakers have long had a tradition of adding an old bread soaker to a new dough. It helps to eliminate waste, save on fresh flours, and add buckets of flavors. Pretty clever.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Before you wrinkle your nose and scream &amp;ldquo;ewwwwwww,&amp;rdquo; the old bread used here is not a green and fuzzy piece of ancient crust, or a 3-day-old slice of supermarket pap, but a drying piece of good (sourdough) bread, e.g. the end of a loaf.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Here is a delicious way to upcycle a good amount of old bread into a new loaf.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>80% extraction wheat flour (Redeemer - Whitesfields Farm, MA)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>roasted barley tea&lt;/td>
&lt;td>105%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>whole wheat levain&lt;/td>
&lt;td>60%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>old WW bread&lt;/td>
&lt;td>50%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>homemade beetroot purée&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>raw seed mix (for coating)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>To make roasted barley tea, first you gotta roast the barley. Spread whole, from-the-field, unhulled barley in a single layer on a sheet pan and place in oven. (I used unhulled Baronesse barley from Joseph&amp;rsquo;s Grainery, WA. It was bred by &lt;a href="http://www.nordsaat.de/ueber-uns/historie/?L=1">Nordsaat&lt;/a> in Germany where they don&amp;rsquo;t care about feed grains as much as in the US.) Roast at 400°F for 15-20 mins, or until the grains take on a golden brown color and exude a popcorn-like aroma. Let cool and store in an air-tight container. Now you can brew some scrumptious tea by steeping roasted barley in hot water for ~12 hours. This cannot be reproduced with pearled or naked barley, since much of the flavor comes from the roasted toasty hull.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Steam or roast some chopped beets. Pulse the cooked beets with coconut milk in a blender until smooth and creamy. The beetroot purée will add extra flavors and delightful swirls to the bread.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Soak the chunks of stale bread (can be any type) in 25% of the total tea. (Depending on how dry your bread is, you may want to adjust the hydration accordingly.) Add half of the levain. Leave in a fridge overnight. Next day, mash up any remaining lumps so that it&amp;rsquo;s a thick and somewhat smooth paste.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Autolyze the freshly milled flour with the remaining tea for 2 hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Mix in the soaker, the rest of the levain, and salt, until thoroughly combined.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Rest 30 mins. Do a strong letter fold.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Rest another 30 mins rest. Laminate with beetroot purée to add extra flavors and colorful swirls to the bread.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Rest 60 mins. Perform a coil-fold.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Rest another 2 hours before shaping. Roll the dough in seeds. No need to toast the seeds, as they will be nicely toasted during baking and add amazing flavors to the bread.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>10 hours final proof in the fridge.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Let the dough warm up for a few hours before baking.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It rose like a beast in the oven.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/zombie-dust/202001241449.jpg"
alt="Zombie Dust"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>OMG!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Every slice is packed with extra flavor and crunch, thanks to the layer of caramelized seeds atop the crust. Reminds me a lot of Whole Foods' Seeduction bread.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This loaf is completely unapologetic in what it is &amp;ndash; a bold and aromatic bread that is made with a hefty amount of old bread.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Gossamer-like crumb texture.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/zombie-dust/202001241639.jpg"
alt="Zombie Dust"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The last 4 slices&amp;hellip;&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/zombie-dust/202001242205.jpg"
alt="Zombie Dust"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Zombie Dust, an unapologetically flavorful bread, made with a shameless amount of old bread. It will be your only respite after the zombie apocalypse.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Few things are as ordinary as a loaf of bread, yet the process by which it is made is extraordinary &amp;ndash; and still something of a mystery even to those who study it or practice it every day. - Michael Pollan&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>A variation of this bread I made later, without seeds:&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/zombie-dust/variation/202001241320.jpg"
alt="Zombie Dust"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/zombie-dust/variation/202001241323.jpg"
alt="Zombie Dust"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/zombie-dust/variation/202001241324.jpg"
alt="Zombie Dust"/>
&lt;/figure></content></item></channel></rss>