<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>zero waste on HERESY LEVAIN</title><link>/tags/zero-waste/</link><description>Latest experiments in zero waste from HERESY LEVAIN</description><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2023 HERESY LEVAIN 🍞 CC BY-NC-SA 4.0</copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 19 Oct 2020 20:28:06 -0600</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/zero-waste/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Dr. Funkenstein</title><link>/posts/dr-funkenstein/</link><pubDate>Mon, 19 Oct 2020 20:28:06 -0600</pubDate><guid>/posts/dr-funkenstein/</guid><description>A zero-waste science experiment to salvage a batch of unbeloved Karl92 wheat, through a long fermendation. It metamorphosed into a whole wheat alveolate ecstasy that you never knew existed.</description><content>&lt;p>A few weeks ago, I got some organic Karl92 wheat from Richard, grown by a local farmer.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Karl92 is a modern high-quality HRWW variety, selected from &amp;ldquo;Karl&amp;rdquo; by R. G. Sears, leader of the Manhattan wheat program from 1982 to 2000. Karl92 has higher yield and better disease resistance than the OG variety. Protein content is ~12%.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This lot of Karl92 got invaded by wild onions while still growing in the fields, and the wheat berries picked up an oniony aroma. I thought naturally onion-scented wheat was quite interesting &amp;ndash; I wondered if it would be a great flour for a herbaceous bread. There&amp;rsquo;s a niche market for everything. If I were to market this batch of Karl92, I would label them &amp;ldquo;Funkadelic Ecstasy organic whole wheat: kissed by wild onions, ingrained with Mother Earth&amp;rsquo;s inherent magic.&amp;rdquo; Coastal foodies and food snobs would go crazy about it. No doubt. FWIW, there&amp;rsquo;s a toy company that sells squishy onions &amp;ndash; stress balls in the shape and color of a red onion and, when you squish them, they actually release onion scents to encourage further stress relief.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I also got a batch of Karl92 whole wheat flour that was milled a while ago and starting to smell musty. I know, 99% of people would just toss it in the trash. But the zero-waster in me was curious whether this batch of flour could be &lt;a href="https://ift.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1111/1541-4337.12481">salvaged through fermentation&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>So I dumped the flour (1,722g) on a BBQ grill, and let it smoke over a bunch of corn husks for a few hours. The smelly flour picked up a nutty, endearing, almost bacon-y aroma. Then I sifted the smoked flour twice: got 237g coarse bran (14%) out the first time, and 220g middlings (13%) the second time, leaving 1,265g flour (73% extraction).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I divided the 237g coarse bran into&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>200g: for levain&lt;/li>
&lt;li>37g: for dusting/coating&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>And thus began my cosmic adventure into the funky world of Karl92.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="levain-425g">Levain: 425g&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>2 builds, in 24h:&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>coarse bran&lt;/td>
&lt;td>200g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>boiling water&lt;/td>
&lt;td>200g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>diastatic barley malt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sourdough starter, stiff WW&lt;/td>
&lt;td>20g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Pour boiling water over the coarse bran in a gass bowl. Mix well. Let it sit for a few hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>You can add the malt while the bran soaker has cooled off some, but add the starter only after the bran soaker has cooled off completely to room temperature.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Based on my previous baking experiments and consumption of scientific studies, the most effective way to process the bran and improve its texture is sourdough starter + alpha amylase + xylanase, let sit for 24 hours at 24°C/75°F. (I&amp;rsquo;ve done this many times on oat hull fiber and have achieved good results. I have a friend who&amp;rsquo;s pathologically obsessed with &amp;ldquo;volume eating&amp;rdquo;, e.g., consuming large volumes of food while taking in minimal calories at the same time. Oat fiber is insanely popular among these volume-eaters, because the boatload of fiber in it increases the volume of food while adding zero net carbs or calories.)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Depending on the genotype, dry wheat bran can contain about 50% dietary fiber and 9%-25% starch. Most of that dietary fiber in bran is insoluble fiber (hemicelluloses):&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>arabinoxylans (~55%)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>celluloses (9-12%)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>lignins (3-5%)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>fructans (3-4%)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>β-glucans (2.2-2.6%).&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Most arabinoxylans are water-unextractable, but a smaller part is water-extractable. Cellulose is insoluble and resistant to many microorganisms and enzymes. Celluloses are often associated with lignins and other non-starchy polysaccharides. Together with lignin and other fibers, cellulose forms a lignocellulose, which is highly resistant towards degradation. Fructans and β-glucans are the main components of the soluble fiber.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Xylanase is an enzyme that can degrade or break down the xylans in insoluble fiber and convert them into a simple sugar (xylose), which then can be metabolized by the yeast and lactic acid bacteria. In the end, this makes insoluble fiber less capable of interfering with and diluting the gluten in grains, so the bread won&amp;rsquo;t lose much volume or taste.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Amylase is another enzyme that breaks down starches, polysaccharides, and complex carbohydrates into easier-to-absorb simple sugars.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Diastatic barley malt packs in amylase and some endogenous xylanase, while wheat bran itself also contains &lt;a href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/10.1021/jf800264a">xylanase and laccase&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Grain kernels themselves usually contain a certain amount of endogenous xylanases for re-modeling and expansion of cell walls during normal cell growth and for more drastic cell wall degradation during seed germination. Additionally, grains also contain microbial xylanases from micro-organisms populating the outer grain kernels layers.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Industrial production of xylanases is mostly manufactured via submerged fermentation of lignocellulolytic substrates such as barley husk, corn cobs, hay, wheat bran or straw.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="scalded-soaker-1100g">Scalded soaker: 1,100g&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>Soak the middlings from the second sift in hot water for 24h.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>middlings&lt;/td>
&lt;td>220g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>boiling water (4x bran weight)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>880g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>I usually give the coarse bits a prolonged, unconstrained hydration to completely satisfy their thirst, before I get the final dough going. (I ended up having to retard both the bran levain and the soaker in the fridge after the first 24 hours, due to traveling.)&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="final-dough">Final dough&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>When you incorporate the levain and the scalded soaker into the final dough, you add every part of the grain back. Not one bit is wasted. Therefore, this bread retains its whole-grain integrity.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sifted Karl92 flour&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1,265g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>scalded soaker&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1,100g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>water&lt;/td>
&lt;td>120g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>levain&lt;/td>
&lt;td>425g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>30g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>No autolyse this time. I simply amalgamated everything and left the shaggy mess in the fridge overnight, à‎ la Jim Lahey&amp;rsquo;s no-knead method.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Another reason I didn&amp;rsquo;t feel like working the dough: The gluten in the sifted Karl92 flour had deteriorated to the point where it performed almost like a pastry flour. The dough was very sticky even at such low hydration.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you must calculate the hydration percentage:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>excluding levain: 1,000g/1,485g = 67%&lt;/li>
&lt;li>including levain: 1,210g/1,700g = 71%&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>The next day, I took the dough out of the fridge and gave it a stretch &amp;amp; fold. Time and cool temperatures worked their magic on the dough &amp;ndash; it was coming together on its own without much manual coaxing.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A few hours later, I pulled the dough out again and laminated it with caramelized onions (not drained), &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->wheat berries&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->, and &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->bread spices&lt;sup id="fnref:2">&lt;a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->. I let the dough rest in the cold until bedtime and gave it a coil-fold. Afterwards, I left it undisturbed in the fridge for 72 hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The overall process was basically similar to what I did with the Turkey Red bread, but at a significantly slower pace.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s percentage&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->flour&lt;sup id="fnref:3">&lt;a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">3&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1,485g (1,265g flour + 220g middlings)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>water&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1,000g (880g + 120g)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>67%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>levain&lt;/td>
&lt;td>425g&lt;/td>
&lt;td>29%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>30g&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>onions&lt;/td>
&lt;td>80g&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5.4%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>spices&lt;/td>
&lt;td>20g&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1.3%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>wheat berries&lt;/td>
&lt;td>107g&lt;/td>
&lt;td>7.2%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>I decided to go for a 72h fermentation for a few reasons:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>to &lt;a href="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/pdf/10.1271/bbb.130027">reduce as much mycotoxin&lt;/a> as possible through prolonged lactic acid bacteria fermentation;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>to mask the musty smell/taste via developing a complex web of flavors;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>to see how long the gluten could hold together before it started to break down.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>72+ hours later, I took the dough out of the fridge and pre-shaped it loosely. The dough had risen by ~30% but felt chock full of air. It hadn&amp;rsquo;t become a soup, so I guess the gluten hadn&amp;rsquo;t collapsed. After a 1-hour bench rest, I shaped it tight (using the reserved 37g coarse bran as coating) and let it proof at room temperature until 100% risen. It took about 5 hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/dr-funkenstein/20201016_1413.jpg"
alt="Funky Karl final proof"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Funky Karl going through final proof.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/dr-funkenstein/20201016_1430.jpg"
alt="Funky Karl final proof"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Funky Karl going through final proof: a closer look.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Then I baked it as usual, in the toaster oven. The dough weighed 3,187g (7.08 lbs) before baking.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It turned out a monstrous loaf: It measured about 11&amp;quot;x9&amp;quot;x5&amp;quot; and weighed just under 6 lbs. after cooling.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Hipsters might call this a &lt;em>miche&lt;/em>, a.k.a. the &lt;a href="https://nypost.com/2017/10/03/new-yorkers-are-paying-20-for-a-loaf-of-bread/">fancy&lt;/a> Parisian way of denoting &amp;ldquo;a supersized rustic sourdough bread,&amp;rdquo; which is in fact a French slang for &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href="https://daysontheclaise.blogspot.com/2009/03/la-miche.html">butt-cheek&lt;/a>.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/dr-funkenstein/20201016_1904.jpg"
alt="Funky Karl baked"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Funky Karl making a glorious debut from the oven.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/dr-funkenstein/20201016_1909.jpg"
alt="Funky Karl baked"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The sweet aroma of freshly baked bread wafted through the whole house &amp;ndash; one of my all-time favorite smells. I let the bread sit in a brown paper bag overnight before slicing.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="crumb-reveal">Crumb reveal&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>The bread was a breeze to cut into. The knife came out clean. A very distinctive and pleasant fragrance immediately hit the nose.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/dr-funkenstein/20201017_1259.jpg"
alt="Funky Karl crumbshot"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The crumb turned out much more aerated than in the Turkey Red loaf and had some large holes; it was also much lighter and fluffier, although a bit less moist, than the TR. (High hydration level promotes bigger holes, but the high percentage of whole grain flours works against them.)&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/dr-funkenstein/20201017_1633.jpg"
alt="Funky Karl crumbshot"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>I don&amp;rsquo;t want to sound like a food snob, but I have to confess that the only words I could think of when slicing this bread were &amp;ldquo;alveolate ecstasy.&amp;rdquo; Each slice felt ethereal, almost weightless, on my hand. In any case, this was a great crumb for sandwiches and toasts.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/dr-funkenstein/20201018_1109.jpg"
alt="Funky Karl baked"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Funky Karl, an alveolate ecstasy you never knew existed.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Now, the flavor: I was struck first by the tender, airy texture &amp;ndash; so delicate on my tongue that it felt like eating cottony clouds &amp;ndash; although there was some nice chew, too.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/dr-funkenstein/20201017_1256.jpg"
alt="Funky Karl crumbshot"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/dr-funkenstein/20201017_1300.jpg"
alt="Funky Karl crumbshot"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Funky Karl crumb porn.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Like the Turkey Red loaf, there was little wheat flavor. Maybe there was, but it was easily overshadowed by a prominent combination of sourness and tanginess. I would describe it as noticeably more tangy than sour &amp;ndash; it likely contained a wider spectrum of piquancy than I could articulate &amp;ndash; and I would compare it to a sour rye bread or even a tamarind/lemon juice combination. Call it a &lt;em>pane picante integrale&lt;/em>?&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/dr-funkenstein/20201018_1103.jpg"
alt="Funky Karl crumbshot"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The brisk flavors of caramelized onions (or was it the wild onions looming in the Karl92?) and crushed spices came through and were nearly assertive enough to go &lt;em>mano a mano&lt;/em> with the lush tartness.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The wheat berries had literally melted into the crumb and were content to stay in the background.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/dr-funkenstein/20201018_2149.jpg"
alt="Funky Karl crumbshot"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The crust was thin, crispy, and chewy except for the ears which crunched. It tasted much more flavorful than the crumb, as usual, and added the nuttiness I always enjoy.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>All in all, I think the long, cold fermentation resulted in a fortified crust giving way to richly complex layers of bold, indulgent, sophisticated flavors. Lots of nutty, earthy and sweet overtones followed by a deep tanginess and a trace of pleasing bitterness. I&amp;rsquo;m a &lt;em>huge&lt;/em> fan of zing and heat, and this bread hit the spot!&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/dr-funkenstein/20201018_2151.jpg"
alt="Funky Karl crumbshot"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/dr-funkenstein/20201018_2153.jpg"
alt="Funky Karl crumbshot"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Best part: I didn&amp;rsquo;t smell or taste any mustiness in it no matter how hard I tried, nor did we feel sick at all from eating it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We devoured half of the loaf in 3 days (delicious as is, but even better toasted), and took the rest to a BBQ at the relatives yesterday. They all grew up eating pre-sliced Wonder Bread (or Bunny® Bread, which &amp;ndash; I just learned yesterday &amp;ndash; has been a household name and an &lt;a href="https://orangebeanindiana.com/2020/05/08/thats-what-i-said-the-story-of-bunny-bread/">iconic brand&lt;/a> in the Midwest for decades, no offense) and have vastly different food preferences than me.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/dr-funkenstein/20201019_1300.jpg"
alt="Funky Karl crumbshot"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Everybody loved the texture of the bread; they thought it was almost as soft and fluffy as the premium mediocre Bunny® Original 100% Whole Wheat Bread! Lol. This may sound like an insult to a coastal foodie, but in a Midwestern context it must be interpreted as the highest form of compliment &amp;ndash; because &amp;ldquo;you can&amp;rsquo;t beat the Bunny!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/dr-funkenstein/20201019_1301.jpg"
alt="Funky Karl crumbshot"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/dr-funkenstein/20201019_1303.jpg"
alt="Funky Karl crumbshot"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>However, nobody liked the pungent flavor of this bread. Someone compared it to balsamic vinegar, and someone else said it tasted as sour as Trolli sour gummy worms (&amp;ldquo;for people who can&amp;rsquo;t get enough tanginess in their life&amp;rdquo;). Still, the bread disappeared quickly &amp;ndash; maybe people just got intense carb cravings.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Oh well. That was fun.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Guess I have just found another failproof (and easier) way of making whole wheat &amp;ldquo;clouds,&amp;rdquo; besides the method I accidentally discovered while making &lt;em>panettone integrale&lt;/em>. What I have done with Karl92 over the last couple of weeks &amp;ndash; from smoking the flour to sifting to the 72h fermentation &amp;ndash; is fairly labor-intensive and time-consuming, not something I&amp;rsquo;d do often or use for production. Just a science experiment for my own curiosity.&lt;/p>
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>Spices consisted of dill seeds, caraway seeds, fennel seeds, coriander, fenugreek seeds, anise, black peppercorns, and papaya seeds; all roasted and coarsely ground just before using.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>I soaked a handful of funky Karl92 wheat berries in liquid whey, and let it ferment for a few days. Drained and incorporated the mushy berries (wet weight 107g).&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:3" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>With 220g midds added back, the total amount of flour used directly in the dough stood at 1,485g (~86% extraction).&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/section></content></item><item><title>Zombie Dust</title><link>/posts/zombie-dust/</link><pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2020 12:09:53 -0500</pubDate><guid>/posts/zombie-dust/</guid><description>This unapologetically flavorful bread, made with a shameless amount of old bread, will be your only respite after the zombie apocalypse.</description><content>&lt;p>Grains used to be widely grown in the northeastern US. In 1845, wheat was grown in every country of New York. There were even four acres of wheat grown in Manhattan.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>New Jersey was one of the &amp;ldquo;bread colonies,&amp;rdquo; where wheat was an important export crop for farmers.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>During Colonial times the wheat belt in New Jersey stretched from New York City to Philadelphia. By 1750 the New Jersey colony had progressed rapidly in milling, and much of the flour marketed in New York City came from the region around New Brunswick. In the first half of the 18th century the New Jersey flouring mills were considered as the best in the country.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Harry B. Weiss, &lt;em>The Early Grist and Flouring Mills of New Jersey&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>In his book, &lt;em>The Third Plate&lt;/em>, Chef Dan Barber mentions that there was one gristmill for every seven hundred Americans in 1840.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The remains of those mills can still be seen along the banks of the Garden State&amp;rsquo;s rivers and major streams. In gristmills, grains were ground between millstones, which crushed the entire kernel (bran, germ, and endosperm) into flour. Once ground, flour had a shelf life of about 1 week. You brought your wheat to the mill or you milled it yourself. Some of the bran and germ could be sifted out, but the volatile oils in the remaining bran and germ turn rancid quickly through exposure to oxygen, reducing the shelf life of stone-ground flour. The invention of the modern roller mill in the late 1800s enabled millers to strip the bran and germ from the endosperm during milling &amp;ndash; and, in the process, remove most of the nutrients and flavors. Flour changed from a locally produced, perishable food into a high-volume, shelf-stable commodity. Many local farmers and millers were unable to compete against large-scale highly-efficient grain operations in the Midwest. By 1955, only &lt;a href="https://morrisparks.net/index.php/parks/cooper-gristmill">one&lt;/a> flour mill remained in New Jersey.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Re-localization of food supply chains has been underway across the world, to promote food sovereignty. The economics of local grains could work. There is a farmer in Ontario who makes a living selling his hand-processed grains direct to consumers. Thor Oechsner, an organic grain farmer in New York, built a mill (Farmer Ground Flour) and a bakery (Wide Awake Bakery) to ensure markets for his grains. Regional hubs and distributors like GrowNYC Grains and The Northeast Grainshed have been pivotal in connecting growers with processors and bakers, and sparking a rise in demand for local grains.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>IMHO, the success of re-localizing grains and flours largely depends on the willingness of bakers to develop a sensory approach to baking, i.e. understand the differences in gluten content, water absorption and flavor in locally-grown grains and locally-milled flours, which lack the consistency that large industrial mills achieve by blending different varieties of wheat. By foregoing strict adherence to recipes, bakers are liberated from the expectation that flour must behave consistently, regardless of the origin, farming practices and conditions in which the grain is grown. They would be able to better accommodate variability in the way locally-grown grains perform during the making of breads and pastries.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>The white flour industrial complex so completely dominates the food landscape&amp;hellip;that to wish for anything substantially different seems, well, wishful and nostalgic.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Michael Pollan, &lt;em>Cooked&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>I have been working my way through Pyotr Kropotkin&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em>Conquest of Bread&lt;/em>. It&amp;rsquo;s hard to forget that bread shortages helped ignite the French Revolution and the Arab Spring. Kropotkin&amp;rsquo;s call for &amp;ldquo;well-being for all&amp;rdquo; has inspired me to think about how to repurpose old bread into new meals, essentially &amp;ldquo;paying it forward&amp;rdquo; so that nothing is wasted and someone could always have a loaf of bread.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>German bakers have long had a tradition of adding an old bread soaker to a new dough. It helps to eliminate waste, save on fresh flours, and add buckets of flavors. Pretty clever.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Before you wrinkle your nose and scream &amp;ldquo;ewwwwwww,&amp;rdquo; the old bread used here is not a green and fuzzy piece of ancient crust, or a 3-day-old slice of supermarket pap, but a drying piece of good (sourdough) bread, e.g. the end of a loaf.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Here is a delicious way to upcycle a good amount of old bread into a new loaf.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>80% extraction wheat flour (Redeemer - Whitesfields Farm, MA)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>roasted barley tea&lt;/td>
&lt;td>105%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>whole wheat levain&lt;/td>
&lt;td>60%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>old WW bread&lt;/td>
&lt;td>50%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>homemade beetroot purée&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>raw seed mix (for coating)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>To make roasted barley tea, first you gotta roast the barley. Spread whole, from-the-field, unhulled barley in a single layer on a sheet pan and place in oven. (I used unhulled Baronesse barley from Joseph&amp;rsquo;s Grainery, WA. It was bred by &lt;a href="http://www.nordsaat.de/ueber-uns/historie/?L=1">Nordsaat&lt;/a> in Germany where they don&amp;rsquo;t care about feed grains as much as in the US.) Roast at 400°F for 15-20 mins, or until the grains take on a golden brown color and exude a popcorn-like aroma. Let cool and store in an air-tight container. Now you can brew some scrumptious tea by steeping roasted barley in hot water for ~12 hours. This cannot be reproduced with pearled or naked barley, since much of the flavor comes from the roasted toasty hull.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Steam or roast some chopped beets. Pulse the cooked beets with coconut milk in a blender until smooth and creamy. The beetroot purée will add extra flavors and delightful swirls to the bread.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Soak the chunks of stale bread (can be any type) in 25% of the total tea. (Depending on how dry your bread is, you may want to adjust the hydration accordingly.) Add half of the levain. Leave in a fridge overnight. Next day, mash up any remaining lumps so that it&amp;rsquo;s a thick and somewhat smooth paste.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Autolyze the freshly milled flour with the remaining tea for 2 hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Mix in the soaker, the rest of the levain, and salt, until thoroughly combined.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Rest 30 mins. Do a strong letter fold.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Rest another 30 mins rest. Laminate with beetroot purée to add extra flavors and colorful swirls to the bread.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Rest 60 mins. Perform a coil-fold.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Rest another 2 hours before shaping. Roll the dough in seeds. No need to toast the seeds, as they will be nicely toasted during baking and add amazing flavors to the bread.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>10 hours final proof in the fridge.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Let the dough warm up for a few hours before baking.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It rose like a beast in the oven.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/zombie-dust/202001241449.jpg"
alt="Zombie Dust"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>OMG!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Every slice is packed with extra flavor and crunch, thanks to the layer of caramelized seeds atop the crust. Reminds me a lot of Whole Foods' Seeduction bread.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This loaf is completely unapologetic in what it is &amp;ndash; a bold and aromatic bread that is made with a hefty amount of old bread.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Gossamer-like crumb texture.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/zombie-dust/202001241639.jpg"
alt="Zombie Dust"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The last 4 slices&amp;hellip;&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/zombie-dust/202001242205.jpg"
alt="Zombie Dust"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Zombie Dust, an unapologetically flavorful bread, made with a shameless amount of old bread. It will be your only respite after the zombie apocalypse.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Few things are as ordinary as a loaf of bread, yet the process by which it is made is extraordinary &amp;ndash; and still something of a mystery even to those who study it or practice it every day. - Michael Pollan&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>A variation of this bread I made later, without seeds:&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/zombie-dust/variation/202001241320.jpg"
alt="Zombie Dust"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/zombie-dust/variation/202001241323.jpg"
alt="Zombie Dust"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/zombie-dust/variation/202001241324.jpg"
alt="Zombie Dust"/>
&lt;/figure></content></item><item><title>Breadford von Regrainton</title><link>/posts/breadford-von-regrainton/</link><pubDate>Mon, 09 Dec 2019 16:41:45 -0800</pubDate><guid>/posts/breadford-von-regrainton/</guid><description>A hearty re-grained bread, made with spent grains and Glenn whole wheat flour.</description><content>&lt;p>I picked up a bag of Glenn wheat berries from Kenter Canyon Farms at the Atwater Village Farmers' Market in Los Angeles. It cost ~$2/lb, not cheap but not ridiculously overpriced either. The Glenn wheat was grown on Kenter Canyon Farms in Ventura County, along the south side of the Santa Clara River.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/files/Glenn.pdf">Glenn&lt;/a> is a modern HRSW developed by a NDSU breeding program to provide better scab resistance and higher yield. It was released by the North Dakota Agricultural Experiment Station in the spring of 2005. It has a fairly high protein content of 13%-14%. I have seen quite a few local and regional mills across the country label Glenn as a &amp;ldquo;heritage&amp;rdquo; wheat &amp;ndash; very curious.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I had long wanted to bake a &lt;em>treberbrot&lt;/em>, a hearty German bread made with the addition of spent grains from brewing beers. The spent grain adds some sweetness, texture and a lot of fiber to the bread.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/regrainton/201912082109.jpg"
alt="Breadford von Regrainton"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Breadford von Regrainton, a hearty re-grained bread that re-uses a lot of brewer&amp;rsquo;s spent grains.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>First, I milled the Glenn wheat berries, and &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/joeliath/">sifted&lt;/a> half into a 80% extraction flour, leaving the other half wholegrain (100% extraction).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Next, I built a levain with&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>sifted-out wheat bran; and&lt;/li>
&lt;li>a smooth purée of spent grains (from brewing Berliner Weiss) and &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fvtmBuTyu1c">boiled jackfruit seeds&lt;/a>.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>To make the dough stronger, I decided to use a 2-dough lamination method.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Dough #1:&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>80% extraction wheat flour (Glenn - Kenter Canyon Farms, CA)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>h&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->2&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->o&lt;/td>
&lt;td>85%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>bran levain&lt;/td>
&lt;td>40%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>This will be the stronger half of the dough that lifts the whole bread. You can totally swap water for beer here.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Dough #2:&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>whole wheat flour (Glenn - Kenter Canyon Farms, CA)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>h&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->2&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->o&lt;/td>
&lt;td>70%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>spent grain purée&lt;/td>
&lt;td>60%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>bran levain&lt;/td>
&lt;td>20%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>toasted flaxseeds&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>I mixed 1 part spent grains to 1 part water, and puréed the mixture in a blender. Then I autolyzed the flour, along with the flaxseeds, in this thick grainy smoothie diluted with water.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>With all of the wheat bran added back to the dough through the levain, this bread retains its whole-wheat integrity.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Add-ins:&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>spent grains&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sunflower seeds&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>roasted papaya seeds, ground&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>raisins&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.taste.com.au/quick-easy/articles/want-use-up-seeds/f45slcr4">Roasted papaya seeds&lt;/a> have a dark cocoa brown color and smell deeply aromatic. They taste like peppercorns.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I did 4 folds with each dough during the first 3 hours. Then I combined both doughs by gently stretching them out into big rectangles and placing dough #2 on top of dough #1. I sprinkled the add-ins during lamination.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The dough was bulk-fermented for 5 hours in total at room temperature, shaped into a taut boule (dusted with grated coconut), and then retarded at 40°F for 10 hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Next day, I let the dough warm up for a few hours until ~100% risen. I baked it on a shitty pizza pan in my ghetto toaster oven.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/regrainton/201912082113.jpg"
alt="Breadford von Regrainton"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>It grew so big during baking that it nearly filled up every cubic inch of the toaster oven!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The crust came out crispy and thin. The crumb is so freakin' airy.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/regrainton/201912082135.jpg"
alt="Breadford von Regrainton"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The taste is deeply flavorful with a mild tang and a subtle sweetness from spent grains and raisins.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/regrainton/201912091249.jpg"
alt="Breadford von Regrainton"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Superbly delightful.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>NGL, it tasted even better the next day.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/regrainton/201912091255.jpg"
alt="Breadford von Regrainton"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>A later variation:&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/regrainton/201912301643.jpg"
alt="Breadford von Regrainton"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Breadford von Regrainton v2.0, an incredibly flavorful re-grained bread that rises from dead spent grains.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Can&amp;rsquo;t believe it&amp;rsquo;s already December. Where did the year go?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In review, 2019 has been my Year of Fermentation. I read Sandor Katz&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em>The Art of Fermentation&lt;/em> and René Redzepi&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em>The Noma Guide to Fermentation.&lt;/em> I got into sourdough breadmaking (and bread chemistry) seriously for the firs time. I experimented audaciously with literally anything I could get my hands on: vegetables, beans, grains, milk, fish&amp;hellip; From lactic acid bacteria (LAB), I ventured into fungi &amp;ndash; koji (&lt;em>Aspergillus oryzae&lt;/em>) and tempeh (&lt;em>Rhizopus oligosporus&lt;/em>). It&amp;rsquo;s been a very memorable year and an unbelievably fulfilling one.&lt;/p></content></item><item><title>Joeliath</title><link>/posts/joeliath/</link><pubDate>Wed, 28 Aug 2019 22:19:17 -0700</pubDate><guid>/posts/joeliath/</guid><description>Joe vs. Bread: Freshly milled grains and spent coffee grounds fuse to create pure magic.</description><content>&lt;h4 id="coffee-grounds-are-edible">Coffee grounds are edible&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>Back in my college days, whenever I needed to pull some all-nighters, I would always chew on a handful of chocolate-covered Colombian coffee beans.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A while ago, I got some Ethiopian Amaro Gayo green coffee beans. I roasted them at home until just after the first crack, and have been drinking the cold brew as my summer morning Joe. It&amp;rsquo;s acidic, floral and citrusy, reminding me of orange marmalade and cocoa.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The zero-waster in me couldn&amp;rsquo;t stand the thought of just throwing out these spent coffee grounds, so memories of chewing gourmet coffee beans in college gave me the idea of incorporating these spent coffee grounds into baked goods. ☕🍞&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A Danish startup has come up with &lt;a href="https://www.kaffebueno.com/post/introducing-kaffe-bueno-coffee-flour">Kaffe Bueno Flour&lt;/a>!&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Kaffe Bueno Flour® comes from used coffee grounds, recycled from selected hotels and offices in Copenhagen. Then, we extract the oil inside the grounds and further sterilise them. &lt;/p>
&lt;p>The result is a naturally gluten-free coffee flour. Although it comes from coffee, its coffee taste is mostly gone along with the oil extracted. Its taste leans towards nutty, chocolaty side. &lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>They even have a &lt;a href="https://www.kaffebueno.com/post/how-to-make-sourdough-bread-with-coffee-flour-vegan-recipe">recipe&lt;/a> for a coffee sourdough, in which the coffee flour is ~11% of flour weight in the final dough.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Dan Lepard has a formula for his famous &lt;a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20190908145402/https://www.jeremycherfas.net/blog/dan-lepard-s-black-pepper-rye">Black Pepper Rye&lt;/a>, which uses brewed black coffee to make a roux with a rye first.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>So, on the spur of the moment, I strained some coffee grounds from my cold brew, and left them to dry over a dehumidifier for a few hours. When the grounds were thoroughly dry, I ground them again in a coffee grinder to yield a much finer &amp;ldquo;coffee flour.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="white-wheat--white-flour">White wheat =/= white flour&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>I wanted to use mild-tasting flour for this bread, so the coffee flavor can come through. Colorado Windy White, a modern hard white winter wheat (HWWW) variety grown by Sunflower Acres (the retail front is Grains from the Plains), fits the bill.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>When you grind up white wheat to make flour, it looks off-white, kind of like unbleached &amp;ldquo;white flour.&amp;rdquo; But they are not the same thing. Most commercial white flour is made from red wheat that has been refined (the bitter, bulky parts of bran and germ are removed, leaving only the starchy endosperm) &amp;ndash; and in most cases it has been treated with bleach and potassium bromate, and then &amp;ldquo;enriched&amp;rdquo; with artificial vitamins since the natural ones have been lost during processing. This results in a homogeneous product with a long shelf life, which produces consistently fluffy baked goods &amp;ndash; but at the cost of nutrition and flavor.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>White wheat is pretty much the same as red wheat, except that it has no major genes for bran color. White whole wheat flour has a milder, sweeter flavor than red whole wheat flour, due to lack of phenolic compounds and lower tannin content.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In the US, many breads are made with hard white (whole) wheat containing &amp;gt;= 10% protein:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Brands owned by Bimbo, the largest bakery company in the US: Arnold, Sara Lee, Mrs. Bairds, Stroehmann, Freihofer&amp;rsquo;s, EarthGrains, Brownberry, Francisco, Grandma Sycamore&amp;rsquo;s, J.J. Nissen, Lender&amp;rsquo;s Bagels, Oroweat, etc.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Brands owned by Flowers Foods, the second largest bakery company in the US: Wonder Bread, Nature&amp;rsquo;s Own, Captain John Derst&amp;rsquo;s, Sunbeam, Evangeline Maid, Mrs. Freshley&amp;rsquo;s, Merita, Cobblestone Mill, European Bakers, Mi Casa, Bunny Bread, HomePride, Tastykake, and Dave&amp;rsquo;s Killer Bread.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Pepperidge Farm (Campbell&amp;rsquo;s)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Wholesome Harvest (Maple Leaf Bakery)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Aunt Millie&amp;rsquo;s (Perfection Bakeries, Inc)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Soft white wheat (typically &amp;lt; 10% protein) is the star ingredient in Kellogg&amp;rsquo;s Mini Wheats and Wheat Flakes, as well as Nabisco&amp;rsquo;s Triscuit crackers. Kellogg&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Open for Breakfast&amp;rdquo; website tells the stories of a 4,000-acre soft white wheat farm in Michigan, close to the company&amp;rsquo;s HQ. There is some evidence that breakfast cereals made with white whole wheat hold their crispness longer in milk. Triscuit&amp;rsquo;s product description goes, &amp;ldquo;We like to think of Soft White Winter Wheat as a kind of cashmere of wheat because of its soft texture and delicious taste. It&amp;rsquo;s what gives Triscuit its golden color, distinctive crunch and 24 grams of delicious whole grain goodness per serving.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Asians love soft white wheat, too, because they believe it makes better noodles &amp;ndash; bright, clear white, soft inside but firm on the surface. When made with white wheat, fresh refrigerated noodles will not develop black specks.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In the Japanese prefecture Kagawa, the home of the &lt;em>udon&lt;/em> noodle, a white wheat reclamation is underway. Before the 1960s, fields of wheat covered the town of Sanuki (the old name of Kagawa). The local Sanuki wheat would be harvested, milled and sifted to make flour for Sanuki &lt;em>udon&lt;/em>. But after repeated bad weather in the early 1960s, wheat production declined sharply and imported Australian Standard White (ASW) wheat soon became the major variety. Some local noodle makers and aficionados found imported wheat to be inferior and produced subpar &lt;em>udon&lt;/em> flour, so they worked together with small farmers to revive Kagawa&amp;rsquo;s soul food, i.e. &lt;em>udon&lt;/em> made from Sanuki-grown wheat. In 2000, they developed a new variety of wheat for &lt;em>udon&lt;/em> named &lt;em>sanuki no yume&lt;/em> (&amp;ldquo;Sanuki&amp;rsquo;s dream&amp;rdquo;) and later in 2009 a newer variety based on the OG. Since 2013, almost the entire wheat field in Kawaga grows &lt;em>sanuki no yume&lt;/em> 2009. Kinoshita Flour Mills in Kagawa sells a &lt;em>udon&lt;/em> flour made with 100% Kagawa-grown wheat (8.5% protein). They use a meticulous milling process to remove all the bran because, as explained on their website, &amp;ldquo;speck, a small piece of bran, would damage the taste and the food texture of the Udon.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>They can keep their noodles, I will make bread. There are thousands of other foods I would rather eat. &lt;em>Mon pain quotidien&lt;/em>, first and foremost.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="milling">Milling&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>Bread made from finely milled wholegrain flour has a tender texture, a slight chew, a rustic hue, and robust wheat flavor.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;code>Note&lt;/code>: Working with freshly milled single-varietal whole grains is not as predictable as a standard bag of King Arthur or other name-brand ﬂour, which remain consistent by blending varieties of wheats from multiple years or regions. Whole grains are living and vibrant; shelf-stable flours are dead. Working with whole grains is challenging and requires you to be willing to learn new skills and pay greater attention to the process, rather than relying on recipes where you can simply plug in your ingredients and yield the same results. Grains are a lot like coffee &amp;ndash; you have to think about, &amp;ldquo;When was this roasted? When was this ground?&amp;rdquo; You can taste the difference in ﬂavor and texture.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Freshly milled flour works a bit differently from shelf-stable flour:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>It contains more enzymes and minerals, and ferments faster than store-bought ones;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>It contains volatile oils from the bran and germ; store-bought flour has had some oils evaporated off or may not even have had the germ in it, depending on the brand.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>Freshly milled wholegrain flour is best for Desem, the old Flemish method specifically developed for 100% wholegrain bread.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="bolting">Bolting&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>I ground up the wheat berries in a grain mill, and sifted the flour through a mesh sieve to screen out the coarsest bits.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Bolted flour contains almost all of the germ, and the softer parts of the bran. In exchange for a loss of mainly fiber and minerals, the resulting flour performs more like a bread or all-purpose flour while maintaining some of the rich flavor, nutritional benefits, and lovely color of wholegrain flours. It has a creamy texture.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Historically, bolted flour was sifted through &lt;a href="https://www.angelfire.com/journal/millbuilder/boulting.html">a piece of cloth&lt;/a>. Nowadays it&amp;rsquo;s typically done through a metal or plastic screen.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The total flour out of the sifter divided by the total flour out of the mill would give you the extraction percentage. The higher the percentage, the closer to whole grain flour it is. 100% extraction is whole wheat. Home-milling and bolting wheat will give you incredible flavor that&amp;rsquo;s impossible to beat.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="formula">Formula&lt;/h4>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>85% extraction wheat flour (Windy White - Sunflower Acres, CO)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>83%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>whole rye flour (Abruzzi rye - Jones Farms, CO)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>homemade coffee flour&lt;/td>
&lt;td>12%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>homemade cold brew coffee&lt;/td>
&lt;td>88%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;em>zakvaska&lt;/em> levain&lt;/td>
&lt;td>40%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>flaxseeds (for coating)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>3%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Do the same thing with whole rye berries &amp;ndash; mill them, but skip the bolting. Leave the rye flour coarse and wholesome. Rye is a cousin to wheat and mills similarly, but the two have very different baking qualities.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>IMO, rye is one of the tastiest, most nutrient-dense grains. It yields a peppery-earthy flavor and improves the keeping quality of whatever you make with it. Feeding sourdough starter with rye keeps it vigorous, sour and fruity.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Abruzzi rye is an Italian heirloom variety. The kernels are bluish-gold in appearance, and smell nutty and sweet like a blend of herbal spices and citrus. It was famous in the Carolinas during the colonial era. Did you know it was the very rye flour used in &amp;ldquo;thirded bread&amp;rdquo;, a cost-cutting recipe that combined rye, wheat, and cornmeal (instead of oats) plus the sweet upgrade of molasses, such as Boston brown bread.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Small amounts have big results. Blending merely 5% of rye into a wheat bread will add a depth of flavor, without overpowering others.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="method">Method&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>I have a big batch of &lt;em>zakvaska&lt;/em> left from making rye bread &lt;em>kvass&lt;/em>. So I used some &lt;em>zakvaska&lt;/em>, instead of the usual WW sourdough starter, to build a 100% hydration levain for this bread. It doubled in volume overnight, brimming with bubbles.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I autolysed all of the flours with coffee for 1 hour. Then I added the levain and salt.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I did 5 folds during the first 3 hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>After 5 hours of warm bulk-fermentation, I shaped the dough into a log, coated it with a handful of flaxseeds, and placed it in my ghetto banneton. I left it in the fridge overnight to proof.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Next day, I left the dough in a warm place for 2.5 hours to finish proofing. The dough rose 80%-90%, and felt so jiggly! Then I baked it.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/joeliath/20190828182954.jpg"
alt="Joeliath"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The bread almost tripled from the initial dough! The crust bloomed nicely from the seams and had beautifully caramelized spots.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/joeliath/20190828183154.jpg"
alt="Joeliath"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/joeliath/20190828183208.jpg"
alt="Joeliath"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;h4 id="cooling">Cooling&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>The final stage of baking bread is letting it cool properly. If you were to slice into a hot loaf of bread, you would not be doing it any justice. The heat retained inside the bread continues to cook it and develop flavor/texture, so slicing it too early interrupts this process prematurely. Also, cutting warm bread allows moisture to escape into the air, which means it will go stale faster.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As the breads cool, the process of starch retrogradation is completed and the water molecules move outward, evenly, toward the crust. If you were to cut into a hot loaf, the crumb is still too soft and the bread won&amp;rsquo;t slice neatly, it will tend to be gummy and stick to your knife. Allow your loaves to firm up and cool to about body temperature before slicing. Breads that can be eaten while they are still warm are rolls and baguettes, because the crust-to-crumb ratio is so high, and there is not much further internal cooking that has to take place.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/joeliath/20190828201251.jpg"
alt="Joeliath"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;h4 id="tasting">Tasting&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>The crust is thin and crispy, and the crumb springy and soft. The cold brew coffee lent a nice color to the bread. The coffee flour definitely added a unique bite and a smoky accent. There is no smell or taste of morning Joe, but you can feel the coffee grounds caressing your tongue.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/joeliath/20190828201313.jpg"
alt="Joeliath"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Joeliath, a wonderful bread made with cold brew coffee and spent coffee grounds.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>I enjoyed the bread with a wedge of Comté &amp;ndash; a flavor explosion! The pair reminded me of condensed milk, cocoa and macadamia nut. Washed it down with some &lt;em>el cheapo&lt;/em> Pacific Peaks merlot. The smokiness of the wine reminded me of the coffee notes in this bread.&lt;/p></content></item></channel></rss>