<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>canada on HERESY LEVAIN</title><link>/tags/canada/</link><description>Latest experiments in canada from HERESY LEVAIN</description><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2023 HERESY LEVAIN 🍞 CC BY-NC-SA 4.0</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 08 Jan 2023 19:21:08 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/canada/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Singin' in ze Grain</title><link>/posts/singing-in-ze-grain/</link><pubDate>Sun, 08 Jan 2023 19:21:08 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/singing-in-ze-grain/</guid><description>45% heritage Sangaste rye + 45% heritage Red Fife wheat + 10% buckwheat, with Argentinian &lt;em>yerba maté&lt;/em> and lots of ancient grains &amp;amp; seeds.</description><content>&lt;p>A bunch of new construction homes are popping up across the road from the woods where I often go hiking. Realtors are trying to lure people in with a roadside ad, &amp;ldquo;Enjoyed the park? Why not live here?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I was just complaining the other day about how we had to drive increasingly longer and longer distances these days to get to a truly wild and natural park. More and more green space has been rezoned for residential housing development. Oftentimes I feel mankind has essentially been running a giant Ponzi scheme with Nature &amp;ndash; who might be &lt;a href="https://peaksurfer.blogspot.com/2022/12/who-is-sam-bankman-fried-of.html">the SBF of the ecological space&lt;/a>?&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>A person deals with the natural elements only through a set of technologies which is so complete that he is actually dealing with those technologies themselves. The natural environment itself disappears. We obviously have to make a comparison with the city, an essential product of technology. In the city, man perceives the natural elements only accidentally (parks, sidewalk trees). Nothing spontaneously natural is left here. And outside nature is reserved for spare time, relaxation, etc., given the decreasing importance of agriculture and the decline in the farming population.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Jacques Ellul, &lt;em>The Technological System&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Home prices have been falling&amp;hellip; 1 out of 3 real estate agents in the US couldn&amp;rsquo;t afford to pay rent in November. But when you go to Zillow and actually check the price history of almost any house on the market right now, you will see that current price drop looks like &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/files/Kovach-statement.pdf">a pimple on an elephant&amp;rsquo;s ass&lt;/a>.&amp;rdquo; The only good news is downpayment requirements are falling, too. Still, total cost of home ownership over a 25-year amortization is significantly higher. Few are advertising that fact.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Some quick mortgage math for Canadians: a C$1.5m mortgage at 3% APR with a 25-year amortization is C$86,141/year (C$2,151,545 total cost). A C$1.1m mortgage at 7% APR with a 25-year amortization is C$94,391/year (C$2,359,789 total cost). Housing prices need to drop a lot more.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Pending Home Sales in the United States decreased 37.80% year-on-year in November of 2022, the 18th straight month of declines and the biggest since November of 2021.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>National Association of Realtors&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>A ramification: Private Equity (PE) is going to see a massive write-down of its non-public assets in 2023, whether it&amp;rsquo;s residential real estate (RRE), commercial real estate (CRE), or venture capital (VC). Blackstone&amp;rsquo;s $68Bn &lt;a href="https://www.breit.com/portfolio/">BREIT&lt;/a> and Starwood&amp;rsquo;s $30Bn &lt;a href="https://www.starwoodnav.reit/portfolio/">SREIT&lt;/a> already froze withdrawals last month. This past week, BREIT got a &lt;a href="https://www.businesswire.com/news/home/20230103005410/en/UC-Investments-Creates-Strategic-Venture-with-Blackstone-to-Invest-4-Billion-in-BREIT-Common-Shares">$4Bn &amp;ldquo;Buffett-style&amp;rdquo; last-resort bailout&lt;/a> from the University of California. Given that Blackstone is the world largest institutional landlord, 2023 is off to an ominous start for the US CRE market.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Markdowns will be severe. This will lead to groupthink of re-evaluating the entire PE world. Not all PE is bad, but the decade-long pyramiding of real estate on ever lower interest rates has ended &amp;ndash; and that will bring a big markdown cycle. Opportunity always exists when the crowd thinks it knows an unknowable future.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Another surprise file will be the Pension Fund Bailout Act of 2023. The City of Chicago is the poster child for this phenomenon, but they are not alone. Pension Funds (PFs) have been gouging on PE and RE over the last decade. That horse is now dead, as the return of real interest rates and above-zero commercial papers crushes the valuations of these investments. Slowly at first, and then all of a sudden, the markdowns will rip holes in the PF balance sheets. The fact that the bulk of the boomers are now retiring is not going to help these PFs. (The tight labor market is partly due to early retirements.) As this pull-forward effect ripples through the PF world, more problems will surface and the cry for a bailout will intensify. Good luck to the bond market and RE market when the buyer from the last decade is now a seller. Prepare for &amp;ldquo;higher for longer&amp;rdquo; in the interest rate world as the demand for commercial papers drops &amp;ndash; especially in a negative-carry world. The current bond yield curve is toxic for leveraged financial positions.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A lot of ridiculous things happened in the last couple of years, e.g. cars launched into space for the memes, degenerates becoming millionaires overnight from their basement and then giving it all back. As the calendar turns to 2023, all those moments will be lost in time, like tears in the rain.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The Dominoes are starting to fall, e.g. &lt;a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/dereksaul/2023/01/05/silvergate-stock-crashes-nearly-50-as-bank-grapples-with-crypto-crisis/">Silvergate&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://www.amny.com/transit/ag-james-sues-auto-lender-credit-acceptance-corp-accuses-of-predatory-loans-and-securities-fraud/">Credit Acceptance Corporation&lt;/a> this past week. Bed Bath and Beyond is worried about &lt;a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2023/01/05/business/bed-bath-beyond-bankruptcy.html">a gloomier future&lt;/a>. &amp;ldquo;Slowly at first, then all of a sudden.&amp;rdquo; Second-tier financial institutions and sovereigns will be the trigger. The higher cost of capital is starting to filter into the financial economy, driving valuations lower and lower.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The layoffs in Tech Land are &lt;a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/05/amazon-to-cut-18000-jobs-as-tech-layoffs-continue/">just getting started&lt;/a>, as the seemingly unending stream of capital supporting profitless Ponzi tech is drying up.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>There has been too much money in finance and tech. There are some who can resist, but not many. Plenty of Harvard grads went on to Wall Street. What a waste. You need enough money to live, but how much is that? Which is precisely the point of &lt;a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt15255876/">&lt;em>Emily the Criminal&lt;/em>&lt;/a> &amp;ndash; Emily needs the money and she makes choices. The middle class has evaporated. And the truth is those at the bottom will do anything to survive. Desperate people do desperate things. Emily says you must make your own rules. You are either the boss or the employee (capital vs. labor). If you are the employee, you don&amp;rsquo;t have much power. Sure, there are unions. Then again, everybody agrees to arbitration and the company always wins and&amp;hellip;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Life is hard.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Yet people can still splurge $140 on a dozen &lt;a href="https://lastcrumb.com/">luxury cookies&lt;/a> and $100 on a single panettone. First-class flights from Zurich to Singapore are fully booked. Channel 2.55 bag went from $1600 in 2008 to $9000 in 2022. More draining in the financial ecosystem is on tap.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In &lt;a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt11564570/">&lt;em>Glass Onion&lt;/em>&lt;/a>, Benoit Blanc eventually figures out that the billionaire is just an idiot &amp;ndash; and he should have seen it all along.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Thoroughly caffeinated, I skimmed through Micheline Maynard&amp;rsquo;s new book, &lt;em>Satisfaction Guaranteed: How Zingerman&amp;rsquo;s Built a Corner Deli into a Global Food Community&lt;/em>. It&amp;rsquo;s one of those quintessential boomer hagiography-cum-business books. The author clearly admires Zingerman&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ndash; almost as much as Kamala Harris publicly idolizes civil rights lawyers &amp;ndash; and keeps comparing it to the world&amp;rsquo;s most successful companies, especially Toyota; whereas I find the niche store&amp;rsquo;s business model more clichéd than inspiring. The owners' purportedly unique &amp;ldquo;Visioning&amp;rdquo; process at ZingTrain, for example, recommends that your &amp;ldquo;effective vision&amp;rdquo; be &amp;ldquo;inspiring,&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;strategically sound,&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;written down,&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;communicated&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; four tenets that, on the whole, seem pretty stale. The same could be said about Zingerman&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;12 Natural Laws of Business,&amp;rdquo; which includes such banal points as &amp;ldquo;profit is good&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;greatness takes time.&amp;rdquo; One story I find particularly intriguing is how Zingerman&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href="https://www.michigandaily.com/uncategorized/campus-206/">handled competition&lt;/a> (e.g. Amer&amp;rsquo;s Mediterranean Deli) in the early years, given that 1) restaurant recipes are virtually never patentable, 2) restaurants have basically no &amp;ldquo;moats&amp;rdquo;, and 3) customer loyalty is fragile, particularly during difficult times. TBH, I find Zingerman&amp;rsquo;s mail-order bread a lot fresher than this book. Michigan has historically been hit hard by national recessions because the state&amp;rsquo;s economy (still) depends heavily on the auto industry and durable goods manufacturing, despite recent efforts to diversify. It would be interesting to see what happens in this round.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>There are only patterns. Patterns on top of patterns. Patterns that affect other patterns. Patterns hidden by patterns. Patterns within patterns. If you watch closely, history does nothing but repeat itself. What we call chaos is just patterns we haven&amp;rsquo;t recognized. What we call random is just patterns we can&amp;rsquo;t decipher. What we call nonsense is just patterns we can&amp;rsquo;t understand. What we call gibberish is just patterns we can&amp;rsquo;t read.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/singing-in-ze-grain/202301081352.jpg"
alt="Singin&amp;#39; in Ze Grain"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Singin' in ze grain&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>I made a bread inspired by German baker Tobias Exner&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em>Brandenburger Urkraft&lt;/em>, which he created together with Olympic canoe champion Sebastian Brendel.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="bran-levain">Bran levain&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>I milled some heritage Sangaste rye (45%), Red Fife wheat (45%), and buckwheat (10%).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I bolted the freshly milled wholegrain flours to remove some course bits (~17%), which I fed to the levain (~85% hydration) in 3 increments over 14 hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The sifted flours came out to be ~83% extraction. Every part of the grain will be re-combined in the final dough.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="altus-soaker">Altus soaker&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>I toasted a piece of day-old sourdough rye bread and ground it into breadcrumbs. I scooped some of the breadcrumbs (15% of final flour weight) into a bowl and poured an equal amount of hot water over it.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s % (of final flour weight)&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>old bread, toasted &amp;amp; ground&lt;/td>
&lt;td>15%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>hot water&lt;/td>
&lt;td>15%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>I covered the soaker and left it at room temperature for a few hours, and then moved it into the fridge overnight.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="grain-soaker">Grain soaker&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>The total amount of dry pseudo-grains used here came up to be 20% of final flour weight.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s % (of final flour weight)&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>quinoa (Bolivian royal white)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>kañiwa&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>amaranth (yellow foxtail)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>teff (brown)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>cool water&lt;/td>
&lt;td>40%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>I soaked the pseudo-grains in double the amount of water, and left them to sprout overnight.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="seeds--raisins">Seeds &amp;amp; raisins&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>I toasted the seeds (23% of final flour weight) until aromatic and very lightly browned.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s % (of final flour weight)&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sunflower seeds&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>pumpkin seeds&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>poppy seeds&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>nigella seeds&lt;/td>
&lt;td>3%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>In the meanwhile, I chopped up some Monukka raisins (5% of final flour weight) and set them aside.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s % (of final flour weight)&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>raisins&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;h4 id="final-dough">Final dough&lt;/h4>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>83% extraction rye flour (Sangaste - Laughing Wolf Farm, CO)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>45%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>83% extraction wheat flour (Red Fife - Merrylynd Organics, ON)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>45%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>83% extraction buckwheat flour (Merrylynd Organics, ON)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>freshly brewed &lt;em>yerba maté&lt;/em> (Liebig Original)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>102%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>bran levain&lt;/td>
&lt;td>40%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>altus soaker&lt;/td>
&lt;td>30%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>salt (Sal Marinho)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>chia seeds (black)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>flax seeds (brown)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>grain soaker&lt;/td>
&lt;td>60%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>toasted seeds&lt;/td>
&lt;td>23%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>raisins&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>I mixed the sifted flours, chia and flax seeds, and the altus soaker with 85% of the water, and left the mixture to autolyze for 30 mins. Then I added the levain and salt, and mixed for a few minutes. I let the dough rest for 10 mins, before adding the rest of the water slowly.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>At this point, I put the dough in the fridge. In the next 24 hours, I took the dough out of the fridge 6 times and gave it a coil-fold, adding some of the sprouted pseudo-grains, toasted seeds and raisins during each fold.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>After a 24-hour cold fermentation in the fridge, I shaped the dough, rolled it in extra sunflower seeds, and let it proof at room temperature for 3 hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Lastly, I baked it as usual, in my toaster oven.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/singing-in-ze-grain/202301081432.jpg"
alt="Singin&amp;#39; in ze Grain"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Like a bird singing in the rain, let grateful memories of forgotten foods survive in time of pain.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>I like the bread toasted, and paired with Kentucky old-school country ham.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This year, I hope to bake with more varieties of heritage grains. I would like to go into the woods more often and get to know more native plants before they disappear for good. And maybe I&amp;rsquo;ll try growing some peppers, too.&lt;/p></content></item><item><title>Arctic Maplemoon</title><link>/posts/arctic-maplemoon/</link><pubDate>Fri, 14 Jan 2022 22:44:20 -0600</pubDate><guid>/posts/arctic-maplemoon/</guid><description>An oaty raisiny whole wheat bread, made with Québécois ingredients.</description><content>&lt;p>Just came back from a Christmas vacation in Québec, with a boatload of good memories and bagfuls of grains. Took the Old Canada Road Scenic Byway from Maine to Québec City, and felt like I had teleported across the Atlantic Ocean to Europe.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Québec sits just below the Arctic, which means it&amp;rsquo;s literally frozen half of the year. Holy shit, winter in Québec is cold &amp;ndash; temperatures could easily drop to -35°C (-31°F) with the windchill. I had to get a parka. But I love how Canadians like to one-up each other over how cold their town is, as if winter was an acquired taste.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>But Québec &amp;ndash; especially la Ville de Québec &amp;ndash; at Christmastime is a true winter wonderland, full of &lt;em>joie de vivre&lt;/em>. It&amp;rsquo;s like Québécois have perfected the art of winter aversion therapy.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Québec is quite different from the rest of Canada (sort of like Scotland vs. England, or Puerto Rico vs. the US mainland). It&amp;rsquo;s a wonder that they have stayed together for this long. Québec gets a bunch of benefits (e.g. tax revenue, currency, and a governmental framework) from Canada that its own constantly-impoverished legislature could never provide, and Canada gets to enjoy a slice of Europe in between Ontario and New Brunswick. Friends with benefits.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Au Québec, on parle français.&lt;/em> But my French is rusty. Québec&amp;rsquo;s language issues are too deep, and some places absolutely refuse to speak a word of English. I wanted to have a good time and experience Québec City like a local, so I brushed up on my &lt;em>français&lt;/em> before arriving.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Holy poutine, Montmorency Falls is actually taller than Niagara Falls and absolutely stunning &amp;ndash; even in the winter. The ice toboggan at Le Château Frontenac was incredibly thrilling and fun.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The two cornerstones of the Québécois cuisine are bread and meat (particularly pork), both of which I&amp;rsquo;m fond of. So I had the good fortune of sampling many local gourmet foods made by &lt;em>les artisans charcutiers&lt;/em> and &lt;em>les boulangers des grains nobles&lt;/em>. If you&amp;rsquo;ve never had &lt;em>saucissons&lt;/em> (&amp;ldquo;French salami&amp;rdquo;) from La Ferme des Quatre-Temps and Charcuterie Charlevoisienne, or cheeses from Fromagerie des Grondines and Laiterie Charlevoix, then you haven&amp;rsquo;t lived!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I found an interesting indie magazine on Québécois food culture, &lt;a href="https://cariboumag.com/">Caribou&lt;/a>. Oh, there&amp;rsquo;s also a 5-volume tome about the history of family cooking in Québec, &lt;em>Histoire de la cuisine familiale du Québec&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Given that Québec produces an overwhelming majority of the world&amp;rsquo;s maple syrup (&lt;em>sirop d&amp;rsquo;érable&lt;/em>), it&amp;rsquo;s not surprising Québécois drizzle maple syrup on everything, even the eggs.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Anyway, I brought back some La Meunerie Milanaise wheat berries. No clue what specific cultivar these wheat berries are, other than some kind of hard red wheat grown in Québec. The nutrition label says it has 11.11% protein.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>According to the Spring 2018 issue of Bread Lines, published by the Bread Baker&amp;rsquo;s Guild of America, La Milanaise whole wheat flour is a blend of hard red winter/spring wheats. The nutrition label says it has 11.67% protein. I doubt La Milanaise uses vastly different blends in its wheat berries and WW flours.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The way the grain industry works in Canada reminds me a lot of America&amp;rsquo;s three-tier system of alcohol distribution: producers sell only to processors, who then &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->sell only through their distributors&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->, and distributors sell only to businesses. You rarely know which specific farm the grains come from, let alone meeting the farmers. You can&amp;rsquo;t buy La Milanaise products directly from La Milanaise anymore. You gotta find them at local retailers or place special orders through Avril Supermarché Santé.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I confess I hesitated about buying these wheat berries because I didn&amp;rsquo;t know what cultivars they were or who grew them, which is against &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/about">my philosophy&lt;/a>, but I decided to fuck it because YOLO&amp;hellip;and it&amp;rsquo;s Canada where the face of flour is Robin Hood, owned by US multinational Cargill.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I also got some La Milanaise oat groats. Québec doesn&amp;rsquo;t exactly grow a lot of oats. There are &amp;gt;=30 organic oat producers in eastern Québec, mostly in Saguenay-Lac-Saint-Jean and Bas-Saint-Laurent, but altogether they produce just ~5% of Canada&amp;rsquo;s oats. The Prairies (especially Saskatchewan) produces 93%.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Obviously, Canada is great at growing oats, but not so great at processing them. Most of them are exported as raw commodities. &lt;a href="https://oatcanada.com/">Oat Canada&lt;/a> gets its crops from Alberta, but only &lt;em>after&lt;/em> the oats have been shipped to a facility in the US or Europe and processed into a concentrated protein powder. That&amp;rsquo;s the Canadian way.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Something else I learned about Québécois grains: a few decades ago, nobody believed that quality bread wheat could be grown in Québec. The hot, dry summers of Western Canada produced hard spring wheat, which yielded the ideal flour for bread.&lt;/p>
&lt;div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
&lt;iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/HHT86JsCpRI" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video">&lt;/iframe>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>Just before the turn of the millennium, the move towards artisan bread was starting to take hold in Québec. Bakers from France arrived in droves, and had an excruciatingly hard time producing French breads locally with the strong flours (~14% protein) milled from hard spring wheat. A growing demand thus emerged for a type of wheat that didn&amp;rsquo;t interest the Western Canadian farmers.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>La Milanaise, which started out as a mixed farming business in &lt;a href="https://lamilanaise.com/en/history/">the 1970s&lt;/a> in the village of Milan in the Estrie region, rose up to the challenge of filling that void. With strong government support, La Milanaise pioneered the organic grain industry in Québec and nurtured the province&amp;rsquo;s wheat culture. Québec now dominates organic farming growth in Canada, and produces winter wheat with far more complex aromas than spring wheat.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>La Milanaise has become a leading &lt;em>processor&lt;/em> of organic grains in Canada, exporting grain products to the US, Europe and Latin America. It sources &amp;gt;=60% of its grain from Québec farmers, and only purchases out West what cannot be grown locally. (Obviously, agriculture is heavily subsidized and protected by &lt;em>le gouvernement du Québec&lt;/em>.) It&amp;rsquo;s hard to tell which La Milanaise grains are grown in Québec and which are from elsewhere.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Additionally, La Milanaise has joined hands with Québécois bakery chain Première Moisson to found another mill, &lt;a href="https://moulinsdesoulanges.com/language/en/home/">Les Moulins de Soulanges&lt;/a>, to develop specialty flours tailor-made to the needs of Québécois artisan bakers. Flours from La Milanaise are featured in Daniel Leader&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em>Local Breads&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;m not as keen on pre-milled flours as whole grains. But I did stop by Première Moisson (majority-owned by supermarket chain Metro since 2014) on Boulevard Lebourgneuf and got a WW buckwheat bread with Charlevoix hemp seeds. It was delicious and I felt fuckin' Canadian.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/arctic-maplemoon/202201091337a.jpg"
alt="Arctic Maplemoon"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>From Canada with love: Arctic Maplemoon, an oaty raisiny whole wheat bread.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>So I made a bread with La Milanaise grains:&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>whole wheat flour&lt;/td>
&lt;td>85%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>whole oat flour&lt;/td>
&lt;td>15%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>whole wheat levain&lt;/td>
&lt;td>45%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->water&lt;sup id="fnref:2">&lt;a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->&lt;/td>
&lt;td>95%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Grade A dark maple syrup (Escuminac)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>grey Guérande salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>raisins (&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->NaturellementBio&lt;sup id="fnref:3">&lt;a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">3&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>I did the usual 24-hour cold ferment.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The whole wheat flour milled from La Milanaise wheat berries is very soft, but not as &lt;em>rouge&lt;/em> as Turkey Red.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/arctic-maplemoon/202201091337c.jpg"
alt="Arctic Maplemoon"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The bread is very aromatic during and after baking. The crust smells like caramel, chocolate and roasted nuts. The crumb is light, open and soft.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/arctic-maplemoon/202201091338.jpg"
alt="Arctic Maplemoon"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>It tastes sweet and creamy, with some toasty wheatiness.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/arctic-maplemoon/202201091338c.jpg"
alt="Arctic Maplemoon"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Madame Benoît, a 20th-century Québécois food writer, once said:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;A recipe is only a theme, which an intelligent cook can play each time with a variation.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>I wholeheartedly agree with her.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/arctic-maplemoon/202201121944.jpg"
alt="Arctic Maplemoon"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Wholegrain rich sweet Hawaiian rolls served, using slight variations of the above recipe.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/arctic-maplemoon/202211190919.jpg"
alt="Arctic Maplemoon"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>La Milanaise whole wheat rolls, ready to go into the air fryer.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>2022/12/23 - Round out the year with &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt15351648/">Three Pines&lt;/a>&amp;rdquo;, a deliciously moreish crime drama set in a small Québec village.&lt;/p>
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>A few small millers in Canada sell directly to consumers.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>Just plain h₂o. I did not bring back any fancy &amp;ldquo;vortex structured water&amp;rdquo; from Québec.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:3" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>Avril Supermarché Santé&amp;rsquo;s private brand. Avril recently invested in its private lines, including Rolland Naturellement (French and Spanish wines), NaturellementBio (canned &amp;amp; dried goods), and Naturellement Gourmet (specialty products like gelato, balsamic vinegar and maple syrup).&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/section></content></item></channel></rss>