<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>coconut on HERESY LEVAIN</title><link>/tags/coconut/</link><description>Latest experiments in coconut from HERESY LEVAIN</description><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2023 HERESY LEVAIN 🍞 CC BY-NC-SA 4.0</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 22 Apr 2020 21:25:44 -0500</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/coconut/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Cosmic Coconut</title><link>/posts/cosmic-coconut/</link><pubDate>Wed, 22 Apr 2020 21:25:44 -0500</pubDate><guid>/posts/cosmic-coconut/</guid><description>A resilience bread inspired by the Caribbean &lt;em>pan de coco&lt;/em>.</description><content>&lt;p>The first time I learned about fermentation was in Puerto Rico in 2017, shortly after Christmas. I traveled to the island a few months after Hurricane Maria. A lot of businesses on the island were closed, and people were running out of everything &amp;ndash; much like everywhere in the world right now, as a result of the Covid lockdown.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Back in Viejo San Juan, I stumbled across a community event on sustainable agriculture called Agro + Cultura. I hung out there all day as probably the only &amp;ldquo;no hablo español&amp;rdquo; attendee, and fumbled my way through a few classes on canning taught by the &lt;a href="https://archive.ph/0J0Dq">Queer Kitchen Brigade&lt;/a>. It was there and then that I made &lt;em>kimchi&lt;/em> for the first time in my life, and learned about the difference between pickling and fermentation. It didn&amp;rsquo;t click with me, until my contacts introduced me to a local politician (who was formerly a very high-ranking official at the broadly powerful &lt;em>Banco Gubernamental de Fomento para Puerto Rico&lt;/em>, a &lt;a href="https://archive.ph/lxHU6">driving force&lt;/a> behind Puerto Rico&amp;rsquo;s debt crisis). In private, he bashed solar energy and dismissed local grassroots agricultural resilience movements as &amp;ldquo;inefficient and ineffective,&amp;rdquo; and said the island &amp;ndash; which imports ~90% of its food and raw materials &amp;ndash; was &amp;ldquo;better off left alone to big corporations.&amp;rdquo; That was a wake-up call for me.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>That&amp;rsquo;s how I got interested in fermentation, as a way to preserve food and build resilience. I grew up with food insecurity. Even though I&amp;rsquo;m fortunate enough to have not experienced scarcity since college, I worry I could again someday.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Stories about bread lines outside food pantries across the country make me feel tremendously grateful to have learned different methods of food preservation during the golden age of American farming.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Over the last few years, America&amp;rsquo;s agricultural abundance allowed me to indulge my curiosity, fortuitously at a time when commodity and consumer prices hit a new decade low. I was completely unaware that the world economy was going through a mild recession in 2019. I was able to fill up my pantry with 25-lb. bags of miscellaneous organic (pseudo)grains &amp;ndash; wheat, rye, durum, buckwheat, teff, amaranth, quinoa, corn, barley, oat, millet, sorghum, etc. &amp;ndash; at rock-bottom prices, just a few months before Covid. I remember Aldi was selling 5-lb. bags of all purpose flour for ~$1 back then (it costs $2.12 as of November 2022). With so much grains on hand, I made a lot of rejuvelac and built a sourdough starter from scratch. That was the beginning of my breadmaking journey.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Breadbaking is one of those almost hypnotic businesses, like a dance from some ancient ceremony. It leaves you filled with one of the world&amp;rsquo;s sweetest smells&amp;hellip; There is no chiropractic treatment, no Yoga exercise, no hour of meditation in a music-throbbing chapel, that will leave you emptier of bad thoughts than this homely ceremony of making bread.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>M.F.K. Fisher, &lt;em>The Art of Eating&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Like Fisher, &amp;ldquo;I came to believe that since nobody else dared feed me as I wished to be fed, I must do it myself, and with as much aplomb as I could muster.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This bread is inspired by the Caribbean &lt;em>pan de coco&lt;/em>, to remind myself of that shock moment in Puerto Rico &amp;ndash; resilience is independence.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>G.Y.O.G. = Grind Your Own Grains&lt;/p>
&lt;p>B.Y.O.B. = Bake Your own Bread&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>80% extraction wheat flour (Bolles - Ben Penner Farms, MN)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>75%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>whole einkorn flour (Jovial)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>25%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>rye levain&lt;/td>
&lt;td>40%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>homemade coconut milk&lt;/td>
&lt;td>90%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>coconut pulp (strained from coconut milk)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>30%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>dates &amp;amp; raisins&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>walnuts, toasted&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Autolyze the flour with coconut milk. Add the levain and salt. Perform 5 folds during a 5-hour warm bulk-fermentation. Incorporate the dried fruits and most of the coconut pulp during the lamination fold. Shape and coat completely in grated coconut. Proof in the fridge for 12 hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I made a few ginormous loaves of this bread and gave all but one away.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The caramelized coconut-covered crust makes my mouth water.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/cosmic-coconut/202004211326.jpg"
alt="Cosmic Coconut"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/cosmic-coconut/202004211451c.jpg"
alt="Cosmic Coconut"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/cosmic-coconut/202004211329.jpg"
alt="Cosmic Coconut"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The crumb is soft and creamy. It tastes a little tangy, but nicely balanced by the sweetness of dried fruits.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/cosmic-coconut/202004211458a.jpg"
alt="Cosmic Coconut"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/cosmic-coconut/202004211456c.jpg"
alt="Cosmic Coconut"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Cosmic Coconut, a resilience bread inspired by the Caribbean pan de coco.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Bake your own f*cking bread, because resilience is independence.&lt;/p></content></item></channel></rss>