<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>spiced syrup on HERESY LEVAIN</title><link>/tags/spiced-syrup/</link><description>Latest experiments in spiced syrup from HERESY LEVAIN</description><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2023 HERESY LEVAIN 🍞 CC BY-NC-SA 4.0</copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 13 Feb 2023 02:15:44 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/spiced-syrup/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>California Dreamin' #1: Joaquin Oro</title><link>/posts/california-dreamin-1/</link><pubDate>Mon, 13 Feb 2023 02:15:44 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/california-dreamin-1/</guid><description>[California Grain Adventure #1] Strawberry rosehip &lt;em>pain d&amp;rsquo;épices au levain&lt;/em>, made with freshly milled Joaquin Oro grown in the San Joaquin Valley of California. Gently sweetened with a homemade spice-infused syrup.</description><content>&lt;p>&lt;em>This is part 1 of my &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/california-grain-adventure/">California Grain Adventure&lt;/a>.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I first got to know California as an undergraduate student on the East Coast, during academic conference trips to the sun-baked campus of the University of California, Davis (UC Davis) where I met my besties; and later as a part-time L-Alien (or Angeleno).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If the rest of America were academic articles, then California would be something like blog posts. The former are often plodding and obtuse, and frequently more concerned with avoiding errors than trying to communicate incisive ideas; the latter may be fuzzy, loosely-defined, or outright mistaken, but tolerable so long as they introduce fresh ideas.&lt;/p>
&lt;div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
&lt;iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/wq-S8CIU7VA" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video">&lt;/iframe>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>To say California is unlike the other 49 states in the US is an understatement. Not just that the Golden State has waaaay more sculpted, sun-bronzed, rich techies with a higher propensity to consume expensive artisan coffees. To this day, I still feel a distinct difference whenever I go to California or do business in the state.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For example:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>California&amp;rsquo;s economy is massive, but two industries dominate popular imagination and exert impact on a global scale: Tech in Silicon Valley/San Francisco, and entertainment in Hollywood/Los Angeles. Far less than 1% of all new startups and movie stars actually break out every year, but those who do achieve exponential success.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>In a country of immigrants, California seems to be &lt;em>the&lt;/em> state of immigrants. Not just that California&amp;rsquo;s population is the most diverse in the US, with no race or ethnic group constituting a majority. About a century and a half ago, California was flooded with serial migrants who came from the East Coast and were willing to decamp once more in search of gold or fame. Does this make California the most American of all states?&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Thinking back, I realize California embodies more of the &amp;ldquo;top line&amp;rdquo; mindset while New York is dominated by the &amp;ldquo;bottom line&amp;rdquo; mindset. In California, venture capital and movie studios try to pick a few outsized winners that makes their losses irrelevant. New York is complicated, obviously finance-driven, and exemplified by the prevalence of insurance in particular.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Insurers apply the law of large numbers to predict the probability and cost of &amp;ldquo;tail events.&amp;rdquo; The insurance business is about collecting a steady stream of revenue (on the liabilities side) without making catastrophic mistakes that wipe out the assets, i.e. picking up nickels in front of a steamroller. Naturally, insurers spend 80% of their time on &amp;ldquo;the losers.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In contrast, venture capital focuses on maximizing &lt;a href="https://medium.com/@quantvc/power-laws-in-venture-capital-why-the-long-tail-matters-22e057c6fa34">fat tails&lt;/a>, by &amp;ldquo;investing in maybe 7 or 8 promising companies from which you think you can get a 10x return&amp;rdquo; (Peter Thiel). Successful VCs spend 80% of their time on a tiny handful of big &amp;ldquo;winners.&amp;rdquo; Their return curves look more like highly skewed power law distributions (&amp;ldquo;the 80/20 curve&amp;rdquo;).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Finding home runs and avoiding catastrophes are very different activities and require different mindsets. Maybe that distinction partly explains why California and New York feel so vastly different.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Subsequently, winner-take-all effects and blockbuster dynamics have continually permeated the Golden State.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="california-optimism">California optimism&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>For nearly a century, California offered ordinary people better lives than they could lead perhaps anywhere else in the world. Sunsets in California are always so singularly beautiful on TV and in movies. No doubt, California is the land of sunny optimism; the Conference Board&amp;rsquo;s California Consumer Confidence Index averaged 113 in the 5 years before Covid, hotter than national baselines.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>I think people who grew up in California have more tolerance for apocalyptic notions. However, mixed up with this tolerance for apocalyptic notions in which the world is going to end dramatically is this belief that the world can’t help but get better and better. It’s really hard for me to believe that everything doesn’t improve, because thinking like that was just so much a part of being in California.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Joan Didion&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Optimism is a valuable form of human capital. Just look at &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->Japan vs. China&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>People want optimism. They don&amp;rsquo;t want to learn that it&amp;rsquo;s almost impossible to make it, that few do, and that even worse it takes years of hard work and dedication and a ton of luck &amp;ndash; and that today even the most talented don&amp;rsquo;t always succeed.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Every now and then, you detect a faint strain of melancholy, a sort of &lt;em>ennui&lt;/em>, that permeates Californians' creative output. You hear it in &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=uU0BOyQRjWM">The Beach Boys&lt;/a> (a rock band instrumental in popularizing a particular California culture of sun, sand, and surfing in the 1960s) and &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=QOOiY0bgrlU">Red Hot Chili Peppers&lt;/a>; see it in &lt;a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt3783958/">&lt;em>La La Land&lt;/em>&lt;/a> (where Los Angeles in the winter and summer scenes looks identical) and &lt;a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt4687880/">&lt;em>Goliath&lt;/em>&lt;/a>; &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/california-books">read it&lt;/a> in Philip K. Dick, Joan Didion, Jack Kerouac, John Steinbeck, etc. What do people have to worry about in the land of sunny beaches and beautiful weather?&lt;/p>
&lt;div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
&lt;iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/w_zz0JNhujE" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video">&lt;/iframe>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>As a matter of fact, California&amp;rsquo;s net migration has been negative in the last two decades, losing about a million more people than it gained through migration. Instead of moving from Oklahoma to California (à la John Steinbeck&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em>The Grapes of Wrath&lt;/em>), traffic has been reversing the other way. This trend has become even more evident in the last few months; when rent is $4k-$5k, making six figures in an industry experiencing mass layoffs is not a comfy situation.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>While tech and entertainment are monstrous sectors with far-reaching impact (even reindeer herders in the arctic forests of Karelia watch Hollywood movies and use Instagram, for instance), altogether they generate only ~10% of the state&amp;rsquo;s GDP (though one could argue for a bigger share under different definitions). The two big blockbuster industries may not have that big of an impact on the daily lives of most Californians.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Maybe that helps to explain a bit of the melancholy in the culture &amp;ndash; a golden age for all has &lt;a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20220517070336/https://isteve.blogspot.com/2009/06/benjamin-schwarzs-laments-end-of.html">passed&lt;/a> and those who were once ahead have tried to lock in their gains.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>You can check out any time you like&lt;/p>
&lt;p>But you can never leave&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&amp;ndash; Eagles, &amp;ldquo;Hotel California&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Maybe the California Dream is more elusive than we believe.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Maybe nothing exemplifies this better than wheat, whose golden age ended ~130 years ago.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="california-wheat">California wheat&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Today, California is a leading producer in &lt;a href="https://asmith.ucdavis.edu/news/we-grow-that">pretty much everything&lt;/a> except for, curiously, the major grains like wheat and corn.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Wheat was brought to California from Mexico; it was first grown by padres during the &amp;ldquo;mission period&amp;rdquo; in the 18th century and later by settlers.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>California became the nation&amp;rsquo;s second largest wheat producer (after Minnesota) in the second half of the 19th century, thanks to the Gold Rush and the associated increased demand for food. Wheat production in California hit a peak in the late 1880s; soon thereafter, it declined as rapidly as it rose, mainly due to soil exhaustion and low farm prices.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>With increasing acreage of irrigated land and better transportation to markets in the eastern US, California began a massive agricultural shift &amp;ndash; diversifying away from grains and towards the more lucrative &lt;a href="https://www.ams.usda.gov/services/grants/scbgp/specialty-crop">specialty crops&lt;/a> like vegetables, fruit, and nuts.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>By 1913, California&amp;rsquo;s wheat-planting area had shrunk to 380,000 acres (from some 3 million acres just three decades earlier). Throughout the 20th century, the wheat acreage fluctuated widely, ranging from a minimum of 270,000 acres in 1966 to a maximum of 1,345,000 acres in 1981. In recent years, the wheat acreage has stabilized somewhat, averaging about half a million acres since the year &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->2000&lt;sup id="fnref:2">&lt;a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->; wheat production averages ~40 million bushels annually. (In comparison, Kansas plants ~7 million acres of wheat annually on average and produces over 300 million bushels.)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Wheat didn&amp;rsquo;t disappear from California; it still is an important rotational crop for many growers, and California&amp;rsquo;s wheat industry is a bit unique.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-1/california-wheat-map.png"
alt="California wheat-producing areas"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>California wheat-producing areas&lt;/p>&lt;p>Source: &lt;a href="http://californiawheat.org/california-wheat/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">California Wheat Commission&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>While Kansas specializes in &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/hard-red-winter-wheat/">hard red winter wheat&lt;/a>, North Dakota in &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/hard-red-spring-wheat/">hard red spring wheat&lt;/a> and durum, and Washington in &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/soft-white-winter-wheat/">soft white wheat&lt;/a>, California grows all of the US wheat classes except soft red, i.e. you can find hard red, hard white, soft white, and durum wheat grown across the state. The two main types of wheat grown in California are &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->hard red winter wheat&lt;sup id="fnref:3">&lt;a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">3&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --> and durum wheat, mainly used for milling.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Given the vast expanse of the state, most of California&amp;rsquo;s wheat production is localized in specific regions. The majority of wheat is grown in the San Joaquin Valley, where Fresno, Kern, Kings and Tulare counties dominate production. (Yolo County in the Sacramento Valley completes the list of the top 5 counties with the largest area harvested.) Eternal sunshine, coupled with a warm and dry climate, produces big plump kernels with low moisture content, consistent kernel size distribution, and high test weight.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-1/TR-vs-Joaquin-Oro.jpg"
alt="Tukey Red (Kansas) vs. Joaquin Oro (California)"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Kernel size comparison: Tukey Red (grown in Kansas) vs. Joaquin Oro (grown in California)&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>It&amp;rsquo;s no surprise that California&amp;rsquo;s wheat yield has been among the highest in the nation. California also happens to have the largest milling capacity in the US, thanks to having the most mills in one state.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Artisan bakers and organic farmers are leading the revival of whole grains and local grain economies. While wheat breeding programs often focus on refined flour markets, UC Davis recently started an organic wheat breeding program to focus on unique wheat varieties for artisan breadmaking and local grain markets. The awesome team (a shout-out to Claudia Carter and Teng Vang) at the California Wheat Commission &amp;ndash; the coolest wheat commission in the country, by the way &amp;ndash; sent me a few of such varieties to experiment with.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-1/cwc-wheats.jpg"
alt="California wheat: Joaquin Oro (HRSW), Sonora Blanca (SWWW), and Desert Gold (durum)."/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>California wheat: Joaquin Oro (HRSW), Sonora Blanca (SWWW), and Desert Gold (durum).&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>The first California-grown wheat that I experimented with was &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/breadford-von-regrainton">Glenn&lt;/a>, a modern hard red spring variety grown by Kenter Canyon Farms along the south side of the Santa Clara River.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This week, I got to play with &lt;strong>Joaquin Oro&lt;/strong>, another California-grown hard red spring wheat. It&amp;rsquo;s a modern cultivar selected from the OG Joaquin variety for morphological, agronomic and quality traits; bred and developed by WestBred to thrive in the wheat-growing areas of the San Joaquin Valley; and released by UC Davis in 2011. Protein content ~14%.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Historically, Joaquin Oro has been the highest-quality bread wheat variety grown in California. It&amp;rsquo;s also one of the highest-rated whole wheat flours by the California Wheat Commission test lab.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-1/joaquin-oro-berries.jpg"
alt="Joaquin Oro wheat berries, from California."/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Plump and vibrant Joaquin Oro wheat berries, grown in the San Joaquin Valley of California.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>This Joaquin Oro was grown by Jon Eck of Eck Farms in Merced County, California. Jon&amp;rsquo;s parents are lifelong farmers, growing primarily almonds and sweet potatoes &amp;ndash; two of the traditional cash crops in the San Joaquin Valley. Jon decided to try growing grain as a rotational crop at the suggestion of a baker friend. John tells of his experience and learning on the excellent &lt;a href="https://www.thesourdoughpodcast.com/episodes/2021/9/27/jon-eck-california-wheat-grower">Sourdough Podcast&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The first thing I noticed with Joaquin Oro was how easily the wheat berries milled to a fine texture on the first run, on a countertop electric WonderMill set to Bread Flour.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The wholegrain Joaquin Oro flour has a finer, smoother texture (and visibly smaller bran particle size) than freshly milled Turkey Red &amp;ndash; and almost boasts of a Unifine feel.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Maybe this is what a French miller would classify as &lt;em>blé tendre&lt;/em> (&amp;ldquo;soft wheat&amp;rdquo;), a bread wheat that shows little &lt;em>résistance&lt;/em> to milling (i.e. requires less force than &lt;em>le blé résistant&lt;/em> to shear the starchy endosperm of the grain).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Despite being categorized as a &amp;ldquo;hard&amp;rdquo; wheat in the US commercial wheat classification system due to its high protein content, Joaquin Oro actually mills quite easily &amp;ndash; like a low-protein wheat. I am amazed.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-1/joaquin-oro-milled.jpg"
alt="Freshly milled Joaquin Oro"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Freshly milled Joaquin Oro.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>My first experiment with Joaquin Oro is inspired by my &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/dulce-locura/">&lt;em>pain d&amp;rsquo;épices au levain&lt;/em>&lt;/a>, in light of the upcoming Valentine&amp;rsquo;s Day. It incorporates strawberries, rosehips, spiced syrup, and dark chocolate. 🌹🍓🍫&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I decided to bolt the freshly milled Joaquin Oro to remove some of the coarsest bran bits and midds, to lighten the load a bit on the gluten in the flour, which shall hold together a boatloat of add-ins. The extracted bits will be used, instead of flour, to dust the workbench and the dough later, so nothing is wasted.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Joaquin Oro, 88% extraction (Eck Farms, CA)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>400g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>strawberry rosehip purée (homemade)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>36%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>145g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;em>sirop d&amp;rsquo;épices&lt;/em> (55% in autolyse + 25% in &lt;em>bassinage&lt;/em>)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>80%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>320g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Joaquin Oro whole wheat levain&lt;/td>
&lt;td>40%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>160g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sea salt (Gustus Vitae, CA)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>8g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>olive oil (Awake - Brightland, CA)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>20g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>dark chocolate, chopped (74% Guatamala Lachuá - Mutari Chocolate, CA)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>20%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>80g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Did you know California is America&amp;rsquo;s largest producer of strawberries? And wild rose (&lt;em>Rosa californica&lt;/em>) grows throughout the coast and foothills of the state?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you are a forager and happen to have collected some wild rosehips and strawberries from Nature&amp;rsquo;s grocery store, you are a hell of &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->a lucky bastard&lt;sup id="fnref:4">&lt;a href="#fn:4" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">4&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->. Otherwise, grab some dried rosehips and good-tasting strawberries from somewhere.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>To make the strawberry rosehip purée 🍓🌹 at home: Boil the rosehips in just enough water until soft; push the pulp through a fine-mesh sieve to remove the seeds and irritating hairs; run the resulting pulp and juice with strawberries (fresh or frozen) in a blender into a smooth purée. Use as much rosehips or strawberries as you like.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Pro tip: Make your own &lt;em>sirop d&amp;rsquo;épices&lt;/em> (spiced syrup), too.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Then proceed as documented in the &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/dulce-locura/">&lt;em>pain d&amp;rsquo;épices au levain&lt;/em>&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>TL;DR, give the dough an overnight bulk fermentation in the fridge, after a series of coil-folds in the initial 4.5 hours; shape; final proof 3-4 hours; bake off.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-1/20230212_195754.jpg"
alt="Pain d&amp;#39;épices au levain, made with freshly milled Joaquin Oro."/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>Pain d&amp;rsquo;épices au levain&lt;/em>, made with freshly milled Joaquin Oro.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Joaquin Oro delivers a nuanced flavor profile. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem to have as much bitterness as many red wheat varieties; instead it&amp;rsquo;s imbued with nutty, malty notes. This pairs exquisitely with the rich fruitiness and faint tartness of rosehips and strawberries. Homemade &lt;em>sirop d&amp;rsquo;épices&lt;/em> cranks up the sweetness and adds a wonderful touch of spice notes.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Joaquin Oro also performs excellently in baking. The dough felt quite elastic during the initial fermentation, and became very pillowy and delicate after overnight cold retard; it showed a pretty decent rise in the oven.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/california-dreamin-1/20230212_195908.jpg"
alt="Pain d&amp;#39;épices au levain, made with freshly milled Joaquin Oro."/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>Pain d&amp;rsquo;épices au levain&lt;/em>, made with freshly milled Joaquin Oro.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The crust of this bread turned out crisp and thin; the crumb tender and springy.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The chewy texture reminded me of a traditional stottie cake in Northumberland, northern England. Irresistible.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Go make this bread and share with your sweetheart, Valentine&amp;rsquo;s Day or not, and enjoy it with a good slather of chocolate cheese fudge &amp;ndash; while everyone is getting worked up about Joe Rogan again or Kansas City Chiefs winning another Super Bowl after being underdogs for half a century.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>&lt;em>This is part 1 of my &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/california-grain-adventure/">California Grain Adventure&lt;/a>. If you enjoyed it, why not check out more &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/archives/">breadstories&lt;/a> or spread the word?&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>The current &lt;a href="https://www3.nhk.or.jp/nhkworld/en/news/20230131_12/">unemployment rate in Japan&lt;/a> is 2.5%. Japanese millennials get to enjoy a fairly tight labor market, which means they ought to choose which company to work for. But few of them have an interest in switching employers or jobs, because they rank perfect stability above high wages. This risk aversion is usually attributed to lingering fears of the previous downturn. The country that lost a decade &amp;ndash; or two &amp;ndash; has fostered a generation of youth highly averse to risk-taking. Optimism is &lt;a href="https://archive.is/vqIPO">in very short supply&lt;/a> in Japan. On the other hand, surveys show the Chinese are much more optimistic about the future. Take Cixin Liu&amp;rsquo;s sci-fi series, &lt;em>Three Body Problem&lt;/em>, for an example. The novel is driven by a fundamentally optimistic vision: It asks why aliens should not be 10,000x more advanced than humans, instead of portraying a typical alien civilization that&amp;rsquo;s only 50%-70% more advanced than humans.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>USDA/NASS historical data.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:3" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>Most varieties grown in California are genetically spring wheat (planted in the spring and harvested in late summer or early fall). However, since the majority of California wheat-growing regions have very mild winters, spring wheat can be sown in the fall or early winter like winter wheat. Wheat market classifications are typically based on the season of production rather than growth habit, which is why California&amp;rsquo;s red wheat production is referred to as hard red winter wheat.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:4" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>According to an academic study titled &amp;ldquo;Morphological and Chemical Characteristics of Fruits of Selected Rosa sp,&amp;rdquo; &lt;em>R. californica&lt;/em> contains 863 mg vitamin C per 100 g of fruit. 4 other species were studied: &lt;em>R. villosa&lt;/em> (706 mg), &lt;em>R. rugosa&lt;/em> (974 mg), &lt;em>R. spinosissima&lt;/em> (845 mg), and &lt;em>R. × damascena&lt;/em> (932 mg). Google claims oranges provide 53 mg vitamin C per 100 g. On average, rosehips tend to have at least an order of magnitude more vitamin C then oranges; &lt;em>R. californica&lt;/em> has about 16x more.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:4" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/section></content></item><item><title>Dulce Locura</title><link>/posts/dulce-locura/</link><pubDate>Thu, 08 Dec 2022 21:39:07 -0600</pubDate><guid>/posts/dulce-locura/</guid><description>A sweet potato &lt;em>pain d&amp;rsquo;épices&lt;/em>, made in an un-French way. Gently sweetened by a homemade spice-infused simple syrup. The crumb was tender and springy, the sweetish flavor in harmony with the chocolate and spices; the crust was crispy and fabulous. Irresistible and toothsome.</description><content>&lt;p>The US is still a superlulz &lt;a href="https://www.investopedia.com/terms/j/jit.asp">JIT&lt;/a> la la land. One bullet is &lt;a href="https://www.npr.org/2022/12/04/1140647869/power-substations-north-carolina-gunfire-vandalism">all it takes&lt;/a> to shut down the power grid for days&amp;hellip;possibly weeks. It reminded me of Juan Zarate&amp;rsquo;s memoir, &lt;em>Treasury&amp;rsquo;s War.&lt;/em> Unlike Europe, Uncle Sam is blessed with extraordinary energy abundance. Still, it feels like a first-world country with third-world infrastructure. As much as it sucks for the people affected, we are all living in an age of energy vulnerability.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I have been to various parts of North freakin' Carolina a number of times. Charlotte, like any other financial center, is the most boring. The Research Triangle (Raleigh, Durham, and Chapel Hill) in the heart of Piedmont is more fun. Of course, nothing beats Asheville &amp;ndash; a hipster mecca. Best memories are licking my fingers after eating N&amp;rsquo;Asheville &amp;ldquo;Mount St. Hell No&amp;rdquo; spicy crispy fried chicken at &lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=JE5SyITVOTE">Rocky&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a>, and getting caught in a rainstorm in Wilmington on the riverwalk and roaming the beaches like a drowned rat.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It wasn&amp;rsquo;t until recently that I learned North Carolina is the #1 producer of sweet potatoes in the US.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Last week I stumbled across a &lt;a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/Breadit/comments/udoyzj/pain_depices_au_levain_naturally_leavened_french/">reddit&lt;/a> on &lt;em>pain d&amp;rsquo;épices au levain&lt;/em>, got sidetracked, and went down a rabbit hole. I still have a ton of sweet potatoes left over from the Gobble Gobble Day. Why not create a &lt;em>pain d&amp;rsquo;épices&lt;/em> of my own, you know, heresy style? Maybe with a North Carolina character? Forgive me, France.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="homemade-spiced-syrup">Homemade spiced syrup&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>First off, I made a simple &lt;em>sirop d&amp;rsquo;épices&lt;/em> in the Instant Pot:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>60g aged orange peels&lt;/li>
&lt;li>30g fresh ginger&lt;/li>
&lt;li>1 whole star anise&lt;/li>
&lt;li>1 piece 4&amp;quot; cinnamon stick&lt;/li>
&lt;li>5 cloves&lt;/li>
&lt;li>2 allspice berries&lt;/li>
&lt;li>10 cardamom seeds&lt;/li>
&lt;li>200g sugar&lt;/li>
&lt;li>200g raisin water (soak 150g raisins in 250g water for a few hours, and squeeze out the liquid)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>200g h₂o&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Pressure-cooked for 1 minute, followed by 30 minutes of natural release. Then I left it overnight, to allow the aromatics to meld together further. The sweet orangey aroma wafted through the house. Next morning, I strained the whole mixture through a through a fine-mesh sieve, and filled up 2 big jars with the thin brown goodness.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This homemade syrup packs quite a punch with its fragrant combination of spices. Delightfully sweet with a deep orange flavor, and chock full of bold, brisk notes.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;code>Pro tip&lt;/code>: Instead of throwing away the leftover aromatic pulp from straining, blend it finely into a sweet fruit paste. Use it as a delicious spread on toasts, or thin it a little and use as a marinade/sauce/glaze in savory dishes.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="tar-heel-blend">Tar Heel Blend&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>I decided to mix up my own Tar Heel Blend wheat flour, instead of using my go-to workhorse Turkey Red.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>60% Appalachian White (Fish Pond Branch Farms, NC): a HWWW with a mild creamy taste and ~12% protein&lt;/li>
&lt;li>20% NuEast (Fish Pond Branch Farms, NC): a HRWW with a delicate nutty flavor and ~10% protein&lt;/li>
&lt;li>20% Sungold spelt (Red Tail Grains, NC): a modern cultivar of spelt with ~12% protein&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Much like Missouri, the eastern US is not hospitable to growing bread wheat, because the area&amp;rsquo;s humidity increases the incidence of disease in the fields and affects yield and quality of the grain. Historically, North Carolina has grown almost exclusively soft wheats (lower protein, better for crackers, biscuits, etc). But, in response to a growing demand from the resurgence of artisan bakeries, two modern high-yielding cultivars of hard winter wheat, Appalachian White and NuEast, were bred by NC State researchers and &lt;a href="https://www.ars.usda.gov/news-events/news/research-news/2009/ars-releases-first-hard-winter-wheat-varieties-for-eastern-us-production/">released in 2009&lt;/a> to farmers as high-quality bread wheats suited for production in the Carolinas.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="levain">Levain&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>Kick the levain into high gear with 2 feedings, 10 hours apart:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Build #1:&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>stiff WW starter&lt;/td>
&lt;td>25%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>WW flour (freshly milled Tar Heel Blend)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>h₂o&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Build #2:&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>build #1&lt;/td>
&lt;td>225%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>WW flour (freshly milled Tar Heel Blend)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>h₂o&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>I let it ferment (for ~18 hours at 65F) until it got loose and bubbly.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="final-dough">Final dough&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>While the levain is fermenting, cook the sweet potatoes.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you want your sweet potatoes sweeter, cook them &lt;a href="https://www.seriouseats.com/the-best-mashed-sweet-potatoes-recipe">low and slow&lt;/a>, so that the enzyme will have more time to break down more starch and convert it to more maltose.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I heated a pot of plain water in an Instant Pot to ~160F, and threw a few whole Carolina Ruby sweet potatoes directly into it. I covered up the pot, and let the spuds rest in the warm water bath overnight. You want to hold the sweet spuds in that 135F-170F (57C-77C) sweet spot for an extended period of time, to activate their endogenous enzymes that bring out their natural sweetness. After a few hours, you can take the sweet spuds out of the water bath, roast and mash them.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Tar Heel Blend, 85% extraction&lt;/td>
&lt;td>80%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>whole rye flour (Wren&amp;rsquo;s Abruzzi rye - Carolina Ground, NC)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>20%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>roasted sweet potatoes, mashed (Carolina Ruby)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>37.5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;em>sirop d&amp;rsquo;épices&lt;/em> (50% in autolyse + 25% &lt;em>eau de bassinage&lt;/em>)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>75%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>ripe levain&lt;/td>
&lt;td>42.5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sea salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1.5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>dark chocolate, chopped (80% Patanemo - Escazú Chocolates, NC)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>12%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>I squished up the flour with 1/2 of the spiced syrupy water and the cooled sweet potato, and autolyzed for 2 hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>After the autolyse, I squeezed all of the levain into the dough, while adding 1/2 of the remaining sweet water in several increments. Gave it a few rounds of slap &amp;amp; fold until it reached a semi-homogeneous texture, to make sure everything was evenly incorproated.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>After a 20-minute rest, I squished in the salt and the rest of the sweet water. The dough looked and felt like a sticky mess.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I did a coil-fold every 20 minutes for the first hour.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>At the 2h mark, I added the chocolate pieces, and gave the dough another coil-fold so that all of the chocolate bits were completely enveloped.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I did two more coil-folds at the 3h and 4h marks, respectively, to make sure the chocolate goodies were totally distributed throughout the dough.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The dough started to feel puffy. I decided to stop turning it, and let it ferment, unmolested, in the sunroom overnight (~43F).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Next morning, the dough had doubled in volume. I let it warm up on the kitchen counter for 2 hours. Then I shaped it into a boule and placed it in a proofing bowl, seam-side down.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>When the surface of the dough reached ~60F, I dumped it out onto a baking tray lined with parchment paper, and baked it in the toaster oven. 350F for the first 20 minutes, and 325F for 20 more minutes.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I let the bread cool for 4 hours before slicing.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The bread surrounding the little nuggets of chocolate was not bland at all! It was ever so gently sweetened by the simple syrup, like everything was magically pulled together.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The crumb was tender and springy, the sweetish flavor in harmony with the chocolate and spices; the crust was crispy and fabulous. Another winner for my repertoire!&lt;/p></content></item></channel></rss>