<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>sweet potato on HERESY LEVAIN</title><link>/tags/sweet-potato/</link><description>Latest experiments in sweet potato from HERESY LEVAIN</description><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2023 HERESY LEVAIN 🍞 CC BY-NC-SA 4.0</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 08 Dec 2022 21:39:07 -0600</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/sweet-potato/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Dulce Locura</title><link>/posts/dulce-locura/</link><pubDate>Thu, 08 Dec 2022 21:39:07 -0600</pubDate><guid>/posts/dulce-locura/</guid><description>A sweet potato &lt;em>pain d&amp;rsquo;épices&lt;/em>, made in an un-French way. Gently sweetened by a homemade spice-infused simple syrup. The crumb was tender and springy, the sweetish flavor in harmony with the chocolate and spices; the crust was crispy and fabulous. Irresistible and toothsome.</description><content>&lt;p>The US is still a superlulz &lt;a href="https://www.investopedia.com/terms/j/jit.asp">JIT&lt;/a> la la land. One bullet is &lt;a href="https://www.npr.org/2022/12/04/1140647869/power-substations-north-carolina-gunfire-vandalism">all it takes&lt;/a> to shut down the power grid for days&amp;hellip;possibly weeks. It reminded me of Juan Zarate&amp;rsquo;s memoir, &lt;em>Treasury&amp;rsquo;s War.&lt;/em> Unlike Europe, Uncle Sam is blessed with extraordinary energy abundance. Still, it feels like a first-world country with third-world infrastructure. As much as it sucks for the people affected, we are all living in an age of energy vulnerability.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I have been to various parts of North freakin' Carolina a number of times. Charlotte, like any other financial center, is the most boring. The Research Triangle (Raleigh, Durham, and Chapel Hill) in the heart of Piedmont is more fun. Of course, nothing beats Asheville &amp;ndash; a hipster mecca. Best memories are licking my fingers after eating N&amp;rsquo;Asheville &amp;ldquo;Mount St. Hell No&amp;rdquo; spicy crispy fried chicken at &lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=JE5SyITVOTE">Rocky&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a>, and getting caught in a rainstorm in Wilmington on the riverwalk and roaming the beaches like a drowned rat.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It wasn&amp;rsquo;t until recently that I learned North Carolina is the #1 producer of sweet potatoes in the US.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Last week I stumbled across a &lt;a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/Breadit/comments/udoyzj/pain_depices_au_levain_naturally_leavened_french/">reddit&lt;/a> on &lt;em>pain d&amp;rsquo;épices au levain&lt;/em>, got sidetracked, and went down a rabbit hole. I still have a ton of sweet potatoes left over from the Gobble Gobble Day. Why not create a &lt;em>pain d&amp;rsquo;épices&lt;/em> of my own, you know, heresy style? Maybe with a North Carolina character? Forgive me, France.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="homemade-spiced-syrup">Homemade spiced syrup&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>First off, I made a simple &lt;em>sirop d&amp;rsquo;épices&lt;/em> in the Instant Pot:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>60g aged orange peels&lt;/li>
&lt;li>30g fresh ginger&lt;/li>
&lt;li>1 whole star anise&lt;/li>
&lt;li>1 piece 4&amp;quot; cinnamon stick&lt;/li>
&lt;li>5 cloves&lt;/li>
&lt;li>2 allspice berries&lt;/li>
&lt;li>10 cardamom seeds&lt;/li>
&lt;li>200g sugar&lt;/li>
&lt;li>200g raisin water (soak 150g raisins in 250g water for a few hours, and squeeze out the liquid)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>200g h₂o&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Pressure-cooked for 1 minute, followed by 30 minutes of natural release. Then I left it overnight, to allow the aromatics to meld together further. The sweet orangey aroma wafted through the house. Next morning, I strained the whole mixture through a through a fine-mesh sieve, and filled up 2 big jars with the thin brown goodness.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This homemade syrup packs quite a punch with its fragrant combination of spices. Delightfully sweet with a deep orange flavor, and chock full of bold, brisk notes.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;code>Pro tip&lt;/code>: Instead of throwing away the leftover aromatic pulp from straining, blend it finely into a sweet fruit paste. Use it as a delicious spread on toasts, or thin it a little and use as a marinade/sauce/glaze in savory dishes.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="tar-heel-blend">Tar Heel Blend&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>I decided to mix up my own Tar Heel Blend wheat flour, instead of using my go-to workhorse Turkey Red.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>60% Appalachian White (Fish Pond Branch Farms, NC): a HWWW with a mild creamy taste and ~12% protein&lt;/li>
&lt;li>20% NuEast (Fish Pond Branch Farms, NC): a HRWW with a delicate nutty flavor and ~10% protein&lt;/li>
&lt;li>20% Sungold spelt (Red Tail Grains, NC): a modern cultivar of spelt with ~12% protein&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Much like Missouri, the eastern US is not hospitable to growing bread wheat, because the area&amp;rsquo;s humidity increases the incidence of disease in the fields and affects yield and quality of the grain. Historically, North Carolina has grown almost exclusively soft wheats (lower protein, better for crackers, biscuits, etc). But, in response to a growing demand from the resurgence of artisan bakeries, two modern high-yielding cultivars of hard winter wheat, Appalachian White and NuEast, were bred by NC State researchers and &lt;a href="https://www.ars.usda.gov/news-events/news/research-news/2009/ars-releases-first-hard-winter-wheat-varieties-for-eastern-us-production/">released in 2009&lt;/a> to farmers as high-quality bread wheats suited for production in the Carolinas.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="levain">Levain&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>Kick the levain into high gear with 2 feedings, 10 hours apart:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Build #1:&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>stiff WW starter&lt;/td>
&lt;td>25%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>WW flour (freshly milled Tar Heel Blend)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>h₂o&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Build #2:&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>build #1&lt;/td>
&lt;td>225%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>WW flour (freshly milled Tar Heel Blend)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>h₂o&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>I let it ferment (for ~18 hours at 65F) until it got loose and bubbly.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="final-dough">Final dough&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>While the levain is fermenting, cook the sweet potatoes.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you want your sweet potatoes sweeter, cook them &lt;a href="https://www.seriouseats.com/the-best-mashed-sweet-potatoes-recipe">low and slow&lt;/a>, so that the enzyme will have more time to break down more starch and convert it to more maltose.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I heated a pot of plain water in an Instant Pot to ~160F, and threw a few whole Carolina Ruby sweet potatoes directly into it. I covered up the pot, and let the spuds rest in the warm water bath overnight. You want to hold the sweet spuds in that 135F-170F (57C-77C) sweet spot for an extended period of time, to activate their endogenous enzymes that bring out their natural sweetness. After a few hours, you can take the sweet spuds out of the water bath, roast and mash them.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Tar Heel Blend, 85% extraction&lt;/td>
&lt;td>80%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>whole rye flour (Wren&amp;rsquo;s Abruzzi rye - Carolina Ground, NC)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>20%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>roasted sweet potatoes, mashed (Carolina Ruby)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>37.5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;em>sirop d&amp;rsquo;épices&lt;/em> (50% in autolyse + 25% &lt;em>eau de bassinage&lt;/em>)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>75%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>ripe levain&lt;/td>
&lt;td>42.5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sea salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1.5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>dark chocolate, chopped (80% Patanemo - Escazú Chocolates, NC)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>12%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>I squished up the flour with 1/2 of the spiced syrupy water and the cooled sweet potato, and autolyzed for 2 hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>After the autolyse, I squeezed all of the levain into the dough, while adding 1/2 of the remaining sweet water in several increments. Gave it a few rounds of slap &amp;amp; fold until it reached a semi-homogeneous texture, to make sure everything was evenly incorproated.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>After a 20-minute rest, I squished in the salt and the rest of the sweet water. The dough looked and felt like a sticky mess.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I did a coil-fold every 20 minutes for the first hour.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>At the 2h mark, I added the chocolate pieces, and gave the dough another coil-fold so that all of the chocolate bits were completely enveloped.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I did two more coil-folds at the 3h and 4h marks, respectively, to make sure the chocolate goodies were totally distributed throughout the dough.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The dough started to feel puffy. I decided to stop turning it, and let it ferment, unmolested, in the sunroom overnight (~43F).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Next morning, the dough had doubled in volume. I let it warm up on the kitchen counter for 2 hours. Then I shaped it into a boule and placed it in a proofing bowl, seam-side down.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>When the surface of the dough reached ~60F, I dumped it out onto a baking tray lined with parchment paper, and baked it in the toaster oven. 350F for the first 20 minutes, and 325F for 20 more minutes.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I let the bread cool for 4 hours before slicing.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The bread surrounding the little nuggets of chocolate was not bland at all! It was ever so gently sweetened by the simple syrup, like everything was magically pulled together.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The crumb was tender and springy, the sweetish flavor in harmony with the chocolate and spices; the crust was crispy and fabulous. Another winner for my repertoire!&lt;/p></content></item></channel></rss>