<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>wisconsin n2 on HERESY LEVAIN</title><link>/tags/wisconsin-n2/</link><description>Latest experiments in wisconsin n2 from HERESY LEVAIN</description><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2023 HERESY LEVAIN 🍞 CC BY-NC-SA 4.0</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 19 Jun 2022 19:32:00 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/wisconsin-n2/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Kornerstone</title><link>/posts/kornerstone/</link><pubDate>Sun, 19 Jun 2022 19:32:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>/posts/kornerstone/</guid><description>An old-school Jewish deli rye, made with a hefty amount of single-grind wholegrain Danko rye flour and two kinds of heritage wheat flours. Infused with caramelized onions, spent brewer&amp;rsquo;s grains, and poppy seeds.</description><content>&lt;p>Charles Bukowski&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em>Ham on Rye&lt;/em> is one of my favorite books. I consider it one of his best works and surely one of the greatest novels in all literature.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A ham on rye sandwich is about the simplest thing an American can eat. Ditto Bukowski&amp;rsquo;s writings are as simple as you get.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The leading rye-producing states in the US are the Dakotas, Nebraska, Minnesota, and Georgia. &amp;lt;50% of the rye grown in the US is harvested for grain, with the rest used as pasture/hay or as a cover crop. ~50% of the amount harvested for grain is fed to livestock or exported, and the remainder is used for distilling, food, and seed. In the Midwest, rye is primarily grown for grain, but occasionally for hay/pasture.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For generations, ham on rye was the proletarian sandwich of choice in the Midwest (pastrami on rye in New York). Rye bread was part of the sacred Midwestern German-American trinity: sauerkraut, dill pickles and chewy rye with caraway seeds. Mothers in America made sandwiches for their kids to take to school, and a ham on rye was what kids would eat. It&amp;rsquo;s boring, but flavorful and filling.&lt;/p>
&lt;div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
&lt;iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/SPkZbJAP7Zc" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video">&lt;/iframe>
&lt;/div>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;Who the hell invented the sandwich? They should write a book about him.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>a fat guy at The Golden Horn in the movie &lt;em>&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SPkZbJAP7Zc">Barfly&lt;/a>&lt;/em> (1987)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;Hamming it up&amp;rdquo; means to overdo something, especially in acting. Bukowski&amp;rsquo;s book has little to do with the sandwich. I interpret the &amp;ldquo;ham&amp;rdquo; as a metaphor for the neon (pretense, not kosher), which he contrasted with the plain humble staple &amp;ldquo;rye,&amp;rdquo; to squeeze all of the pretense out of his life.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="the-rye-pyramid">The rye pyramid&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>In my mind, there are generally 3 categories of rye breads, based on the percentage of rye they have.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Brick ryes&lt;/strong> (&amp;gt;=66% rye): these breads are dense and brick-like; made completely or mostly from rye (rye flour, soaked rye, or cracked rye); leavened with rye levain; very sticky, must be mixed with a paddle; soft, despite the lack of wheat flour.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;em>walliserbrot&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;em>roggenbrot&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;em>gersterbrot&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;em>vollkornbrot&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;em>pumpernickel&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;em>borodinsky&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;em>rugbrød&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;em>rupjmaize&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;em>ruisleipä&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Intermediate ryes&lt;/strong> (30%-65% rye): these breads have a solid backbone of wheat, with varying degrees of rye, making them something akin to farmers' breads but with more rye and less wheat; they are distinctly chewy and flavorful.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;em>kornbroyt&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;em>pain de seigle&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;em>pain de méteil&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Rye-flavored breads&lt;/strong> (&amp;lt;30% rye): the bulk of the flour in these breads is wheat; the wheat provides structure, while the rye adds flavor.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;em>landbrot&lt;/em> (country bread)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;em>bauernbrot&lt;/em> (farmer&amp;rsquo;s bread)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>In this category, there is a sub-group of enriched, flavored ryes (usually &amp;lt;15% rye) that became quite popular in America in the last century or so:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>American &lt;em>pumpernickel&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Jewish deli rye&lt;/li>
&lt;li>marbled rye (the combination of American &lt;em>pumpernickel&lt;/em> and Jewish deli rye)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>onion rye&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>There is another sub-group of lean ryes (&amp;lt;10%) such as the San Francisco Sourdough that add rye for some rustic nuance but I don&amp;rsquo;t consider them to be rye breads.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="the-american-bastardization-of-rye">The American bastardization of rye&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>As a matter of fact, the so-called Jewish rye bread found in a contemporary Jewish bakery or delicatessen is &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/attack-of-the-ryeclops">an American invention&lt;/a> &amp;ndash; an American bastardization of a European rye. It&amp;rsquo;s a light, mild rye loaf made with a large amount of wheat flour and seasoned with caraway seeds, lacking the intensity of Minsk rye and Bavarian rye. It was popularized by Jewish delicatessens, but it&amp;rsquo;s not specific to the Jewish tradition, unlike &lt;em>challah&lt;/em> or &lt;em>matzah&lt;/em>. IMO, it&amp;rsquo;s as Jewish as General Tso&amp;rsquo;s chicken is Chinese.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Rye is the main cereal crop in those areas of Eastern Europe most densely populated by Jews and was correspondingly cheap, especially compared with wheat. Rye has been a staple ingredient of vodkas for centuries.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Over there, the most common type of rye bread &amp;ndash; the one with the highest proportion of rye &amp;ndash; was called &lt;em>razeve broyt&lt;/em>, literally &amp;ldquo;black bread.&amp;rdquo; It was usually prepared at home, and consisted of as much rye flour as the bread could bear. The Yiddish writer and scholar Hirsh Abramovitch, who was born in 1881, described making such bread from single-grind rye flour, as follows:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>The whole kernel was used &amp;ndash; the bran, the starch, the germ, and everything else. Some flour and warm water were mixed together in a kneading trough and left to stand overnight, covered with a tablecloth which was covered in turn with a fur coat or a pillow. The warmth made the mixture start to ferment. Sometime before dawn, the sourdough was kneaded by hand for about three-quarters of an hour, while more flour and water were added. Once everything was thoroughly mixed, the trough was covered up again and left to stand somewhere warm for four or five hours until the mixture had risen, when it would be formed into loaves of between fifteen and twenty-five pounds. &amp;hellip; The loaves would sit in the oven for four to six hours, depending on their size. Women who didn&amp;rsquo;t want the tops of their loaves to be black would sift rye flour in a thick sieve, mix the sifted flour with water, and smear it on the tops of the loaves before putting them into the oven. &amp;hellip; They called this mixture &lt;em>kharmushke&lt;/em>; it gave the bread a &amp;ldquo;Jewish look,&amp;rdquo; in contrast to gentile bread, which was &amp;ldquo;as black as coal.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Michael Wex, &lt;em>Rhapsody in Schmaltz&lt;/em> (2016)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>This doesn&amp;rsquo;t even remotely resemble the wheaty light rye served in most Jewish delis today. Although people in the old days may have guts of iron rather than abs of steel, eating these dense rye bricks (allegedly 2 lbs. a day on average!) was hardly a lifestyle choice. &lt;em>Razeve broyt&lt;/em> was the food of poverty &amp;ndash; the most fundamental food that was available to everyone. The poorest people would stretch their rye flour by grating potatoes into it, and unwillingly eat the bread &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ea6OET3Zi20">dry&lt;/a>.&amp;rdquo; White bread was considered a luxury, and many Jews started switching to the lighter, more wheaty bread as soon as they could afford it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As a matter of historical fact, wherever in Europe Jews settled, they adopted the local breads and slightly modified them to reflect the strictures of &lt;em>kashrut&lt;/em>. Therefore, the dark, sweet-sour ryes of Lithuania are every bit as Jewish as the light caraway-flecked ryes of southern Poland and Ukraine. The rye breads that managed to survive the journey to America, with the thousands of Jewish immigrants at the beginning of the 20th century, were those that best lent themselves to American conditions, namely, lower-percentage ryes that took advantage of the cheaper, easier-to-handle, and more abundant wheat that Eastern European Jewish bakers found when they arrived. The high-percentage ryes that represented the taste of home for Jews from Lithuania, Belarus and northern Poland had morphed into something new and uniquely American by the end of World War II. To mask the change, immigrant bakers loaded their breads with caraway seeds, which lent baked goods a fleeting flavor of anise/licorice.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="the-regression-of-jewish-deli-rye">The regression of Jewish deli rye&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The Jewish rye that caught on in the US &amp;ndash; the iconic bookends for pastrami &amp;ndash; probably began as some variation on the &lt;em>kornbroyt&lt;/em>. The OG unadulterated &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->&lt;em>kornbroyt&lt;/em>&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --> originated in central Europe, where &amp;ldquo;korn&amp;rdquo; is not maize/corn, but &lt;a href="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/%D7%A7%D7%90%D6%B8%D7%A8%D7%9F#Yiddish">Old High German&lt;/a> for &amp;ldquo;grain,&amp;rdquo; which in bread almost always refers to rye, and &amp;ldquo;broyt&amp;rdquo; is derived from Old High German &amp;ldquo;brōt,&amp;rdquo; meaning a loaf of bread. &lt;em>Kornbroyt&lt;/em> (literally &amp;ldquo;rye bread,&amp;rdquo; but nowadays often referred to as &amp;ldquo;Jewish corn rye&amp;rdquo;) is traditionally a heavy sourdough loaf built on a solid backbone of wheat, 30%-60% rye, and no maize/corn at all. It&amp;rsquo;s akin to farmer&amp;rsquo;s breads but with less wheat; it has a distinct chewiness and depth of flavor. As in &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/attack-of-the-ryeclops">Scandinavian &lt;em>smørrebrød&lt;/em>&lt;/a>, the peppery earthiness of rye pairs marvelously with rich and savory fillings like chopped livers, pastrami, and kosher salami.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Obviously, &lt;em>kornbroyt&lt;/em> was one of the building blocks of the Jewish-American bread microcosm. In the early Jewish deli rye inspired by the &lt;em>kornbroyt&lt;/em>, 30%-40% of the total flour was either medium rye (~85% extraction) or white rye (65%-70% extraction, with the bran and germ removed), and the rest was wheat flour. The blend lets the rye shine through without taking over. The whiter the rye, the milder the flavor &amp;ndash; sometimes just a hint of rye.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>By mid-20th century, an even lighter (~20% rye), mildly tangy, &amp;ldquo;shissel&amp;rdquo; (Yiddish for caraway, also spelt &amp;ldquo;sissel&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;cissel&amp;rdquo;) rye bread had swept across the US like wildfire. It&amp;rsquo;s fluffier, whiter, and less crusty than the old-fashioned 40% version, but closer to American-style white bread. It&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Jewish&amp;rdquo; because one could routinely find it on the shelves of the bakeries and delis that anchored Jewish settlements in major US cities and wherever else they established communities.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This &amp;ldquo;Jewish deli rye&amp;rdquo; became the American default, towering over other American rye breads such as sweet earthy &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->&lt;a href="https://www.allneedfulthings.net/NT_Breads/Old_Milwaukee_Rye.html">Old Milwaukee Rye&lt;/a>&lt;sup id="fnref:2">&lt;a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->, austere &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->Dakota rye&lt;sup id="fnref:3">&lt;a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">3&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->, and &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->Boston brown bread&lt;sup id="fnref:4">&lt;a href="#fn:4" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">4&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->, all of which use at least &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/joeliath/">1/3 rye&lt;/a>. Its popularity probably contributed to people&amp;rsquo;s biggest misconception about rye bread: rye = caraway. Rye has &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/attack-of-the-ryeclops">so many faces, possibilities, and flavor elements&lt;/a> that to denigrate it to that one astringent note is to do it a tremendous injustice. People who think they don&amp;rsquo;t like rye probably just don&amp;rsquo;t like caraway.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Unfortunately, in today&amp;rsquo;s delis, a 20% rye begrudgingly tossed with a tiny amount of &lt;em>shissel&lt;/em> is considered the standard of good deli rye &amp;ndash; and even such a loaf is hard to find these days. The Jewish deli rye at Zingerman&amp;rsquo;s, reputedly &lt;a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120305231242/http://www.saveur.com/article/Travels/best-rye-breads-in-america">America&amp;rsquo;s very best deli rye&lt;/a>, contains ~25% rye. By contrast, most commercial Jewish rye breads have &amp;lt;= 5% rye and rarely come with any &lt;em>shissel&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The shift came about during the post-WWII years, when white flour became cheaper, and easier to work with, than rye flour. The modern &amp;ldquo;rye&amp;rdquo; bread didn&amp;rsquo;t just lack in flavor and quality compared to traditional Jewish rye loaves: It was cheaper and lasted longer. In the 1960s-70s, industrial bakeries, such as Levy&amp;rsquo;s in Brooklyn, hooked many &lt;a href="https://forward.com/culture/482193/levys-jewish-rye-you-dont-have-to-be-jewish-model-joseph-attean-native/">conspicuously non-Jewish&lt;/a> New Yorkers on the taste of a packaged rye bread (pasteurized for a longer shelf life), with the &lt;a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2014/01/12/business/judy-protas-writer-of-slogan-for-levys-real-jewish-rye-dies-at-91.html?_r=0">viral slogan&lt;/a> &amp;ldquo;You don&amp;rsquo;t have to be Jewish to love Levy&amp;rsquo;s Real Jewish Rye.&amp;rdquo; That was a watershed moment. As independent Jewish bakeries failed to beat their larger, industrial competition, quality rye bread disappeared from delis.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/kornerstone/Levys-jewish-rye-walmart.png"
alt="Levy&amp;#39;s Real Jewish Rye"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Levy&amp;rsquo;s Real Jewish Rye (from Walmart)&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Over the past 40-50 years, according to Stan Ginsberg and Norm Berg in their book &lt;em>Inside the Jewish Bakery&lt;/em>, the flavor and texture of commercial rye bread have been drastically watered down as baking companies went national &amp;ndash; and Americanized with it. Rye bread became paler and lighter in texture, with less and less rye flour and more and more additives (oils, conditioners, and preservatives). Commercial bakeries also started using commercial dry yeast instead of sourdough; the latter takes too long (as time has become the most precious commodity) and, for a long time, wasn&amp;rsquo;t generally considered reliable or controlled enough a process for mass production &amp;ndash; probably not good for FDA and local health inspectors, either. So most commercial rye bread lacks the true rye sour starter flavor, and is no longer naturally chewy or dark. Or crusty.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The Jewish delicatessens of New York are often sacrosanct institutions. Landmarks like Katz&amp;rsquo;s, Carnegie Deli, and 2nd Ave Deli serve up lovingly spiced pastrami and corned beef, but their bread is a disgrace. There, I said it! Rye at these &amp;ldquo;legendary&amp;rdquo; NYC delis is shoddy slices of dry, thin, bland, and oftentimes stale white bread that pass for Jewish rye by default, similar to the way DiGiorno can technically be called pizza.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Orwasher&amp;rsquo;s, one of NYC&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ChZ4ZBQ1dkQ">most legendary&lt;/a> bakeries, still make 10-lb. loaves of &lt;em>shissel&lt;/em> rye daily, and customers can buy as much or as little as they need.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/kornerstone/Orwashers-community-rye_2022-06-17.png"
alt="Orwasher&amp;#39;s community rye in 2022"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Orwasher&amp;rsquo;s community rye in 2022, on UberEats.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The original Orwasher&amp;rsquo;s opened in 1916 on East 78th Street between 1st and 2nd Avenues, by a Hungarian immigrant named Abraham Orwasher, when a stretch of Yorkville used to be known as &amp;ldquo;Little Hungary.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Under current owner Keith Cohen, who took over in 2007, the bakery has become more internationally-focused (i.e. more French baguettes and brioches, and American-style white bread) while maintaining its mom-and-pop feel. They have paid heed to the &amp;ldquo;local movement&amp;rdquo; (who hasn&amp;rsquo;t?) by incorporating regionally-grown grains.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Cohen has pushed hard to build out the distribution arm of the business, and the bakery now churns out ~10,000 loaves a day and sells to 100+ different places around NYC. Cohen &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=yfrOH5OwKBk&amp;amp;t=270s">says&lt;/a> Orwasher&amp;rsquo;s still makes its rye bread from an OG rye sour starter that hasn&amp;rsquo;t been remade in 100+ years, but the bakery&amp;rsquo;s rye bread is no longer what it was.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Cohen published &lt;em>Orwasher&amp;rsquo;s Artisan Bread&lt;/em> in 2014. Out of curiosity, I looked it up. Bingo, the book has a recipe for the bakery&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;New York rye bread.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/kornerstone/NY_Rye_Orwashers_Artisan_Bread_2014.png"
alt="book recipe for Orwasher&amp;#39;s NY classic deli rye"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Recipe for Orwasher&amp;rsquo;s NY classic deli rye, published in &amp;lsquo;Orwasher&amp;rsquo;s Artisan Bread&amp;rsquo; (2014)&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The recipe doesn&amp;rsquo;t list any rye flour as an ingredient, but does call for a &amp;ldquo;rye biga.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The book says the bakery keeps two rye bigas: one white at 46% hydration and one dark at 133% hydration. I would guess that the dark rye biga is built with dark rye flour, which is usually a wholegrain (100% extraction) flour complete with all the bran and germ; and the white rye biga is built with all-purpose rye flour (65%-70% extraction, with the bran and germ removed).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The book specifies &amp;ldquo;white rye biga&amp;rdquo; as such wherever it&amp;rsquo;s called. Elsewhere, it lists simply &amp;ldquo;rye biga,&amp;rdquo; such as in this recipe. I&amp;rsquo;m assuming it either refers to the dark rye biga by default or they are meant to be interchangeable.&lt;/p>
&lt;pre tabindex="0">&lt;code>453.6g of dark rye biga (133% hydration) = 194.6g dark rye flour + 259g water
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;p>This means the total amount of (dark) rye present in the entire loaf is&lt;/p>
&lt;pre tabindex="0">&lt;code>194.6g / (194.6g + 1110g) = 14.9%
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/kornerstone/NY_Rye_photo_Orwashers_Artisan_Bread_2014.png"
alt="book photo for Orwasher&amp;#39;s NY classic deli rye"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Photo for Orwasher&amp;rsquo;s NY classic deli rye, published in &amp;lsquo;Orwasher&amp;rsquo;s Artisan Bread&amp;rsquo; (2014)&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>But in case it uses the white rye biga,&lt;/p>
&lt;pre tabindex="0">&lt;code>453.6g of white rye biga (46% hydration) = 310.6 white rye flour + 143g water
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;p>The total amount of (white) rye present in the entire loaf would be&lt;/p>
&lt;pre tabindex="0">&lt;code>310.6g / (310.6g + 1110g) = 21.9%
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;p>Even if this &amp;ldquo;rye biga&amp;rdquo; turns out to be a blend of the dark and the white, you know the range of rye percentages in Orwasher&amp;rsquo;s NY rye bread: &lt;code>14.9% dark rye&lt;/code> ~ &lt;code>21.9% white rye&lt;/code>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>And caraway is a skimpy 4% of the total flour weight. That will probably get even skimpier given the caraway shortage caused by Covid-related supply disruptions.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/kornerstone/Orwashers-rye-2019.png"
alt="Orwasher&amp;#39;s NY classic deli rye in 2019"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Orwasher&amp;rsquo;s NY classic deli rye in 2019&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/kornerstone/Orwashers_rye_bread_UberEats_20220617.png"
alt="Orwasher&amp;#39;s NY classic deli rye in 2022"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Orwasher&amp;rsquo;s NY classic deli rye in 2022, on UberEats.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>I guess trying to run the business as a bakery, sandwich shop and café simultaneously that serves breakfast, lunch and dinner has diluted the quality of the oldie that made it famous. Still, kudos to Orwasher&amp;rsquo;s for being able to pay Manhattan rents every month and stay in business for 100+ years.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>On weekends, Orwasher&amp;rsquo;s also makes a postmodern &amp;ldquo;corn rye&amp;rdquo; with a local spin, using local Sixpoint Brewery&amp;rsquo;s Righteous Rye Ale in the dough.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/kornerstone/Corn_Rye_Orwashers_Artisan_Bread_2014.png"
alt="book recipe for Orwasher&amp;#39;s corn rye"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Recipe for Orwasher&amp;rsquo;s corn rye, published in &amp;lsquo;Orwasher&amp;rsquo;s Artisan Bread&amp;rsquo; (2014)&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/kornerstone/Orwashers-righteous-rye_2022-06-17"
alt="Orwasher&amp;#39;s Righteous Rye bread in 2022"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Orwasher&amp;rsquo;s Righteous Rye bread in 2022, on UberEats.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>A traditionally made &lt;em>kornbroyt&lt;/em> is highly prized by Jewish bread aficionados today because 1) as George Greenstein says in his 1993 book, &lt;em>Secrets of a Jewish Baker&lt;/em>, &amp;ldquo;there are few bakeries left that haven&amp;rsquo;t compromised its real flavor, moisture, and texture&amp;rdquo;; and 2) in this hyper-Instagrammable era of openest-crumb breadporn and hypnotizing unicorn bagels, the rougher-textured, leathery-looking loaf still has the pull and tang of tradition that transcends time.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Jewish deli rye made with &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->&amp;gt;=20% of coarse rye flour&lt;sup id="fnref:5">&lt;a href="#fn:5" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">5&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --> hasn&amp;rsquo;t existed for years in NYC. Sadly, most New Yorkers don&amp;rsquo;t know the difference between good and &lt;a href="https://larissazimberoff.com/articles/2014/07/why-is-new-york-rye-bread-so-bad.html">bad rye bread&lt;/a>. They just firmly believe in the superiority of their ryes, and foolishly brag about the magic of &lt;a href="https://www.ediblemanhattan.com/food-for-thought/why-is-new-york-tap-water-good/">NYC tap water&lt;/a>, which they love to credit for bestowing everything from pizzas to bagels to coffee with the city&amp;rsquo;s unique flavor. Apparently, that holy water has done nothing to save NYC&amp;rsquo;s rye bread from condemnation.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The author Andrew Coe &lt;a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20141230123837/https://www.seriouseats.com/2014/06/rebuilding-the-jewish-bakery.html">explained&lt;/a> in a 2014 article:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;You may have never heard of Shissel Rye before &amp;ndash; it&amp;rsquo;s a bread that didn&amp;rsquo;t survive the softening and blandification of the New York rye tradition. &amp;ldquo;Shissel&amp;rdquo; means bowl in Yiddish, and maybe it&amp;rsquo;s so named because the loaf looks like an inverted bowl. From the outside, it&amp;rsquo;s easy to mistake it for a corn rye, because it has a similar leathery crust. But it&amp;rsquo;s made from wetter dough than corn rye, which gives the loaf a denser crumb and more pronounced sour twang.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Sure, there are dozens of new artisan bakeries that have tried to revive the real Deli rye bread and &lt;em>kornbroyt&lt;/em>. They are not rye bread as such, but &amp;ldquo;Old World&amp;rdquo; artisan wholegrain sourdough breads that seek to imitate &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WUxClvWBHtk">Poilâne&amp;rsquo;s legendarily crusty boules&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="heartland--jewish-soul-food-mecca">Heartland = Jewish soul food mecca&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Few have looked west and figured out &lt;a href="https://www.myjewishlearning.com/the-nosher/the-best-jewish-food-in-detroit/">the plethora of Jewish delis in Detroit&lt;/a> are some of America&amp;rsquo;s best-kept culinary secrets. That&amp;rsquo;s where the process of double-baking rye bread was pioneered and where legit Jewish rye breads are still made.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Jews have lived in Detroit for &amp;gt;200 years. The earliest Jewish immigrants were mostly German, but plenty of Hungarian, Russian, and Polish Jews settled in the Detroit-Ann Arbor-Ypsilanti area as well and brought their family recipes with them.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Many of the region&amp;rsquo;s early Jewish families opened grocery stores (Farmer Jack&amp;rsquo;s, Hiller&amp;rsquo;s, Freeman &amp;amp; Reese Grocers, etc.) and delis (Zingerman&amp;rsquo;s, the Stage Deli, etc). It was at the Stage Deli in Oak Park, in the post-WWII years when the composition of rye bread started incorporating larger and larger portions of cheaper and longer-lasting white flour, where the now-famed Detroit-style rye bread really began.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In the 1960s, Jack Goldberg, founder of the Stage Deli, was intent on serving the freshest rye bread to customers. Local bakeries delivered bread early in the morning, but most of Jack&amp;rsquo;s customers were coming in at lunch, when the rye bread they wanted was already cold. So he started ordering his rye bread partially cooked (baking halted ~80% of the way through). Just before the lunch rush, he would finish baking the bread in a steaming oven in house, so they were still warm in time for lunch. That last-minute steam gives the bread a soft, moist center and a crackly crispy crust. Additionally, forgoing the thin slicer that everyone else was using, Jack put the loaves on a deli meat slicer and cut the hot bread, fresh to order, into roughly 1&amp;quot; thick slices &amp;ndash; perfect for supporting the hulking pile of fatty meat without falling apart.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Most [sandwiches] are served on Jack Goldberg&amp;rsquo;s famous double-baked rye, a Detroit specialty. The rye in New York generally comes pre-sliced, in small disks about half an inch thick. The best deli ryes have a crisp, amber-colored crust and soft center, though these are increasingly difficult to find, especially in New York. Back when he started, Jack Goldberg pioneered the process of double-baking his rye breads. &amp;hellip; The warm loaf is cut into inch-thick slices on a diagonal. When you bite into a slice of double-baked rye, the difference in taste and texture is astounding. A thick, rustic crust greets your teeth, recalling the pleasurable chewiness of sourdough. The warm center of a double-baked rye has an airier density about it and doesn&amp;rsquo;t break apart when stressed with a Bye-Bye-Birdie (house-roasted turkey breast, chopped liver and Russian dressing). It makes New York&amp;rsquo;s rye taste like pigeon food.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>David Sax, &lt;em>Save the Deli&lt;/em> (2009)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Jack&amp;rsquo;s double-baked rye distinguished the Stage Deli from the competition. The method caught on, and soon enough every single Jewish deli across the Motor City was selling warm rye bread that held up well under pressure. Jack&amp;rsquo;s winning business formula is still used today at the Stage Deli in West Bloomfield.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The Stage Deli, along with other local joints like Steve&amp;rsquo;s Deli and the Bread Basket Deli, all use thick-cut rye that employs a decent amount of rye flour blended with the white flour, unlike most of the rye-less loaves in New York masquerading as Jewish rye.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>I first experienced double baked rye at the Bread Basket, a small chain of Detroit delicatessens, with Sy Ginsberg, the corned beef king of Michigan and much of the Midwest. As the waitress set down a sandwich of Ginsberg&amp;rsquo;s trademark corned beef in front of us, I was equally impressed with the bread. It had a darker flecked color to it, with a golden crust that reminded me of good sourdough. The crumb was warm to the touch, and the heat of the oven had released a tangy perfume of yeast. It felt like a little pillow in my hand, cradling the tender corned beef slicked with mustard. The crust had crackle and chew, the crumb was soft and doughy. It tasted like rye bread ought to.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>David Sax&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Those who grew up in eastern Missouri / southern Illinois would vividly recall the taste of &amp;ldquo;tzitzel&amp;rdquo; rye from Pratzel&amp;rsquo;s Bakery, the last Jewish-owned kosher bakery in St. Louis. This round caraway rye bread came coated in cornmeal, and was the pride of the bakery&amp;rsquo;s founders, who opened shop in ~1913, and of their successors who operated the business until 2011.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A 2011 book, &lt;em>From the Jewish Heartland: Two Centuries of Midwest Foodways&lt;/em>, by Ellen F. Steinberg and Jack H. Prost, includes a long interview with the descendants of Max Pratzel, with particular fervor about the &lt;em>tzitzel&lt;/em> rye, which also appears in many other food memories about this bakery.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.losttables.com/pratzels/pratzels.htm">Lost Tables&lt;/a>, an amazing website that chronicles lost restaurants in St. Louis, tells the story behind Pratzel&amp;rsquo;s rye:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Long before sourdough was a word associated with San Francisco, Jewish bakers were creating ryes and pumpernickel breads using sourdough starters they brought with them from Europe. When Max Pratzel came to St. Louis, he went to another Jewish baker and asked him for a small portion of his sour culture. Pratzel&amp;rsquo;s continued to grow that culture for almost 100 years and used it to make their rye bread.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Bakers used cornmeal to glide loaves in and out of the baking ovens. Nate Pratzel liked the taste of the cornmeal coated rye bread bottoms so much that he would cut them off and take them home. Eventually, it occurred to him that it might be a good idea to cover the entire loaf with cornmeal, which is how one of Pratzel&amp;rsquo;s bestseller, tzizel rye bread, was born.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Luckily, the sister site Lost Dishes has posted a &lt;a href="https://www.lostdishes.com/pratzels/tzizel.htm">recipe&lt;/a> for the &lt;em>tzitzel&lt;/em> rye, for anyone who&amp;rsquo;s interested. It&amp;rsquo;s from a &lt;a href="http://littlecreekpress.com/bookstore/manna-cafe-and-bakery-cookbooka-memoir-of-two-businesses-a-community-and-the-food-that-connected-them/">recent cookbook&lt;/a> by descendants of the Pratzel family who moved to Wisconsin, opened a bakery there, and shipped the tzizel rye bread to hungry former St. Louisans around the country. The bakery &lt;a href="https://www.northsidenews.org/manna-cafe-bakery-closes-after-15-years-nourishing-the-northside/">closed&lt;/a> in the midst of Covid, as the Pratzels were at the end of their lease and approaching their own retirement age.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Like everything else these days, Jewish deli rye &amp;ndash; like the bagel &amp;ndash; is becoming &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->an endangered species&lt;sup id="fnref:6">&lt;a href="#fn:6" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">6&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->, with fewer and fewer bakeries making it the traditional way.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="diy-old-school-deli-rye">DIY old-school deli rye&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>If you want a good deli rye, you gotta make it at home. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t take years to bake yourself a decent loaf of rye bread that tastes delicious and can stand up to corned beef. Your great-(great-etc.) grandmothers most likely didn&amp;rsquo;t apprentice at a Paris &lt;em>boulangrie&lt;/em> and still churned out great rye bread with whatever starters they had and kept going throughout some pretty challenging winters. I also highly doubt they had the luxury of building a sour culture meticulously with all kinds of grains à la Tartine, discarding &amp;gt;=90% of it, replenishing it with a new supply of flour, and letting it mature for the right number of days until it was ready to set up in loaves.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>You just have to be willing to experiment and fail a couple of times and pay attention to how it looks, feels, smells, and be willing to fiddle around and adjust the next time. Early delivery, continual improvement, and flexible adjustment, much like agile software development.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This rye I made is a variation of the old-school deli rye, closer to a &lt;em>kornbroyt&lt;/em> than a contemporary rye-flavored bread at delis.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/kornerstone/202206181714.jpg"
alt="kornerstone: Jewish deli rye"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>I used a whole lot of single-grind wholegrain rye flour: 30% of final flour weight, and 45% of total flour weight (including the levain).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Since this dough contains a relatively high percentage of whole grains, I used a 2-dough lamination method to make it stronger. It has &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/breadford-von-regrainton/">worked well&lt;/a> for me before. I was able to give it a long fermentation.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I also added some &amp;ldquo;altus,&amp;rdquo; which was originally a way for bakers to re-use bread they hadn&amp;rsquo;t sold. They would cut &amp;ldquo;old&amp;rdquo; rye bread into small pieces, soak in water until saturated and wrung out. It makes for a more tender and flavorful bread. I didn&amp;rsquo;t &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/zombie-dust/">soak my &amp;ldquo;old&amp;rdquo; rye bread&lt;/a> (you can use any type of bread); I just let it dry out a bit and ground it into crumbs in a coffee grinder.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Instead of caraway seeds, I used caramelized onions, spent brewer&amp;rsquo;s grains, and poppy seeds. If you are concerned about the opioids in poppy seeds, &lt;a href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fchem.2021.692045/full">studies&lt;/a> have shown that crushing and intensively cooking them significantly decrease their morphine content. Additionally, poppy seeds only truly develop their nutty flavor after crushing and baking.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The rye flour I used is freshly milled &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/files/danko-rye.pdf">Danko&lt;/a> (&lt;em>Dańkowskie Nowe&lt;/em> in Polish), which is a high-yielding winter rye developed in 1976 by the Poznań Plant Breeding Center in Poland, for the purpose of milling. It was bred from a lineage of northern European ryes known for their high starch content and excellent baking performance in traditional whole rye loaves. Quite a few &lt;a href="https://danko.pl/en/odmiany-categories/rye/">newer Dańkowskie varieties&lt;/a> have been developed since. Danko itself hails from Poland&amp;rsquo;s Warta River Valley and adapts well to the Mid-Atlantic climate. It has a floral aroma when freshly milled, and a good flavor balance between bready and spicy. (I haven&amp;rsquo;t been able to track down a &lt;a href="https://www.ryerevival.org/projects">Midwestern source&lt;/a> for Danko rye. If you know of any, &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/say-hi/">drop me a line&lt;/a>!)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Similar to how grape varietals and terroir influence the style and character of wines, so do varieties of rye &amp;ndash; and the soils and micro-climates they grow in. Rye whiskey derives its unique spicy and flavorful characteristics from the complexity of the grain. A traditional rye bread is definitively more flavorful than white bread. Many of the ryes that grow well in the US are old varieties brought over from Europe. There are also some newer hybrids that are being tested especially for local climate and soil conditions.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/kornerstone/202206191549.jpg"
alt="kornerstone: Jewish deli rye"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>As usual, I refreshed the levain 3 times with freshly milled wholegrain rye flour (80% hydration) over a period of 24 hours, and let it ferment at 60°F-70°F until it doubled in volume and was brimming with bubbles and a clean vinegary smell. Alternatively, you could sift the wholegrain rye into a medium rye flour and some coarse bits; use the former in the final dough, and feed the latter to the levain. You can manipulate the balance of acetic acid to lactic acid in the rye sour by changing the hydration: a dryer, more dough-like sour will contain more acetic acid and give a more vinegary flavor, while a wetter one (more like a thick paste at the start and a pancake batter once it&amp;rsquo;s developed) will tend more towards the lactic side and a yogurty/cheesy flavor.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>80% extraction wheat flour (Marquis - Anarchy Acres, WI)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>50%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>100% extraction wheat flour (Wisconsin #2 - Anarchy Acres, WI)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>15%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>100% extraction rye flour (Danko - Zeng Farm, NJ)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>30%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>old rye bread crumbs (aka. altus)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>cold water (50°F)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>92%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>rye levain (80% hydration)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>50%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>caramelized onions&lt;/td>
&lt;td>20%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>spent brewer&amp;rsquo;s grains&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Dutch blue poppy seeds, crushed (Savory Spice)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>kosher salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>America loves sweet onions! They are so popular that nowadays you can find them in any grocery store anytime of the year. I used a large Vidalia onion from a farmers' market. I cut the onion into medium-width slices, and cooked them on a George Foreman grill until brown and fragrant.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Dough #1: Autolyze the rye flour, whole wheat flour and breadcrumbs with just a little over half (~55%) of the total water. Mix thoroughly to hydrate every particle of the grain, cover, and leave for ~2 hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Dough #2: Mix together the 80% extraction wheat flour with the rest of the water. Cover and leave for ~2 hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Next, add equal portion of the levain and the salt to each dough. Mix or slap &amp;amp; fold for 5-10 mins. The wholegrain rye-wheat dough is weak and sticky, but it&amp;rsquo;s OK. The 80% extraction wheat flour dough should be strong and extensible.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Fold each dough 3 times in the next 2 hours, at 30-min intervals.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Now, the lamination: Wet your work surface with a spray bottle filled with water, to prevent the dough from sticking to it. Turn each dough out onto the damp surface, and gently spread it out as thinly and evenly as possible without tearing, into one large rectangle.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Carefully place the wholegrain rye-wheat dough on top of the other one. Try to line them up as much as possible.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Sprinkle all of the add-ins (onions, spent grains, and poppy seeds) all over the dough. Fold the dough into thirds (left-right, up-down) evenly and symmetrically to create the lamination and layer everything together.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Transfer the dough into a fridge to finish bulk fermentation overnight. I did take it out a few hours later to do another couple of coil-folds, and returned it to the fridge immediately after. Total bulk-fermentation: 2.5 hours at room temperature (~70°F) and 12 hours in the fridge (~40°F).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Next morning, take the dough out of the fridge. Mine doubled in volume overnight and felt so full of air pockets.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Pre-shape it loosely via a coil-fold. After a 30-min rest, shape the dough tightly into whatever form you desire. I shaped mine into a log, rolled it in additional onions and spent grains, and placed it in a parchment paper-lined loaf pan for final proof. You can, of course, roll the dough in a copious amount of caraway seeds or coarsely ground cornmeal.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>After 2 hours of final rise at room temperature, I baked it, as usual, in my ghetto toaster oven. The first 20 mins at 350°F, followed by another 30 mins at 300°F.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/kornerstone/202206181722.jpg"
alt="kornerstone: Jewish deli rye"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>It turned out a magnificent rye, without a fancy pizza stone or preheated Le Creuset Dutch oven.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/kornerstone/202206181715.jpg"
alt="kornerstone: Jewish deli rye"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>I waited 24 hours before cutting it. Patience is a virtue in short supply.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The crumb is highly moist and delicate. As soft as the finest goose down pillow.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/kornerstone/202206191228.jpg"
alt="kornerstone: Jewish deli rye"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>It tastes much bolder than a typical deli rye.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I like it toasted, smeared with cream cheese, and topped with olives.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>That tender crumb mingles marvelously with fatty, flaky corned beef, conjuring up a guilty pleasure so heavenly that it&amp;rsquo;s worth the heartburn.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/kornerstone/202206191239.jpg"
alt="kornerstone: Jewish deli rye"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>A real Jewish treat, before everyone became uber health-conscious, used to be a roast beef sandwich on rye with Bermuda onions and &lt;em>schmaltz&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The bread also pairs exquisitely with &lt;em>komijnekaas&lt;/em> (a classic Dutch gouda-style cheese seasoned with cumin and caraway seeds) or Veldhuizen&amp;rsquo;s caraway cheddar.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/kornerstone/202206191542.jpg"
alt="kornerstone: Jewish deli rye"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Bon appétit!&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>2022/12/31 update&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Just watched a Hallmark movie called &lt;em>Hanukkah on Rye&lt;/em>. All the sandwich breads featured in the movie looked so white that it made me think of this rye&amp;hellip; So I made another loaf &amp;ndash; with &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/attack-of-the-ryeclops">heritage Finnish rye&lt;/a>. I put some raw onions in the rye levain and added more caramelized onions to the final dough. Seriously onion-y.&lt;/p>
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>For recipes, see either &lt;em>Inside the Jewish Bakery: Recipes and Memories from the Golden Age of Jewish Baking&lt;/em> by Stanley Ginsberg and Norman Berg, or &lt;em>Secrets of a Jewish Baker&lt;/em> by George Greenstein.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>Bernard Clayton&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em>New Complete Book of Breads&lt;/em> includes a recipe for Old Milwaukee Rye, originally from Bernadine Landsberg of Milwaukee. Additionally, the 1st edition (2001-2002) of &lt;em>Home Cooking: Dickinson County Style&lt;/em> features a &lt;a href="https://cookingwithbarryandmeta.blogspot.com/2012/12/old-milwaukee-rye-bread.html">recipe&lt;/a> for Old Milwaukee Rye from Rethie Foster, who initially discovered this bread in the newspaper and it became a favorite.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:3" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>North Dakota is rye country as well as wheat country, a rich land where 19th-century Norwegian settlers come to life in Ole Edvart Rølvaag&amp;rsquo;s classic family saga, &lt;em>Giants in the Earth&lt;/em>. Dakota Harvest Bakers in Grand Forks, ND developed a quintessentially American interpretation of a traditional rye bread, for its Scandinavian-American customers who craved &amp;ldquo;bread like Nana used to make.&amp;rdquo; Stanley Ginsberg included a recipe in his 2016 book, &lt;em>The Rye Baker&lt;/em>.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:4" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>17th-century settlers in the Massachusetts Bay Colony tried to grow wheat, but the unfavorable climate and soil forced them to switch to rye.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:4" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:5" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>20% rye and 80% wheat is roughly the ratio that George Greenstein uses in his 1993 book, &lt;em>Secrets of a Jewish Baker&lt;/em>.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:5" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:6" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>See David Sax&amp;rsquo;s 2009 book, &lt;em>Save the Deli: In Search of Perfect Pastrami, Crusty Rye, and the Heart of Jewish Delicatessen&lt;/em>.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:6" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/section></content></item></channel></rss>