<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>barley on HERESY LEVAIN</title><link>/tags/barley/</link><description>Latest experiments in barley from HERESY LEVAIN</description><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2023 HERESY LEVAIN 🍞 CC BY-NC-SA 4.0</copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 16 Sep 2019 15:59:36 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/barley/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Broom Rider</title><link>/posts/broom-rider/</link><pubDate>Mon, 16 Sep 2019 15:59:36 -0700</pubDate><guid>/posts/broom-rider/</guid><description>A powerfully tasty broom for your colon.</description><content>&lt;p>In Deuteronomy 8:8, the Lord promised the Israelites a land &amp;ldquo;of wheat and barley.&amp;rdquo; And it was five barley loaves that Jesus divided to feed the five thousand in the story of &amp;ldquo;the loaves and the fishes.&amp;rdquo; Many people are familiar with the mild, nutty flavor of barley in soup and stews, but few have probably eaten barley in a bread.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The ancient Greeks had a method of divination using barley cakes or loaves of barley bread. It&amp;rsquo;s called alphitomancy (&amp;ldquo;álphito&amp;rdquo; means &amp;ldquo;barley&amp;rdquo;), and the diviner who used barley is a &lt;em>alphitómantis&lt;/em>. A quantity of pure barley was kneaded with milk, a little salt and without leaven. Then it was wrapped up in a greased paper, baked directly in a fire, and rubbed with verbena leaf when finished. When someone in a group was suspected of a crime, all of the suspects would be fed slices of this barley bread, as it was assumed that those innocent could eat it perfectly, while the guilty person would choke and get indigestion. On certain days of the year, young women would enter the woods carrying cakes made of barley and honey. It was said that the devil led the women into the woods. Supposedly, the serpent ate the cakes of the innocent women, but refused the cakes of the others.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A &amp;ldquo;barleycorn&amp;rdquo; is an English unit of length based on the size of a dried grain of barley. One inch was defined as being equal to three barleycorns. Used as early as the 10th century in Britain, it was mostly replaced by imperial units through the Weights and Measures Act of 1824. But the barleycorn legacy remains &amp;ndash; it&amp;rsquo;s still used as the basis of shoe sizes in English-speaking countries.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>During the Irish Rebellion of 1798 (known as &lt;em>Éirí Amach 1798&lt;/em> in the Irish and &lt;em>The Hurries&lt;/em> in Ulster Scots), soldiers often carried barley in their pockets as provisions when on the march. Every spring after the rebellion, the folklore goes, small fields of barley would sprout and mark &amp;ldquo;croppy-holes,&amp;rdquo; unmarked mass graves into which these man were thrown in. To many Irish nationalists, barley growing every spring from these &amp;ldquo;croppy-holes&amp;rdquo; symbolized the regenerative nature of Irish resistance to British rule. The Irish poet Robert Dwyer Joyce wrote a ballad to memorialize the soldiers, titled &amp;ldquo;The Wind That Shakes the Barley.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Caffè d&amp;rsquo;orzo was a coffee substitute in Italy during the two World Wars, made mainly
from finely ground roasted barley. It&amp;rsquo;s still a popular drink today, and marketed worldwide as a healthy (naturally caffeine-free) and delicious Italian alternative to coffee.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The modern word &amp;ldquo;barn&amp;rdquo; comes from the Old English word &amp;ldquo;bærlic&amp;rdquo;, which means &amp;ldquo;of
barley.&amp;rdquo; You see, all of our barns are really just barley houses. Until ~200 years ago, barley was probably the No.1 bread grain of continental Europe and was carried to the New World by the early settlers.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Barley (&lt;em>Hordeum vulgare L.&lt;/em>) has a thick fibrous hull, a high level of ß-glucans and simply-arranged starch granules. Over the last half-century, worldwide production of wheat has quadrupled while the production of barley has barely doubled. Global production of barley is about 30% of that of corn. Compared to corn, barley has more protein, methionine, lysine, cysteine and tryptophan.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Barley has been cultivated and consumed since ancient times. But why hasn&amp;rsquo;t it been granted the same &amp;ldquo;ancient grain&amp;rdquo; status that einkorn, emmer, and spelt now enjoy?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Today, barley is cultivated mostly as animal feed, with two uses: grain yield and grazing. For ruminants, barley is the third most readily degradable cereal behind oats and wheat, and has a more rapid starch fermentation rate than corn.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The world&amp;rsquo;s most nutritious barley is said to be grown in the Red River Valley, a beautiful stretch of land between the rolling plains of North Dakota and the lakes and forests of Minnesota. It isn&amp;rsquo;t your traditional valley &amp;ndash; it&amp;rsquo;s nestled on flat, fertile ground that follows the coils of the mighty Red River as it flows north from South Dakota to Canada. The soil is what sets the Red River Valley apart. The rich, dark soil produces barley that contains the highest amounts of protein and other nutrients.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The value-added market for barley is in malting and beer production, and as such the malting and brewing industry has set the quality specifications for barley grain being delivered after harvest. The key malt trait is hot water extract (HWE). High levels of HWE are desirable, as it provides an indication of malt quality as well as potential brewhouse performance.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Malted barley is used for brewing ales and lagers, pilsners, IPAs and pale ales. Besides providing the sugars that get fermented into alcohol, malts and grains provide a full range of flavors in beer &amp;ndash; from light cracker, toast, and biscuit to coffee, dark chocolate, dried fruits and brown sugar. Malt is what gives a beer color, richness, and complexity. It&amp;rsquo;s obviously a key ingredient for breweries, yet nearly all domestically malted barley comes just from a few companies &amp;ndash; Rahr, Briess, Cargill, and Great Western. In recent years, craft maltsters have been on the rise, but craft malt is still a tiny fraction of overall malt production.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A powerfully tasty, barley-infused broom for your colon:&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>85% extraction wheat flour (Windy White - Sunflower Acres, CO)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>85%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>90% extraction barley flour (Doubting Thomas Farms, MN)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>15%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>barley levain&lt;/td>
&lt;td>35%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>homemade almond milk&lt;/td>
&lt;td>85%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>homemade milk kefir&lt;/td>
&lt;td>40%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>whole flaxseeds&lt;/td>
&lt;td>20%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>cinnamon powder&lt;/td>
&lt;td>a pinch&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>ICYMI, see my &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/joeliath/">previous post&lt;/a> on how to bolt freshly milled wholegrain flour.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Barley has such a low gluten content that it must be mixed with wheat flour to make a tall, fluffy loaf. The flavor of barley is mild, and the color is a grayish white. It adds a subtle nutty barley flavor to the bread.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Nothing beats the warm, nutty flavor of toasted flaxseeds. So you should totally toast the flaxseeds first &amp;ndash; in a skillet, oven or microwave &amp;ndash; to bring out the richest flavors they have. Then soak the flaxseeds in milk kefir (could use plain vanilla h₂o, buttermilk, etc). Leave the pudding in the fridge for a few hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Gently shake a pinch of cinnamon into the flours. Autolyze with almond milk for 2 hours. You can keep it in the fridge, too.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Add the levain and salt. Mix well until thoroughly combined. Add all of the flaxseed pudding, and mix until evenly distributed.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Perform 4-5 folds in the next 3 hours. Warm bulk-fermentation should last 5 hours in total.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Shape. 18 hours final proof in a fridge.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Let the dough warm up before baking.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/broom-rider/201909161258.jpg"
alt="Marbled rye whole loaf"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Open and nutty crumb enrobed in golden crispy crusts. Mildly tangy and pleasantly chewy. Not dense or heavy at all. Powerfully tasty.&lt;/p></content></item></channel></rss>