<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>brewers spent grains on HERESY LEVAIN</title><link>/tags/brewers-spent-grains/</link><description>Latest experiments in brewers spent grains from HERESY LEVAIN</description><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2023 HERESY LEVAIN 🍞 CC BY-NC-SA 4.0</copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 09 Dec 2019 16:41:45 -0800</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/brewers-spent-grains/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Breadford von Regrainton</title><link>/posts/breadford-von-regrainton/</link><pubDate>Mon, 09 Dec 2019 16:41:45 -0800</pubDate><guid>/posts/breadford-von-regrainton/</guid><description>A hearty re-grained bread, made with spent grains and Glenn whole wheat flour.</description><content>&lt;p>I picked up a bag of Glenn wheat berries from Kenter Canyon Farms at the Atwater Village Farmers' Market in Los Angeles. It cost ~$2/lb, not cheap but not ridiculously overpriced either. The Glenn wheat was grown on Kenter Canyon Farms in Ventura County, along the south side of the Santa Clara River.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/files/Glenn.pdf">Glenn&lt;/a> is a modern HRSW developed by a NDSU breeding program to provide better scab resistance and higher yield. It was released by the North Dakota Agricultural Experiment Station in the spring of 2005. It has a fairly high protein content of 13%-14%. I have seen quite a few local and regional mills across the country label Glenn as a &amp;ldquo;heritage&amp;rdquo; wheat &amp;ndash; very curious.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I had long wanted to bake a &lt;em>treberbrot&lt;/em>, a hearty German bread made with the addition of spent grains from brewing beers. The spent grain adds some sweetness, texture and a lot of fiber to the bread.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/regrainton/201912082109.jpg"
alt="Breadford von Regrainton"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Breadford von Regrainton, a hearty re-grained bread that re-uses a lot of brewer&amp;rsquo;s spent grains.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>First, I milled the Glenn wheat berries, and &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/joeliath/">sifted&lt;/a> half into a 80% extraction flour, leaving the other half wholegrain (100% extraction).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Next, I built a levain with&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>sifted-out wheat bran; and&lt;/li>
&lt;li>a smooth purée of spent grains (from brewing Berliner Weiss) and &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fvtmBuTyu1c">boiled jackfruit seeds&lt;/a>.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>To make the dough stronger, I decided to use a 2-dough lamination method.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Dough #1:&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>80% extraction wheat flour (Glenn - Kenter Canyon Farms, CA)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>h&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->2&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->o&lt;/td>
&lt;td>85%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>bran levain&lt;/td>
&lt;td>40%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>This will be the stronger half of the dough that lifts the whole bread. You can totally swap water for beer here.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Dough #2:&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>whole wheat flour (Glenn - Kenter Canyon Farms, CA)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>h&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->2&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->o&lt;/td>
&lt;td>70%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>spent grain purée&lt;/td>
&lt;td>60%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>bran levain&lt;/td>
&lt;td>20%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>toasted flaxseeds&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>I mixed 1 part spent grains to 1 part water, and puréed the mixture in a blender. Then I autolyzed the flour, along with the flaxseeds, in this thick grainy smoothie diluted with water.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>With all of the wheat bran added back to the dough through the levain, this bread retains its whole-wheat integrity.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Add-ins:&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>spent grains&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sunflower seeds&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>roasted papaya seeds, ground&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>raisins&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.taste.com.au/quick-easy/articles/want-use-up-seeds/f45slcr4">Roasted papaya seeds&lt;/a> have a dark cocoa brown color and smell deeply aromatic. They taste like peppercorns.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I did 4 folds with each dough during the first 3 hours. Then I combined both doughs by gently stretching them out into big rectangles and placing dough #2 on top of dough #1. I sprinkled the add-ins during lamination.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The dough was bulk-fermented for 5 hours in total at room temperature, shaped into a taut boule (dusted with grated coconut), and then retarded at 40°F for 10 hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Next day, I let the dough warm up for a few hours until ~100% risen. I baked it on a shitty pizza pan in my ghetto toaster oven.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/regrainton/201912082113.jpg"
alt="Breadford von Regrainton"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>It grew so big during baking that it nearly filled up every cubic inch of the toaster oven!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The crust came out crispy and thin. The crumb is so freakin' airy.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/regrainton/201912082135.jpg"
alt="Breadford von Regrainton"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The taste is deeply flavorful with a mild tang and a subtle sweetness from spent grains and raisins.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/regrainton/201912091249.jpg"
alt="Breadford von Regrainton"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Superbly delightful.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>NGL, it tasted even better the next day.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/regrainton/201912091255.jpg"
alt="Breadford von Regrainton"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>A later variation:&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/regrainton/201912301643.jpg"
alt="Breadford von Regrainton"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Breadford von Regrainton v2.0, an incredibly flavorful re-grained bread that rises from dead spent grains.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Can&amp;rsquo;t believe it&amp;rsquo;s already December. Where did the year go?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In review, 2019 has been my Year of Fermentation. I read Sandor Katz&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em>The Art of Fermentation&lt;/em> and René Redzepi&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em>The Noma Guide to Fermentation.&lt;/em> I got into sourdough breadmaking (and bread chemistry) seriously for the firs time. I experimented audaciously with literally anything I could get my hands on: vegetables, beans, grains, milk, fish&amp;hellip; From lactic acid bacteria (LAB), I ventured into fungi &amp;ndash; koji (&lt;em>Aspergillus oryzae&lt;/em>) and tempeh (&lt;em>Rhizopus oligosporus&lt;/em>). It&amp;rsquo;s been a very memorable year and an unbelievably fulfilling one.&lt;/p></content></item></channel></rss>