<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>schiacciata on HERESY LEVAIN</title><link>/tags/schiacciata/</link><description>Latest experiments in schiacciata from HERESY LEVAIN</description><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2023 HERESY LEVAIN 🍞 CC BY-NC-SA 4.0</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 05 May 2021 23:10:46 -0600</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/schiacciata/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Aquaboogie</title><link>/posts/aquaboogie/</link><pubDate>Wed, 05 May 2021 23:10:46 -0600</pubDate><guid>/posts/aquaboogie/</guid><description>&lt;em>Pan de Cristal&lt;/em>, an elusive gem. A whopping 110% hydration plus 15% oil results in an extremely wet formless mixture which, after proper mixing, transforms into a marvelously glossy and almost fluid blob of a dough that spreads willingly &amp;ndash; and yields elastic translucent crumbs and a terrain of air bubbles.</description><content>&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;ve been playing with &lt;em>pan de cristal&lt;/em>, using freshly milled whole wheat flour bolted down to 80% extraction.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Pan de cristal&lt;/em> (called &lt;em>pa de vidre&lt;/em> in Catalan) is a Spanish &amp;ldquo;glass bread&amp;rdquo; invented in ~2004 by Barcelonian baker Jordi Nomen. It&amp;rsquo;s characterized by high hydration and double fermentation, which causes a very hollow and alveolate crumb that&amp;rsquo;s almost non-existent. &lt;em>Pan de cristal&lt;/em> is now a registered trademark &lt;a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/913153046">owned by its creator&lt;/a>. Nomen&amp;rsquo;s next bakery, Concept Pa, has developed a more extreme variety called &lt;em>&lt;a href="http://www.pandecristal.com/products/diamond-crystal-bread-r/">pan de cristal® diamante&lt;/a>&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Claudio Perrando, a German-Panamanian baker who rose to international stardom over the last decade through the internet, seems to be the most famous ambassador of &lt;em>pan de cristal.&lt;/em> His version has translucent crumb and such MASSIVE holes that it undoubtedly wins the competition for the Bread with the Fewest Calories per Cubic Centimeter. He sells his recipes online. I&amp;rsquo;ve never bought his recipes, but from what I can tell, he uses an over-ripe poolish and a long autolyse (with high-gluten super-fine flour) to add more extensibility to the dough. He does a 3-4h warm bulk-fermentation and a 1h final proof.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>80% extraction wheat flour (Turkey Red - Aspen Moon Farm, CO)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>cold &lt;em>aqua&lt;/em> (autolyse 75% + bassinage 30% + salt mixing 5%)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>110%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>rye levain&lt;/td>
&lt;td>35%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>olive oil&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->10%-20%&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Autolyze the flour with 75% of the &lt;em>aqua&lt;/em> for 1-2 hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Add the levain and mix until gluten development.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Add the next 30% &lt;em>aqua&lt;/em> in 4 increments &lt;em>à la bassinage&lt;/em>. Make sure each addition of water is well absorbed before adding more.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Let rest for 15-20 mins, and mix in the salt with the last 5% &lt;em>aqua&lt;/em>. The dough will noticeably tighten after absorbing the salt.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Let rest for 30 mins before mixing in the oil. The dough should be super airy and jiggly.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Perform 5 coil folds, at 45-min intervals. Sprinkle any add-ins at each fold, e.g., cinnamon sugar, chocolate chips, herbs.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Bulk ferment at 75F for 3h and retard in the fridge overnight. (Or straight to the fridge for 36-48h after the first 2 folds at room temperature.)&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/aquaboogie/202205050812.jpg"
alt="80% extraction pan de cristal"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/aquaboogie/202205050813.jpg"
alt="80% extraction pan de cristal"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Next day, take it out of the fridge, divide and rest 2-3h. No shaping necessary.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Bake at 375°F for the first 20 mins, until the crust is brown and blistered. Bake for another 10-15 mins at 350F until cooked through.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/aquaboogie/202205051301.jpg"
alt="80% extraction pan de cristal"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Pan de cristal, made with 80% extraction Turkey Red.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>A whopping 110% hydration plus 15% oil results in an extremely wet formless mixture which, after proper mixing, transforms into a gorgeously glossy and almost fluid blob of a dough that spreads willingly, and yields elastic translucent crumbs and a terrain of air bubbles.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/aquaboogie/202205051305.jpg"
alt="80% extraction pan de cristal"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Crispy. Chewy. Bubbly. Wheaty. With flecks and sheen in the crumb like Italian terrazzo floors.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This bread makes fantastic and ginormous sandwiches as the way Roman Gods intended. Also an excellent delivery vessel for tomatoes and Iberian ham.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/aquaboogie/202205051307.jpg"
alt="80% extraction pan de cristal"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>BTW, I make &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/aquaboogie-van-wheatsworth/">wholegrain versions&lt;/a>, too.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>This is also the base recipe I use for my scandalous &lt;em>schiacciata toscana&lt;/em>. It&amp;rsquo;s supposedly a Florentine flat bread that is characteristically closer to a &lt;em>pizza bianca&lt;/em> than anything else, made famous by All&amp;rsquo;antico Vinaio (rumored to be the greatest sandwich shop in the world).&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>The Florentine &lt;em>schiacciata all&amp;rsquo;olio&lt;/em> uses a goodly amount of olive oil and large grain salt, and the best is cooked in a wood burning oven. It should be crispy but not hard, oily but not greasy.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>If making &lt;em>schiacciata&lt;/em>, flip the dough onto a rectangular baking sheet. Use fingers to gently dent and push the dough outwards towards all four corners, preserving the air bubbles inside, until the dough is about 3/4&amp;quot; (2 cm) at its thickest part. Make random dimples 2&amp;quot; (5 cm) apart that puncture all the way through the dough to the pan. This will prevent the dough from doming too much while baking and help create even thickness for sandwiches. Drizzle olive oil all over the surface of the dough.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The best way to appreciate the unique flavor of Turkey Red &lt;em>pan de cristal&lt;/em> is to add a touch of salted butter and/or honey and eat while still slightly warm. When the bread starts to stale, toast it and dunk it into a warm, funky dip like a &lt;em>bagna càuda&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;ve experimented with increasing the amount of oil to ~20% of flour weight, and had great results.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/section></content></item></channel></rss>