<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>barm on HERESY LEVAIN</title><link>/tags/barm/</link><description>Latest experiments in barm from HERESY LEVAIN</description><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2023 HERESY LEVAIN 🍞 CC BY-NC-SA 4.0</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 06 Jun 2023 19:09:09 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/barm/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>levure de bière #5.4: Tropical cornucopia</title><link>/posts/byb-5-4/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Jun 2023 19:09:09 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/byb-5-4/</guid><description>Portuguese-inspired &lt;em>broa de milho&lt;/em> with two leavens: a Framgarden kveik barm and a London Tropics yeasted soaker. Baked outdoors and imbued with the wonderful smoky flavor of open-fire bakery. Hearty and rustic.</description><content>&lt;p>&lt;em>Beer = liquid bread. Want to stay updated on my &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/craft-beer-yeast">craft beer yeast bread-plays&lt;/a>? Subscribe to the &lt;a href="https://tinyletter.com/breadbuster">newsletter&lt;/a>!&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Key West, the southernmost point of the continental US, is one of my favorite summer spots. Ernest Hemingway once said Key West was &amp;ldquo;a St. Tropez of the poor.&amp;rdquo; He came for a day and ended up staying for a decade.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The island is still a source of endless joy: fishing, scuba diving, dancing, slumming, and drinking. The most beautiful thing about Key West is spending the night on the beach (not the best in Florida), swimming there as if it were daytime, and tanning, like vampires, under the moonlight. And I always like to bring &lt;em>medianoches&lt;/em> and &lt;em>chicharones&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This time, I drank lots of corn. First of all, a fermented &lt;em>chicha morada&lt;/em> (I can&amp;rsquo;t stand the sweet and fruity non-fermented version), made with Peruvian purple corn, pineapple, apples, lime, and spices. It tasted like a &lt;em>kombucha&lt;/em>. Next, a &lt;em>chicha venezolana&lt;/em>, which turned out more like a Mexican &lt;em>horchata&lt;/em>. On my way out, I drank homemade &lt;em>chicha de jora&lt;/em> and ate &lt;em>estofado de carne&lt;/em> (rich and flavorful beef stew with garden vegetables and &lt;em>chicha de jora&lt;/em>); the stew reminded me of &lt;em>bœuf bourguignon&lt;/em> and was a lot better than this Ohio &amp;ldquo;delicacy&amp;rdquo; called Cincinnati chili 3-way I had earlier at Skyline just outside Fort Lauderdale, which is a pound of shredded cheese on top of mediocre chili on top of poorly cooked spaghetti.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>These brought back good memories of backpacking in Peru and eating at &lt;em>picanterías&lt;/em>, where &lt;em>chicha morada&lt;/em> and &lt;em>chicha de jora&lt;/em> are commonly brewed in-house.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Chicha&lt;/em> is an ancient pre-Columbian corn drink widespread in the Andes. It was absolutely essential to the Incas; for them it was a fundamental domestic product, traded from coast to inland, up and down the continent. &lt;em>Chicha&lt;/em> was a community necessity, a ritual libation, an imperative social lubricant to the Incas' communication with the gods, a drink worthy of being sipped by a farmer straight out of a clay pot as well as lapped up by the sun itself out of a gold vessel.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The brewing process for &lt;em>chicha&lt;/em> is essentially &lt;a href="https://beerconnoisseur.com/articles/chicha-bolivias-tart-beer">similar&lt;/a> to that of European-style beer.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Doña Leonor Mariscal, 70 years old, does just that for her fellow villagers. In her tiny ramshackle building, once a chicheria itself, she steeps the corn and lets it germinate a bit on a large piece of cloth laid out in the sun, directly on the cobblestone street in front of her building. The sun is sometimes hot enough to dry out her corn malt, but she admits to using ashes sometimes to complete the process. She then bags the malt and lets the area chicha brewers grind this corn into a flour at their own breweries. &amp;hellip;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The fermentation therefore seems to be nearly entirely carried out by the natural content of the corn. Many traditional cochabambina brewers like Doña Narcissa do not seem aware that the lactic acid bacteria contained within the corn is the true origin of the alcohol, light fizz and acidic flavor of their brew. But what matters is that they are always able to quench chicha lovers' thirst for delicate tartness; the science behind their brewing methods isn&amp;rsquo;t a major concern.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Outside Latin America, the one thing most people remember about &lt;em>chicha&lt;/em> is that it&amp;rsquo;s often fermented with human saliva. In particular, &lt;em>chicha de jora&lt;/em> (&lt;em>jora&lt;/em> is a specific kind of yellow maize) is typically prepared by chewing said corn into a clump before fermenting it into a boozy concoction. Since the starch in corn is well locked into the grain kernel and thus unavailable for fermentation on its own, chewing allows the enzymes (e.g. amylases) in your mouth to break down the starch into sugar.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-4/20230604_224406.jpg"
alt="malted yellow corn"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>malted yellow corn from Grouse Malt House&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The chewing inevitably raises many eyebrows. The idea of consuming a drink brewed from someone else&amp;rsquo;s saliva is viscerally disturbing, particularly in the post-COVID era. Using saliva as a fermentation starter is not unique to South America, however; there&amp;rsquo;s evidence that chewing as a way of kicking off fermentation was practiced in prehistoric Europe before the emergence of malting; Finnish folklore tells the legend of a woman by the name of Kalevatar, who invented beer by mixing honey with bear saliva; some traditional Japanese &lt;em>sakes&lt;/em>, such as &lt;em>kuchikamizake&lt;/em> (口噛み酒, meaning &amp;ldquo;mouth-chewed &lt;em>sake&lt;/em>&amp;quot;), are made from chewed rice; and &lt;em>kava&lt;/em>, produced by the peoples of the Pacific Islands from chewing the roots of kava (aka. &lt;em>Piper methysticum G. Forst&lt;/em>), was born in this way.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Fetishes and aesthetics aside, saliva contains diverse microbiomes, and each person&amp;rsquo;s saliva is different and therefore gives different flavors to the fermented product.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;ve been smitten with grain corns. You may remember the loaf of &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/byb-4/">blue corn bread&lt;/a> I made with East Coast ale yeast a few weeks ago. This time, inspired by the wonderful Peruvian corn dishes and drinks I had in Key West, I&amp;rsquo;d like to up the corn percentage and make a Portuguese-style &lt;em>broa de milho&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-4/20230606_161110.jpg"
alt="broa de milho"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Portuguese-style &lt;em>broa de milho&lt;/em> (corn bread), crumbshot.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;h3 id="corn-mash">Corn mash&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Some brewers have described dealing with malted corn as &amp;ldquo;pure, unadulterated pain from hell&amp;rdquo; that comes in many folds:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Malted corn has low diastatic power &amp;ndash; barely 35 °L. That&amp;rsquo;s hardly enough to fully convert itself, and requires exogenous amylase from either malted barley or powdered additive.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Corn has a higher gelatinization temperature than barley to break apart the starch molecules. Boiling corn would do the trick. However, high temperatures will kill those natural enzymes meant to convert the starches to fermentable sugars.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Also, while corncobs as a whole do have husks, the corn kernels do not contain husks, making lautering comparable to the 9th layer of hell. Luckily, this challenge doesn&amp;rsquo;t exist in solid beer (aka. bread).&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Undermodifed malts, including corn, have dimethyl sulfide (DMS) in spades, so when you combine the two you may develop unpleasant off-flavors if the proper precautions aren&amp;rsquo;t taken.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>You know, none of this sounds that excruciating to me.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you really are a single-malt purist, you will&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>chew the corn to break it into smaller bits for the mash and add the enzymes from your saliva that will break down the starches to sugars; or&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>go through European-style triple-decoction mashing.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>If you aren&amp;rsquo;t that much of a purist, then you need to add exogenous enzymes. One way is to add dry amylase powder; another is to use some pale barley malt to get the enzymes.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-4/20230605_004913.jpg"
alt="malted yellow corn"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Freshly ground malted yellow corn delivers an earthy, sweet flavor reminiscent of a classic Southern cornbread.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>I wanted to do the single-malt triple-decoction mashing, because mashing is fun and I had never done an all-corn mash before.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>%&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>yellow corn malt (Grouse Malt House)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>375g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>tap water&lt;/td>
&lt;td>87.2%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>327g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Total: 702g&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Since maize doesn&amp;rsquo;t contain large amounts of phytase, acid rest isn&amp;rsquo;t necessary.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I started the mixture at ~125°F where I left it for 2 hours (protein rest). Then I decocted 1/3 of the mash and boiled it for 2 minutes. I tasted a small sample of the decoction &amp;ndash; it was insanely sweet, and reminded me of a Southern cornbread but slightly more starchy.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>After a few minutes, I added the boiled decoction back to the main mash and it raised the temperature to 150°F. I held the mash at ~150°F for the next 5 hours, turning the stove top burner on occasionally to keep the temperature consistent. Further sweetness didn&amp;rsquo;t begin to manifest until the end of it, with plenty of residual starchiness. So I decocted 1/3 of the mash again, and boiled for 2 minutes; when I returned the decoction to the main mash, it brought up the temperature to 158°F, where I left it for another 2.5 hours. Lastly, I decocted 1/3 of the mash again, raising the temperature of the main mash to 168°F &amp;ndash; and held it there for 1 hour.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>After all that, starch was no longer perceivable to my tongue. The saccharified corn mash had the fragrance of sweet corn cookies, with intriguing background notes of chestnuts. It tasted insanely sweet and malty, and had a distinct caramelized corn flavor &amp;ndash; almost like a corn muffin. I quite enjoyed the mash, and honestly could have devoured it as is (like a breakfast porridge or dessert).&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="corn-barm">Corn barm&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Once the saccharified corn mash had cooled off to body temperature, I measured 150g out into a separate bowl for yeast inoculation, reserving the remaining 552g in the fridge until needed.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>%&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>saccharified corn mash&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>150g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Framgarden liquid yeast (Escarpment Labs)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1.5g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Total: 151.5g&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Framgarden expresses a tropical profile with lots of pineapple leading the way and subtler notes of hay and white pepper in the background.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Escarpment&amp;rsquo;s recommended temperature range for Framgarden is quite wide (68-95°F). I let the inoculated mash ferment, loosely covered, at 80-85°F for 12 hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="yeasted-rye-soaker">Yeasted rye soaker&lt;/h3>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>%&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Gazelle rye flour, 100% extraction&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>75g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>London Tropics liquid yeast (Berkeley Yeast)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>75g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Total: 150g (100% extraction = whole grain)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I mixed the wholegrain rye flour with the yeast slurry until thoroughly hydrated, and let the mixture ferment (loosely covered) at ~68°F for 12 hours. I didn&amp;rsquo;t expect this to biotransform or ferment much &amp;ndash; it was more of a soaker (à la Peter Reinhart&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em>Whole Grain Breads&lt;/em>) that utilized excess liquid yeast, in this case, to thoroughly hydrate the whole grains and enhance flavors in the final bread.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Oh boy, biotransformation kicked off as soon as I mixed everything together; the artificial fruit aroma didn&amp;rsquo;t get as overwhelming as in my first &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/byb-5-1/">POG bomb&lt;/a>, but very noticeable. I started to regret underestimating this &amp;ldquo;weapon of mass thiolization&amp;rdquo;&amp;hellip;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>After ~12 hours, the soaker showed slight signs of fermentation and smelled pungently fruity &amp;ndash; Mr. Fusion-powered DeLorean time machine was back in full stride. A hyperrealistic simulacrum. A hallucinatory fantasy. It reminded me of a quote from Jean Baudrillard:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;What every society looks for in continuing to produce, and to overproduce, is to restore the real that escapes it.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Interestingly, Untitled Art in Waunakee, WI just released a &lt;a href="https://www.drinkuntitled.com/product/non-alcoholic-berliner-weisse/">non-alcoholic &lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em>&lt;/a> brewed with London Tropics, de-alcoholized with membrane filtration technologies.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Since thiols are more soluble in alcohols than in water, doesn&amp;rsquo;t the filtration remove quite a bit of the thiols as well? I wonder how much of the fruity aroma/flavor from Tropics remains in the NA beer. As far as I know, de-alcoholization generally removes the fermentation products &amp;ndash; which can be added back in, but that process can be pretty violent to the flavor structure of the beer and, most notably, quite expensive.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Wouldn&amp;rsquo;t arrested fermentation (e.g. interrupting full attenuation) with Tropics make more sense in producing NA beers? In my bread experiments, London Tropics kicks off biotransformation waaaay before attenuation.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="final-dough">Final dough&lt;/h3>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>%&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>einkorn flour, 100% extraction&lt;/td>
&lt;td>50.0%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>khorasan wheat flour, 100% extraction&lt;/td>
&lt;td>50.0%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>corn mash&lt;/td>
&lt;td>276.0%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>552g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>corn barm&lt;/td>
&lt;td>75.8%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>151.5g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>yeasted rye soaker&lt;/td>
&lt;td>75.0%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>150g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sea salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2.0%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>4g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>(100% extraction = whole grain)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I mixed all of the ingredients together into a homogeneous dough, and let it ferment at ~73°F for 2 hours. Then I shaped it into a &lt;em>boule&lt;/em>, and placed it in a proofing colander liberally coated with toasted oat bran. The dough was left to proof at ~58°F for 14 hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Once I got the BBQ grill to 400°F, I flipped the dough into a cast-iron skillet and slid it onto the grill. I added black walnut shells to the bottom of the grill, closed the lid, and let the bread bake at 400°F for 1 hour.⁠&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-4/20230606_131550.jpg"
alt="broa de milho"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Portuguese-style &lt;em>broa de milho&lt;/em> (corn bread), in cast-iron skillet.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Summer is a completely different experience when you know how to grill.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The crust came out thick, smoky, charred, and crunchy; the inside moist and tender, plush with a flavor that absolutely reverberated with corn. Mouthfuls of smokiness, too. The tropical fruit profile got subdued by the wonderful smoky flavor of open-fire bakery.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It&amp;rsquo;s that perfect, forever corn bread that I want to bring to the beach. The summer wish I never knew I had.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-4/20230606_161227.jpg"
alt="broa de milho"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Portuguese-style &lt;em>broa de milho&lt;/em> (corn bread), crumbshot.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>This corn bread went so well with summer salads and snacky things. I took it to a park today, along with some butter (not optional), and enjoyed the hell out of it under a tree, while watching the clouds float across the sky.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>And so with the sunshine and the great bursts of leaves growing on the trees, just as things grow in fast movies, I had that familiar conviction that life was beginning over again with the summer.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&amp;ndash; F. Scott Fitzgerald&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote></content></item><item><title>levure de bière #5.3: Tropical buckwheat dream</title><link>/posts/byb-5-3/</link><pubDate>Thu, 25 May 2023 01:54:31 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/byb-5-3/</guid><description>An audacious &lt;em>Buchweizenbrot&lt;/em> (46.88% caramel buckwheat malt + 46.88% ancient grains + 6.25% pale barley malt). Mixed-fermentations with Escarpment Labs' traditional Latvian Kolnasāta, Berkeley Yeast&amp;rsquo;s GM thiolized London Tropics, and Imperial Yeast&amp;rsquo;s Suburban Brett. Boldly earth, charmingly fruity, and deeply satisfying.</description><content>&lt;p>&lt;em>Beer = liquid bread. Want to stay updated on my &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/craft-beer-yeast">craft beer yeast bread-plays&lt;/a>? Subscribe to the &lt;a href="https://tinyletter.com/breadbuster">newsletter&lt;/a>!&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;m surprised how many people watch only HBO and whatever the Netflix algorithm recommends. It&amp;rsquo;s kind of like the folks who email me asking factual questions &amp;ndash; have they never heard of the internet? There&amp;rsquo;s a vast cornucopia of streaming series out there; if you pick the right one, your life will be enhanced.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Last night I watched the final two episodes of &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Farzi">Farzi&lt;/a>&amp;rdquo; while licking a plate of buttery &lt;a href="https://authenticsimplifiedrecipes.wordpress.com/2019/02/21/pav-bhaji/">&lt;em>pav bhaji&lt;/em>&lt;/a>. When the show was over, I spontaneously exclaimed, &amp;ldquo;That was great!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Frankly, not as great as &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Bureau_(TV_series)">&lt;em>Le Bureau des Légendes&lt;/em>&lt;/a>&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt2324587/">&lt;em>Počivali u miru&lt;/em>&lt;/a>&amp;rdquo;, but really fulfilling. And it&amp;rsquo;s hard to find those shows these days.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;Farzi&amp;rdquo; is about the rigid caste system in India, where upward mobility is extremely limited. But that doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean you can&amp;rsquo;t dream. Opportunities are closed. But that doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean you&amp;rsquo;re not smart or willful.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Most people are so addicted to brands (e.g. HBO or Apple TV+). They watch only light stuff like comedy; they say real life is daunting enough, they don&amp;rsquo;t want to be brought down by a show.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>That&amp;rsquo;s what life is all about: new experiences, stretching your horizons, because otherwise you&amp;rsquo;d end up living on repeats, waiting to die.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Which is why I&amp;rsquo;ve been experimenting with uncommon grains.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Wheat has been the hegemony in the bread world, while barley reigns supreme in the brewing industry. Malt has become synonymous with barley the way that flour has with wheat, but malt can be made from any type of (pseudo)grain.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="buckwheat">Buckwheat&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The only exposure most people in the West have to buckwheat is in pancakes, which is quite sad.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-3/20230520_124107.jpg"
alt="buckwheat soba"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Handmade &lt;em>soba&lt;/em> noodles from scratch, with caramel buckwheat malt, &lt;em>bonito&lt;/em>, London Tropics liquid yeast, and sourdough starter. All done within 30 minutes by a newbie! Contrary to popular belief, it doesn&amp;rsquo;t take 10 years of training to master making 100% &lt;em>soba&lt;/em> noodles.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Buckwheat (&lt;em>Fagopyrum sagittatum syn. F. esculentum&lt;/em>) is a curious and misunderstood food. It&amp;rsquo;s not a &amp;ldquo;wheat&amp;rdquo;, but is treated like one. It&amp;rsquo;s actually a shrub, related to rhubarb; it produces seeds on the flower heads. These seeds (or kernels) are what get ground into flour.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Like other seeds, buckwheat is high in both protein (18% by weight!) and fiber, but it&amp;rsquo;s unique among the seeds we typically eat, because it&amp;rsquo;s mainly composed of carbs, with lower fat and higher starch content than, say, sunflower seeds or chia seeds. IMO, buckwheat has a well-balanced starch, protein, fat, and mineral composition, and is absolutely delicious. Hands-down one of my favorite &amp;ldquo;cereals.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Buckwheat was long thought to have originated in central Asia, somewhere between Lake Baikal and Manchuria. Recent &lt;a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/BF02861199">research&lt;/a> now leans toward southwest China and the Himalayan region as the center of origin. The two cultivated species of buckwheat, &lt;em>Fagopyrum esculentum&lt;/em> (common buckwheat) and &lt;em>Fagopyrum tataricum&lt;/em> (tartary buckwheat) are Chinese domesticates, presumably originating in upland southwest China, outside the major rice and millet centers.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Buckwheat is known as &lt;em>grano saraceno&lt;/em> in Italian and &lt;em>sarrasin&lt;/em> in French, leading the late food writer Waverly Root to assume that buckwheat originated in Asia Minor and was introduced by either the Turks, the Crusaders, and/or the Moors to places in Europe where other grains didn&amp;rsquo;t grow well and where the people ate &amp;ldquo;robustly&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; such as Brittany, Finland, Styria, central France and the Tyrolian Alps. Europeans of the Middle Ages, however, used the term &amp;ldquo;saracen&amp;rdquo; to describe many things that simply came from the East, whether they were Arabian or not.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>According to the contemporary Italian botanist Valerio Giacomini, who has made a thorough study of buckwheat, there are three possible ways buckwheat arrived in Europe:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>through southern Russia, Poland, and Germany &amp;ndash;&amp;gt; Belgium and France;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>through Turkey &amp;ndash;&amp;gt; Greece, Hungary, and southern Russia; and&lt;/li>
&lt;li>through the maritime contacts of Venice, which might explain in part the ascription of &amp;ldquo;saracen.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>There is a legend that Joos van Ghistele brought it back with him from his journey to the Holy Land in 1485. Who knows. In any case, the origin of buckwheat is unknown, even if its name in Latin languages suggests an Arab provenance. The plant&amp;rsquo;s English name, &amp;ldquo;buckwheat&amp;rdquo;, came from the Dutch word for &amp;ldquo;beech&amp;rdquo; (&lt;em>boec&lt;/em>) and wheat, because it can be used in food, like wheat.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-3/20230520_131249.jpg"
alt="buckwheat soba"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>100% buckwheat &lt;em>soba&lt;/em> noodles made with caramel buckwheat malt, &lt;em>bonito&lt;/em>, London Tropics liquid yeast, and a little sourdough starter; cooked in &lt;em>kombu dashi&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>What seems certain, though, is that buckwheat has been a traditional food around the world, particularly in regions with short growing seasons and poor soil. Eastern Europeans eat a porridge of toasted buckwheat groats (&lt;em>kasha&lt;/em>). In the mountainous valley of Lombardy, Italy, a traditional winter dish is &lt;em>pizzoccheri&lt;/em>, basically short buckwheat pasta tossed with butter, cabbage, cheese, garlic, and sage &amp;ndash; a poor &amp;ldquo;peasant&amp;rdquo; tradition.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Buckwheat has a rich history in the United States as well, unlike other ancient grains. It was common during the Colonial era, but began to decline in popularity after the Civil War ended.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="malted-buckwheat">Malted buckwheat&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>I had the good fortune of experimenting with some caramel buckwheat malt from &lt;a href="https://grousemalthouse.com/">Grouse Malt House&lt;/a>, a dedicated gluten-free craft malthouse in Wellington, Colorado. (I was not looking for gluten-free alternatives &lt;em>per se&lt;/em>, but rather malts made from uncommon grains. Grouse has been crafting a ton of those since ~2013.)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The dark, triangular-shaped hulls covering the buckwheat seeds are left on, to help brewers lauter/filter more easily. The hull is very tough, but is edible when ground and provides a good source of fiber. Even after soaking and boiling, though, unhulled buckwheat is too chewy and too earthy for most people&amp;rsquo;s palates.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-3/20230522_200750.jpg"
alt="Grouse BK1060 caramel buckwheat malt"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Caramel buckwheat malt (BK1060), from Grouse Malt House (Wellington, Colorado).&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>This malt, out of the box, smelled like a forest right after a rain.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Buckwheat can be milled with or without the hull. The traditional method is milling with the hulls. And yes, some millers even add extra hulls. Flour ground from unhulled buckwheat will be greyish, with tiny black specks &amp;ndash; it looks darker and tastes a tad stronger than flour made from hulled buckwheat (groats).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>When freshly ground, this caramel buckwheat malt has an unmistakable earthy aroma &amp;ndash; it creates a woodsy vibe that&amp;rsquo;s bold but not overly aggressive, evoking mental imagery of a deep, verdant forest. There&amp;rsquo;s also a little sunflower seed-like nutty aroma. It tastes predominantly earthy &amp;ndash; like unmalted buckwheat or yellow split peas &amp;ndash; with a hint of malty sweetness. Just how I like my buckwheat, despite the lack of a quintessential &amp;ldquo;caramel&amp;rdquo; malt vibe.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-3/20230522_201317.jpg"
alt="Grouse BK1060 caramel buckwheat malt"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Freshly ground caramel buckwheat malt (BK1060), from Grouse Malt House. Listed color value is 3-6 SRM.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Many Westerners don&amp;rsquo;t like that robust flavor of unhulled buckwheat. So there&amp;rsquo;s a large market for buckwheat flour &lt;em>sans&lt;/em> the hulls.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I know pretty well how buckwheat performs and tastes in food, but in beer? I&amp;rsquo;m not so sure. Enzymatic activities are &lt;a href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/228618138_The_Impact_of_Kilning_on_Enzymatic_Activity_of_Buckwheat_Malt">found&lt;/a> to be low in pale buckwheat malt. I would probably agree with what &lt;a href="https://www.homebrewtalk.com/threads/buckwheat-questions.449416/#post-5789674">this brewer&lt;/a> said about buckwheat:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>I suspect that you will be disappointed with the flavor and diastatic power of pale-malt buckwheat, though. If my experience with Colorado Malting Company&amp;rsquo;s buckwheat malt is any indicator, about the only way to coax any flavor out of it is to make crystal malt; but even that doesn&amp;rsquo;t do much, considering very little saccharification takes place during the crystal-making process so you don&amp;rsquo;t get much in the way of caramelized sugars. The only use I have for buckwheat in my beers is unmalted as an adjunct to improve head retention (the malted stuff doesn&amp;rsquo;t do as well in that regard due to changes in protein contents), or else roasted really dark, as a stand-in for Briess &amp;ldquo;Midnight Wheat&amp;rdquo; to impart a smooth roast character to darker beers.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Which is why I picked &amp;ldquo;caramel&amp;rdquo; buckwheat malt, not the other two buckwheat options (BK1001 pale and BK1100 roasted) offered by Grouse.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Caramel malt is typically made from &amp;ldquo;green malt&amp;rdquo; (wet germinated malt) or rehydrated base malt, mashed at 140-160°F so that the amylase in each individual grain kernel degrades the starch within into simple sugars, and subsequently dried out at &amp;gt;=170°F, which causes the sugars inside the malt to crystallize. It also causes the sugars and nitrogen-based compounds (mostly amino acids and proteins) to combine to form melanoidins. The major variable in the process is the kilning temperature, which determines the depth of the color and the degree of caramelization. The higher the drying temperature, the darker the color will be.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>During roasting, most (if not all) of the enzymes in the malt become denatured, and many of the sugars in the malt become caramelized and thus unfermentable, which is why caramel malt is usually used (like an adjunct) to add sweetness and body to the finished beer, instead of as a base malt.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="buckwheat-mash">Buckwheat mash&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>In &amp;ldquo;caramel&amp;rdquo; malts made from common grains like barley and wheat, the starch is already gelatinized and saccharified in the core. Malted buckwheat gelatinizes at a temperature that is higher than that at which the amylase becomes denatured. To get any significant fermentables out of buckwheat, a decoction mash or exogenous enzymes may be necessary. Andrew Lavery has some &lt;a href="https://glutenfreehomebrewing.com/lavery_brewing_tutorial.php">good info&lt;/a> on mashing gluten-free grains.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Total dry malts: 80g&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>%&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>pale barley malt (Genie - Gallatin Valley Malt)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>50%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>40g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>caramel buckwheat malt (Grouse Malt House)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>50%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>40g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>water&lt;/td>
&lt;td>125%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Total: 180g&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I mixed everything together and did a triple-decoction mash starting at 95°F:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>30 minutes at 95°F&lt;/li>
&lt;li>1 hour at ~113°F&lt;/li>
&lt;li>1 hour at ~130°F (decocted 1/3 at the end; boiled for 5 minutes)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>3 hours at ~150°F (decocted 1/3 at the end; and boiled for 5 minutes)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>1 hour at ~160°F (decocted 1/3 at the end; boiled for 5 minutes)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>1 hour at ~170°F&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>The buckwheat malt soaks up water like a sponge, so this mash turned out very thick. It smelled mildly sweet and smoky, reminiscent of toasted sesame seeds. Not at all what you&amp;rsquo;d expect with a typical &amp;ldquo;caramel&amp;rdquo; malt made from barley or wheat.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>After saccharification, the mash tasted sweet-ish and boldly buckwheaty.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="buckwheat-barm">Buckwheat barm&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>A lot of people consider the flavor of buckwheat to be in the same general category as rye, but far more rustic, earthy, and flavorful than any of the routinely used grains. Part of that character derives from buckwheat&amp;rsquo;s caprylic acid content. Caprylic acid (octanoic acid) is a medium-chain fatty acid that is naturally found in palm oil, coconut oil, and milk. It&amp;rsquo;s a part of medium-chain triglyceride (MCT) products, and believed to have potent antibacterial, antifungal, and anti-inflammatory properties. FYI, &lt;em>capr&lt;/em>- comes from Latin &lt;em>capra&lt;/em>, meaning &amp;ldquo;goat&amp;rdquo;; a lot of people say buckwheat adds a load of &amp;ldquo;goaty&amp;rdquo; flavor, which I disagree with.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-3/20230522_205356.jpg"
alt="Buckwheat mash, before fermentation"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>50% buckwheat 50% barley mash, before fermentation.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>One great thing about some &amp;ldquo;off&amp;rdquo;-tasting fatty acids is that they provide appealing aromas after &lt;em>Brettanomyces&lt;/em> combines them with a molecule of ethanol to form an ester. Buckwheat has been &lt;a href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/228761224_Processing_of_a_Top_Fermented_Beer_Brewed_from_100_Buckwheat_Malt_with_Sensory_and_Analytical_Characterisation">researched&lt;/a> for its possible caprylic acid contribution to &lt;em>Brettanomyces&lt;/em> fermentation, during which the Brett might convert these fatty acid precursors to create ethyl caprylate, an ester often described as sweet, waxy, floral, fruity, pineapple, and wine.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Stage 1: Kolnasāta&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>%&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>saccharified mash&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>180g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Kolnasāta liquid yeast (Escarpment Labs)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>0.5%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Total: 181g&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I added 1g of liquid &lt;a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20220925144154/https://escarpmentlabs.com/products/the-kveik-ring-kolnasata">Kolnasāta&lt;/a>, a continental European farmhouse ale yeast sourced from Bērzpils, Latvia by Escarpment Labs.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-3/20230522_105944.jpg"
alt="Kolnasāta from Escarpment Labs"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Kolnasāta liquid yeast from Escarpment Labs (Guelph, Ontario)&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Kolnasāta is traditionally used to &lt;a href="https://www.kulinaraismantojums.lv/en/biedri/home-producers/production-of-home-brewed-beer-kolnasata/">brew beers at home in Latgale&lt;/a> (aka. the land of blue lakes), a historical region in eastern Latvia. The brewing usually takes place in wooden tuns, and calls for locally-grown barley malt that&amp;rsquo;s dried in a smoke sauna.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This yeast is expected to produce &amp;ldquo;ample doses of pineapple esters along with medium attenuation and flocculation.&amp;rdquo; I thought this profile would pair well with the other yeasts I was going to add to the barm later on.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Escarpment&amp;rsquo;s recommended temperature range for Kolnasāta is 68-86°F, so I let the inoculated mash (aka. barm) ferment, loosely covered, at 80-84°F for 12 hours. The barm began to show signs of fermentation and exude a subtle fruity aroma like peach and pineapple.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Stage 2: London Tropics&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>%&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>stage 1 barm&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>181g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>London Tropics (Berkeley Yeast)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>0.5%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>0.9g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Total: 181.9g&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Next, I added 0.9g of London Tropics from Berkeley Yeast. This London ale yeast-derived thiolized strain produced a POG bomb in a &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/byb-5-1/">previous experiment&lt;/a>, and I&amp;rsquo;d like to tone down the thiol level this time to see how the final bread might turn out.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-1/20230429_140316.jpg"
alt="London Tropics from Berkeley Yeast"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>London Tropics liquid yeast from Berkeley Yeast (Oakland, California)&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Berkeley&amp;rsquo;s recommended temperature range for London Tropics is 64-72°F. I let the barm ferment at 66-70°F for 24 hours. By the end, the thick mash had nearly risen by 50%-70% and felt fluffy. It smelled much more fruity, pleasantly balanced between guava and pineapple.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Stage 3: Brettanomyces&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I intended to add 2g of &lt;em>Brettanomyces bruxellensis&lt;/em>. Due to a squirting accident with the homebrew pouch, I ended up adding 6g of the liquid yeast. The 6% inoculation rate was not intentional, but it is what it is.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>%&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>stage 2 barm&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>181.9g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Suburban Brett (Imperial Yeast)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>3.3%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>6g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Total: 187.9g&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I let this barm sit in my fermentation fridge (set to ~45°F) for 4 days. The barm puffed up like my Italian &lt;em>lievito madre&lt;/em>, and developed a more complex aroma that was very pleasing, but hard to put into words.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="buckwheat-soaker">Buckwheat soaker&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>I thought another way to get the best flavor out of buckwheat is to cold-soak it for 12+ hours. Let hydrolysis do all the work.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>%&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>caramel buckwheat malt (Grouse Malt House)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>92.9%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>260g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>golden flax seeds, whole&lt;/td>
&lt;td>7.1%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>20g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>water (room temperature)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>120%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>336g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sea salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2.8g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Total: 618.8g&lt;/p>
&lt;p>After mixing everything together, I let the stiff paste rest, covered, at room temperature for 2 hours; then I moved it into the fridge (~38°F) and left it there until needed.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-3/20230522_223804.jpg"
alt="Buckwheat soaker"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Caramel buckwheat malt soaker, with golden flax seeds and sea salt.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;h4 id="final-dough">Final dough&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>Total flours: 300g (100%)&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>%&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>einkorn flour, 100% extraction&lt;/td>
&lt;td>65%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>195g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Asturian spelt flour, 100% extraction&lt;/td>
&lt;td>20%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>60g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Ethiopian Blue Tinge emmer flour, 100% extraction&lt;/td>
&lt;td>15%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>45g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>water (room temperature)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>73.3%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>220g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>buckwheat soaker&lt;/td>
&lt;td>206.3%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>618.8g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>buckwheat barm&lt;/td>
&lt;td>62.7%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>187.9g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sea salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>3g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Total: 1,329.7g (100% extraction = whole grain)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I mixed all ingredients together into a supple and sticky dough.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>bulk fermentation: 2 hours at ~70°F (the dough started to ferment so fast that I had to slow it down by chilling it) + 14 hours at ~45°F&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>final proof: 3 hours at ~70°F&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>bake: 45 minutes in total; 10 minutes at 400°F and 35 minutes at 350°F.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>I was delightfully surprised by how much the bread rose during fermentation and baking.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-3/20230524_160701.jpg"
alt="Buckwheat bread sliced"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>Buchweizenbrot&lt;/em> (German-style buckwheat bread), freshly sliced.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The bread had a pleasant fruity fragrance, far less overpowering than in my &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/byb-5-1/">first experiment&lt;/a>. I detected some tantalizing notes of pineapple with a hint of lemon. The subtle tropical complexity and breezy tiki vibe complemented the toasty, earthy aroma of buckwheat quite nicely.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Flavor-wise, it was predominantly earthy buckwheat (reminding me of toasted black sesame seeds), with a charming malty character and mildly fruity undertone. I liked it, a lot. While biting into it, I pictured myself in a hammock swaying on a sun-soaked island in the Black Sea.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-3/20230524_161334.jpg"
alt="Buckwheat bread sliced"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>Buchweizenbrot&lt;/em> (German-style buckwheat bread), crumbshot.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>If you grew up poor like me and got used to eating &amp;ldquo;peasant food&amp;rdquo; like &lt;em>galettes de sarrasin&lt;/em>, &lt;em>kissel&lt;/em>, &lt;em>inaka soba&lt;/em>, etc., then you&amp;rsquo;ll most likely find the deep and earthy flavor of unhulled buckwheat satisfying and nourishing. Otherwise, it&amp;rsquo;s probably an acquired taste.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I guess quartering thiol levels in this bread worked out well. Once again, more isn&amp;rsquo;t (always) better. It&amp;rsquo;s all about understanding what you want to achieve and how your yeast will behave. Recipes are very overrated.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-3/20230524_160927.jpg"
alt="Buckwheat bread sliced"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>Buchweizenbrot&lt;/em> (German-style buckwheat bread)&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>🍻🍻🍻🍻&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Special thanks to Richard Preiss (&lt;a href="https://escarpmentlabs.com/">Escarpment Labs&lt;/a>) for offering me the opportunity to experiment with unique yeasts.&lt;/p></content></item><item><title>levure de bière #5.2: Tropical Chico bomboloni</title><link>/posts/byb-5-2/</link><pubDate>Mon, 15 May 2023 02:02:44 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/byb-5-2/</guid><description>Experimental thiol-complimentary wholegrain &lt;em>bomboloni&lt;/em> (yeasted Italian donuts), via co-fermentation of 2 yeast strains: California ale yeast and thiolized London Tropics. An intentionally austere dough that highlights the yeast&amp;rsquo;s super power.</description><content>&lt;p>&lt;em>Beer = liquid bread. Want to stay updated on my &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/craft-beer-yeast">craft beer yeast bread-plays&lt;/a>? Subscribe to the &lt;a href="https://tinyletter.com/breadbuster">newsletter&lt;/a>!&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Since making that &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/byb-5-1/">POG bomb&lt;/a> with Berkeley&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href="https://berkeleyyeast.com/strains/london-tropics/">London Tropics&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://berkeleyyeast.com/boost/thiol/">Thiol Boost&lt;/a>, I&amp;rsquo;ve been thinking a lot about the goldmine of thiol precursors in malts &amp;ndash; and malts alone.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Given a lot more thiol precursors come from malts than hops, it probably makes more sense to play with different base malts and malt varieties than with new age hops.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>German scientists have devised &lt;a href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/full/10.1021/acs.jafc.0c06305">a solvent-free, automated method&lt;/a> for brewers to measure and track hop-derived thiols during the brewing process. How cool would it be, to be able to quantify the amount of thiol precursors in different malts, and find out which malt varieties pair the best with a particular thiolized yeast?&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-2/montana_barley_green.jpg"
alt="Montana barley into harvest"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Gorgeous barley heading into harvest, on Karl De Jonge&amp;rsquo;s farm in Gallatin Valley, Montana.&lt;/p>&lt;p>Source: &lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/gallatinvalleymaltco/photos/a.707201556296362/978615135821668/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">Gallatin Valley Malt Co.&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Most maltsters don&amp;rsquo;t list information about their grain varieties, only generic info like the malt type (pale, pilsner, crystal, etc). To find out the specific varietals of grains the malts are made from, I&amp;rsquo;ve had to ask the maltsters directly for COAs (certificates of analysis).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;ve worked with enough grains (of different varieties) to know that the varietal can make a big difference in the end-product, e.g. a bread made from 100% &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/turkey-red/">Turkey Red&lt;/a> is noticeably different from one made from 100% &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/joaquin-oro/">Joaquin Oro&lt;/a> or &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/white-sonora/">Sonora Blanca&lt;/a>. In pale ales, modern barley varieties like Metcalfe and Copeland from Montana or western Canada may be more suited to the American style than the others, while heirloom varieties like Golden Promise or Maris Otter add a bit of nutty character to British variations.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Many brewers proudly describe their base malts &amp;ndash; the vast majority of the grist in most beers &amp;ndash; simply as &amp;ldquo;2-row.&amp;rdquo; That label merely indicates it&amp;rsquo;s not the &amp;ldquo;inferior&amp;rdquo;, higher-protein 6-row barley variety. But those are broad categories &amp;ndash; just like &lt;a href="https://newenglandapples.org/2020/10/16/russets-small-size-big-flavor/">russet&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://www.chelseagreen.com/2022/surprisingly-sweet-crab-apples/">crab&lt;/a>, and club are categories of apples (so much for the Johnny Appleseed fairy tale) &amp;ndash; and imply nothing about the actual barley variety, even less about how the grain is malted. Most brewers just take whatever malt variety is available, maybe occasionally thinking about 2-row vs. 6-row, winter vs. summer, maltster vs. maltster, and US-Canada vs. Europe.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As with wheat, I&amp;rsquo;ve learned that if a malt is generic enough to be characterized by just its category, it&amp;rsquo;s not going to give the end-product much flavor or character. But what really made me appreciate malt as a craft, in and of itself, was 2 things:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Learning how to make traditional Baltic peasant rye bread from single-variety grain (rye) during 2020 COVID lockdown. In rural villages in Belarus and Latvia, for example, grandmas still make some of the world&amp;rsquo;s most flavorful (and underrated) breads today &amp;ndash; with only rye flour, water, salt, and natural yeast; they coax incredibly complex flavors out of the unassuming rye kernel through different stages of chemical reactions. That inspired me to malt my own rye for breadmaking: pale rye malt, Russian red fermented rye malt (&lt;em>solod&lt;/em>), chocolate rye malt, and even malt syrup, from different varieties of rye (Abruzzi, Gazelle, Hazlet, Ryman, &lt;em>Svedjerug&lt;/em>, Prima, etc). I was absolutely mesmerized by the different flavor profile and intensity each rye malt (and each rye variety) added to the final bread.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Studying European beer history. European beer styles evolved in tandem with local barley varieties and malt. Particularly in places like Bavaria, &lt;em>Helles&lt;/em> (pale lagers) &amp;ndash; despite being delicately hopped and regularly made with just a single malt &amp;ndash; taste different across breweries, because the malt, which is the whole ballgame, is different. Breweries have access to dozens of different malthouses, each making their pilsner malts slightly differently, from a range of different barley varieties. The same is true &amp;ndash; and even more pronounced &amp;ndash; in the UK, where ale brewers not only know which facility makes their malt, but also have passionate opinions about the barley variety. In cask ales, for example, the differences between different barley varieties and malts are magnified, creating distinct flavors.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-2/montana_barley.jpg"
alt="Montana barley"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Heritage barley near harvest time, on Karl De Jonge&amp;rsquo;s farm in Gallatin Valley, Montana.&lt;/p>&lt;p>Source: &lt;a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/ChQ6zVeLJDc/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">Gallatin Valley Malt Co.&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>One of the factors that contributed to the development of the brewing industry as a whole was the spread of pale malts. In the Late Middle Ages, England had been struggling with wood shortages and switched to using the cheaper coal. A major problem with coal was that it produces sulfurous fumes during burning, and the flavors imparted to malt dried in coal-fueled kilns &amp;ndash; and subsequently the beer &amp;ndash; were &lt;a href="https://www.beeretseq.com/where-theres-smoke-theres-pale-ale/">not acceptable&lt;/a>. Hence, in &lt;em>ye olden times&lt;/em> malt had to be dried over wood, peat, or straw &amp;ndash; all of which infused malt with the smoky character of the heat source and gave it a brown color &amp;ndash; or the best Welsh anthracite, the supply of which was quite limited.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In 1603, &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hugh_Plat">Sir Hugh Plat&lt;/a> suggested that coal might be charred in a manner analogous to the way charcoal is produced from wood. He heated some coal without burning it, which distilled the coal, removed its offensive sulfurous smell, and left a residue with a high carbon content and few impurities. This was coke, which proved to be a highly useful fuel for heating and industry.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The coke process remained unnoticed until 1642, when malt makers in Derbyshire began to employ coke for roasting malt. Coke demonstrated superior qualities over other fuels at the time: It generates a great deal of heat without the attendant soot and smoke, and it allows better thermal control. Coke-dried malt was considered an improvement in quality over wood-dried malt, and brought about an &amp;ldquo;alteration which all England admired.&amp;rdquo; Brewers were finally able to mass-produce a lighter roast of the malt that was not &amp;ldquo;smoked.&amp;rdquo; This malt was called &amp;ldquo;pale,&amp;rdquo; and it led to the creation of what by the end of the 17th century was called &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->&amp;quot;&lt;strong>pale ale&lt;/strong>.&amp;quot;&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --> Coke became the &lt;em>crème de la crème&lt;/em> of fuels in England. Coke-fired blast furnaces made the production of inexpensive cast iron possible, which was one of the factors that drove the Industrial Revolution.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The British Empire was in full sway, with merchants and traders traveling around the world. India was the &amp;ldquo;crown jewel&amp;rdquo; of the empire, hosting a large British military and civilian population with a thirst for beer. The tropical climate in India made local brewing of typical English pale ales impossible. Casks of porters and stouts shipped in from England fared poorly because of the long sea voyage and temperature fluctuations; bottled products produced mixed results as well.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In 1790, George Hogeson of the Bow Brewery in London developed a recipe for pale ale that included a huge increase in hops and a much higher alcohol content (both known to have preservative qualities). The export casks were primed with sugar and dry-hopped prior to shipping. The resulting beer arrived in India unspoiled, but much stronger and hoppier than the domestic version. This &amp;ldquo;India Pale Ale&amp;rdquo; (&lt;strong>IPA&lt;/strong>) quickly became hugely popular and profitable.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Pale malt has a huge advantage over darker malts: It contains more enzymes and more fermentable sugars, which allows for more efficient beer production; the taste of the finished beer is much cleaner, as yeasts are able to break down a higher percentage of the chemical compounds dissolved in wort. This fact was likely not explicitly known to brewers until the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hydrometer#Saccharometer">saccharometer&lt;/a> was invented in the late 18th century. Given that coke was too expensive for commercial brewing back then, pale ales remained mostly exclusive to the households of the wealthy gentry in northern England.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-2/barley-germinating.jpg"
alt="germinating barley"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Germinating barley&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>In the US, light lager was the focus of domestic breweries until ~2000. The specific needs of breweries for producing this style of beer trumped the beer&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;character&amp;rdquo; development. 2-row malt is good enough; the barley and malt industries became streamlined to efficiently produce this neutral, light-flavored product for the purpose of brewing domestic light lagers. This specialization, however, created a structural problem for craft breweries looking for malt flavors &amp;ndash; worse, it led to a zymurgic myopia.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As a result, American breweries don&amp;rsquo;t have nearly the selection of malts that Germans have. Weyermann, a common source, makes a high-quality pilsner malt from 2-row spring barley. Brewers love its strong, distinctive character, which really makes a lager pop. The problem is every lager tastes like Weyermann® pilsner malt, which is why so many breweries in Bavaria use different malthouses to differentiate their beers.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Craft brewing has gone through eras of hop enlightenment and yeast consciousness. Not too long ago, brewers were content with a handful of C-hops and some Chico yeast. Now hop breeders release dozens of new hops a year; yeast labs and yeast varieties are mushrooming. Brewers are constantly tinkering with ingredients to produce new flavors, and highly attuned to subtle differences.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;I ask my maltsters to include the barley variety mix in their analysis data. Having a malt analysis without varietal data is like describing a dog without knowing the breed.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Dan Carey, New Glarus Brewing&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>It seemed like a watershed moment when we first scratched the surface of &amp;ldquo;biotransformation&amp;rdquo; and, subsequently, the effect of ester-rich yeasts on IPAs. As this style has evolved by leaps and bounds, we have gained a better understanding of how hops interact with different processes &amp;ndash; and with yeast.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>How might different base malts affect beers?&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-2/gallatin_malts.jpg"
alt="Gallatin malts steeps"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Color &amp;amp; flavor analysis steeps at Gallatin Valley Malt&lt;/p>&lt;p>Source: &lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/gallatinvalleymaltco/photos/a.707201556296362/1198845917131921/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">Gallatin Valley Malt Co.&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>America does have a number of &lt;a href="https://craftmalting.com/">craft malthouses&lt;/a>. Although many aren&amp;rsquo;t yet able to supply breweries with a reliable source of base malts for a year of regular-production beer, things might change with growing interest that will allow them to increase production and lower prices to compete with mass-produced malts. Some of these craft malts are not only interesting and flavorful, but also benefit the local economy and environment. A world with dozens of small, viable malthouses has the potential to transform beer tremendously, like hops and yeasts did.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For example, the single-origin base malts crafted by &lt;a href="https://www.gallatinvalleymalt.com/">Gallatin Valley Malt&lt;/a> (a farmer-owned craft malthouse in Manhattan, Montana) are quite distinct from the same types I&amp;rsquo;ve tried from several other malthouses (including &lt;a href="https://montanacraftmalt.com/">Montana Craft Malt&lt;/a>, which is located only ~1 hour away from Gallatin Valley Malt).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Heather Sargent, Head Maltstress at Gallatin Valley Malt, articulates the variability to me:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;Malts will generally vary in flavor and analysis between malt houses for several reasons. Where the barley is grown and how it&amp;rsquo;s grown play a huge part in the quality that the Maltster has to work with. Whether or not the grain is blended is another factor. Dry farming vs. irrigated. The way in which the grain is malted. Therefore, brewers can make their determinations based on the outcomes and what they like.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>That means, there are thousands of variations in just the &amp;ldquo;pale malt&amp;rdquo;! And the malt that goes into the recipe matters.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Breweries' chalkboards and printed menus often boast hop varieties, hoping (often correctly) that words like Citra, Enigma, or Lemondrop will entice customers to order a pint.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It&amp;rsquo;s rare, literally unheard of, for a brewery to advertise the malt bill on a menu (although it does show up from time to time on labels). The most overlooked ingredient can mean the difference between an enjoyable pint and a drain pour, and even help a brewery stand out and differentiate itself from the pack.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In what appears to be a fairly mature industry, craft malts have a chance to inject a new wave of innovation into our glasses.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The varieties of the grains that go into the malt are just as important as the hops that go into the wort. And not only the variety, but also the growing region (terroir) affects the malt&amp;rsquo;s flavor, haze, and foam stability.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-2/20230509_175115.jpg"
alt="tropical bomboloni"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Wholegrain thiolized &lt;em>bomboloni&lt;/em> (co-fermentation: London Tropics + California ale yeast)&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>In this experiment, I wanted to change the grains in the malt and see how that would impact the thiols in the final product.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="saccharified-mash">Saccharified mash&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>I limited thiol precursor-loaded, diastatic barley malt to 30% of total grains in the mash; the rest was all adjuncts, as far as diastatic powers and thiol precursors are concerned.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The light-golden &lt;a href="https://www.gallatinvalleymalt.com/gallatin-pale">pale malt&lt;/a> by Gallatin Valley Malt, made from Genie barley (grown, harvested, and malted right on GVM&amp;rsquo;s own farm in Montana&amp;rsquo;s breadbasket, the fertile &lt;a href="https://bozemanmagazine.com/articles/2018/09/04/102964-gallatin-agricultural-history">Gallatin Valley&lt;/a>, in a true field-to-kiln fashion), has an endearing aroma of sweet biscuits out of the box. When freshly ground, the malt tastes like Honey Nut Cheerios with a yummy sunflower seed butter drizzle &amp;ndash; none of the grass/straw/hay notes I&amp;rsquo;ve noticed in pale malts from some other malthouses.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>%&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Oberkülmer spelt flour (unmalted, unsifted)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>40%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>68g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>pale barley malt (Genie - Gallatin Valley Malt)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>30%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>51g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sourdough breadcrumbs, toasted&lt;/td>
&lt;td>30%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>51g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>warm water (~100°F)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>135%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>230g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Total: 400g&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I milled the grains into a flour, and mixed everything with water. I intentionally kept the mash thick, because I wanted to create an Italian &lt;em>lievito madre&lt;/em>-style stiff barm.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The mash then went through&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>30 minutes at ~105°F&lt;/li>
&lt;li>30 minutes at ~114°F&lt;/li>
&lt;li>4 hours at 144-154°F&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>After saccharification, the mash tasted brightly sweet and malty &amp;ndash; it reminded me of &lt;em>cannelés bordelais&lt;/em> drizzled with a decadent caramel sauce. GVM&amp;rsquo;s flagship &lt;a href="https://www.gallatinvalleymalt.com/gallatin-pale">pale malt&lt;/a> well deserved the silver medal at the 2022 Craft Maltsters Guild.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="barm">Barm&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>People seem to love to hate on the &amp;ldquo;Chico&amp;rdquo; strain. I&amp;rsquo;m guessing the main reason is that it&amp;rsquo;s a &amp;ldquo;boring&amp;rdquo; strain that doesn&amp;rsquo;t get you &amp;ldquo;fun&amp;rdquo; flavors like some other yeasts.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Interestingly, Jeremy Myers, head of production for Bachs Biermanufaktur in Saarland, Germany, &lt;a href="https://beerandbrewing.com/cold-healthy-and-crowded-lager-fermentation-simplified/">suggests&lt;/a> using White Labs WLP001 for lagers. He says &amp;ldquo;fermenting cold with that yeast leaves behind a beer with just the kind of clean, crisp flavor we want in a lager.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>IMO, &amp;ldquo;boring&amp;rdquo; strains like WLP001 are clean, versatile, low-ester, and low-phenol. They can be super useful and valuable in the right context. For example, they are &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/wlp001/">terrific for breads&lt;/a> that are intended to highlight a grain&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em>terroir&lt;/em>. If you ferment a few doughs with WLP001, keeping everything the same except the flours (use different varieties of wheat, e.g. Joaquin Oro vs. Sonora Blanca vs. Turkey Red), I bet you&amp;rsquo;d taste different flavors and &amp;ldquo;grain-forwardness&amp;rdquo; in each baked product. At least I did. In the &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/byb-1-2/">whole wheat bread&lt;/a> I made with WLP001, the yeast elevated the character of Turkey Red to such a degree that I never thought it was possible (with sourdough or bread yeast), and produced a stunningly pure, robust wheat flavor without the slightest hint of acidity &amp;ndash; it was like eating a box of Triscuit Original or drinking an American wheat beer. Pure, authentic, natural wheatopia.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Like how the Chico strain drove IPA 2.0 due to its &amp;ldquo;cleanness&amp;rdquo; that emphasizes malt and allows hops to shine through, I think it has the potential to do the same thing for Pizza/Bread 3.0 (especially when coupled with the &amp;ldquo;local grain&amp;rdquo; movement). Clean strains highlight the humble grain and let the grain flavor shine through, much more so than sourdough or bread yeast.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In this case, I scooped out 140g of the cooled mash (260g remaining), and added a 50/50 blend of &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/london-tropics/">London Tropics&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/wlp001/">WLP001 California ale yeast&lt;/a>. I intended to temper the thiol levels and let other characteristics stand out, to create a multi-layered, balanced bouquet of tropical aromas/flavors. (ICYMI, London Tropics proved to be an incredibly powerful &amp;ldquo;weapon of mass thiolization&amp;rdquo; in my &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/byb-5-1/">last experiment&lt;/a>.)&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>%&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>saccharified mash&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>140g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>London Tropics liquid yeast (Berkeley Yeast)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>0.5%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>0.7g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>California ale yeast (WLP001 - White Labs)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>0.5%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>0.7g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Total: 141.4g&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I added both yeasts at the same time, since they have similar optimal temperature range. I let the barm ferment, loosely covered, at 68-72°F for ~18 hours. The barm doubled in volume by the end.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Like &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/byb-5-1/">last time&lt;/a>, POG-type tropical aromas started to manifest ~3 hours in, but never got as pungent, which was expected, since the amount of precursors in the mash was drastically reduced and the inoculation rate of thiolized yeast was halved.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="final-dough">Final dough&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>This time, I decided to make a batch of &lt;em>bomboloni&lt;/em> (yeasted Italian donuts), instead of a loaf of bread. And I intentionally made these &lt;em>bomboloni&lt;/em> much more austere than &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/california-dreamin-5/">the Sonora Blanca version&lt;/a>. I wanted the yeasts to shine, untempered by spices or other add-ins.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>%&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Turkey Red whole wheat flour&lt;/td>
&lt;td>50.0%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>150g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>India Jammu whole wheat flour&lt;/td>
&lt;td>50.0%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>150g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>barm&lt;/td>
&lt;td>47.1%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>141.4g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>saccharified mash&lt;/td>
&lt;td>86.7%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>260g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>tap water&lt;/td>
&lt;td>15.0%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>45g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sea salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1.0%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>3g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Total: 749.4g &amp;mdash;-&amp;gt; makes 12 donuts @ ~62g each&lt;/p>
&lt;p>No sugar in the dough, because I wanted the sweetness to come from the coating on the outside, which would make the layers complement each other as you bite through them. Heterogeneity and contrast!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Unadorned ingredients can make something greater than the sum of its parts.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-2/20230509_174455.jpg"
alt="tropical bomboloni"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Wholegrain thiolized &lt;em>bomboloni&lt;/em> (co-fermentation: London Tropics + California ale yeast)&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The process was straightforward, too.&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Mix everything together into a stiff dough. (The dough smelt gently sweet and fruity, like a floral forest after rain.)&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Bulk ferment at ~72°F for 6 hours. Fold once every 30 mins, 4 times in total.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Retard in the fermentation fridge (~45°F) for 12 hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Divide into 12 pieces (~62g each), and shape into taut balls.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Proof at ~72°F for ~6 hours until doubled in size.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Heat a pot of coconut oil to 350°F; fry for 5-7 minutes on each side until brown and crispy.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Remove from oil and let dry on a wire rack lined with paper towels.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Once cool (but still warm), coat in homemade powdered sugar enhanced with a dash of cinnamon.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-2/20230509_174710.jpg"
alt="tropical bomboloni"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Wholegrain thiolized &lt;em>bomboloni&lt;/em> (co-fermentation: London Tropics + California ale yeast)&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>These donuts had a super fluffy, airy texture, almost completely concealing the fact they were made from unsifted whole grains. They also had a substantial mouthfeel &amp;ndash; quite contrary to the emptiness I always experience when eating donuts from national donut chains, which tend to be so overloaded with sugar that they melt in your mouth like cotton candy (in a bad way).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The tropical aroma was hard to distinguish underneath the cinnamon sugar coating, but a ripe fruit flavor was noticeable in the crumb, alongside an unyielding wheat flavor. It mildly reminded me of Kellogg&amp;rsquo;s Tropical Froot Loops cereal. Definitely not POG bombs this time.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Overall, I think these thiol-complimentary &lt;em>bomboloni&lt;/em> turned out much more balanced and delectable than my &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/byb-5-1/">last thiol-dominant bake&lt;/a> &amp;ndash; once again, proving &amp;ldquo;more isn&amp;rsquo;t always better.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Still, I don&amp;rsquo;t think the flavor was quite right &amp;ndash; it didn&amp;rsquo;t have the multi-layered bouquet of aromas/flavors I was expecting. Something was still amiss.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-2/20230509_175742.jpg"
alt="tropical bomboloni"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Wholegrain thiolized &lt;em>bomboloni&lt;/em> (co-fermentation: London Tropics + California ale yeast)&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Never underestimate what a yeast can do.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>🍻🍻🍻🍻&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Special thanks to&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://berkeleyyeast.com/">Berkeley Yeast&lt;/a>, for generously offering me the opportunity to do these fun thiol experiments.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Heather Sargent (the awesome Head Maltstress at &lt;a href="https://www.gallatinvalleymalt.com/">Gallatin Valley Malt&lt;/a>), for indulging my curiosity in malts and giving me the opportunity to experiment with GVM&amp;rsquo;s high-quality, single-origin malts.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>Peckham, Stephen (1880). &lt;em>Special Reports on Petroleum, Coke, and Building Stones.&lt;/em> United States Census Office. 10th census. p. 53.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/section></content></item><item><title>levure de bière #5.1: thiol and error</title><link>/posts/byb-5-1/</link><pubDate>Mon, 08 May 2023 11:39:22 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/byb-5-1/</guid><description>My very first trip down the thiol rabbit hole. Split-batch bake: one recipe, two experimental thiol-forward breads. One loaf was inoculated with Berkeley Yeast&amp;rsquo;s London Tropics, the other with London Tropics + Thiol Boost. The breads turned out COMPLETELY different. POG bombs.</description><content>&lt;p>&lt;em>Beer = liquid bread. Want to stay updated on my &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/craft-beer-yeast">craft beer yeast bread-plays&lt;/a>? Subscribe to the &lt;a href="https://tinyletter.com/breadbuster">newsletter&lt;/a>!&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p> &lt;/p>
&lt;p> ̶«̶ ̶̶̶ ̶ ̶ ̶̶̶ ̶«̶　🍞 🍻 🍞 🍻  ̶»̶ ̶̶̶ ̶ ̶ ̶̶̶ ̶»̶&lt;/p>
&lt;p> &lt;/p>
&lt;p>ICYMI, there has been a huge thiols-at-all-cost craze going on in the brewing world. Heavily hopped IPAs with novel tropical fruit aromas and flavors have been a massive growth category. Triple New England IPA has consistently topped Untappd&amp;rsquo;s list of highest-average rated beer styles, and 1/3 of Untappd&amp;rsquo;s 120 million check-ins in 2022 were some kind of IPA. (Which makes one wonder about Heineken&amp;rsquo;s new American debut, Heineken® Silver, brewed specifically to meet &lt;em>Americans' distaste for bitter beers&lt;/em>.)&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>In 2022, the top three beer styles for the highest number of overall Untappd check-ins were: American IPA, New England IPA and Imperial IPA (the style distinction between an American and a New England IPA is hard to define as almost all of the world’s top 50 highest rated American IPAs are hazy in appearance). &amp;hellip;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The IPAs of 2013 were so bright you could read that year’s best-of list through any of the beers. Sparkling and golden-amber in colour, they were simply American IPAs and didn’t need a West Coast prefix to make drinkers realise it’s not a hazy New England beer – the whole prospect of a cloudy yellow IPA was still a curiosity. Viewed from 2023, where almost all IPAs (and Pale Ales) are now at least a bit hazy, and many are totally opaque with a mouthfeel often described with adjectives like smooth, thick and juicy, those original West Coasters feel like a throwback. That clean clarity and crispness of flavour has gone sweet and squidgy, and it’s not just the IPAs.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Mark Dredge, &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href="https://www.beer52.com/ferment/article/1605/ten-years-that-changed-beer">Ten years that changed beer&lt;/a>&amp;rdquo;, Beer52&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Commercial breweries and home-brewers all over the world are injecting new products (e.g. Thiolized® yeasts and Phantasm® thiol powder), switching to fancy hops (e.g. Vic Secret™, Amarillo®, Mandarina Bavaria, Nelson Sauvin™, and Motueka™) and hop products (e.g. Cryo Hops®, Incognito®, Salvo™, and SubZero Hop Kief™), and trying new techniques (e.g. mash-hopping) to make &amp;ldquo;thiol bombs.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-1/phantasm-basqueland-2023-04-08.png"
alt="Basqueland Phantasm Crush"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Basqueland Phantasm Crush Hazy IPA, brewed with a whirlpool charge of Phantasm thiol powder and dry-hopped with Nelson Sauvin™, Citra®, and Citra® Cryo Hops®.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The results have been mixed. There are some success stories underneath the hype, but a number of brewers say it&amp;rsquo;s just a cranked-up odd flavor (mostly aroma) that may not even compliment the finished beer.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Evidently, tinkering with thiols takes a lot of &amp;ldquo;trial and error.&amp;rdquo; The wine industry has been researching and creating thiol-optimized strains since ~2004, nearly 20 years before the beer industry.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I wanted to go down the thiol rabbit and see what it was all about.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-1/Stone-phantasm.jpg"
alt="Stone Brewing Patio Magic"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Stone Brewing just released the experimental thiol-packed Patio Magic Double IPA in February 2023. It&amp;rsquo;s brewed with Phantasm thiol powder, as well as the experimental hop 843 developed by Hop Breeding Company. The 8.8% ABV India Pale Ale has amplified orange, berry, floral, and wood notes.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;h3 id="thiology">Thiology&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Over the last several decades, there have been endless studies on the hop plant and the enormous impact hops have had on craft brewing, particularly in America. New hop varieties have been &lt;a href="https://daily.sevenfifty.com/beer-hops-are-going-high-tech/">R&amp;amp;D&amp;rsquo;ed&lt;/a>, specifically focusing on the creation of compounds that humans perceive to impart bold tropical fruit aromas and flavors.&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="embed music-spotify">
&lt;iframe
style="border-radius:12px"
src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/episode/3wt0SOKLtPqdTaGM9FXNAV?utm_source=generator&amp;theme=0"
width="100%"
height="152
"
frameBorder="0"
allowfullscreen=""
allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture">&lt;/iframe>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>American hop varieties are characteristically fruity; they add aromas of citrus, pine, tropical fruit, black currant, sweat, and onion/garlic to beer, thanks to the aromatic compounds that originate in the hops' essential oil, which is comprised predominantly of mono- and sesqui-terpenes (volatile organic compounds that play crucial roles in human perception of table grape and wine flavors), some terpene alcohols, and a tiny bit of sulfur-containing &lt;strong>thiols&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Researchers have found that these biotransformative thiols are the main contributors to the highly sought-after tropical aromas, and thus may be giving certain hop varieties an edge over others. (Biotransformation just means the development of new aromas and flavors when yeast interacts with this &lt;em>smörgåsbord&lt;/em> of compounds.)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Thiols (also called mercaptans, with the general formula R-SH), are sulfur analogs of alcohols.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Three volatile thiol molecules responsible for tropical aromas in beer have been in the spotlight across the winemaking and brewing communities:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>3-mercaptohexanol (&lt;strong>3MH&lt;/strong>), which creates citrus aromas like grapefruit and gooseberry;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>3-mercaptohexyl acetate (&lt;strong>3MHA&lt;/strong>), which can come across as guava or passion fruit; and&lt;/li>
&lt;li>4-mercapto-4-methylpentan-2-one (&lt;strong>4MMP&lt;/strong>), which the nose recognizes as black current or wood aromas.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Instead of smelling sulfury like rotten eggs, these free, volatile thiols have tropical and fruity aromas.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As you can see, the first 2 molecules &amp;ndash; 3MH and its acetate ester, 3MHA &amp;ndash; are almost solely responsible for imparting strong tropical fruit aromas.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-1/what-are-thiols.png"
alt="An overview of thiols"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>An overview of thiols: structure, aroma profile, and threshold. The small concentrations make a ton of difference in human perceived aromas and flavors.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The thiol content in hops depends strongly on the variety, and can be influenced by harvest maturity, terroir, and other seasonal variables. Several of the most popular hops of the last decade, e.g. Cascade, Citra®, Simcoe®, Nelson Sauvin™, and Mosaic®, are found to contain&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>free thiols&lt;/strong>, which are aroma-active, volatile compounds such as 3MH, 3MHA and 4MMP that are soluble in beer; as well as&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>thiol precursors&lt;/strong>, which are &amp;ldquo;bound&amp;rdquo;, non-aroma-active, non-volatile compounds that can be liberated &amp;ndash; with the help of a specific enzyme &amp;ndash; from the amino acids they are bound to, and thus become free and aromatic.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>The presence of these thiol compounds, alongside the complex array of terpenes and other essential oils, seem to give these hop varieties an edge when creating fruit-forward beers such as American IPAs. Some of these hops are running out in places, probably due to this thiol craze (and supply chain disruptions).&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-1/hops-free-thiols.png"
alt="free thiols in hops"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Published data on free thiols in hops&lt;/p>&lt;p>Source: &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/files/CBC-Development-of-Thiols-and-Thiol-Precursors-in-Different-Hop-Varieties.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">Christina Schönberger and Laurent Dagan, Craft Brewers Conference 2020&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Most common thiol precursors, in their conjugated (glutathionylated or cysteinylated, often written as &lt;strong>Glut-3MH&lt;/strong> or &lt;strong>Cys-3MH&lt;/strong>) and therefore non-active forms, have been identified in multiple other plant raw materials as well, such as grapes (and musts), tannin, fruits, and malts.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Many plants naturally produce an odorless molecule (Glut-3MH) as a byproduct of glutathione metabolism. Some of this Glut-3MH is converted into a second, non-volatile molecule, Cys-3MH, through the activity of naturally occurring plant enzymes; then, another plant enzyme converts some of this Cys-3MH into the aroma-active thiol, 3MH.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-1/F2_pathway-01.png"
alt="Biosynthesis of 3MH in plants"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Biosynthesis of 3MH in plants (red arrows = enzymatic reactions)&lt;/p>&lt;p>Source: &lt;a href="https://berkeleyyeast.com/science-lesson/enhance-thiol-biotransformation-with-tropics/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">Berkeley Yeast&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Pure natural magic.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The efficiency of each step in this biosynthetic pathway varies dramatically across different plants.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In tropical fruits like guava and passion fruit, for example, the conversion of Glut-3MH &amp;ndash;&amp;gt; Cys-3MH &amp;ndash;&amp;gt; 3MH is very efficient, and these plants contain a high concentration of 3MH as a result. That&amp;rsquo;s why tropical fruits smell like tropical fruits &amp;ndash; they contain significant sources of volatile thiol compounds.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In barley malts and hops, however, the efficiency of these two reactions is obviously low (that&amp;rsquo;s why these two naturally don&amp;rsquo;t smell like tropical fruits). The enzymes that catalyze each conversion are inefficient, producing few 3MH molecules. Even in hops that are famous for tropical fruit characters, researchers have found that &amp;lt;=1% of the Glut-3MH is actually converted to 3MH.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Consequently, barley malts and hops contain a low concentration of free thiols like 3MH, but high concentrations of thiol precursors like Glut-3MH and Cys-3MH.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-1/thiol-precursors-malts-hops.png"
alt="Average percentages of thiol precursors in barley and hops"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Average percentages of thiol precursors in barley and hops&lt;/p>&lt;p>Source: &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/files/CBC-Development-of-Thiols-and-Thiol-Precursors-in-Different-Hop-Varieties.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">Laurent Dagan&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>That means, the abundance of thiol precursors found in hops and malts have the potential to be converted into volatile thiols during fermentation &amp;ndash; just think about how exciting it would be to figure out how to unlock it all! This, indeed, has recently become a subject of great interest &amp;ndash; or even obsession &amp;ndash; for brewers. The reason is simple: While these thiol precursor molecules are flavorless, it only takes 1-2 enzymatic reactions to biotransform them into aroma-active 3MH and unleash a tropical fruit nirvana.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>One of these yeast-encoded enzymes capable of converting flavorless precursor molecules into volatile thiols during &amp;ldquo;biotransformation&amp;rdquo; is &lt;strong>cysteine S-conjugate beta-lyase&lt;/strong> (&lt;strong>CSL&lt;/strong>), from the class of carbon-sulfur lyases. This enzyme can break the carbon-sulfur bond present in these odorless cysteinylated thiol precursors, releasing the highly aroma-active unconjugated form (polyfunctional/free thiols).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A number of companies have created various new products that focus on enhancing thiol biotransformation. There are currently two main approaches, and they often go hand in hand:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>increase the load of thiols in the mash, especially in the bound form (since thiol precursors are abundant in nature and non-volatile);&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>manipulate the enzymes to turbocharge the thiol biosynthesis process.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>I will look at some of the most popular products in each category.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="thiol-precursor-enhancers">Thiol precursor enhancers&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Outside of thiol precursor-laden hops like Calypso™, Cascade, Mittelfrüh, and Žatec (Saaz), one (overhyped) product that claims to enhance or elevate thiol precursors is Phantasm®, a powder made from New Zealand Marlborough Sauvignon Blanc grapes, which are said to be incredibly rich in both free thiols and Cys-3MH &amp;ndash; allegedly a much higher concentration of thiols than hops and malts.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-1/Phantasm-powder.jpg"
alt="Phantasm thiol powder"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Phantasm thiol powder, frequently touted as &amp;lsquo;the biggest modern-day game-changer for hop aroma.&amp;rsquo; Like new iPhones, this product has a super long waiting list and is hard to get.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Phantasm came from the owner of Garage Project, a brewery based in the Aro Valley of Wellington, New Zealand, near the Marlborough region, famous for producing exceptionally high-quality Sauvignon Blancs known for their intense tropical fruit aromas. New Zealand has been ground zero for thiol research as it pertains to the wine industry, with scientists working to better understand how to unlock thiols in Marlborough&amp;rsquo;s expressive Sauvignon Blanc grapes.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It turns out that after winemakers use those thiol-laden grape skins, they throw them away.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;Maybe one winemaker&amp;rsquo;s trash is another beermaker&amp;rsquo;s treasure.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Jos Ruffell, founder of Phantasm and owner of Garage Project&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Ruffell found a way to dehydrate and powderize those leftover Marlborough Sauvignon Blanc grape skins, making a thiol-rich product that brewers could use to enhance the aromas of their beers. A pretty clever business idea.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-1/garage-project-phantasm-2023-04-17.png"
alt="Garage Project Phantasm Hazy IPA"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Garage Project Phantasm Hazy IPA, transmogrified with Phantasm® thiol powder.&lt;/p>&lt;p>Source: &lt;a href="https://garageproject.co.nz/products/phantasm-hazy" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">Garage Project&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Ruffell brought Phantasm to market in late 2020, marketing it primarily as an aroma-enhancer in hazy IPAs. Stories of early successes by popular brewing companies, including Ruffell&amp;rsquo;s own Garage Project, went viral on the internet, and created instant, fervent demand that far exceeded supply.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet">&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr">Phantasm is an experimental product in extremely short supply out of New Zealand, derived from Sauvignon Blanc grape skins. We&amp;#39;re very honored to be one of the first few breweries in the world, and first in Canada with access to play with this super magical powder.&lt;/p>&amp;mdash; Kilter Brewing (@kilterbrewing) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/kilterbrewing/status/1371661768838107144?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">March 16, 2021&lt;/a>&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8">&lt;/script>
&lt;p>Unsurprisingly, Phantasm (both the name of that company and its flagship product) has taken the brewing world by storm. (I wonder how much of a role the scarce availability and perceived exclusivity have played in Phantasm&amp;rsquo;s stratospheric popularity.) Outside of the core four (hops, malt, yeast, and water), Phantasm® is the &amp;ldquo;hottest&amp;rdquo; brewing ingredient on the market today.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;Essentially, brewing with Phantasm is like an MSG addition for aroma.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Jos Ruffell, founder of Phantasm and owner of Garage Project&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>In December 2022, Phantasm (the company) held the inaugural Phantasm Cup, a new (annual) competition to find the best thiol-forward beer in North America, sponsored by Half Acre Brewing and Omega Yeast, in Chicago. The grand prize &amp;ndash; an all-expenses-paid trip to New Zealand during hop harvest &amp;ndash; went to Wise Man Brewing (Winston-Salem, North Carolina), which won for a New Zealand-hopped NEIPA incorporating the theme ingredient.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-1/Phantasm-Cup-Wiseman.png"
alt="Wiseman NEIPA won 2022 Phantasm Cup"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Be Your Future, Wise Man Brewing&amp;rsquo;s New England IPA collaboration with Protagonist Beer, won the inaugural Phantasm Cup in December 2022. This hazy IPA features Phantasm® powder to crank up thiols and maximize juicy, tropical fruit flavors. Mash-hopped with Saaz and double dry-hopped with Nelson Sauvin™, Rakau™, and Idaho 7®, this beer boasts a big fruity aroma, soft mouthfeel, and notes of ripe pineapple, dried mango, and white grape.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-1/Phantasm-Cup-Explorium.jpg"
alt="Explorium Fancy Italian Boater Pils"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Fancy Italian Boater Pils, The Explorium Brewpub&amp;rsquo;s collab with 608 Brewing Company, won 3rd place. The original dry-hopped lager (the Italian Pilsner) is given a South Pacific facelift, with Phantasm® powder; dry-hopped with Nelson Sauvin™ and Motueka™. This crisp lager pops with effervescent tropical fruit and finishes with lime, white grape, and berry. Phil Humphrey, 608 Brewing Company&amp;rsquo;s owner and head brewer, said, &amp;lsquo;If you love wine, you&amp;rsquo;re gonna love this beer.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p>&lt;p>Source: &lt;a href="https://z-upload.facebook.com/exploriumbrew/posts/3401842456740901" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">The Explorium Brewpub&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Other standout Phantasm-enriched beers include a trio of Phuture beers, brewed via 3-way collaboration among three San Diego breweries, each featuring Phantasm® but a different beer style and hop combination:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Pure Project Brewing: Phuture I (New England / Hazy IPA; 6.5% ABV)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Harland Brewing: Phuture II (New England / Hazy Double IPA; 8.0% ABV)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>North Park Beer Co.: Phuture III (New England / Hazy Triple IPA; 10% ABV)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Another California-based collaborative brew from Alvarado Street Brewery and Green Cheek Beer Co., a double-dry-hopped Imperial Hazy IPA with Phantasm®, Nelson Sauvin™, Riwaka™, and Citra®, named Thiology 101, also impressed. Notice the pattern?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Meanwhile, Ruffell continues to capitalize on the worldwide &amp;ldquo;thiol craze&amp;rdquo;, by working on thiol-packed blends of Phantasm® and hops. He&amp;rsquo;s collaborating with Yakima Chief Hops to develop an experimental blend of Phantasm® combined with Citra®, Mosaic® and Simcoe® Cryo hops, and teaming up with Freestyle Hops to create a &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href="https://www.freestylehops.com/hop-varieties/mega-motueka/">Mega Motueka&lt;/a>&amp;rdquo; blend of Phantasm® and Motueka™ hops.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Expansion of Phantasm&amp;rsquo;s operation is also on the table. In fact, a liquid version of Phantasm® is in the pipeline, which is shown during trials to be up to 40x as concentrated as the powder, and successful in contributing deepened aromas to finished beers.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-1/phantasm-liquid-motueka-2023-04-16.png"
alt="Basqueland Phantasm Crush"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>One Drop Brewing Co. Liquid Motueka, a 8.4% ABV single-hop DIPA. In this collaboration brew with Freestyle Hops and Phantasm, One Drop experiments with some juicy new hop products, such as 1) thiol-bumped Mega Motueka pellets, which consist of Phantasm® powder and late-harvested Motueka™ hops from Nelson, NZ; and 2) a liquid hop product from Freestyle called SubZero Hop Kief™, which is the oil distillate of Motueka™ hops achieved through a process that removes all of the vegetative green matter contained in hop pellets, leaving just the aromatic, sticky oils.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Some brewers use Phantasm® powder in tandem with hop varieties that already produce a solid base of thiol precursors, such as Citra® and Nelson Sauvin™, and add a thiolized yeast strain to coax the fullest range of tropical aromatics out of the brew.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;We just threw a bunch of shit in the beer and called it good.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Phil Humphrey, 608 Brewing Company&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.craftbrewingbusiness.com/news/weldwerks-explains-its-use-of-a-thiol-named-phantasm-and-other-beers-to-know-this-week/">Craft Brewing Business&lt;/a> recently asked Skip Schwartz, Innovation and Wood Cellar Lead at WeldWerks Brewing Co., about what it was like brewing with Phantasm:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Did Phantasm save costs by perhaps requiring less hops than usual to attain an even bigger flavor?&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Since this is our first time using this product, there is still a lot for us to learn and how best to use it. We are planning on trying at least a few more beers using Phantasm before we fully make any decisions. The bigger thing is that it does not change the flavor, just the aroma. Since Phantasm is a thiol, it works more on your orthonasal than it does on your taste buds, but you do notice more defined hop characteristics on your retronasal as well.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Like I said earlier, tinkering with thiols is a lot of &amp;ldquo;trial and error.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="thiolized-yeasts">Thiolized yeasts&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Having a glut of thiol precursors alone isn&amp;rsquo;t enough. The true trick is unlocking them.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Enter &amp;ldquo;thiolized&amp;rdquo; yeasts, which are capable of producing CSL during fermentation to free thiols from their precursors, allowing them to have a sensory impact on the end-product.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0740002011000141">IRC7&lt;/a> is the key gene at the center of current research, because it encodes a CSL enzyme. A &lt;a href="https://academic.oup.com/femsyr/article/15/5/fov034/2467698">research paper&lt;/a> found that &amp;ldquo;a full-length copy of IRC7 is absolutely required for the cleavage of both precursors.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Many brewing yeast strains naturally contain the IRC7 gene. However, most of the naturally occurring CSLs in brewing yeasts aren&amp;rsquo;t as active as CSLs from other species, e.g. the CSL of &lt;em>S. hominis&lt;/em>, a natural bacterium commonly found on human skin, is far more active and more specific in generating tropical aromas.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The ideal yeast strains for thiol biotransformation are those that are capable of &lt;em>both&lt;/em> fermentation and high CSL activity. Unfortunately, this combination is quite rare in the yeast world. Most traditional brewing yeasts have mutations in the IRC7 gene that deactivate the enzyme. Of those that do have a functional IRC7 gene, they are capable of only releasing 3MH from the Cys-3MH precursor, while leaving all of the Glut-3MH untapped.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Current methods used to develop new yeasts for efficiently catalyzing thiol biotransformation include&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>interspecifically crossing strains with naturally high IRC7 activity to achieve &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s00217-022-04132-6">hybrid vigor&lt;/a>&amp;quot;; and&lt;/li>
&lt;li>genetically modifying existing yeast strains to galvanize higher CSL activity.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>FWIW, lager yeast (&lt;em>Saccharomyces pastorianus&lt;/em>) is a natural hybrid between &lt;em>Saccharomyces cerevisiae&lt;/em> and the newly discovered &lt;em>Saccharomyces eubayanus&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It&amp;rsquo;s an exciting time for yeast lovers between bio-engineered yeasts and heirloom kveiks.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>A mention of GMO inevitably evokes the popular stigma of Monsanto Roundup Ready®. Indeed, GMO has become a politically charged and highly polarizing topic; GMO foods are widely considered bad and dangerous, so much so that the EU has basically banned GMO crops.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Like artificial intelligence (AI), genetic modification is a tool, which can be utilized to transform our society, for better or worse. A blanket rejection of all GM products seems silly. Learning more about the history and place of genetic engineering in our society helps to fully understand and perhaps form an informed opinion on this technology.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Saccharomyces cerevisiae&lt;/em> probably contains ~6,000 genes, and genetically modifying them to produce specific chemicals and pharmaceuticals has &lt;a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/24677744/">already been done&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In GMO yeasts, researchers essentially delete or add a targeted gene for a specific purpose, e.g. release certain esters, remove certain phenols, or enhance biotransformation potential. Also, a GMO yeast strain doesn&amp;rsquo;t require potentially dangerous pesticides and herbicides, like GMO seeds might. This distinction seems worth pointing out and keeping in mind.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;div class="embed music-spotify">
&lt;iframe
style="border-radius:12px"
src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/episode/0FVxpZvcQr4bHSCIXNTIpY?utm_source=generator&amp;theme=0"
width="100%"
height="152
"
frameBorder="0"
allowfullscreen=""
allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture">&lt;/iframe>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>To catalyze efficient conversion of bound thiols to free thiols, the enzymatic activity of CSL needs to be turbocharged during fermentation. So far, there are 2 ways to do that:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Activate or turn up the IRC7 gene within the yeast to (over)express CSL.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Add exogenous hyperactive CSL.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>Both can boost CSL enzyme activity during fermentation to elevated levels, to maximize the thiol biotransformation potential.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A handful of thiol-unlocking strains have shown up on the market, specifically developed to enhance the yeast&amp;rsquo;s ability to biotransform compounds found in malt and hops to unleash thiols. The process of making each strain is different, even though the final product is advertised as being comparable, if not the same.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>White Labs&lt;/strong>, which caught the rising yeast wave and has sold some iconic products for nearly three decades around the world, is a latecomer. It only recently released its first thiol-unlocking product, &lt;a href="https://www.whitelabs.com/yeast-single?id=267&amp;amp;type=YEAST">WLP077 Tropicale&lt;/a>, which is &lt;a href="https://www.whitelabs.com/news-update-detail?id=74">a non-GMO blend of previously available strains&lt;/a> that are specifically selected for high IRC7 enzyme activity. (I could be wrong, but I doubt this blend will live up to the thiol-releasing potential of the new GMO strains from other labs. This seems like White Labs' way of catching up to the other companies while keeping the non-GMO tag.)&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Escarpment Labs&lt;/strong> has bred &lt;a href="https://escarpmentlabs.com/products/thiol-libre">Thiol Libre&lt;/a> from strains naturally high in IRC7 activity. (I&amp;rsquo;ve heard that the yeast appears to have lost quite a bit of its English ale character during the hybridization, while also not overexpressing the IRC7 gene that produces the required CSL enzyme to unlock thiols.)&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Omega Yeast&lt;/strong> has taken the GMO route and used CRISPR-Cas9 to cisgenically insert activated IRC7 gene (OYL-402 Cosmic Punch™), or transgenically add skin bacteria-derived CSL gene (e.g. Helio Gazer™, Star Party™, and Lunar Crush™), to produce Thiolized® versions of its popular yeast strains.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Berkeley Yeast&lt;/strong>, a startup founded by UC Berkeley scientists and funded by NSF, NIH, and USDA, as well as venture capital, has taken the transgenic GMO approach to bio-engineer the &lt;a href="https://berkeleyyeast.com/available-yeast-strains/">Tropics™ series&lt;/a>, which likely produce the strongest thiol characters of the bunch, because they sourced the &lt;em>TnaA&lt;/em> gene (encoding a tryptophanase with strong CSL activity &amp;ndash; probably the most active CSL known to the natural world so far) from &lt;em>Citrobacter freundii&lt;/em>, a commensal bacterium found in water, soil, food, and the intestines of humans and animals. (&lt;a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1002/yea.1493">Research&lt;/a> has demonstrated that expression in yeast of a bacterial enzyme with CSL activity results in very high levels of thiol production.)&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>It seems yeast companies are drawing a line in the sand and deciding if they&amp;rsquo;re going to be GM or non-GM. The latter opens up the EU market.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Is yeast going to be the new hops? I think so.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="berkeley-yeast">Berkeley Yeast&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Since I always root for entrepreneurial endeavors, I&amp;rsquo;d like to devote some ink to &lt;a href="https://berkeleyyeast.com">Berkeley Yeast&lt;/a>. The 6-year-old startup (based in Oakland, California) has risen out of the ashes of GigaYeast, which ended operations in July 2021. (Berkeley Yeast offers a &lt;a href="https://berkeleyyeast.com/strains/vermont-tropics/">thiolized version&lt;/a> of GigaYeast Vermont IPA.)&lt;/p>
&lt;div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
&lt;iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/1ZXWtUdaKD8" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video">&lt;/iframe>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>Berkeley Yeast&amp;rsquo;s first prototype was a &lt;a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41467-018-03293-x#auth-Rachel_A_-Li">bio-engineered brewer&amp;rsquo;s yeast that makes terpenes&lt;/a> (linalool, geraniol, and citronellol), which produce hop-like citrus and floral flavors &amp;ndash; and make the &lt;a href="https://berkeleyyeast.com/strains/chico-superbloom/">yeast&lt;/a> a potential drop-in replacement for hops.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Hops are a key ingredient in beer, and they grow best in just a few places on earth. Most of the US hop crop is grown in Yakima Valley in the state of Washington, which benefits from the Cascade mountains' watershed and sunny, fairly dry climate. Hop production is resource-intensive and increasingly unsustainable.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Disrupting the hop industry inevitably invites pushback. After all, using hops is part of the tradition of brewing and nobody wants to phase out hops entirely. Complementing hops, on the other hand, and allowing brewers to obtain similar tropical aromas without using those highly-demanded thiol-loaded hops, would be a smarter move.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>And that&amp;rsquo;s precisely how Berkeley Yeast evolved &amp;ndash; from hop-disruptive to hop-complimentary.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Berkeley Yeast&amp;rsquo;s main thing, though, seems to be engineering &lt;a href="https://berkeleyyeast.com/science-lesson/diacetyl-free-strains-prevent-diacetyl-formation/">diacetyl-free strains&lt;/a> that keep diacetyl (a buttery-tasting compound that&amp;rsquo;s undesirable in many types of beer) low during fermentation and after packaging, by inserting a gene that encodes the alpha acetolactate decarboxylase (ALDC) enzyme into the yeast genome. An ordinary yeast naturally converts fermentable sugars into α-acetolactate (precursor to diacetyl) during fermentation. The ALDC enzyme consumes α-acetolactate as it&amp;rsquo;s produced, and converts it into acetoin (the end product of the pathway), thus bypassing diacetyl formation. This ensures beer will stay fresh and clean after it leaves the brewery.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>They also have a STA1- Sacch Trois, dubbed Alexandre Trois, that &lt;a href="https://berkeleyyeast.com/science-lesson/diastaticus-and-sta1/">has the STA1 gene deleted&lt;/a>, solving a big headache for breweries. (Middle finger to &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->White Labs &lt;a href="https://www.whitelabs.com/yeast-single?id=182&amp;amp;type=YEAST&amp;amp;style_type=5">WLP644&lt;/a>&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->?)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>CRISPR-Cas9 is one way to edit genomes. The technology took a big step forward in the US in 2016 when the Department of Agriculture decided it &lt;a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/nature.2016.19754">would not regulate a CRISPR-edited mushroom&lt;/a>, which was engineered to resist browning by targeting a family of genes.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Berkeley Yeast started GM trials with CRISPR, but now utilizes a different set of (open source) molecular scissors.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Compared to Omega&amp;rsquo;s top-selling Thiolized® series, Berkeley Yeast developed the Tropics™ in a different way, but the purpose is the same: to produce more of the hyperactive enzyme that unlocks thiols.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-1/Tropics_3MHA.png"
alt="3MH and 3MHA production in London Tropics"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Illustration of 3MH and 3MHA production in London Tropics.&lt;/p>&lt;p>Source: &lt;a href="https://berkeleyyeast.com/science-lesson/enhance-thiol-biotransformation-with-tropics/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">Berkeley Yeast&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Based on what I&amp;rsquo;ve gathered so far from research papers, podcasts, and various corners of the internet, my high-level understanding of how Berkeley&amp;rsquo;s Tropics™ strains work is &amp;ndash; it&amp;rsquo;s two-fold:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Precursors &amp;ndash;&amp;gt; 3MH: a CSL-encoding gene (&lt;em>TnaA&lt;/em>) is transgenically sourced from a commensal bacterium, &lt;em>Citrobacter freundii&lt;/em>, and inserted into a parent London ale yeast strain to turbocharge the CSL enzyme, which breaks the carbon-sulfur bond in these odorless cysteinylated thiol precursors, releasing non-active thiols into the free, volatile, aromatic form (3MH).&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>3MH &amp;ndash;&amp;gt; 3MHA: esters in &lt;em>Saccharomyces cerevisiae&lt;/em> are produced by the alcohol acyltransferase (AAT), another yeast-encoded enzyme. One or more of the &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->native AATs&lt;sup id="fnref:2">&lt;a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --> expressed in the Tropics™ strains is capable of acetylating 3MH to its acetate ester, 3MHA.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>Because human sensory threshold for 3MHA (aromas of guava and passionfruit) is &lt;em>waaaay&lt;/em> lower than for 3MH (citrus aromas like grapefruit and gooseberry), a single molecule of 3MHA is perceived to be as potent as at least a dozen molecules of 3MH. It&amp;rsquo;s the synergy of these two molecules that creates a tropical fruit nirvana. Voila!&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-1/20230429_140316.jpg"
alt="London Tropics"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>London Tropics from Berkeley Yeast&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;h3 id="pain-de-thiol">&lt;em>Pain de Thiol&lt;/em>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The best way to delve into thiols is to actually play with it, through hands-on &amp;ldquo;trial and error.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;code>TL;DR&lt;/code>: I made a simple wholegrain bread, with 38.5% barley malt flour and 61.5% whole wheat flour. I cooked up a big batch of the mash and split it into two equally. One was inoculated with Berkeley Yeast&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href="https://berkeleyyeast.com/strains/london-tropics/">&lt;strong>London Tropics&lt;/strong>&lt;/a>, the other with &lt;strong>London Tropics &lt;em>and&lt;/em> &lt;a href="https://berkeleyyeast.com/boost/thiol/">Thiol Boost&lt;/a>&lt;/strong>. Otherwise, these were exactly the same. (Equivalent of split-batch brewing; one recipe, two beers.)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;code>Spoiler&lt;/code>: The breads turned out COMPLETELY different. A tiny drop of Thiol Boost made a ton of difference. One had a crisp, assertive maltiness with a fruity undertone, the other had crazy fruit punch energy like a POG (passion fruit, orange, and guava) bomb.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Total ingredients&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Each loaf (~900g/2lbs baked):&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Turkey Red whole wheat flour&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100.00%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>400g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>barley malts, assorted&lt;/td>
&lt;td>62.50%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>250g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>tap water&lt;/td>
&lt;td>162.50%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>650g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sea salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1.00%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>4g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>London Tropics (Berkeley Yeast)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>0.725%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2.9g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>&lt;code>Only variable&lt;/code>: 0.5mL &lt;a href="https://berkeleyyeast.com/boost/thiol/">Thiol Boost&lt;/a>, which is a proprietary clear liquid that has been extracted from plants (not grapes, i.e. not a Phantasm® copycat) and purified to contain only the precursors to 3MH and 3MHA, to amplify POG (passion fruit, orange, and guava) flavors. All the other undesirable plant molecules, such as 4MMP which may come across as diesely and dank, are stripped away.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-1/20230428_162742.jpg"
alt="thiol boost"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Thiol Boost from Berkeley Yeast. The aroma of this clear liquid, out of the box, reminds me of colorful summer popsicles. The flavor transports me back to childhood days of eating popsicles on a hot summer day. 1 tiny drop (0.5mL) goes a loooong way.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>This is very much like brewing a beer, &lt;em>sans&lt;/em> hops. Instead, it relies on the gluten in wheat flour for structure.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The aroma and flavor produced by London Tropics were very, very noticeable throughout the process and in the baked bread; that one drop of Thiol Boost made a ton of difference.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The devil, as always, is in the details.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="1-all-barley-malt-mash">1. All-barley malt mash&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>Since thiol biotransformation begins with the precursor molecules (Glut-3MH and Cys-3MH), the amount of 3MH and 3MHA produced by thiolized yeast depends on the concentrations of these precursors in the grains used for baking.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As mentioned earlier, thiol precursors are not just in hops, but also &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/files/143_Dagan.pdf">largely abound in malts&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
&lt;iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Ob5Jxy2cKLs" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video">&lt;/iframe>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>Researchers' key findings:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Glut-3MH was the most abundant precursor across malts considered.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Roasting appears to considerably reduce the amount of precursors, since no precursors were found in the most roasted malt sample. In other words, un-kilned or lightly kilned malts are shown to contain more precursors than kilned ones.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Malts made from barley are all higher in thiol precursors than non-barley varieties. Barley malts exhibited the highest concentrations of Glut-3MH and Cys-3MH with levels ranging from 40-700 mg/kg and from 1-7 mg/kg, respectively, much higher than malted rice, sorghum or wheat.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-1/malt-thiol-precursors.png"
alt="thiol precursors in barley malts"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Thiol precursors identified in barley malts&lt;/p>&lt;p>Source: &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/files/143_Dagan.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">Roland et al.&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>TL;DR, if you want to create an overload of thiol precursors in the mash, stick with un-kilned or lightly-kilned barley malts.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For this mash, I used a total of 250g dry barley malts:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>unkilned: 20%&lt;/li>
&lt;li>lightly kilned: 56%&lt;/li>
&lt;li>others: 24%&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>%&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Bavarian Pilsner (Steffi - Montana Craft Malt)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>28%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>70g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Munich Light (Voyager - Montana Craft Malt)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>28%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>70g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sun-dried barley malt (Chevalier - homemade)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>20%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>50g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Melanoidin Gold (Genie - Montana Craft Malt)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>12%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>30g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Cara Ruby (Montana Craft Malt)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>12%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>30g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>tap water&lt;/td>
&lt;td>132%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>330g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-1/20230501_193959.jpg"
alt="craft barley malts from Montana Craft Malt"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>4 craft barley malts from Montana Craft Malt&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>I used a 5-step infusion mash to maximize the potential of endogenous enzymes. I did the whole thing on a kitchen stove top so I could easily apply direct heat when needed. It took 8 hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Finely grind all the malts into flour. Mix with water. Start at 95°F. Hold at 95-110°F for 30 minutes (acid rest).&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Gradually raise the temperature to ~130°F. Hold at 128-133°F for 30 minutes (protein rest; since most of the malts used here are well-modified and already contain higher levels of amino acids, the mash benefits from a protein rest closer to 133°F than 122°F, IMO).&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Gradually raise the temperature to ~145°F. Hold at 140-149°F for 4 hours (beta-amylase conversion).&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Gradually raise the temperature to ~158°F. Hold at 155-162°F for 2 hours (alpha-amylase conversion).&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Gradually raise the temperature to ~168°F. Hold at 168-170°F for 1 hour (dextrin conversion).&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>After 8 hours, the mash took on a darker brown color, and tasted incredibly malty and sweet, like a condensed wort. No fruity aroma or flavor whatsoever, as far as I could tell.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Total: 580g (to be divided into 2 equal portions)&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="2-thiolized-barms">2. Thiolized barms&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>I wanted to make 2 loaves of bread, one with London Tropics and Thiol Boost and the other with only London Tropics, to see how much of a sensory difference the booster would make.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>So I let the mash cool off to room temperature, and divided it into 2 equal portions, placed in 2 separate containers.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Berkeley Yeast&amp;rsquo;s recommended dosage for Thiol Boost is 200-400 mL/BBL of wort, which is 0.17%-0.34% of wort volume.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I added the liquid yeast to both mashes at the same time, and mixed it in thoroughly. One hour later, I added a drop of Berkeley Yeast&amp;rsquo;s liquid Thiol Boost to barm #2.&lt;/p>
&lt;h5 id="barm-1-control">Barm #1: control&lt;/h5>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>%&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>mash&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>290g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>thiolized yeast (London Tropics - Berkeley Yeast)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2.9g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Total: 292.9g&lt;/p>
&lt;h5 id="barm-2-thiol-boost">Barm #2: thiol boost+&lt;/h5>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>%&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>mash&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>290g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>thiolized yeast (London Tropics - Berkeley Yeast)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2.9g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>thiol boost (Berkeley Yeast)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>0.17%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>0.5mL&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Total: 294.3g&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I loosely covered both, and let them ferment at ambient temperatures (65-68°F) until the yeast told me it had done its job. And that ended up taking ~50 hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;h5 id="-observation-log-">📝 Observation log 📝&lt;/h5>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>After ~4 hours&lt;/strong>, tropical aromas started to manifest. Both barms smelled pungently fruity, with subtle differences.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Barm #1 (control) smelled like a pile of overripe guavas, bananas, and pineapples, with slight citrusy notes.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Barm #2 (thiol boost+) smelled about the same, but with more sweetness to it that reminded me of persimmons.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>The taste of both matched the aroma, too. Sweet and fruity; no off-flavors.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>After ~12 hours&lt;/strong>, the aromas evolved a bit.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Barm #1 (control): still smelled like overripe, sugar-laden tropical fruits (pawpaws, guavas, mangoes, bananas, and oranges); intensely sweet and chocolaty; a little boozy.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Barm #2 (thiol boost+): the difference from control became more noticeable &amp;ndash; wildly sweeter, fruitier, and boozier. The chocolaty sweet aromas became a lot stronger, almost overwhelming, like Tootsie Rolls next to tropical fruits that were too far gone. All of the aromas from control were present, but 10x amplified. The caramelly sugary and chocolaty aromas became so immensely dominant that the fruity aromas became less pronounced.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>The taste matured, too.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Barm #1 (control): the sweetness deepened, reminiscent of chocolate, caramel, and maybe artificial sweetener, with heavy doses of overripe tropical fruit flavors; a slight bitter aftertaste.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Barm #2 (thiol boost+): 50%-70% sweeter than control; stronger flavors of overripe fruits and alcohol, overpowering the chocolaty sweetness; less bitter aftertaste; didn&amp;rsquo;t taste as pleasant as it smelled anymore.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Still no sign of fermentation.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>After ~24 hours&lt;/strong>, some tiny bubbles finally started to show up.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Aromas:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Barm #1 (control): aromas of chocolate and caramel deepened further to smell more like Tootsie Rolls; citrus notes became more pronounced and pleasant (no more nauseatingly overripe fruits), inviting mental images of Tootsie Rolls on top of pineapples; boozy smell was gone.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Barm #2 (thiol boost+): less Tootsie Roll, more &lt;em>fresh&lt;/em> tropical fruits picked at peak ripeness; a little grassy note, evoking mental images of tropical fruit salad atop a freshly mowed lawn.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Taste:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Barm #1 (control): a bit sweeter and a lot fruitier; mildly chocolaty and caramely; tasted like Tootsie Rolls and overripe tropical fruits; still a boozy undertone; the bitter aftertaste mellowed out.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Barm #2 (thiol boost+): deeply Tootsie Roll; sweeter, fruitier, and more pleasant than earlier; a boozy undertone, reminiscent of vanilla-infused bourbon; the mild bitter aftertaste moved to the middle, right after the exorbitant sweetness.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>It seems biotransformation started (3-4 hours in) waaaay before any signs of fermentation showed up (~24 hours in).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>After ~48 hours&lt;/strong>, both barms were brimming with bubbles and nearly doubled in volume.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Aromas:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Barm #1 (control): about the same, with a clearer emphasis on Tootsie Rolls sweetness.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Barm #2 (thiol boost+): about the same.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Taste:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Barm #1 (control): sweeter, fruitier, and much more pleasant; loads of fresh, perfectly ripe guava and pineapple, with a slightly tart finish; the citrus flavor moved to the foreground and became much more pronounced.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Barm #2 (thiol boost+): intensely fruity; a wide range of tropical fruits like pineapple, guava, mango, passion fruit, etc.; a brighter and much more pleasant flavor profile on the palate; a grapefruit-like metallic aftertaste.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>I stirred both barms back down, and they came back up almost immediately.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-1/20230429_141522.jpg"
alt="thiolized barm"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>thiolized barm #2 (thiol boost+), ~48 hours after London Tropics inoculation&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;h4 id="3-final-dough">3. Final dough&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>I added the same ingredients to each barm to make the final dough.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Dough #1: control&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>%&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Turkey Red wheat flour, 100% extraction&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100.00%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>400g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>water&lt;/td>
&lt;td>80.00%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>320g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>barm #1&lt;/td>
&lt;td>73.23%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>292.9g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sea salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1.00%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>4g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Total: 1,016.9g&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Dough #2: thiol boost+&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>%&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Turkey Red wheat flour, 100% extraction&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100.00%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>400g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>water&lt;/td>
&lt;td>80.00%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>320g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>barm #2&lt;/td>
&lt;td>73.58%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>294.3g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sea salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1.00%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>4g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Total: 1,018.3g&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Process&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For both doughs, I did&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>autolyse: 30 minutes at ~64°F&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>bulk fermentation: 8 hours at ~70°F&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>final proof: 16 hours at ~64°F&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>bake: 45 minutes in total; 10 minutes @ 400°F and 35 minutes at 350°F.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>The pungent tropical fruit aromas persisted into the final dough, carried over to my hands during dough-mixing, and stayed for hours after.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>No tropical fragrance during baking, just typical bread crust aroma.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I let the baked breads rest for 12 hours before cutting.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="taste-test">Taste test&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>What emerges from the spectral mist?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A wholegrain bread, transmogrified through fermentation by Berkeley Yeast&amp;rsquo;s London Tropics, with the addition of Thiol Boost, naturally releasing an aromatic phantasmagoria of ripe tropical fruits.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-1/20230501_210859.jpg"
alt="pain de thiol #1"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>pain de thiol&lt;/em> #1: the control&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The aromas from the dough apparently persisted into the baked bread. Very little thermal degradation. Those who say beer yeasts lose their characters in breads are obviously not doing it right. LOL.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>To me, each bread tasted exactly like how it smelled, from barm to dough.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A panel of 3 taster (excluding me) donated their palates to this blind taste test. None of them was informed of the ingredients in the bread beforehand, only that it was not gluten-free.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I had so much fun watching the tasters' reactions. The panel&amp;rsquo;s combined description of these 2 breads:&lt;/p>
&lt;h5 id="bread-1">Bread #1&lt;/h5>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>aroma: massively sugary and chocolaty, with a fruity undertone, like some kind of fruit candy; one taster mentioned &amp;ldquo;caramel&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Tootsie Roll&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>flavor: mildly sweet; guava, passion fruit, and mango upfront, with a pineapple aftertaste and a little wheaty finish. All 3 tasters pointed out a weird artificial off-flavor, like artificially flavored water.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-1/20230501_213312.jpg"
alt="pain de thiol #1"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>pain de thiol&lt;/em> #1: the control&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-1/20230501_212311.jpg"
alt="pain de thiol #1"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>pain de thiol&lt;/em> #1, crumbshot&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;h5 id="bread-2">Bread #2&lt;/h5>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>aroma: immensely fruitier than bread #1; mainly overripe tropical fruits (ridiculous amounts of guava and passion fruit, with pineapple undertone); subtle chocolaty note (not as pronounced as in bread #1)&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>flavor: pungently sickeningly fruity and sweet, like &amp;ldquo;fruit leather rolled in whole wheat.&amp;rdquo; One taster described it as &amp;ldquo;off-putting&amp;rdquo;, one said it was &amp;ldquo;disgusting&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;nearly inedible&amp;rdquo;, and the third one immediately screamed &amp;ldquo;something is wrong with this!&amp;rdquo; and had to spit it out. They all noted artificiality was much more outstanding in this loaf. An overdone POG bomb.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-1/20230501_215723.jpg"
alt="pain de thiol #2"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>pain de thiol&lt;/em> #2: thiol boost+&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-1/20230501_214809.jpg"
alt="pain de thiol #2"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>pain de thiol&lt;/em> #2, crumbshot&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>All 3 tasters were able to tell these 2 breads apart, right away, despite identical crust and crumb textures. They unanimously preferred &lt;strong>bread #1 (the control)&lt;/strong> over bread #2 (thiol boost+), and said bread #1 was much more balanced and more pleasant to eat, comparatively. They enjoyed bread #1 as PB&amp;amp;J, but would not touch bread #2 again.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;h3 id="thoughts">Thoughts&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>It was a tremendously fun bread experiment. The flavors from London Tropics are unmistakable. Tropical fruit characters were on steroids in these 2 loaves of thiol-enriched bread, especially in the one with a drop of Thiol Boost added.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Tropics + Thiol Boost take fermentation and the end-product to an aroma blast of overripe exotic fruits, beyond realism. It transports you into a kind of infinity feeling. The fermentation goes through several stages, and you end up on a tropical island, touching down via &lt;a href="https://backtothefuture.fandom.com/wiki/Mr._Fusion">Mr. Fusion-powered DeLorean time machine&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Berkeley Yeast&amp;rsquo;s tests have shown that Tropics strains are capable of biotransforming unhopped beers. My experiment confirms it can biotransform an &amp;ldquo;unhopped&amp;rdquo; bread (aka. solid beer).&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="thiol-dominant----thiol-complimentary">thiol-dominant &amp;ndash;&amp;gt; thiol-complimentary?&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>The aromas/flavors that are reported to fade away using Phantasm® remain very heavily in the end-product using Tropics + Thiol Boost. This could be the game-changing combo, instead of Phantasm + Omega.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>These thiol-dominant breads turned out a bit too much (there&amp;rsquo;s apparently enough thiol precursors in the malts alone), so I think I&amp;rsquo;ll go light on thiols in the next experiment and make a thiol-complimentary bread, by&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>adding a lot of adjuncts in the mash starter (to decrease precursor load), or&lt;/li>
&lt;li>blending London Tropics with a traditional strain&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>to halve or even quarter thiol levels in the final bread.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As for Thiol Boost, I might have to dip a toothpick in it and swirl the toothpick around in the mash to add just the tiniest hint of the booster.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A lot of info on internet homebrewing forums seems to suggest the biggest benefit of thiolized yeasts is that it enhances the aroma experience of a beer more than the flavor. I consider flavor to be a combination of taste and aroma. A more pleasant aroma inevitably leads our brains to interpret the overall flavor as better. Some people say they can&amp;rsquo;t decidedly tell the difference between thiol-boosted beers and those without. Well, I bet they won&amp;rsquo;t fail to notice the difference between these 2 loaves of &amp;ldquo;thiol bombs.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="thiols-have-quirks-too">thiols have quirks, too&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>Neither the panel of tasters nor I detected any wine-like aromas/flavors at all from Berkeley&amp;rsquo;s London Tropics and Thiol Boost (despite that bread #2 was an overdone POG bomb), but some brewers have reported a weird &lt;strong>white wine-ish character&lt;/strong> in their Phantasm® and Omega Thiolized® brews that detracts from the beer.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Since the wine industry figured out thiols way ahead of the beer industry and have already done a staggering amount of research on thiols, some brewers say these thiols are mostly wine-like, wine-adjacent or wine-related flavors &amp;ndash; synonymous with New Zealand-type hops (e.g. Nelson Sauvin™ and Motueka™) or even some new age European hops (i.e. Hallertau Blanc and Mandarina Bavaria). They can be awesome in the proper context, but they&amp;rsquo;re hardly a cheat code or shortcut (although they might save you 20% on hops, which probably nets to nothing per unit dollar spent). When does a beer become a grape ale? Perhaps brewers should step back and bear in mind that there are many more dimensions to a good beer, outside just a juicy burst of tropical aromas.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;If you love wine, you&amp;rsquo;re gonna love this beer.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Phil Humphrey, 608 Brewing Company&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Now that almost every brewer is thiol-conscious, hopping every IPA with New Zealand-style hops or lupulin-enriched hop products, and boosting it with Phantasm powder, how are breweries going to &lt;strong>differentiate&lt;/strong> themselves?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>There seems be a ceiling for the thiols&amp;hellip; Once you get there, it&amp;rsquo;s just all the same. Human &lt;strong>sensory threshold gets so saturated&lt;/strong> that stimuli no longer elicit an increased response. More isn&amp;rsquo;t better.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>All of these thiols are produced by precursors found on the ingredients you put in. Some people have reported a &lt;strong>sulfury/diesely character&lt;/strong> in beers made with Phantasm and thiolized yeasts. Since the CSL expression is fairly non-specific (outside of its proclivity for cysteinylated substrates, as it can barely work on glutathionylated precursors), I&amp;rsquo;m guessing all types of bound sulfur-containing molecules are released by thiolized yeast, resulting in a sulfury aroma.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Thiols &lt;strong>dissipate rather quickly&lt;/strong> over time, since free thiols are so sensitive to oxygen. I left bread #2 on the kitchen countertop, cut-side down, for ~2 days, and ~80% of the tropical fruit aromas vanished. Free thiols are found to be &lt;a href="https://dial.uclouvain.be/pr/boreal/object/boreal:157890">almost entirely absent after 1 year&lt;/a> and as quickly as 6 months in some samples, likely due to their &amp;ldquo;high propensity to undergo oxidation, nucleophilic additions or substitutions.&amp;rdquo; Like life, thiols are fleeting. Best enjoy your thiolized brews while fresh.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="how-to-nuke-your-thiols">how to nuke your thiols&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>Berkeley Yeast&amp;rsquo;s Tropics strains obviously already express enzymes that convert Glut-3MH to Cys-3MH during fermentation. More isn&amp;rsquo;t better.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>With these powerful thiolized yeasts,&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>loading additional precursors (especially Cys-3MH) through Phantasm or mash-hopping may be unnecessary (in this case, mash-hopping is likely to produce astringent vegetal off-flavors);&lt;/li>
&lt;li>late addition, or double/triple dry-hopping, with modern fancy hops, is &lt;em>not&lt;/em> a must (&amp;ldquo;hop creep&amp;rdquo; aside, these may even counterproductively reduce the impact of thiols);&lt;/li>
&lt;li>IPAs (double, triple, cold, New England, West Coast, etc.) are &lt;em>not&lt;/em> the only &amp;ldquo;thiol bombs&amp;rdquo; one can make. (I personally think thiols make more sense in simple blondes, &lt;em>witbiers&lt;/em>, and lagers.)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>A tiny amount of hops (as whirlpool additions) goes a long way towards complementing the thiol character &amp;ndash; unless the goal is to pack as many hops as possible into the beer.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>To create unique, great-tasting breads/beers, you need to understand which bio-active compounds are present in the different ingredients you put in, how high their content is, how they affect aromas/flavors in the end-product, and how they change during the fermentation process and storage.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A while ago, Brülosophy did a &lt;a href="https://brulosophy.com/2023/02/20/exbeeriment-impact-phantasm-powder-has-on-a-hazy-ipa/#more-142752">trial&lt;/a> with thiolized yeast and Phantasm thiol powder, and the results were quintessentially &amp;ldquo;inconclusive.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Curiously, tasters in this xBmt were unable to reliably distinguish a Hazy IPA made with Phantasm powder from one made without it when both were fermented with thiolized yeast.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>In the trial, the author hopped the living crap out of the beer, which inevitably masks the flavor from the thiols and any benefit that the Phantasm thiol powder may bestow.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It seems to me that guys at Brülosophy often don&amp;rsquo;t really understand the value they are testing. For example, they did a pressure-fermentation test where the pressurized side was done at only 8 psi and transferred into an open keg &amp;ndash; basically nullifying the factors that make pressure-fermentation useful. They also did some direct comparisons of yeasts, using highly hopped beers. Of course, you won&amp;rsquo;t be able to tell US-05 from BRY-97 in a triple IPA. And then peeps on the internet just eat their stuff up too much and take it as the gospel truth that yeast choice doesn&amp;rsquo;t matter, rather than arrive at the correct conclusion &amp;ndash; one data point suggests that in hoppy ales, the yeast&amp;rsquo;s contribution to the flavor profile can be less perceptible.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Yeast matters. Just ask the Belgians.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-1/20230501_211527.jpg"
alt="pain de thiol #1"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>pain de thiol&lt;/em> #1, crumbshot&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>🍻🍻🍻🍻&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Special thanks to &lt;a href="https://berkeleyyeast.com/">Berkeley Yeast&lt;/a>, especially Nick Harris and Jeremy Roop, for generously offering me the opportunity to do these fun thiol experiments and answering my questions.&lt;/p>
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>Research on the evolutionary history of STA1 has shown the gene was not present in the wild ancestor of brewing yeast (&lt;em>Saccharomyces cerevisiae&lt;/em>), but rather arose during the course of brewing &amp;ndash; formed by a mutation that fused two ancestral genes &amp;ndash; as an alternative evolutionary strategy for efficient utilization of sugars in brewer&amp;rsquo;s wort. The resulting diastatic strain (&amp;ldquo;STA1+&amp;rdquo;, i.e. &lt;em>Saccharomyces cerevisiae var. diastaticus&lt;/em>) is able to consume complex sugars like oligosaccharides from dextrins and starches, which has allowed the strain to outcompete its ancestor. The STA1+ strains mainly rely on the Sta1p glucoamylase to break down maltotriose (unlike Ale/Beer 1 strains), which means these STA1+ strains will ferment fast initially when it gorges on glucose and maltose, but slow down as it moves on to consume maltotriose, since it produces low levels of Sta1p (hence the slow finish to the fermentation). &lt;a href="https://www.whitelabs.com/yeast-single?id=182&amp;amp;type=YEAST&amp;amp;style_type=5">WLP644&lt;/a>, a Belgian strain, was originally thought to be &lt;em>Brettanomyces&lt;/em> due to its funky character (e.g. low flocculation, tropical fruit esters, ability to form a pellicle, etc), but through DNA sequencing it was later revealed to be &lt;em>Saccharomyces&lt;/em>. Maybe not &lt;em>Saccharomyces cerevisiae&lt;/em>, but genetically it doesn&amp;rsquo;t belong to &lt;em>Brettanomyces&lt;/em>. WLP644 is STA1+, but it&amp;rsquo;s among the strains with low diastatic ability, thanks to &lt;a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC6719335/">a 1162-bp deletion in the promoter of STA1&lt;/a>. Other closely related strains are the &amp;ldquo;Duvel&amp;rdquo; family (WLP570, WY1388, WB-06), which also tend to be slow fermenters. Diastaticus has been widely deemed a nasty contaminant in the brewing industry; cross-contamination often leads to unexpected over-attenuation, potentially exploding bottles or cans, and even &lt;a href="https://www.denverpost.com/2017/12/18/left-hand-brewing-milk-stout-nitro-damages/">lawsuits&lt;/a>.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>Based on Berkeley Yeast&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;science lesson&amp;rdquo; &lt;a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20230327014233/https://berkeleyyeast.com/science-lesson/enhance-thiol-biotransformation-with-tropics/">post&lt;/a> on thiol biotransformation, as well as a &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/files/fermentation-08-00370.pdf">research paper&lt;/a> co-authored by Berkeley Yeast&amp;rsquo;s scientists and published in &lt;em>Fermentation&lt;/em> (August 5, 2022) that paired CSL expression with expression of a heterologous AAT enzyme, I initially assumed that a heterologous AAT enzyme via an AAT-encoding gene (MpAAT1 or CATec3), transgenically sourced (from &lt;em>Malus pumila&lt;/em> or &lt;em>Escherichia coli&lt;/em>), was inserted into the Tropics strains as well, to acetylate 3MH to its acetate ester, 3MHA. Based on how pungent the guava and passion fruit aromas were in my London Tropics-leavened breads, I thought it odd that Tropics would have added ATT since the paper showed that the addition seemed to reduce the total concentrations of 3MH &amp;amp; 3MHA. Additionally, Berkeley Yeast&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20230127053700/https://berkeleyyeast.com/available-yeast-strains/">strain catalog webpage&lt;/a> says all Tropics strains produce the CSL; there was no mention of the AAT at all. I was confused, so I reached out to Nick Harris, co-founder of Berkeley Yeast, for clarification. Nick explained to me that &amp;ldquo;the only gene that was inserted during the engineering was the CSL&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;the addition of the AAT was into a strain that we have yet to commercialize.&amp;rdquo; Ah huh! So, whatever AATs present in the Tropics are native, not an exogenous addition. As for why Tropics produced more 3MHA, both in absolute and relative terms, than the strains possessing an additional AAT &amp;ndash; well, it still remains a mystery.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/section></content></item><item><title>levure de bière #4: corn-fused on East Coast</title><link>/posts/byb-4/</link><pubDate>Sun, 23 Apr 2023 20:04:07 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/byb-4/</guid><description>A tasty and uniquely blue-colored Midwestern corn bread that combines Kansas wheat, Illinois corn, and East Coast ale yeast. Earthy and toasty aroma, reminiscent of cornfields. Subtle nutty corn flavor with toasty sweetness.</description><content>&lt;p>&lt;em>Beer = liquid bread. Want to stay updated on my &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/craft-beer-yeast">craft beer yeast bread-plays&lt;/a>? Subscribe to the &lt;a href="https://tinyletter.com/breadbuster">newsletter&lt;/a>!&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>I spent a few days in New York City and did some things I had not done before.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I took a trip uptown to the &lt;a href="https://www.wholefoodsmarket.com/stores/harlem">125th Street Whole Foods&lt;/a>. I went there, because it was a nice change from Lower and Midtown Manhattan. It was an easy trip (right by the 2/3 train), and I liked having reasons to go to Harlem. That Whole Foods is an easy punch line &amp;ndash; widely dubbed &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href="https://nymag.com/intelligencer/2017/07/harlem-gentrification-whole-foods-vanishing-new-york.html">the ultimate gentrifier&lt;/a>.&amp;rdquo; But I feel like people who say that don&amp;rsquo;t actually go there, because it fits in the neighborhood pretty well. And I saw lots of Black Harlemites there.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Getting away from middle-class urban spaces was refreshing to me. I enjoyed going out to Flushing, Elmhurst, and Ridgewood. It&amp;rsquo;s a totally different world out there. I went to see some friends who live near Yankee Stadium, and we hit one of the Jamaican spots there. Honestly, I didn&amp;rsquo;t get out of Manhattan much until my second year living in NYC. Then I&amp;rsquo;d start getting off at every stop along the 7 train, discovering all the amazing cuisines I could find there: Asian, African, South American, Persian, Mediterranean, Balkan&amp;hellip;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I walked to FieldTrip (a restaurant chain by Chef JJ Johnson that highlights &amp;ldquo;freshly milled, heirloom rice grains&amp;rdquo;) on Malcolm X Boulevard. I got the shrimp bowl (with coconut sticky rice), and a rice crispy treat spiked with dragon fruit juice for dessert. Every cuisine is getting the fast-casual bowl treatment these days.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I went to the new Harlem location of Charles Pan-Fried Chicken, on Edgecombe Avenue, for Harlem&amp;rsquo;s best remaining soul food. There used to be a little sandwich shop here that had really good cheesesteaks with a special sauce. I think it was run by the Nation of Islam.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>On my final day, I met up with some friends at BierWax Queens, a hip-hop and vinyl-themed bar in Ridgewood, run by some DJ, and had an imperial stout on draft (Memory &amp;amp; Perception by Finback Brewery in Queens). Lastly, I stopped by Newyorktitlan, a small hole-in-the-wall Mexican brunch spot nestled in the shadow of the M train near Myrtle-Wyckoff in Bushwick, and had &lt;em>chilaquiles&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Why do people live in New York? There is no relationship between them. Except for an inner electricity which results from the simple fact of their being crowded together. A magical sensation of contiguity and attraction for an artificial centrality. This is what makes it a self-attracting universe, which there is no reason to leave. There is no human reason to be here, except for the sheer ecstasy of being crowded together.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&amp;ndash; Jean Baudrillard, &lt;em>Amérique&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;hr>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-4/20230422_203120.jpg"
alt="blue corn bread"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Midwest blue corn bread: Kansas wheat + Illinois corn + East Coast ale yeast&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Contrary to what most people think, I always associate corn with the East Coast of the United States. I was first introduced to corn tortillas and &lt;em>paste di meliga&lt;/em> (Italian cornmeal shortbread cookies) in New York City, and then grits in South Carolina.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In Old English, corn meant &amp;ldquo;grain&amp;rdquo; instead of maize, because the latter was native to America. Brewing farmhouse ale from maize in Europe was an impossibility, simply because maize didn&amp;rsquo;t grow here. In Orkney, ales brewed from grains are referred to as &amp;ldquo;corn ale.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In the New World, however, corn = maize. Corn defined drinking and bread culture during America&amp;rsquo;s Colonial Era as well as the years after the Revolutionary War. Pilgrims made &amp;ldquo;thirded bread&amp;rdquo; (or Boston brown bread) with equal quantities of rye, wheat, and corn. Slather some butter, and it was a complete meal.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The colony of Connecticut couldn&amp;rsquo;t sustain wheat production, which meant that &amp;ldquo;thirded bread&amp;rdquo; was not a cultural survivor in the Provision State, although it was popular in other New England colonies. Instead, rye &amp;lsquo;n&amp;rsquo; injun, a steamed bread made with just rye and cornmeal &amp;ndash; &lt;em>sans&lt;/em> the wheat &amp;ndash; survives in Connecticut to this day. It&amp;rsquo;s famously mentioned in Laura Ingalls Wilder&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em>Farmer Boy&lt;/em> as part of one of Mother Wilder&amp;rsquo;s delicious meals.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Many varieties of corn had their origin in the northeastern US. Cultivated into the early years of the 20th century, the varieties disappeared from the region almost overnight. Changing farm practices and the abandonment of the local gristmills led to the demise of New England&amp;rsquo;s traditional corn varieties, even as the same varieties were being cultivated and milled widely around the world, from Spain to Japan.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Corn is remarkable among the grains, because it&amp;rsquo;s used as food from the emergence of the flower buds to the time the kernels are mature. Even among the dry, mature kernels, there is a range of colors, textures, and flavors. No other grain provides such culinary elasticity.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>More than just a kitchen ingredient, the corn plant is an elegant organism. The cornfield itself provides more than just a crop of wholesome kernels.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-4/20230417_220211.jpg"
alt="Rovey blue corn"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Blue corn from Rovey Seed Co. (Farmersville, Illinois)&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Once viewed as a gift of the gods, corn has slipped under a cloud, a victim of modernity&amp;rsquo;s prodigal and detached ways. Today few people actively produce corn from seed to harvest, crack the dry corn kernels into small pieces for backyard chickens, grind it for bread, or nixtamalize it for hominy, tamales, tortillas, etc. Furthering that detachment: Over the last century or so, corn has been transformed from a wholegrain dietary staple into an industrial chemistry kit.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Most of the corn produced in the US is turned into alcohol, starch, oil, and numerous chemicals used widely in food processing; the by-products are used to fatten livestock. The kernels are treated with a strong acid and &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Corn_wet-milling">wet-milled&lt;/a>, which allows the corn refiner to separate the starches, proteins, fibers, and oils. We consume corn throughout the day in the form of meat, soft drinks, and processed foods, but only rarely as a whole grain. As early as 1954, the corn-refining industry estimated that 50% of Americans' diet was based on corn &amp;ndash; that percentage is probably a lot higher now. Grain corn has been bred and engineered in astounding quantities to provide certain chemical and energy qualities, yet the modern cultivars of the grain are barely suitable as human food. In fact, some genetically modified types of corn are not even approved for human consumption.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>I just had a chance to experiment with some non-GMO food-grade grain corns from Derek Rovey, the 3rd-generation owner of &lt;a href="http://www.roveyseed.com/">Rovey Seed Co.&lt;/a>, based in Farmersville, Illinois. Turns out the tortillas I enjoyed in New England a few years ago were made with Rovey&amp;rsquo;s corn; I didn&amp;rsquo;t realize it until now.&lt;/p>
&lt;div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
&lt;iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/4ZXIqfJez5o" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video">&lt;/iframe>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>Rovey&amp;rsquo;s corn kernels are good-sized and thoroughly cleaned; I guess they utilize some of the latest cleaning and sorting technology.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This variety of blue corn has slightly less protein, less starch, and more sugar than its white and red counterparts. Its deep purple-blue color comes from its rich anthonyacin content, the same health-promoting compound found in dark berries.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Blue corn just hits different, and this variety is no exception.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-4/20230417_220446.jpg"
alt="Rovey blue corn"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Blue corn from Rovey Seed Co. (Farmersville, Illinois)&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>First, I tossed a handful of the blue corn kernels on a popcorn popper just out of curiosity. I knew that dent corn has softer kernels (higher content of soft starch) than popcorn, and I just wanted to see how the kernels differ when heated.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Well, the blue corn kernels popped more than I expected. They didn&amp;rsquo;t fully explode into a white, fluffy substance like popcorn, but turned out brittle and concussively crunchy like CornNuts® Crunchy Corn Snacks!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>These bluish-brown &amp;ldquo;corn nuts&amp;rdquo; had a very interesting tortilla flavor, too. It&amp;rsquo;s like eating a super crunchy taco shell. Maybe thousands of years ago, in these very lands, corn was toasted in hot sand until the kernels popped?&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-4/20230418_192351.jpg"
alt="Rovey blue corn popped"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Rovey&amp;rsquo;s blue corn kernels, popped!&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>I also made a bread with milled blue corn and WLP008 East Coast ale yeast.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="saccharified-corn-porridge">Saccharified corn porridge&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>I intended to achieve 2 goals with the corn porridge:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>To heighten the flavor of corn in the final dough; and&lt;/li>
&lt;li>To provide some fermentable starch for amylase in the diastatic malt. Amylase breaks down starch (made up of long chains of water-insoluble glucose molecules) into simple sugars (branched but shorter chains of water-soluble glucose), which can be metabolized by the yeast.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>To make corn fermentable, the starch it contains in the endosperm must first be gelatinized (i.e. breaking down the intermolecular bonds of starch molecules).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Grain starch is composed of glucose molecules bound together in chains. These grain starch chains come in two types: amylose and amylopectin. Amylose is essentially a straight chain of glucose molecules, not too complicated, but it has the ability to form pretty dense starch granules, particularly in some varieties of corn. Amylopectin has a branched structure of glucose strands and, for many grains, makes up ~75% of the total starch content.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-4/starch-amylose-amylopectin.png"
alt="Different sources of starch"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Different sources of starch, and their respective percentages of amylose and amylopectin.&lt;/p>&lt;p>Source: &lt;a href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/332008553_Starch-based_films_Major_factors_affecting_their_properties" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">Thakur et al. (2019)&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Different starches require different temperatures to properly gelatinize. Conveniently, the gelatinization temperature for barley starch is in a similar range to the amylase enzyme activity optimum. However, for corn starch, the gelatinization temperature is significantly higher. Corn starch granules are typically small in size, polyhedral in shape, and have relatively low amylopectin contents. This makes water penetration into the granule difficult at lower temperatures.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-4/starch-gelatinization.png"
alt="Different starches gelatinize at different temperature"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Different starches gelatinize at different temperatures (°C)&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Therefore, commonly recommended corn starch gelatinization temperature range is 158-176°F for ~30 minutes. Since I want to be certain that gelatinization is complete, the simplest way to do this is to cook the corn in boiling water. After gelatinization is complete, the starch can then be converted to sugar by amylase.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>wholegrain blue corn (Rovey Seeds, Illinois)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>90%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>180g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->diastatic barley malt (wind-dried Chevallier)&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>20g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>boiling water&lt;/td>
&lt;td>144%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>252g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Process:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Mill the whole-kernel blue corn into a fine flour (slightly finer than cornmeal).&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Roast the corn flour in a dry skillet on the stovetop until fragrant. This helps to bring out the rich, deep aroma and flavor of corn.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Set the malt aside. Mix roasted corn flour with boiling water, until evenly combined. Simmer on the stovetop over low heat (185-195°F) for 30 minutes, stirring frequently. This will sufficiently gelatinize the corn starch.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Cool down to ~155°F, stir in the malt, and mix well. Cover and hold at 140-150°F for 12 hours. Saccharification takes place in this temperature range, i.e. amylase converts sugar derivatives or complex carbohydrates into simple soluble fermentable sugars.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>After 12 hours, cool off slowly to room temperature.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>The saccharified roasted corn porridge made from Rovey&amp;rsquo;s blue corn took on a beautiful dark blue color and intoxicating aroma &amp;ndash; reminiscent of fresh tortilla chips and popcorn at the same time! It tasted sweet like unbaked cookies.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Total: 452g (to be divided into 152g and 300g)&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-4/20230422_204035.jpg"
alt="blue corn bread"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Blue corn bread, crumbshot&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;h3 id="corn-barm-wlp008">Corn barm: WLP008&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Remove 152g of the saccharified corn porridge &amp;ndash; this will become the barm. Set aside the rest for the final dough.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>saccharified corn porridge&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>152g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>East Coast ale yeast (WLP008 - White Labs, CA)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1.5g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.whitelabs.com/yeast-single?id=108&amp;amp;type=YEAST">WLP008&lt;/a> East Coast ale yeast &amp;ldquo;possesses a similar neutral character of WLP001 California Ale Yeast® with slightly higher ester production.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This strain has a slightly lower attenuation (70%-75%) compared to &lt;a href="https://www.whitelabs.com/yeast-single?id=101&amp;amp;type=YEAST">WLP001&lt;/a> (73%-85%), which &amp;ldquo;leaves some mouthfeel and residual sweetness which balances hop bitterness.&amp;rdquo; Sounds perfect for a slightly sweetish corn bread!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The recommended temperature range for WLP008 is 68°-73°F. I fermented the barm (semi-aerobically) at 70-73°F for 14 hours. When ripe, the barm became very bubbly and porous, with a faint ethanol aroma.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Don&amp;rsquo;t go overboard with fermentation here &amp;ndash; you&amp;rsquo;re making a bread, not moonshine!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Total: 153.5g&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-4/20230422_213722.jpg"
alt="blue corn bread"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Blue corn bread, crumbshot&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;h3 id="final-dough">Final dough&lt;/h3>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Turkey Red wheat, 100% extraction&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>350g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>saccharified corn porridge&lt;/td>
&lt;td>85.7%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>300g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>corn barm&lt;/td>
&lt;td>43.9%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>153.5g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>water (bassinage)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>16%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>56g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1.1%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>4g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Kansas-grown Turkey Red wheat + Illinois-grown dent corn. How &lt;a href="https://www.buzzfeed.com/martyfcmly/how-midwestern-are-you-b7kpy2yh9w">much more Midwestern&lt;/a> can it get?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Add everything together and mix thoroughly. The dough will be sticky and delicate. Adjust hydration as necessary. Corn seems to have an endless appetite for water.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Cover with a breathable, damp towel. Ferment at 70-73°F for 4 hours; perform 4 rounds of coil-fold, 45 minutes apart.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Keep the dough at 68-63°F for another 14 hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Shape as desired.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Final proof: 2 hours at ~72°F.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Bake: 45 minutes at 350°F.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-4/20230422_202150.jpg"
alt="blue corn bread"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Blue corn bread, fresh out of the oven.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;h3 id="tasting">Tasting&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>This true Midwestern bread had a striking natural blue color, an incredibly tender texture, and deeply nutty flavor.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Aroma&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Earthy and subtly toasty, with faint ethanol; reminded me of walking through a cornfield.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Texture&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The crust was thin and firm, but not unyielding; it held up the crumb well. Very easy to bite through and evidently gum-friendly (great for grandparents and kids).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The crumb felt springy in between my fingers; not crumbly at all like a &lt;a href="https://sallysbakingaddiction.com/my-favorite-cornbread/">typical cornbread&lt;/a>. The corn added a little firmness to the crumb, but it was still very moist and tender, custardy and creamy. The slices held up well like as bookends in sandwiches.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-4/20230422_204116.jpg"
alt="blue corn bread"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Blue corn bread, crumbshot&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Flavor&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A mild tortilla chip flavor upfront, quickly developing into a mellow sweetness with a fruity undertone and a little hoppiness, and ending with a mouthwatering sensation. Clean taste and a nice balance between nutty corn flavors and toasty sweetness.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I guess switching from West Coast ale yeast to East Coast ale yeast increased the malty sweetness and fruity esters, along with other subtle yeast characteristics.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-4/20230422_204411.jpg"
alt="blue corn bread"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Blue corn bread, sliced.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Corn definitely has some special emotional pull. I&amp;rsquo;m besotted.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Corn&amp;rsquo;s marvelous color and high soft starch content gave me a dozen ideas&amp;hellip; Stay tuned!&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>🍻 Special thanks to&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Derek Rovey, &lt;a href="http://www.roveyseed.com/">Rovey Seed Co.&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Bert Sheffield &amp;amp; Erik Fowler, &lt;a href="https://www.whitelabs.com/">White Labs&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>Homemade, fully modified.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/section></content></item><item><title>levure de bière #3: Lactobacillus + Kveiks + Brettanomyces</title><link>/posts/byb-3/</link><pubDate>Sun, 16 Apr 2023 15:55:25 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/byb-3/</guid><description>&lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em> reincarnated as a wholegrain bread. A mightily aromatic and tasty scald with craft malts. Sequential mixed-fermentation with cultures from Imperial Yeast: A44 Kveiking, W25 Lacto Brevis, and W15 Suburban Brett.</description><content>&lt;p>&lt;em>Beer = liquid bread. Want to stay updated on my &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/craft-beer-yeast">craft beer yeast bread-plays&lt;/a>? Subscribe to the &lt;a href="https://tinyletter.com/breadbuster">newsletter&lt;/a>!&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>One of my all-time favorite beer styles is &lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em> (German: &lt;em>Berliner Weiße&lt;/em>), a deliciously tart wheat beer that originated in the region around Berlin, Germany and developed gradually from the 17th to the 20th century. A popular story has it that in 1809, Napoleon and his troops celebrated their Prussian victory with &lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em>; the soldiers described the beer as sweet and tart, strong and effervescent, and dubbed it &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->&amp;ldquo;the Champagne of the North.&amp;quot;&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em> is defined by its mouth-watering sour tang &amp;ndash; slightly less sour than a &lt;em>gueuze&lt;/em>, and not as funky or vinous. A great &lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em> is complex but straightforward, acidic but infinitely enjoyable. It&amp;rsquo;s malty but dry, crisp, refreshing, and light &amp;ndash; rarely with oakiness, hoppiness, tannins, or acetic flavors.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Whereas &lt;em>weissbier&lt;/em> makes the drinker monosyllabic, reserved, and retiring, the Bavarian brewings open his heart and let loose his tongue.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Henry Vizetelly&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>The origins of &lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em> are hazy at best. Along with its sour cousin, Leipziger &lt;em>gose&lt;/em>, the wheat ale hearkens back to a time when brewers in northern Germany lived by their own rules. Literally. The area evaded the Bavarian &amp;ldquo;beer purity&amp;rdquo; laws known as &lt;em>Reinheitsgebot&lt;/em> for centuries, allowing brewers to create funky, sour ales that resemble Belgian styles more than those of the Rhineland.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Weisse&lt;/em> in German means &amp;ldquo;wheat&amp;rdquo;, and &lt;em>weissbier&lt;/em> is usually translated into English as &amp;ldquo;wheat beer&amp;rdquo;, which includes a faulty assumption that there is usually a heavy component of wheat in the malt bill. Like the famous &lt;em>witbiers&lt;/em> (&amp;ldquo;white beers&amp;rdquo;) of Belgium, &lt;em>weisse&lt;/em> also means &amp;ldquo;white.&amp;rdquo; That is, &lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em> is traditionally brewed from air-dried rather than kiln-dried malt.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-3/Friedies-berliner-weisse.jpg"
alt="Friedies Berliner Weisse"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Friedies &lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em>&lt;/p>&lt;p>Source: &lt;a href="https://friediesbrauhaus.blog/berliner-weisse-das-ergebnis/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">Friedies Brauhaus&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>There are several competing theories surrounding the development of the style. One theory holds that the French Huguenot refugees, who fled to Berlin in the 17th and early 18th centuries, developed the beer after migrating through Flanders and picking up techniques from brewers of Flanders brown and red ales. There is little hard evidence supporting this theory, although the Landré family, who were prominent &lt;em>weissbier&lt;/em> brewers and had factories at &lt;em>Stralauer Straße&lt;/em> 36/37 and &lt;em>Münzstraße&lt;/em> 3, were French-born Huguenots. But the Landrés didn&amp;rsquo;t come to Berlin until &lt;a href="https://www.hugenottenmuseum-berlin.de/sammlung/objekt-des-monats/jubilaeumskelch-der-weissbierbrauerei-landre-1885">the second half of the 18th century&lt;/a>, and Charles Fréderic Edouard Landré didn&amp;rsquo;t acquire the wheat beer brewery at &lt;em>Stralauer Straße&lt;/em> 36/37, which was founded in 1780, until 1835. It seems rather late, given the brewing of &lt;em>weissbier&lt;/em> in northern Germany predates the 1600s.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Another theory points to an improvement of a beer called &lt;em>Halberstädter Broihan&lt;/em>, a &lt;em>weissbier&lt;/em> that was first developed by the brewer Cord Broihan in the 16th century and became incredibly popular across northern Germany for several centuries. A Hanover native, Broihan returned to his homeland in 1526 after a stay in Hamburg, and tried to copy the then-popular Hamburg beer, but failed. So he invented a wheat beer that soon became fashionable. Berlin brewers succeeded in further developing the recipe and brewing a wheat beer that tasted better and was more digestible. The &lt;em>Berlinische Weitzenbier&lt;/em> was born; it was praised by the Berlin doctor J. S. Elsholz as early as 1642. It was officially mentioned for the first time in a 1680 document.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The Bohemian military leader and statesman Albrecht von Wallenstein reportedly appreciated the white beer. However, during the turmoil of the Thirty Years' War (1618-1648), wheat was in short supply. The situation in the &lt;em>Mark Brandenburg&lt;/em> was so dire that Wallenstein complained bitterly in a letter to his subordinate Arnim von Boitzenburg, &amp;ldquo;&amp;hellip;&lt;em>dahero denn nicht weiß, wie den Durst löschen muss, dieweil ich das Gerstenbier nicht trinken kann&lt;/em>&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo; (&amp;rdquo;&amp;hellip;so I don&amp;rsquo;t know how to quench my thirst, since I can&amp;rsquo;t drink the barley beer&amp;hellip;&amp;quot;)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>19th-century Berliners no longer had this problem. By the late 18th century, &lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em> seemed to have emerged as a distinct style of its own, and became available at all times and practically everywhere. &lt;a href="https://barclayperkins.blogspot.com/2015/03/berliner-weissbier-breweries-in-1890s.html">Specialty &lt;em>weissbier&lt;/em> breweries&lt;/a> such as Landré on &lt;em>Stralauer Straße&lt;/em>, Breithaupt on &lt;em>Palisadenstraße&lt;/em>, and &lt;a href="https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wei%C3%9Fbierbrauerei_Willner">Willner&lt;/a> in Pankow brewed excellent beer.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>From the late 1850s to 1870s, however, &lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em> fell out of favor &amp;ndash; so much so that an English publisher named Henry Vizetelly predicted in 1859, &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->&amp;ldquo;Ten years hence and guide-books will describe [&lt;em>weissbier&lt;/em>] with the same reverence as the Colosseum in Rome, or the Palace of the Doges in Venice. Ten years later there will be a case in the Berlin Museum containing the mysterious goblets, representing a &amp;lsquo;white or a half white,&amp;rsquo; and the so-called &amp;lsquo;cool blonde.'&amp;quot;&lt;sup id="fnref:2">&lt;a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A revival did ensue. In 1879, Vizetelly paid homage to the &amp;ldquo;&lt;em>kühle blonde&lt;/em>&amp;rdquo; in &lt;em>Berlin Under the New Empire&lt;/em>, describing in detail its place in a Berliner&amp;rsquo;s life.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>In front of everyone stood a gigantic tumbler which could have been fitted with ease upon any ordinary head, and which contained a liquid pale and clear as Rhine wine, surmounted by a huge crown of froth not unlike a prize cauliflower. This was the famous &amp;ldquo;weiss,&amp;rdquo; the mere mention of which suffices to send a Berliner into raptures and into the mysteries of which I was about to be initiated. &amp;hellip; [Berlin was] the city where the &lt;em>kühle blonde&lt;/em> is obtained in the greatest perfection and where &lt;em>bier-stuben&lt;/em> offering no other beverage to their frequenters abound. The beer is drunk by preference when it is of a certain age, and in perfection it should be largely impregnated with carbonic acid gas and have acquired a peculiar sharp, dry, and by no means disagreeable flavor.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>The modern &lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em> developed relatively late, towards the end of the 19th century. Shortly after the turn of the 20th century, &lt;em>weißbier-stuben&lt;/em> (wheat beer bars) mushroomed all over Berlin. At the height of its popularity, &lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em> was the most popular alcoholic drink in Berlin, with &lt;a href="https://barclayperkins.blogspot.com/2015/03/berliner-weissbier-breweries-in-1890s.html">dozens of breweries&lt;/a> producing it.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-3/Crabtree-berliner-weisse.jpg"
alt="Crabtree Berliner Weisse"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em> by Crabtree Brewing Company (Colorado, US)&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>History suggests that wheat beers brewed around Berlin were not originally sour (i.e. not any different from those brewed in Hamburg or Nürnberg), but rather light and easy to drink compared to the heavier &lt;em>braunbier&lt;/em> (brown beer). Most of the &lt;em>weissbiers&lt;/em> were about 3% ABV and used a mash of at least 50% wheat. Interestingly, the wort was not boiled and the amount of hops used was minimal. The hops were typically not added in the kettle, but blended into the mash as a separate boiled infusion to increase the mash temperature.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Since the wort wasn&amp;rsquo;t sterilized, you can easily imagine the enormous diversity of microorganisms that survived into the cooled wort. Thus, it was crucial to start the fermentation as quickly as possible to suppress most of the spoilage microorganisms. Even so, heat-tolerant lactic acid bacteria (LAB) survived and synergistically fermented the worts into beers with a dry and lightly acidic character. This was not true spontaneous fermentation as carried out in &lt;em>lambics&lt;/em> &amp;ndash; yeast was pitched, but carried both yeast and bacteria from previous fermentations.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A. F. Zimmermann wrote in &lt;em>Der Bier-Brauer als Meister in seinem Fache&lt;/em> (1842), &amp;ldquo;all wheat beers, especially in the summer, easily turn sour and sometimes even sour during the brewing process.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Other microorganisms survived wort production, too; malts have plenty of their own LAB, for instance. Fermentation took place in wood, which is porous and thus difficult to sanitize.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Therefore, there are 3 production stages where acidification could have taken place:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>During mashing: if the mash stood too long, especially at room temperatures&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>During fermentation: primarily caused by yeast cross-contaminations&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>During storage: mainly caused by microflora in the storage vessels&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>The result was a range of beers with vastly differing levels of acidity. Although acidity was not uncommon in beers of the 17th-18th centuries, the variability of the beer meant that it often failed to meet consumers&amp;rsquo; expectations.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Both J. G. Krünitz (in &lt;em>Oekonomische Encyklopädie&lt;/em>, published in 1773) and &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->Johann Samuel Halle&lt;sup id="fnref:3">&lt;a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">3&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --> described the brewing process used in the second half of the 18th century, both indicating production was brewery-specific. For example, Halle offered a recipe made with equal parts of barley and wheat malts, while Krünitz provided one with 2/3 wheat and 1/3 barley. Such differences continued until only two breweries made the beer at the beginning of the 21st century &amp;ndash; and until they merged, &lt;em>Berliner Kindl&lt;/em> and &lt;em>Schultheiss&lt;/em> followed very different brewing processes.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Krünitz also wrote about how some of the distinctive features of the style&amp;rsquo;s brewing methods had already appeared by the 1770s:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>A decoction method, in which Berlin brewers pulled off the thinnest portion of a mash from the top, brought it to a boil, and then added hops to the decoction. The remaining wort was never boiled. This was an important technique. LAB is very sensitive to hops and could easily be killed by over-hopping. This is not a problem &amp;ndash; in fact, a blessing &amp;ndash; when brewing most styles. But &lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em> relies on &lt;em>lactobacilli&lt;/em> to acquire its trademark sour note. Over the years, brewers have used several techniques to get around this problem. To this day, the brewers of &lt;em>Berliner Kindl Weisse&lt;/em> split the wort, leave half raw, and add hops to only the other half.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Some of the wort was drawn off before cooling and pitched with yeast. By the time the rest of the wort had cooled, this yeasted portion would already be fermenting, and pitched into the main body of wort.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>Franz Schönfeld pointed out in his 1902 book, &lt;em>Die Herstellung obergähriger Biere&lt;/em>:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>In the early decades of the 19th century, &lt;em>Berlin Weissbier&lt;/em> brewers regularly refreshed their yeast with fresh &lt;em>Bitterbier&lt;/em> yeast brought in from &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cottbus">Cottbus&lt;/a>. If they kept re-pitching harvested yeast, their beer would get too sour.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Only in the 1830s or 1840s did brewers begin using mixed cultures that could be safely re-pitched without needing to be periodically refreshed.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>After World War II, the style started to wane again. Even though it&amp;rsquo;s protected under &lt;em>appellation d&amp;rsquo;origine contrôlée&lt;/em> (AOC) within Europe &amp;ndash; no beer produced outside Berlin can carry the name &amp;ndash; &lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em> no longer enjoys the popularity that it once did in its home city. The Berlin tradition has sadly slipped through the cracks and remained in a very mournful state, hanging on by a thin thread.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-3/450-berliner-weisse.jpg"
alt="450 North Brewing Slushy Blueberry Dessert Berliner Weisse"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Slushy Blueberry Dessert &lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em> by 450 North Brewing (Indiana, US)&lt;/p>&lt;p>Source: &lt;a href="https://www.craftbeerjoe.com" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">Craft Beer Joe&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The consolidated &lt;em>Berliner-Kindl-Schultheiss-Brauerei&lt;/em> (now part of the massive Radeberger Gruppe), the last brewery in Berlin producing &lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em>, and therefore the last brewery on Earth that may use the appellation, does not even feature the historic beer during its brewery tours. The ubiquitous brand it produces, &lt;em>Berliner Kindl Weisse&lt;/em>, has such a sharp, one-dimensional, lactic sourness that it&amp;rsquo;s hard to drink without those colorful sugar syrups.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The few commercial breweries that still produce &lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em> no longer use a yeast/bacterial blend to co-ferment the beer; the bacterial fermentation is conducted separately from the yeast fermentation, and the beer is blended to achieve a pre-defined acidity. Beers produced this way are very pale, slightly hazy, and effervescent, with a light tang. They are refreshing oddities, but show little complexity.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>Like any beer style that has been around for more than 5 minutes, &lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em> has gone through several transformations, adapting to technological, political and social changes along the way.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>One of my biggest qualms about beers labeled as &lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em> on the market is that they are often too light and &lt;a href="https://barclayperkins.blogspot.com/2017/10/how-sour-was-berliner-weisse.html">not sour enough&lt;/a> for me. I&amp;rsquo;d like to amp up the flavor.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Here&amp;rsquo;s my journey of making a &lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em>-inspired bread from scratch, in the melting pot that is America.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Size: one 9&amp;rdquo; x 4&amp;quot; loaf&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-3/20230415_143916.jpg"
alt="Berliner Weisse bread sliced"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em> bread, sliced.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;h3 id="scald-2h--100-105f-2h--109-114f-4h--150-155f">Scald (2h @ 100-105°F, 2h @ 109-114°F, 4h @ 150-155°F)&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>These days, everyone tells you that &lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em> is brewed with 50% wheat malt and 50% pilsener malt.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>From the beginning, Berlin&amp;rsquo;s brewers sought to keep the beer as white as possible, and used air-dried or lightly kilned wheat. The grist varied throughout history:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://barclayperkins.blogspot.com/2022/06/lets-breew-1834-berliner-weisse.html">75% smoked wheat + 25% lager&lt;/a> in 1834&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://barclayperkins.blogspot.com/2022/06/brewing-berliner-weisse-in-1840s.html">83.3% wheat + 16.7% barley&lt;/a> in 1842&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://barclayperkins.blogspot.com/2022/06/another-way-of-mashing-berliner-weisse.html">87.5% wheat + 12.5% barley&lt;/a> in 1845&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://barclayperkins.blogspot.com/2022/06/lets-brew-wednesday-1907-berliner.html">75% wheat + 25% lager&lt;/a> in 1907&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Benedikt Koch has an interesting &lt;a href="https://wilder-wald.com/2017/12/08/historic-berliner-weisse-homebrew-recipe/">recipe&lt;/a> for a historically accurate version; it uses 70% wheat malt and 30% pilsner malt to create &amp;ldquo;enough mouthfeel and doughiness from the wheat.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>My focus wasn&amp;rsquo;t on historic accuracy, but on how to play yeasts, bacteria, and grains off each other to create a balanced, tasty bread that has a similar flavor profile to &lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Total dry malts: 200g&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;em>Ölandsvete&lt;/em> wheat malt (Root Shoot Malting, Colorado)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>70%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>140g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->diastatic barley malt&lt;sup id="fnref:4">&lt;a href="#fn:4" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">4&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->(sun-dried Chevallier)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>20%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>40g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>honey malt (Root Shoot Malting, Colorado)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>rye malt (Root Shoot Malting, Colorado)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>boiled water (from cooking pasta), cooled off to ~120°F&lt;/td>
&lt;td>140%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>280g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Process&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Grind the malts, individually or collectively, into a flour. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t have to be super fine.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Place all the malt flours in a bowl or small saucepan; pour the hot pasta water (aka. liquid gold) in 2-3 increments, stirring constantly. It should have the consistency of a slightly thick porridge.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Hold the mash at&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>100-105°F for 2 hour (to help phytase break down phytin molecules and release phytic acid which lowers the mash pH);&lt;/li>
&lt;li>109-114°F for 2 hours (to help maximize the release of ferulic acid, which is a precursor to 4-vinyl-guaiacol, a molecule that&amp;rsquo;s credited with giving off a clove-like aroma);&lt;/li>
&lt;li>raise the temperature to 150-155°F and hold for 4 hours (to saccharify).&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>The mash tasted mightily malty and sweet after 8 hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Total: 480g (to be split into 400g and 80g)&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-3/20230413_151535.jpg"
alt="craft malts from Root Shoot Malting"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>craft malts from Root Shoot Malting (Colorado): Bono rye, &lt;em>Ölandsvete&lt;/em> wheat, and honey malt.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;h3 id="thermophilic-sour-lactobacillus-brevis-24h--100-95f">Thermophilic sour: &lt;em>Lactobacillus brevis&lt;/em> (24h @ 100-95°F)&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Breweries are split between their methods in souring &lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em>. On one side, there are kettle-soured proponents; on the other, you have the staunch traditionalists.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Kettle souring allows for a quick turn-around and eliminates a brewery&amp;rsquo;s concern for cross-contamination. Souring bacteria need a special cleaning procedure, so some brewers prefer the kettle sour technique to lower this risk. Most American breweries use this technique for brewing &lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em>, because it&amp;rsquo;s fast, simple, and consistent.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The traditional brewing method is to co-ferment with &lt;em>lactobacilli&lt;/em> and yeast to make a more expressive flavor profile. This takes longer and requires dedicated sour beer fermenters.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I do what works for me in my home lab. And I&amp;rsquo;m going to combine the method that Krünitz mentioned in his 1773 book with Otto Francke&amp;rsquo;s method of souring patented in 1908.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Important Question for Breweries which produce Acid Beers of the Type of Berlin &amp;ldquo;Weiss&amp;rdquo; Beer. O. Francke (&lt;em>Wochensch. Brau.&lt;/em>, 1907, 24, 621-624). — &amp;ldquo;Weiss&amp;rdquo; beer is prepared by fermenting wort with yeast and lactic acid bacteria. It is a very difficult matter, however, to acclimatise a mixture of lactic acid bacteria and pure yeast in constant proportions. The author recommends a process (which has been employed for two years with very satisfactory results) in which the lactic acid and yeast fermentations are carried out separately. The wort, as it runs off from the spent grains, is subjected to the action of pure culture lactic acid bacteria until the required degree of acidity is attained. The wort is then boiled, cooled, and fermented with pure culture yeast. The beer thus prepared has a pleasant acid taste, and does not require the aid of certain non-slime forming pediococci (see this Journal, 1907, 13, 626-630) to impart a pleasant flavour to it. If a mature, vinous &amp;ldquo;Weiss&amp;rdquo; beer is required, it is only necessary to treat the lactic acid-containing wort with ordinary bacteria-containing &amp;ldquo;Weiss&amp;rdquo; beer yeast. The presence of the lactic acid protects the fermenting wort against the attack of dangerous pediococci, and the beer acquires a sound, vinous taste. The beer prepared by the first method (i.e., that in which the lactic acid fermentation is followed by a pure yeast fermentation) only requires a short period of storage before it is ready for consumption. For the lactic acidification, the author employs distillery culture lactic acid bacillus &lt;em>Delbrücki&lt;/em>, and for the alcoholic fermentation, top-fermentation pure yeast, Race B (high attenuating).&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;em>Journal of the Institute of Brewing&lt;/em>, Volume 14, Issue 2, 1908, pages 196-197&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>I drew off 80g of the scald and inoculated with yeast (see &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/byb-3/#barm-kveiks-8h--100-95f">barm&lt;/a>), while souring the rest 400g.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Let the saccharified scald cool off to ~110°F.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>saccharified scald&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>400g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Lacto Brevis (Imperial Yeast, Oregon)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>8g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>I could let the scald ferment spontaneously over the course of a few days to develop a harmony of lactic acid, like Berliners did a few hundred years ago. But I opted to lacto-ferment the scald with a thermophilic culture, e.g. &lt;em>Lactobacillus delbrückii subsp. bulgaricus&lt;/em>, to build a particular aroma and tart-sweet taste. I have a homemade thermophilic starter (containing multiple wild &lt;em>Lactobacillus&lt;/em> strains) that easily achieves this goal, or I can take a shortcut by using a Bulgarian yogurt that contains &amp;ldquo;live and active cultures.&amp;rdquo; (IIRC, the &lt;a href="https://www.poilane.com/en/products/poilane-the-secrets-of-the-world-famous-bread-bakery-par-apollonia-poilane">&lt;em>Poilâne&lt;/em>&lt;/a> book has a recipe for a 2-day levain that uses yogurt.)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This time, I wanted to try acidifying the scald with a strain of &lt;em>Lactobacillus brevis&lt;/em> from &lt;a href="https://www.imperialyeast.com/organic-yeast-strains/yeast-types/wild-sour/lacto-brevis/">Imperial Yeast&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Lacto Brevis is a great strain for souring wort in the kettle or fermenter, prior to adding yeast for fermentation.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>I recall reading somewhere that &lt;em>Lactobacillus brevis&lt;/em> typically produces more lactic acid than strains like &lt;em>Lactobacillus delbrückii&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Thermophilic cultures love and thrive off heat. Unless you plan to ferment outdoors in the thick of summer in Arizona, you generally need some setup (yogurt maker or crockpot) to keep the heat consistent.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Other LAB strains you could consider, instead of &lt;em>Lactobacillus brevis&lt;/em>:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;em>Lactobacillus delbrückii&lt;/em>: The species name &lt;em>delbrückii&lt;/em> came from Max Delbrück, a Berlin native and a founder of microbiology, who characterized bacteria in the sour beers of Berlin in the 1930s.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;em>Lactobacillus helveticus&lt;/em>: a primary culture used in the manufacturing of hard and extra-hard Italian and Swiss cheeses.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;em>Lactobacillus acidophilus&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;em>Lactobacillus lactis&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;em>Lactobacillus plantarum&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;em>Lactobacillus paracasei&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;em>Streptococcus salivarius subsp. thermophilus&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;em>Pediococcus pentosaceus&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Regardless of which strain you use, any of them, to an extent, has a positive effect on the aroma and taste of the bread.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I added 9.6g of &lt;a href="https://www.imperialyeast.com/organic-yeast-strains/yeast-types/wild-sour/lacto-brevis/">Lacto Brevis&lt;/a> to the scald as an inoculation medium, and mixed it in evenly. Then I covered the mixture with a plastic wrap, pressing down to remove as much oxygen as possible. Keep in mind that liquid yeast cultures from different labs have different concentrations; adjust inoculation percentage accordingly.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I typically hold the thermophilic stage at 110-120°F, but Imperial Yeast recommends a temperature range of 100-85°F for Lacto Brevis (&lt;a href="https://www.whitelabs.com/news-update-detail?id=45&amp;amp;type=NEWS">White Labs&lt;/a> has also shown that &lt;em>Lactobacillus brevis&lt;/em> struggles with lactic acid production at &amp;gt;107°F), so I left the scald to sour for 24 hours at 100-95°F.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>After 24 hours, the scald showed little activity, which is probably a good sign. Pure cultures of &lt;em>Lactobacillus&lt;/em> &lt;a href="https://www.milkthefunk.com/wiki/Lactobacillus">cannot fully ferment wort&lt;/a>. If it starts bubbling and producing CO₂ visibly, then it&amp;rsquo;s likely cross-contaminated with yeast. Thomas Hübbe, in his 2016 master thesis &amp;ldquo;effect of mixed cultures on microbiological development in &lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em>&amp;rdquo;, supports that &lt;em>Lactobacillus&lt;/em> attenuates &amp;lt;10% of the sugars in wort.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The scald smelled neutral (no funky, phenolic aroma), and tasted mildly tart and sweet. I thought that was a sweet spot &amp;ndash; I didn&amp;rsquo;t want the thermophilic souring to go too far or have a very low pH that could disrupt the yeast&amp;rsquo;s fermentation. The scald will develop its maximal character later from other cultures.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Total: 408g&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="barm-kveiks-8h--100-95f">Barm: Kveiks (8h @ 100-95°F)&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>About 2/3 of the way through the thermophilic sour, I made a barm with a blend of kveik ale yeasts.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>saccharified scald&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>80g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>A44 Kveiking (Imperial Yeast, Oregon)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>0.5%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>0.4g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>I used Imperial Yeast&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href="https://www.imperialyeast.com/organic-yeast-strains/yeast-types/ale/kveiking/">A44 Kveiking&lt;/a>, a blend of 3 kveik strains that &amp;ldquo;thrives in hot fermentations when big complex ester profiles are desired&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;can produce an insane amount of pineapple, guava and other exotic tropical fruit aromas.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Typically, one would use a neutral German or European ale yeast to ferment a &lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em>, so the resulting flavors won&amp;rsquo;t contradict each other. But this Kveiking&amp;rsquo;s ester profile happens to match the tropical tart sweetness of Root Shoot&amp;rsquo;s honey malt. It would be really nice if the former could accentuate the latter.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>The Kveiking blend also works well when fermenting kettle soured worts for a strong tropical fruit character.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>As with other kveiks, a little bit goes a long way. A low pitch rate (e.g. on the dangerous edge of underpitching), coupled with a continuously high fermentation temperature, can drive these aromatics even higher.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Kveiking has an attenuation rate of 75-85% and low flocculation. Imperial Yeast recommends a temperature range of 97-75°F for Kveiking. So I mixed in 0.4g of the liquid yeast (adjust the inoculation percentage accordingly based on concentration), gave it a vigorous mix, and let the barm ferment at 100-95°F (same temperatures as Lacto Brevis) for 8 hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The barm already doubled in volume after 6 hours. The surface was very bubbly. I stirred it back down, and let it ripen for another 2 hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>When fully ripe, the barm smelled faintly beery and mildly alcoholic, with some fruity notes. It tasted explosively flavorful, like a pineapple-based tropical fruit punch infused with guava, persimmon, and cinnamon apple!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Maybe the intrigue of &lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em> comes from what the yeast does in an acidic environment: It comes up with some fun cider, &lt;em>sauvignon blanc&lt;/em>, passion fruit, funky tropical-ness &amp;ndash; which makes this style &lt;em>uber&lt;/em> interesting.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Total: 80.4g&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="mesophilic-sour-3h--95-85f-3h--85-75f">Mesophilic sour (3h @ 95-85°F, 3h @ 85-75°F)&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Once the barm and the thermophilic sour were both done with their respective fermentation, I proceeded to the mesophilic phase.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Step 1&lt;/strong>: 3h @ 95-85°F&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I dropped 40% (32g) of the ripened barm to the surface of the thermophilic sour, did &lt;em>not&lt;/em> mix at all, and just left it to open-ferment at falling temperatures from 95°F to 85°F for 3 hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In this temperature range, &lt;em>Lactobacillus brevis&lt;/em> continues to work, acidifying the scald further. The barm begins yeast fermentation of the soured scald.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>After 2 hours, I began to notice some very active bubbling (CO₂) on the surface where the barm was dropped.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Step 2&lt;/strong>: 3h @ 85-75°F&lt;/p>
&lt;p>After 3 hours, I added the remainder of the barm, gave it a thorough mix, and left it to open-ferment at 85-75°F for another 3 hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In this temperature range, yeast fermentation continues. &lt;em>Lactobacillus brevis&lt;/em> should show reduced activity or even become dormant in this temperature range.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Total: 488.4g&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="complex-sour-brettanomyces-bruxellensis-24h--70-60f">Complex sour: &lt;em>Brettanomyces bruxellensis&lt;/em> (24h @ 70-60°F)&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>It was not until the second half of the 20th century that brewing scientists identified &lt;em>Brettanomyces&lt;/em> in &lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em>. F. J. Methner&amp;rsquo;s 1987 thesis on &lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em> showed that the mixed pitching cultures contained &lt;em>Brettanomyces&lt;/em> and a second variety passed on through brewery equipment. The slow-acting strains affected flavor and aroma only in bottles that were cellared for a long time.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Over the last few years, a number of people (e.g. &lt;a href="https://escarpmentlabs.com/en-us/blogs/resources/tales-from-the-lab">Richard Preiss&lt;/a> of Escarpment Labs) have isolated &lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em> &lt;em>Brettanomyces&lt;/em> strains out of old bottles and even kept some of them alive. Brewing with &lt;a href="https://schneeeule.berlin/en/portfolio/marlene-en/">historical strains&lt;/a> must be fun!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Funk and &lt;em>Brettanomyces&lt;/em>-derived flavors are not required in modern &lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em>. Since I&amp;rsquo;m a hopeless fan of funk, I had to seek out some &lt;em>Brettanomyces&lt;/em> and added a little bit during the tertiary fermentation to accentuate the bread&amp;rsquo;s complexity. IMO, the main function of &lt;em>Brettanomyces&lt;/em> in &lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em> is to transform lactic and acetic acid to ethyl lactate and ethyl acetate.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-3/Brettanomyces-wheel.jpg"
alt="Brettanomyces aroma/flavor wheel"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Brettanomyces aroma/flavor wheel, showing the major metabolic pathways, enzymes, and metabolites produced by different &lt;em>Brettanomyces&lt;/em> strains during beer fermentation. The data suggest that &lt;em>Brettanomyces&lt;/em>, especially &lt;em>B. bruxellensis&lt;/em>, is capable of producing large amounts of acetate and medium-chain fatty acid esters including ethyl acetate, ethyl lactate, isoamyl acetate and phenethyl acetate, which are mainly found in lambic beers and American coolship ales.&lt;/p>&lt;p>Source: &lt;a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1002/jib.580" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">&amp;lsquo;Molecular and biochemical aspects of &lt;em>Brettanomyces&lt;/em> in brewing&amp;rsquo; (2019)&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Keep in mind, though, too much &lt;em>Brettanomyces&lt;/em> can throw a &lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em> off balance, and detract from its inherent thirst-quenching character. Great funky beers/breads are balanced and fresh-tasting.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>mesophilic sour&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>488.4g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>W15 Suburban Brett (Imperial Yeast, Oregon)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>I added 5g (about 1% of total scald weight thus far) of Imperial Yeast&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href="https://www.imperialyeast.com/organic-yeast-strains/yeast-types/wild-sour/suburban-brett/">Suburban Brett&lt;/a> to the finished mesophilic sour. This &lt;em>Brettanomyces bruxellensis&lt;/em> strain is said to produce &amp;ldquo;complex and balanced aromas of sour cherry, dried fruit and balanced by a unique tropical fruit profile.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>According to &lt;a href="https://www.milkthefunk.com/wiki/Brettanomyces">Milk The Funk wiki page on Brettanomyces&lt;/a>:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>If pitched into a beer that has already been fermented by &lt;em>Saccharomyces&lt;/em> or if co-pitched with &lt;em>Saccharomyces&lt;/em>, a wider range of flavors including the funkier flavors can be produced by changing some of the flavor compounds produced during the &lt;em>Saccharomyces&lt;/em> fermentation into other flavor compounds, although &lt;em>Brettanomyces&lt;/em> can also produce funky phenols on its own (&lt;em>de novo&lt;/em>) without phenolic precursors produced from &lt;em>Saccharomyces&lt;/em>. A small cell count of &lt;em>Brettanomyces&lt;/em> is plenty for creating these flavors if pitched after and co-pitched with &lt;em>Saccharomyces&lt;/em>, and normally a starter is not necessary unless pitching &lt;em>Brettanomyces&lt;/em> as the primary fermenter.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Imperial Yeast recommends a temperature range of 74-64°F for this &lt;em>Brettanomyces bruxellensis&lt;/em> strain, so I let it ferment (loosely covered) at 70-60°F for 24 hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>At these cooler temperatures, kveiks slow down and sit quietly in the background (e.g. lower attenuation and less fruity esters), while &lt;em>Brettanomyces&lt;/em> shines.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>When done, the mash became incredibly lively. It had an intensely fruity aroma and flavor that reminded me of pineapple, guava, passion fruit, tamarind, and even the Swedish mesophilic yogurt, &lt;em>filmjölk&lt;/em>! Not one-dimensionally sour, but deeply tropical with a complex sweet tartness. Unbelievably tasty.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Brettanomyces&lt;/em> certainly contributed a different touch of tartness than &lt;em>Lactobacillus brevis&lt;/em>; they complemented each other well in this barm. &lt;em>Brettanomyces&lt;/em> can be funky / fruity and tart, but not sour.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Total: 493.4g&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-3/20230414_135809.jpg"
alt="complex sour after 60&amp;#43; hours"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>the complex sour: incredibly lively, aromatic, and tasty!&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>By now, the scald has gone through &lt;strong>all of the fermentation phases&lt;/strong> that would normally take place in an 18th- or 19th-century &lt;em>weissbierbrauerei&lt;/em>:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>155-150°F: saccharification&lt;/li>
&lt;li>100-95°F: thermophilic LAB fermentation&lt;/li>
&lt;li>95-85°F: mesophilic LAB and &lt;em>Saccharomyces&lt;/em> yeast fermentation&lt;/li>
&lt;li>85-75°F: &lt;em>Saccharomyces&lt;/em> yeast fermentation&lt;/li>
&lt;li>70-60°F: &lt;em>Brettanomyces&lt;/em> yeast fermentation&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-3/20230414_135906.jpg"
alt="complex sour"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>The 62-hour sour, after going through all of the fermentation phases that would normally take place in an 18th- or 19th-century &lt;em>weissbierbrauerei&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;h3 id="final-dough--35h--68f">Final dough (3.5h @ ~68°F)&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Total wholegrain flour: 350g&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Turkey Red wheat flour, 100% extraction&lt;/td>
&lt;td>80%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>280g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>oat flour, 100% extraction&lt;/td>
&lt;td>20%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>70g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sour (all)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>141%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>493.4g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>water&lt;/td>
&lt;td>34%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>120g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sea salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>3.5g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>I prefer my bread to have just a hint of natural sweetness, rather than plenty sweet. Add malt syrup or honey, if desired.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I basically mixed everything together into a smooth, cohesive, and soft dough (adjust hydration as necessary). I let it sit at room temperature (~68°F) for 20 minutes to autolyze, before giving it a few rounds of stretching and folding. The gluten was somewhat weak, but it&amp;rsquo;s okay.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I fermented the dough at room temperature (~68°F) for 90 minutes. It expanded by ~50% and felt very puffy.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Then I degassed the dough and shaped it into a log (form into a &lt;em>boule&lt;/em> or &lt;em>bâtard&lt;/em> if desired), and placed it in a 9&amp;quot; x 4&amp;quot; loaf pan for final proof.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>After another 90 minutes at ~68°F, the dough rose by ~50% and formed a domed surface with a few cracks. I sprayed the dough with water and baked it for 45 minutes in my ghetto toaster oven (first 15 minutes at 375°F; then 30 minutes at 325°F).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>After baking, I let the bread cool off and cure for 12 hours before cutting.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-3/20230415_144616.jpg"
alt="Berliner Weisse bread sliced"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em> reincarnated as bread, with &lt;em>Lactobacillus&lt;/em>, &lt;em>kveiks&lt;/em>, and &lt;em>Brettanomyces&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;h3 id="tasting">Tasting&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Who knew a surprise was awaiting me when I sliced into this bread?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The &lt;strong>aroma&lt;/strong> was very interesting and inviting, like a zesty Granny Smith apple with a hint of raisin and cinnamon.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-3/20230415_144016.jpg"
alt="Berliner Weisse bread sliced"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em> bread, crumbshot&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The &lt;strong>color&lt;/strong> of the crumb was somewhere between soft yellow orange and luscious grapefruit (probably due to the bran and germ in unsifted whole red wheat flour).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The &lt;strong>texture&lt;/strong> was comparable to that of my regular sourdough breads. The crust was very thin and crisp; the crumb tight and soft. Mouth-filling, biscuity, and wheaty. Not ethereally fluffy, but still light on the palate.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The &lt;strong>flavor&lt;/strong> was mellow yet deeply layered. It started off with a delicate apple pie; continued to a medley of fruits (banana, orange, raisins, cinnamon apple, strawberries, apricot, peach, lychee, passion fruit&amp;hellip;) that somehow reminded me of banana nut muffins or blueberry streusel cakes; and then transitioned perfectly to a mild wheat sweetness with a little slightly clove-ish undertone.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-3/20230415_145258.jpg"
alt="Berliner Weisse bread sliced"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em> bread, crumbshot&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The finish was mildly tangy (reminiscent of pineapple), and a little &amp;ldquo;dry&amp;rdquo; after I swallowed. There was a wheaty aftertaste. The touch of smooth, rounded acidity left my mouth watering and wanting another bite. Whole wheat seemed to have played off the tartness that defines &lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It was subtly tart and well balanced, not unduly sour or puckering. You can tell the nice balance of lactic acid in this bread by its lack of sharp bitterness or a salty-type quality.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Wheat-forward, apple-esque, and unexpectedly nuanced.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-3/20230415_145623.jpg"
alt="Berliner Weisse bread sliced"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em> bread, crumbshot&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Like a &lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em> that&amp;rsquo;s light, zippy, zingy, and drinkable, this bread was very pleasant to eat on its own.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A little sweet, a little sour, and a whole lot of complex fruity notes. It&amp;rsquo;s the perfect buddy to soak in that summer social sun with. I&amp;rsquo;m amazed by the harmonious balance of sweetness and acidity, the marvelous self-conducted symphony by different yeasts and bacteria.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The slices paired exquisitely with raspberry jam and goat cheese for breakfast; with leftover Easter ham (or a hot bratwurst) and some sauerkraut for lunch/dinner.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-3/20230415_144042.jpg"
alt="Berliner Weisse bread sliced"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em> bread, crumbshot&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>When toasted, this bread took on a slightly different flavor profile: more subtle, less cinnamony, more fruity. It smelled more like freeze-dried apple slices, fruit punch, and Jolly Rancher; and tasted more like field-fresh apples.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>One things for sure &amp;ndash; this bread was too easy to enjoy. The whole loaf disappeared in record time (I invited 4 tasters, each of whom gobbled up a few slices; nobody believed this bread had no fruit in it). Simple and elegant, delicious and refreshing. I can see how the mystique of &lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em> has defied convention and beguiled invaders and imbibers for centuries.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I would think this bread tastes best 24 hours after baking.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-3/20230415_145911.jpg"
alt="Berliner Weisse bread sliced"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em> bread, crumbshot&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;h3 id="post-baking-thoughts">Post-baking thoughts&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>I have learned a lot more about yeasts through this experiment. Yeast is going to be the new hops.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Once again, it&amp;rsquo;s crazy to think that a bread with such complex flavors was made from just some humble grains, without any modern high-tech add-ins.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I should have doubled the recipe and made more than 1 loaf. This is a bread I will definitely make again (it was so worth it, and I could easily adapt the timing to my own WFH schedule). I may even top-crop some cultures from the barm for future batches.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Fruity sweetness&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In the 19th century, Germans started to find &lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em> a little too tart and added sweeteners to soften its acidity. Originally, they added &lt;em>kümmel&lt;/em> (a caraway-based liqueur), but today it&amp;rsquo;s common to add a shot of &lt;em>schuss&lt;/em>, or syrup, directly to the glass before it&amp;rsquo;s filled with beer. In Berlin, when you order a &lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em>, the waiter will often ask, &amp;ldquo;&lt;em>rot oder grün&lt;/em>?&amp;rdquo; (&amp;ldquo;red or green?&amp;quot;)&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-3/berliner-weiss.jpg"
alt="Berliner Weiße mit Schuß"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>Berliner Weiße mit Schuß&lt;/em>: Berliner Weisse with red &lt;em>himbeersirup&lt;/em> (raspberry syrup) or green &lt;em>waldmeistersirup&lt;/em> (woodruff syrup)&lt;/p>&lt;p>Source: &lt;a href="https://willkommen-in-germany.tumblr.com/post/161499667736/berliner-weisse-mit-schu%C3%9F-berlins-traditional" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">Willkommen in Deutschland&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The colors refer to the type of syrup you&amp;rsquo;d like to add to the beer. Red is usually a sweet raspberry syrup known as &lt;em>himbeersirup&lt;/em>. Green is a more traditional grassy herbal syrup made from &lt;em>waldmeister&lt;/em> (woodruff).&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;A great favourite with the ladies is the frothy Berlin white beer, drunk out of large bowl-shaped glass, and with a liqueur-glass of raspberry syrup added to it.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Dundee Evening Telegraph (Wednesday 01 November 1905, page 6)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>While Germans commonly add syrups to their &lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em> to balance its funky sourness, Americans put their own twists on the style by adding different combinations of fruits. I don&amp;rsquo;t think this bread needed any extra fruitiness (it&amp;rsquo;s not a fruit juice), but I may experiment with adding ~10% of wild pawpaw purée in a future iteration.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>&lt;strong>Lactobacillus brevis&lt;/strong>&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>According to &lt;a href="https://wilder-wald.com/2017/12/08/historic-berliner-weisse-homebrew-recipe/">Benedikt Koch&amp;rsquo;s research&lt;/a>, the main &lt;em>Lactobacillus&lt;/em> strain found in &lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em> was &lt;em>Lactobacillus brevis&lt;/em>. I did not know this at all before making this bread. I used Lacto Brevis because that was what I had on hand at the moment, other than my homemade thermophilic starter. Other hop-tolerant &lt;em>Lactobacillus&lt;/em> strains, such as &lt;em>L. lindnerii&lt;/em>, &lt;em>L. casei&lt;/em>, &lt;em>L. coryniformis&lt;/em> and &lt;em>L. plantarum&lt;/em>, have also been found in &lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I found a wealth of information on &lt;em>Lactobacillus brevis&lt;/em> in a 2003 paper called &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/14623377/">beer spoilage bacteria and hop resistance&lt;/a>.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Additionally, I read that a &amp;ldquo;symbiosis&amp;rdquo; between yeast and &lt;em>Lactobacillus&lt;/em> only seems to work when the &lt;em>Lactobacillus&lt;/em> is &lt;em>L. brevis&lt;/em>. This rod-shaped &lt;em>Lactobacillus&lt;/em> strain seems to leave the simpler sugars to the yeast, which keeps the yeast somewhat fitter in a hostile, acidic environment. There is little information on how this works in beer literature. In sourdough literature, however, it&amp;rsquo;s mentioned and researched several times.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Malts and thiols&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>How much of the bread&amp;rsquo;s bright, tropical-fruit aromas and flavors are contributed by malts and yeasts, respectively?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Currently, hops high in bound thiols (e.g. Saaz and Calypso) and genetically-modified &amp;ldquo;thiolized&amp;rdquo; yeasts are the go-to tools that brewers are employing to maximally unleash previously inaccessible tropical aromas into their beers. However, a few scientists and brewers are &lt;a href="https://brewingindustryguide.com/what-malt-can-do-for-your-thiols/">discovering&lt;/a> malts may be the most powerful player in this realm.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-3/20230415_150238.jpg"
alt="Berliner Weisse bread sliced"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>Berliner Weisse&lt;/em> reincarnated as bread, with &lt;em>Lactobacillus&lt;/em>, &lt;em>kveiks&lt;/em>, and &lt;em>Brettanomyces&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>🍻 Special thanks to&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Rory @ &lt;a href="https://www.imperialyeast.com/">Imperial Yeast&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Craig Miller @ &lt;a href="https://www.rootshootmalting.com">Root Shoot Malting&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>See &lt;em>The Simon &amp;amp; Schuster Pocket Guide to Beer&lt;/em> (1997) by Michael Jackson, p.65.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>See &lt;em>Bentley&amp;rsquo;s Miscellany&lt;/em>, Vol. 46, by Richard Bentley, et al. (London: Richard Bentley, 1859), 418.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:3" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>See &lt;em>Die Berliner Weisse: Ein Stück Berliner Geschichte&lt;/em> (&amp;ldquo;Berliner Weisse: A Piece of Berlin History&amp;rdquo;), by Gerolf Annemüller, Hans-J. Manger, and Peter Lietz (Berlin: VLBFachbücher, 2001), 34.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:4" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>I malted a batch of heritage Chevallier barley at home (slightly undermodified) and sun-dried them before grinding into a flour, to ensure the malt remained as pale as possible.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:4" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/section></content></item><item><title>levure de bière #2: keptinis + Opshaug kveik ale yeast</title><link>/posts/byb-2/</link><pubDate>Sat, 08 Apr 2023 12:24:42 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/byb-2/</guid><description>Lithuania&amp;rsquo;s best-kept secret, &lt;em>keptinis alus&lt;/em> (an exotic farmhouse raw ale made with &amp;lsquo;baked&amp;rsquo; mash), translated into bread. Aromatic caramelized &lt;em>barm&lt;/em> with craft malts. Leavened exclusively with Opshaug &lt;em>kveik&lt;/em> ale yeast.</description><content>&lt;p>&lt;em>Beer = liquid bread. Want to stay updated on my &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/craft-beer-yeast">craft beer yeast bread-plays&lt;/a>? Subscribe to the &lt;a href="https://tinyletter.com/breadbuster">newsletter&lt;/a>!&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>Lithuania has a best-kept secret: &lt;em>&lt;strong>keptinis alus&lt;/strong>&lt;/em>, an exotic farmhouse raw ale made with &amp;ldquo;baked&amp;rdquo; mash.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This beer style &amp;ndash; like a softer, rounder porter but with stronger, deeper caramel and toffee flavors &amp;ndash; dates back to the Viking era. Nowadays it&amp;rsquo;s made by only a few farmhouse brewers in northeastern Lithuania and 3 commercial breweries: &lt;a href="https://dundulis.lt/en/">Dundulis&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://www.ratebeer.com/brewers/ramuno-cizo-alaus-darykla/10373/">Ramunas Čižas&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://www.ratebeer.com/brewers/kupiskio-alus/12065/">Kupiškio Alus&lt;/a> (&lt;em>kupiškėnų keptinis&lt;/em> was once voted the best Lithuanian beer on RateBeer.com).&lt;/p>
&lt;div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
&lt;iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Kfc-EycOBvk" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video">&lt;/iframe>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>The brewing process, which has been passed down orally from generation to generation over the centuries, usually begins with a conventional, but thick, mash for an hour. Meanwhile, the brewer heats an oven to incredibly high temperatures &amp;ndash; likely &amp;gt;700˚F (371˚C). Then the brewer packs the mash into tins that look like bread pans and bake them in the oven. Just before the loaves go in, the brewer removes the fuel from the oven, so that it cools over the course of a few hours. While in the oven, the mash forms a centimeter-thick, deep-brown crust, and goes through Maillard reactions in addition to caramelization. Beneath that crust, the firm mash becomes, in &lt;a href="https://www.garshol.priv.no/blog/394.html">Lars Garshol&lt;/a>&amp;rsquo;s words,&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;sweet, toasted, and caramelly sugary, with earthy, honey-like notes.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Imagine sweet mash cookies&amp;hellip;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The brewer breaks up the charred mash and creates a second mash, adding hop tea (it&amp;rsquo;s a raw ale, after all) before fermenting. The boatload of toasted sugars imparts massive toasty toffee flavors. I can only imagine the depth of flavors in an old-fashioned &lt;em>keptinis&lt;/em>, as well as its robust notes of caramel and toffee that probably linger for a long time.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Lars Garshol also mentioned that Martin Warren of the Poppyland Brewery in Norfolk, England &lt;a href="https://poppylandbrewer.blogspot.com/2015/04/a-great-way-to-lose-day.html">tried to brew a &lt;em>keptinis&lt;/em>&lt;/a> and failed miserably. Here&amp;rsquo;s what Warren did:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>The dry malt bill was mixed in a large bucket until even. Then 1.5kg at a time were put into a large mixing bowl and about 1.4 litres of near boiling water added, enough to wet all the grains and make a stiff mix.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This was quickly put into a shallow baking tray to form a flat &amp;lsquo;loaf&amp;rsquo; and turned out onto a newspaper.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;m guessing the reasons he wound up with black, unfermentable water with no sugar in it are:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>the mash was too dry;&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>the mashing process didn&amp;rsquo;t last long enough to activate the enzymes that convert starches into fermentable sugars; all the enzymes in the malt were destroyed via baking before any conversion took place.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>Of course, you&amp;rsquo;d end up with a sugarless water this way.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-2/keptinis-baked-mash.jpg"
alt="traditional keptinis baked mash"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Lithuanian traditional baked mash, at &lt;em>Dundulio Koštuvė&lt;/em> 2022&lt;/p>&lt;p>Source: &lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/dundulis.alus.gira/posts/pfbid0291AL9yjwHsfeshtTdo48c6irt12VozD6YkCyvDh7o7ZigUgcSoiL5dqpPUKkmj52l" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">Dundulis&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>When Lithuanians brew &lt;em>keptinis&lt;/em>, they mix the grist and water into a thick porridge-like consistency, and leave it for an hour to convert. After that, they scoop the mash out and caramelize it in the oven.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Technically, caramelization is the thermal degradation of sugars which leads to the formation of both volatiles (caramel aroma) and brown-colored products (caramel colors). It is similar to Maillard reactions in that it is a non-enzymatic browning reaction, but caramelization occurs by pyrolysis (thermochemical degradation in the absence of oxygen) instead of by chemical reaction. Caramelization is catalyzed by an acid or a base, and generally requires temperatures above 120°C and a pH between 3 and 9.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>John Mallett, &lt;em>Malt: A Practical Guide from Field to Brewhouse&lt;/em> (the Brewing Elements series)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Baking 30% of the mash probably doesn&amp;rsquo;t give enough flavor to &lt;em>keptinis&lt;/em>. A few years ago, Lithuanian brewery Dundulis made a new effort to &lt;a href="https://dundulis.lt/en/keptinis-baked-ale/">reconstruct traditional &lt;em>keptinis&lt;/em>&lt;/a> that had ~55% of the mash baked, which gave more of the right &lt;em>keptinis&lt;/em> flavor.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-2/kurko-keptinis.jpg"
alt="kurko keptinis from Širvenos Bravoras (Dundulis)"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>kurko keptinis&lt;/em> from &lt;em>Širvenos Bravoras&lt;/em> (Dundulis)&lt;/p>&lt;p>Source: &lt;a href="https://mgkolekcija.wordpress.com/2016/04/04/dundulio-magistra-ir-kurko-keptinis/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">Modesto blogas apie kolekcijas ir alų&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Curiously, I remember reading about an Iberian beer called &lt;em>caelia&lt;/em> brewed during Roman times with wheat germ that was also formed into loaves and baked. Some sources suggest the bread was heated at very low temperatures and removed while it was still wet; essentially the brewers were creating a yeast bomb to inoculate fermentable grains.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>During an episode of Milk the Funk podcast, Lars Garshol made the point that historically a large metal kettle for brewing would have been prohibitively expensive for most people, so either adding hot stones to a mash vessel or baking the entire mash was a more affordable option. (This is probably true for most of Europe, at least at one point in time.)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>So, here&amp;rsquo;s my translation of &lt;em>keptinis&lt;/em> into a loaf of bread.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="saccharified-scald">Saccharified scald&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Malt is &lt;a href="https://exarc.net/issue-2021-2/at/ancient-magic-malt-making">ancient magic&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Yeast can&amp;rsquo;t live on sugar alone. It also needs nutrients like nitrogen, amino acids, minerals (Zn, Mg, Ca), and vitamins to thrive and grow. The primary source for these building blocks is the free amino nitrogen (FAN) and lipids from malted barley. Refined sugars don&amp;rsquo;t contain any of these nutrients.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Wort is the liquid extracted from the mashing process during the brewing of beer or whisky. Wort contains the sugars (especially maltose and maltotriose) that will be fermented by the brewing yeast to produce alcohol. An all-malt wort contains all the nutrients yeast needs for fermentation, except oxygen and zinc.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Lab studies have shown that rye malt worts contain less maltose and more nitrogen than barley malt worts. Further, rye malts tend to be richer than barley malts in alpha amylase, although barley malts provide slightly higher diastatic power. Including rye also increases the wort&amp;rsquo;s pH.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Total dry malts: 300g&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>rye malt (Root Shoot Malting, Colorado)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>70%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>210g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>honey malt (Root Shoot Malting, Colorado)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>30g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;em>Ölandsvete&lt;/em> wheat malt (Root Shoot Malting, Colorado)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>30g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->sun-dried barley malt (Chevallier, homemade)&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>30g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>hot water (140-150°F)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>300g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Total scald: 600g&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.rootshootmalting.com">&lt;strong>Root Shoot Malting&lt;/strong>&lt;/a> is a craft malthouse located in Loveland, Colorado &amp;ndash; the first in the US to operate on a Kaspar Schulz malting system. They won a gold medal for Genie Pale in 2019, a bronze for Munich 10 in 2020, and a bronze for Genie Pale in 2021.&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="embed music-spotify">
&lt;iframe
style="border-radius:12px"
src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/episode/6NX9ir3DiRoM0VRgzvM4Mh?utm_source=generator&amp;theme=0"
width="100%"
height="152
"
frameBorder="0"
allowfullscreen=""
allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture">&lt;/iframe>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>I incorporated some high-quality, locally-sourced malts from Root Shoot Malting to add aromas and flavors in the bread:&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-2/20230403_221136.jpg"
alt="3 malts from Root Shoot Malting"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>3 craft malts from Root Shoot Malting: honey (top left), Ölandsvete (top right), and Bono rye&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The rare heritage &lt;strong>&lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-2/RootShoot-Oland-wheat-malt.png">&lt;em>Ölandsvete&lt;/em> wheat malt&lt;/a>&lt;/strong> adds light caramel and roasty flavors, as well as full-bodied character.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Ölandsvete&lt;/em> (or &lt;em>Ølandsvete&lt;/em>) is an ancient variety of wheat first grown over 6,000 years ago on the second-largest Swedish island &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/%C3%96land">Öland&lt;/a>, just off of Sweden&amp;rsquo;s east coast in the Baltic Sea. &lt;em>Ölandsvete&lt;/em> is a low-yield, high-protein (14%-16%) spring wheat that was once common all across Europe and northern Africa. Like many other heritage varieties, &lt;em>Ölandsvete&lt;/em> nearly disappeared &amp;ndash; until a few Swedish farmers started bringing it back in the late 1990s and local bakers started using it in traditional sourdough recipes. The Danish celeb chef Claus Meyer, for example, made a highly popular &lt;a href="https://meyers.dk/opskrifter/the-oland-wheat-bread/p/75089/">Öland bread&lt;/a>. Today, there are only a few farmers in the world who grow the &lt;em>Ölandsvete&lt;/em> variety. One of them is Olander Farms in Loveland, Colorado, the &lt;em>château&lt;/em> of Root Shoot Malting, which is quite possibly the only malthouse in the country to malt this variety. The Family Jones Distillery in Denver, Colorado uses this heritage wheat for its unique single-estate &lt;a href="https://thefamilyjones.co/#premium-spirits-section">Annika Jones Vodka&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-2/20230403_221256.jpg"
alt="Ölandsvete wheat malt"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Rare heritage &lt;em>Ölandsvete&lt;/em> wheat malt, crafted by Root Shoot Malting.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Unmilled &lt;em>Ölandsvete&lt;/em> malt from Root Shoot smells sweet and nutty, with a hint of honeydew melon. Upon milling, that aroma becomes more pronounced. The fact that this variety came from Scandinavia, grown by farmers with Scandinavian ancestry, for a US baker making a Nordic-Baltic-style bread &amp;ndash; is quite interesting all around.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-2/20230403_221323.jpg"
alt="Bono winter rye malt"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Bono winter rye malt, crafted by Root Shoot Malting.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-2/RootShoot-rye-malt.png">&lt;strong>Bono winter rye malt&lt;/strong>&lt;/a> contributes some earthy and nutty sunflower seed flavors as well as spiced notes.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-2/20230403_221244.jpg"
alt="honey malt"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Honey malt, from Genie (a 2-row spring barley), crafted by Root Shoot Malting.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-2/RootShoot-honey-malt.png">&lt;strong>honey malt&lt;/strong>&lt;/a>, from Genie (a 2-row spring barley), lends a pretzel aroma and some tropical tart sweetness. This malt is produced through a very distinct malting process, which makes it closely resemble a melanoidin malt.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The honey malt, especially when freshly milled, has an absolutely intoxicating aroma and flavor. I don&amp;rsquo;t smell or taste grapefruit, but I do notice complex sweet tartness of mango, guava, passion fruit, soursop, and lychee; honeyed, tangy, tropical, and terrifically punchy citrus. It leaves an exclamation mark at the tip of my nose &amp;ndash; and reminds me of Java, Indonesia in March/April, when an abundance of tropical fruits are in season. I almost suggested to Root Shoot that they should rename the malt &amp;ldquo;Tropical Fruit Punch.&amp;rdquo; It&amp;rsquo;s a real unique malt that I&amp;rsquo;m definitely going to use a lot more of in my breads.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Process&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Grind the malts, individually or collectively, into a flour.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Place all the malts in a bowl or small saucepan; add hot water in 2-3 increments, stirring constantly.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Hold the scald at ~125°F for 2 hours; then raise the temperature to ~150°F and hold for another 6 hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>Upon initial mixing, the scald had a sweet roasty aroma and a sweet taste.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-2/20230404_161820.jpg"
alt="scald before saccharification"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>scald right after mixing, before saccharification&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>After saccharification, the sweet roasty aroma and taste went through the roof. Most people don&amp;rsquo;t have the opportunity to see or to experience this magical process. I&amp;rsquo;m extremely fortunate.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-2/20230405_015628.jpg"
alt="scald after saccharification"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>scald after saccharification&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Saccharification is an essential part of the brewing process. A few hundred years ago, making malt and brewing beer at home was a common activity. It happened on farms and in large households. It was a household task.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Today it seems to be a mystery to many.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="caramelized-scald">Caramelized scald&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The trick with &lt;em>keptinis&lt;/em> is to properly caramelize the mash in the oven. You want a crust that is charred. Lithuanians typically bake the mash in a deep, wood-fired &lt;em>dúonkepis&lt;/em> oven (&amp;gt;700˚F) to achieve &lt;a href="https://www.curiouscook.com/site/2012/09/caramelization-new-science-new-possibilities.html">caramelization&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>After 6 hours of saccharification, I scooped &lt;strong>400g&lt;/strong> (two-thirds) of the sweet scald onto a baking sheet lined with parchment paper, and let the remaining 200g (one-third) continue saccharifying for another 2 hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Remember I mentioned earlier that Dundulis' recent revival of &lt;em>keptinis&lt;/em> had ~55% of the mash baked to produce more of the right flavor? 2/3 (or ~67%) seemed about right to me, at least for starters.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I spread it out into a thin layer, to optimize the crust area for caramelization. Then I baked it in a 350°F oven for 20 minutes until it started to look dark brown in spots and smell toasty (and even slightly burnt).&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-2/20230404_225328.jpg"
alt="oven-caramelized scald"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>oven-caramelized sweet scald crackers&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The process of caramelization creates one of the most naturally delectable and complex combinations of sweet, savory, and bitter flavors there is.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As the water evaporates, the sugar concentration and the temperature of the sugar molecules continue to increase. The (now pure) molten sugar will rise above 212°F/100°C (the boiling point) and will go through its &lt;a href="https://www.joyofbaking.com/StagesOfCookedSugar.html">different cooking stages&lt;/a>. Gradually, the sugar molecules begin to break down and new compounds form (including caramel); the thermal decomposition accelerates significantly as the sugar reaches a temperature of 320°F (160°C).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>IMO, it&amp;rsquo;s best to get a wide range of caramel colors, from the alluring darkest shades (with smokey bitter notes) to the lightest hues.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The key to caramelization is the combination of cooking temperature and cooking time. I find it absolutely fascinating that sugar can actually &lt;a href="https://www.seriouseats.com/dry-toasted-sugar-granulated-caramel-recipe">caramelize at temperatures below its melting point&lt;/a>. I speculate this scald might have a different flavor if it&amp;rsquo;s caramelized low and slow, e.g. baked in the gentler heat of a 300°F (149°C) oven for a few hours, or &lt;a href="https://www.curiouscook.com/site/2012/09/caramelization-new-science-new-possibilities.html">at 250°F (125°C) overnight and longer&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Caramelization will reduce fermentability, because caramelizing also binds simple sugars into more complex ones &amp;ndash; possibly too complex for the yeast to digest. Generally, yeast can digest only mono-, di-, and tri-saccharides. Anything more complex than that will remain in solution, adding some residual sweetness but not much (think &lt;em>&lt;a href="https://www.atlasobscura.com/articles/how-to-make-medieval-mead-bochet">bochets&lt;/a>&lt;/em>, a type of Medieval mead made from caramelized honey).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In reality, most of the colors and flavors of &amp;ldquo;caramelization&amp;rdquo; are actually due to Maillard reactions where the sugars interact with amino acids to make large and complex molecules. The amount of browning can be a good clue to how much of the sugars have bonded to create large molecules. The more brown the caramelized sugar, the less fermentable it will be. Some simple sugars are indeed created in the process, but the end result is larger flavor and aroma molecules, which are formed from the initial sugars present.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Caramelization doesn&amp;rsquo;t caramelize all sugar molecules, so some sugars will still remain fermentable. A number of Belgian beers use &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Candi_sugar">candi sugar&lt;/a>, a type of caramelized beet sugar, to add flavors, colors, as well as gravity points.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The caramelized scald turned out like a Nordic crispbread, but very sticky &amp;ndash; there was a layer of sticky syrupy substance underneath the parchment paper!&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-2/20230404_233038.jpg"
alt="oven-caramelized scald"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>oven-caramelized scald crackers: net weight 149.5g&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Once the caramelized scald cooled off, I broke it up into smaller pieces. My 400g of liquidy scald yielded ~150g of dried concentrate.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Then I ground them up in a coffee grinder into a flour. The ground flour smelled very toasty and caramelized &amp;ndash; like churro, cocoa, and bread crust.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-2/20230404_235538.jpg"
alt="oven-caramelized scald ground"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>oven-caramelized scald crackers, ground into a flour&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>After the remaining 200g scald had gone through another 2 hours of saccharification, I stirred all of the caramelized scald flour (~150g) back into it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The scald instantly transformed into something much more wonderful &amp;ndash; a darker shade of chocolaty brown, with a seductive caramel aroma. After vigorous mixing, I let the newly-infused scald sit for another hour at ~150°F, so the flavors could meld.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The 600g scald I started with got reduced down to 350g, and became much more concentrated in aromas and flavors.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Total scald: 350g&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="barm-opshaug-kveik-ale-yeast">Barm: Opshaug kveik ale yeast&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>I decided to inoculate the scald with White Labs' &lt;a href="https://www.whitelabs.com/yeast-single?id=157&amp;amp;type=YEAST&amp;amp;style_type=1">WLP518&lt;/a> Opshaug kveik, a clean-fermenting farmhouse ale yeast from Norway.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>this Kveik strain was isolated from a mixed culture which belonged to Harald Opshaug, a farmhouse brewer in Stranda, Norway. This strain was originally used in the 1990s to produce several kornøl-style beers. It is a clean fermenting yeast and has tolerated temperatures up to 95°F (35°C) while finishing fermentation within three to four days. The hop-forward, clean characteristics of this strain make it ideal for IPAs and pale ales.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>This yeast is traditionally used for Norwegian &lt;em>kornøl&lt;/em> (a farmhouse raw ale), and its low esters complement hops. Maybe it will complement the insanely malty character of the scald, too?&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-2/20230403_221937.jpg"
alt="WLP518 Opshaug kveik"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>WLP518 Opshaug kveik ale yeast, by White Labs.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Here&amp;rsquo;s how to get the most out of &lt;a href="https://www.milkthefunk.com/wiki/Kveik">kveiks&lt;/a>, based on my research:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Use an all-malt scald.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Saccharify the scald as much as possible (&amp;gt;=6 hours).&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Use just a tiny bit of kveik (seriously underpitching).&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Ferment aerobically; oxygenate often.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Ferment hot (~95°F).&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>I transferred all of the scald into a clean, shallow, wide-mouthed bowl. I let it cool down to ~95°F. Then I added 1g (~40 drops) of WLP518 liquid yeast.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>caramelized saccharified scald (all)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>350g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>liquid ale yeast (WLP518 - White Labs, CA)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>0.3%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>I covered the bowl loosely, and fermented it at &lt;strong>90-95°F&lt;/strong> for &lt;strong>7 hours&lt;/strong>. I gave it a stir every 30 minutes during the first 3 hours to aerate.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>After 6 hours, the barm more than doubled in volume and became very bubbly.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-2/20230405_155731.jpg"
alt="barm after fermentation"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>barm doubled in volume, after 6 hours of fermentation with WLP518 Opshaug kveik ale yeast&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>I stirred it back down, and it bubbled back up again within an hour. Indeed, the kveik ferments a lot faster than common ale yeasts.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-2/20230405_160055.jpg"
alt="barm after fermentation"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>barm, after 6 hours of fermentation with WLP518 Opshaug kveik ale yeast&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The fermented barm had a faintly fruity and beery smell, and a slightly sweet but still very toasty flavor. Very sticky, also.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-2/20230405_160202.jpg"
alt="barm after fermentation"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>barm, after 7 hours of fermentation with WLP518 Opshaug kveik ale yeast&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Total: 351g&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="final-dough">Final dough&lt;/h3>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Turkey Red wheat flour, 100% extraction&lt;/td>
&lt;td>60%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>180g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;em>Svedjerug&lt;/em> rye flour, 100% extraction&lt;/td>
&lt;td>40%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>120g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>water&lt;/td>
&lt;td>43%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>130g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>WLP518 barm&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>351g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>3g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>I mixed everything together into a shaggy mass (increase hydration as needed), and let it sit at room temperature for 30 minutes to autolyze.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I did a few minutes of stretching and folding to aerate the dough and make sure everything was evenly distributed.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Bulk ferment: 90 minutes at ~86°F.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Shape &amp;amp; final proof: 90 mins at ~90°F.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Bake: 400°F for the first 5 minutes, then 350°F for another 40 minutes.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Let the baked bread cool off and cure for 12+ hours before cutting. &lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-2/20230406_155858.jpg"
alt="keptinis &amp;#43; kveik"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>the bread form of Lithuanian &lt;em>keptinis&lt;/em>, fermented with Opshaug kveik ale yeast&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;h3 id="tasting">Tasting&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The bread turned out quintessentially brown like a dark caramel. Its dense, opaque, and mysterious appearance reminded me of a brown ale rather than a questionable hazy IPA.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Aroma&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The bread had a very complex aroma: aggressively caramel upfront, followed by scents of chocolate, &lt;a href="https://www.thespruceeats.com/english-toffee-520453">toffee&lt;/a>, molasses, and dark brown sugar; deeply malty and subtly wheaty. It reminded me of the sugary wafts of &lt;a href="https://walkers-nonsuch.co.uk/about-walkers/our-history/">Walker&amp;rsquo;s Nonsuch Toffee&lt;/a> in Longton, Stoke-on-Trent, England.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The aroma was so sweet and rich that it immediately transported me into an old-time candy shop where I was surrounded by handmade caramels, dark chocolate, truffles, fudge, etc&amp;hellip;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Notes of toasted bread crusts, graham crackers, orange, and cinnamon sat contently in the background.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-2/20230406_165734.jpg"
alt="keptinis &amp;#43; kveik"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>the bread form of Lithuanian &lt;em>keptinis&lt;/em>, fermented with Opshaug kveik ale yeast&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Texture&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The texture was decidedly chewy, soft, moist, and sticky; the tenderness reminded me a lot of &lt;a href="https://www.latimes.com/recipe/mantou-steamed-chinese-buns">Chinese steamed buns&lt;/a> (&lt;em>mantou&lt;/em>). Both the texture and the flavor reminded me of &lt;a href="https://thewoksoflife.com/nian-gao-recipe/">lunar new year sweet rice cake&lt;/a> (made with basic ingredients like brown sugar, water / coconut milk, and glutinous rice flour).&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-2/20230406_175123.jpg"
alt="keptinis &amp;#43; kveik"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Lithuanian &lt;em>keptinis&lt;/em> bread with Opshaug kveik ale yeast, crumbshot&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Flavor&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The flavor was complex with immediate competition of toffee, toasted bread, orange, cinnamon, walnut, and molasses. There was a hint of butteriness and wheatiness.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The flavor kept on developing: There was an explosion of caramel and chocolate flavors as the bread first hit the tongue, balanced by a faintly hoppy undertone. When combined with the subtle earthiness of the grains, the malty flavors became more pronounced. The mildly sweet and nutty flavors of wholegrain wheat and rye started to shine through and became more endearing.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As I was about to swallow, the flavors deepened even further &amp;ndash; to rival the aggressively caramely and malty aroma I was smelling initially. Coupled with lingering hints of dates, raisins, plums, and chocolate, it made for a soul-satisfying taste.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-2/20230406_173249.jpg"
alt="keptinis &amp;#43; kveik"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Lithuanian &lt;em>keptinis&lt;/em> bread with Opshaug kveik ale yeast, crumbshot of a half-eaten slice&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>After I swallowed, the caramely flavor mellowed out and gently transitioned to some bitter / hoppy notes. This was followed by a deluge of saliva &amp;ndash; my mouth was begging for more of this flavor bomb.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I don&amp;rsquo;t recall ever having a bread with such a long progression of flavors that slowly marched across my taste buds or teased my palate in such deliberate ways.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As the bread was toasted, the caramel flavor gave way to more burnt notes &amp;ndash; not acrid but more like the deep caramelization on the surface of grilled fruits. With further toasting, walnut and molasses took over the flavor. The bread was sweet, although less sweet as it toasted, but it was not cloying.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This bread looked and tasted like it should be really sweet &amp;ndash; on par with the tooth-aching intensity of marshmallows, angel food cake, and fudge &amp;ndash; but it just isn&amp;rsquo;t. It&amp;rsquo;s gently sweet with an enjoyable toffee flavor, &lt;em>sans&lt;/em> toothaches.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-2/20230406_173057.jpg"
alt="keptinis &amp;#43; kveik"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Lithuanian &lt;em>keptinis&lt;/em> bread with Opshaug kveik ale yeast, top crust shot&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Mouthfeel&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The crust was thin and crisp. The crumb was juicy (i.e. an evocative sensation that brought back sensory memories of biting into a ripe plum or peach, but not a juicy apple or pear) and soft, not heavy at all like its appearance or flavor suggested. It reminded me of eating a bowl of toasted oatmeal.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-2/20230406_173201.jpg"
alt="keptinis &amp;#43; kveik"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Lithuanian &lt;em>keptinis&lt;/em> bread with Opshaug kveik ale yeast, crumbshot&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Overall&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I was &amp;ndash; and still am &amp;ndash; honestly blown away by how good this bread turned out.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The flavor was so deep and complex that it&amp;rsquo;s crazy to think this bread was made from just some austere barley, rye, and wheat without any specialty ingredients.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;m a fan of Baltic black breads, but this bread is radically different from any black bread I&amp;rsquo;ve ever tasted. It aligns very well with how people describe &lt;em>keptinis&lt;/em> from experienced brewers.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Hazy dark brown, thin, tan head. Aroma of brown bread, toast, chestnut, cashew, raisin, old banana. Taste has sweetish raisin &amp;amp; prune, sourish berries over brown-bready, almost wholemeal maltiness.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>an internet review of &lt;em>&lt;a href="https://brewver.com/beers/23908/Kurko-Keptinis">kurko keptinis&lt;/a>&lt;/em> from &lt;em>Širvenos Bravoras&lt;/em> (Dundulis)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>This is definitely an interesting twist on the Baltic bread tradition. Baking the saccharified scald into caramelized sugars is intriguing &amp;ndash; and kind of reminds me of &lt;a href="https://www.thefreshloaf.com/node/13369/altus-amp-formula">altus&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://www.thefreshloaf.com/node/55979/alt-altus">alt altus&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The bread had no weird fermentation character or sourness at all. The WLP518 Opshaug kveik strain helped a &amp;ldquo;clean&amp;rdquo; grain flavor shine through &amp;ndash; just like the grain-forward &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/wlp001/">WLP001&lt;/a> California ale yeast did in my &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/byb-1-2/">previous bread-plays&lt;/a> &amp;ndash; underneath the complex caramely flavors. I have no doubt this bread will taste completely different if fermented with a sourdough levain instead of a kveik.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-2/20230406_175350.jpg"
alt="keptinis &amp;#43; kveik"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Lithuanian &lt;em>keptinis&lt;/em> bread with Opshaug kveik ale yeast, crumbshot&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>I have a lot of craft beer yeast breads in the pipeline&amp;hellip;&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>🍻 Special thanks to&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Bert Sheffield &amp;amp; Erik Fowler, &lt;a href="https://www.whitelabs.com/">White Labs&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Craig Miller, &lt;a href="https://www.rootshootmalting.com">Root Shoot Malting&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>I malted a batch of heritage Chevallier barley at home (probably undermodified) and sun-dried them before grinding into a flour, to ensure the malt remained as pale as possible.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/section></content></item><item><title>levure de bière #1.2: California ale yeast</title><link>/posts/byb-1-2/</link><pubDate>Sun, 02 Apr 2023 22:55:42 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/byb-1-2/</guid><description>A high-hydration whole-wheat bread leavened exclusively with WLP001 California ale yeast &lt;em>barm&lt;/em>. The crumb turned out much lighter and airier than the poolish version, more like sourdough breads. The taste was similarly clean and wheat-emphatic, without the slightest tang of acidity, reminiscent of Triscuit Original whole wheat crackers or Anchor Brewing&amp;rsquo;s Summer Wheat.</description><content>&lt;p>&lt;em>Beer = liquid bread. Want to stay updated on my &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/craft-beer-yeast">craft beer yeast bread-plays&lt;/a>? Subscribe to the &lt;a href="https://tinyletter.com/breadbuster">newsletter&lt;/a>!&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>As mentioned in my &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-1/">last breadpost&lt;/a>, &lt;strong>barm&lt;/strong> is simply a thick yeasty froth or scum formed on the top of a fermenting liquid, like beer or wine.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The original method of making yeast bread in Britain was a by-product of ale-making. When traditional ale is made, a yeasty froth appears on top of the fermenting liquid (the wort). This used to be scooped off, washed, and then added to bread dough as a leaven. Bread made this way is sweet, light, and fluffy, and the leavening yeast used to be called &amp;ldquo;barm&amp;rdquo;. Its unpredictability gives us the word &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->&amp;ldquo;barmy&amp;rdquo;&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Barm first appeared in written records before the 12th century. It came from Middle English &lt;em>berme&lt;/em>, which came from Old English &lt;em>beorma&lt;/em>; it&amp;rsquo;s akin to Middle Low German &lt;em>berm&lt;/em> (yeast), Latin &lt;em>fermentum&lt;/em> (yeast), &lt;em>fervēre&lt;/em> (to boil), and Old Irish &lt;em>berbaid&lt;/em> (he boils). The word has been in use more loosely since the 13th century in reference to the foam or &amp;ldquo;head&amp;rdquo; of a pint of beer.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Using barm to leaven bread appears to be an ancient method developed by Gaelic peoples in the mists of time (no wonder Scottish bakers were the last in Britain to ditch baking with barm), and was quite different from that used in Europe, i.e. leaven bread with a sourdough or leaven (called &amp;ldquo;levain&amp;rdquo; in French). When the Romans first conquered Gaul (modern-day France), they were astonished by the light sweet bread made by the Celtic inhabitants. Barm bread survived with the Celtic peoples in Britain, Scotland and Éire, but was not common in Europe &amp;ndash; in fact, it was even condemned during the Enlightenment as &amp;ldquo;unwholesome&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-2/20230402_111008.jpg"
alt="WLP001 whole-wheat barm bread"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>whole-wheat barm bread, leavened exclusively with White Labs' WLP001 California ale yeast.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>In England, noblemen&amp;rsquo;s bread &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Manchet">manchet&lt;/a>&amp;rdquo; was always made with barm, whereas the commoners' bread &amp;ldquo;maslin&amp;rdquo; was usually leavened with a sourdough. Barm bread survived until World War II &amp;ndash; and even later in northern England largely as &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Barm_cake">barm cakes&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In the 19th century, the barm process was refined and industrialized; &amp;ldquo;yeast&amp;rdquo; began to be manufactured on a large scale, and used worldwide as &lt;em>the&lt;/em> method to leaven bread.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Curiously, the old method of making a sponge, i.e. a thick batter of flour and water with the barm, was still used with the new industrially-produced yeast, and was re-introduced to Europe from Vienna where the first yeast factories were established. Viennese bakers who emigrated to France around 1840 initiated the production of Viennese breads and other luxury bakery products in Paris using such technique. This became popular in France as a &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href="https://bakerpedia.com/processes/poolish/">poolish&lt;/a>&amp;rdquo; (an Old English version of &amp;ldquo;Polish&amp;rdquo;, as this method was first developed in Poland); bakers switched from using combinations of yeast and sourdough (&lt;em>sur levain&lt;/em>) to yeast alone for making crusty bread such as baguettes at bakeshops.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-2/20230402_111040.jpg"
alt="WLP001 whole-wheat barm bread"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>whole-wheat barm bread, leavened exclusively with White Labs' WLP001 California ale yeast.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>At the beginning of the 20th century, barm was no longer universally held in high esteem.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A 1902 domestic science book, &lt;em>&lt;a href="https://chestofbooks.com/food/science/Handbook-Of-Household-Science/Yeasts-Part-2.html">Hand-Book Of Household Science&lt;/a>&lt;/em> by Juniata L. Shepperd, considered acidity in barm bread a defect:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>There is another variety of patent yeast known as &amp;ldquo;flour barm.&amp;rdquo; This is extensively used in Scotland. The chief peculiarity of bread from this is its decidedly acid taste, thought to be due principally to lactic acid. Much salt is used in making this bread, and it has not the flavor of what, in some other countries, is called the best bread.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>A decade later, James Grant wrote in &lt;em>&lt;a href="https://archive.org/stream/grantsbreadchem00granrich/grantsbreadchem00granrich_djvu.txt">The Chemistry Of Breadmaking&lt;/a>&lt;/em> (1912):&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Bread prepared by the aid of barms is generally of poor volume and colour, rather liable to be holey, with dull bloom and texture somewhat variable, but the flavour as a rule is good. Barms are suitable for working strong, harsh flours by long, slow processes.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Hmmmm. The artisanal, open-crumb, slightly tangy, naturally leavened bread &lt;em>en vogue&lt;/em> all over the US today was not beloved in Europe a century ago.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-2/20230402_111157.jpg"
alt="WLP001 whole-wheat barm bread"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>whole-wheat barm bread, leavened exclusively with White Labs' WLP001 California ale yeast.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Interestingly, the old barm method survived the invasions of Romans, Saxons and Normans. Which makes sense because it produced the sweetest, lightest bread in the right hands. Like other ancient breads, barm bread was highly digestible and nutritious because the ferments were never single strains like they are today, and included lactic acid bacteria which also gave the bread a marvelous flavor.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Barm bread has recently enjoyed some revival because it&amp;rsquo;s a characteristic ancient bread of Britain, a true heritage. Today some British bakers still add ale to bread dough to give it the ancient flavor, which sets the British bread culture apart from others. It&amp;rsquo;s a shame that the process was &lt;a href="https://sourdough.com/blog/enzyme-bread-tech">bastardized by industrialization&lt;/a> to produce modern unwholesome yeast breads.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="how-to-get-barm">how to get barm&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>So how do you get barm? There are several ways.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Option #1: You can always ask your neighborhood &lt;strong>craft brewers&lt;/strong> or &lt;strong>home-brewing friends&lt;/strong> for some spare barm. It can be an interesting educational process, as apparently an ancient law declares that the brewer is bound to accede to your request. Your first task, though, is to convince the brewer that you mean to create bread with the barm and not a rival beer!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Option #2: &lt;a href="http://www.danlepard.com/">Dan Lepard&lt;/a>, an Australian-British baking celeb, has a famous &lt;strong>shortcut for a quick barm&lt;/strong> in his book &lt;em>&lt;a href="https://www.thehandmadeloaf.com/">The Handmade Loaf&lt;/a>&lt;/em>, intended for people who don&amp;rsquo;t have malts and hops lying around the kitchen.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Basically, it involves gelatinizing 1 part of white flour with 5 parts of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brewing#Bottle_conditioning">bottle-conditioned&lt;/a> ale (heated to 158°F/70°C), letting it cool off to room temperature, and then inoculating with 0.4 part of leaven or yeast culture.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I haven&amp;rsquo;t tried his recipe, because there seems to be some weird contradiction. I bet a lot of people assume that the live yeast in the beer has something to do with making the bread rise. Nope, it doesn&amp;rsquo;t. Heating a fresh bottle of beer to &amp;gt;104°F (40°C) kills the live yeast in it, long before it reaches 158°F/70° where you&amp;rsquo;re supposed to whisk in the flour.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>You use bottle-conditioned beer for the same reasons you use freshly milled organic flour &amp;ndash; a bottle-conditioned beer has more flavor than one without. If you don&amp;rsquo;t understand these reasons, the recipe will still work.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I believe the purpose of heating the beer is to cook off some of the alcohol, which retards the action of yeast. Lepard was effectively using the beer as a flavoring, and then re-introducing yeasts via a leaven; however lovely the results may be, it&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em>not&lt;/em> a genuine barm bread. Lepard also says this is a perfect replica of the complex barm of the old times for the home bakers. Meh. I&amp;rsquo;m not satisfied with this method nor do I care for shortcuts. I want to make a barm from scratch.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Which leads me to option #3: &lt;strong>DIY from scratch&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-2/20230402_110840.jpg"
alt="WLP001 whole-wheat barm bread"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>whole-wheat barm bread, leavened exclusively with White Labs' WLP001 California ale yeast.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;h4 id="historic-barm">historic barm&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>William Jago&amp;rsquo;s 1911 classic, &lt;em>&lt;a href="https://archive.org/details/technologyofbrea00jagorich">The Technology of Bread-Making&lt;/a>&lt;/em>, gives three variations:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>compound barm (malt and hops);&lt;/li>
&lt;li>virgin barm (spontaneous fermentation with flour and water only); and&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Parisian barm (malt and flour).&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;Compound barm&amp;rdquo; is essentially unboiled wort, made with malt, hops and water, and then inoculated with an existing culture.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;Virgin barm&amp;rdquo;, containing only water and flour, differs from a sourdough starter in that it&amp;rsquo;s made with boiling water, i.e. the flour is gelatinized. Virgin barm should be left alone to ferment spontaneously, but even in 1911 bakers added &amp;ldquo;store&amp;rdquo; (an existing culture) to speed up the process.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;Parisian barm&amp;rdquo; includes malt again, together with scalded flour, but no hops. Virgin barm differed from Parisian only in being self-fermented.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;m interested in creating a barm that will increase the biodiversity of yeasts and maximize the aroma/flavor of the bread.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-2/20230402_112234.jpg"
alt="WLP001 whole-wheat barm bread"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>whole-wheat barm bread, leavened exclusively with White Labs' WLP001 California ale yeast.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;h4 id="19th-century-parisian-barm">19th-century Parisian barm&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>John Kirkland, in his 1927 book &lt;em>The Baker’s ABC&lt;/em>, wrote about barm:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;hellip;since bakers, or others for them, began to make a fermenting agent for themselves, about 1800, that has been described as bar, while the word yeast has been retained for the brewery product, as well for the more modern article sold in more solid form. Barm contains yeast cells, generally as a variety of species, as well as some of the liquor in which the yeast has been grown. Barms are of many kinds and all degrees of “strength”; that is, a particular lot may contain few or many yeast cells and much or little of the acids, peptones, alcohols, &amp;amp;c., which have resulted from earlier fermentations. Probably the earliest barm made, as distinguished from leavens &amp;ndash; was that from malt and hops as the baker in the first instance merely copied the brewer or the distiller.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This barm was known as compound or comp or patents. Some makers used a quantity of flour in the mixture, some did not. In Scotland, where barms were first made and where they continue in favour, the compound barm was displaced by a kind made with &lt;strong>scalded flour and malt&lt;/strong>. To this was given the name of &amp;ldquo;Parisian&amp;rdquo;, although no precise evidence to show that it was copied from the practice of Parisian bakers. Another sort which may contain a little malt , but may be all scalded and raw flour, is called “Virgin barm”.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>If there is such a thing as a &amp;ldquo;Parisian barm&amp;rdquo;, then I first learned this &amp;ldquo;scalded flour and malt&amp;rdquo; method from &lt;em>Russian&lt;/em> bakers, not Parisians.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Parisian barm was introduced from Paris to Scotland in the late 19th century. It&amp;rsquo;s essentially a scientific modification of the techniques of ancient Egypt and modern France.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>William Jago&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em>&lt;a href="https://archive.org/details/technologyofbrea00jagorich">The Technology of Bread-Making&lt;/a>&lt;/em>, mentioned above, does offer a recipe for &amp;ldquo;Parisian barm&amp;rdquo;, supplied by a Mr. J. Meikle, who was apparently a well-known baker and bread writer familiar with the Scottish baking trade. Meikle&amp;rsquo;s descriptions show an evolution of baking practice beginning with, and developing away from, beer-brewing techniques.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-2/1910-Parisian-barm.png"
alt="Meikle&amp;#39;s Parisian barm recipe"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Mr. J. Meikle&amp;rsquo;s Parisian barm recipe&lt;/p>&lt;p>Source: &lt;a href="https://archive.org/details/technologyofbrea00jagorich/page/238/mode/2up" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">The Technology of Bread-Making (1911) by William Jago&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>This is very similar to the &lt;em>opara&lt;/em> (yeasted scald-sponge) method I&amp;rsquo;ve always relied on to make complex Baltic rye breads.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>&lt;a href="https://www.gutenberg.org/files/53627/53627-h/53627-h.htm">The Bread and Biscuit Baker&amp;rsquo;s and Sugar-Boiler&amp;rsquo;s Assistant&lt;/a>&lt;/em> (1890) by Robert Wells gives a Parisian barm recipe using hops:&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-2/1890-Parisian-barm.png"
alt="Robert Wells&amp;#39; Parisian barm recipe"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Robert Wells' Parisian barm recipe&lt;/p>&lt;p>Source: &lt;a href="https://www.gutenberg.org/files/53627/53627-h/53627-h.htm" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">&lt;em>The Bread and Biscuit Baker&amp;rsquo;s and Sugar-Boiler&amp;rsquo;s Assistant&lt;/em> (1890)&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Why does Wells include hops in Parisian barm and Jago doesn&amp;rsquo;t? I speculate there might be a few reasons:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Barm made with hops is able to &amp;ldquo;overcome the power of foreign ferments longer than that made without hops, because the bitter of the hops is not suited to bacterial growth&amp;rdquo;, according to Shepperd&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em>&lt;a href="http://chestofbooks.com/food/science/Handbook-Of-Household-Science/Yeasts-Part-2.html%20">Hand-Book Of Household Science&lt;/a>&lt;/em> (1902). However, &amp;ldquo;one can use but little of a yeast made with hops without injuring the flavor of the bread, and a weak yeast acts so slowly as to cause disastrous results, it is better to make yeast oftener without hops, and use plenty of it in bread making.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Since barm without hops didn&amp;rsquo;t keep as well, maybe some bakers just continued using hops to prevent barm spoilage while others didn&amp;rsquo;t. Pasteurisation arrived in the late 1870s and fewer hops were needed as a preservative. It certainly shows that disputes over what is or isn&amp;rsquo;t a poolish, a sourdough, a barm, etc. predate internet bread-geek forums.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Hopstalgia, i.e. carryover from tradition or reverence for the old days, when barm used to be made from malt and hops as the baker copied the brewer/distiller. As mentioned above, one of the reasons that bakers moved away from beer yeast in the first place was because the hops made it unpleasantly bitter. The older generations who had grown up eating hoppy barm bread most likely developed an acquired taste and nostalgia for it. Compound barm (malt and hops), for example, was considered by many of the older bakers to be &amp;ldquo;&lt;em>the&lt;/em> barm for flavour in bread&amp;rdquo;, according to Jago&amp;rsquo;s 1911 &lt;a href="https://archive.org/details/technologyofbrea00jagorich">book&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;h4 id="my-21-century-barm">my 21-century barm&lt;/h4>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Turkey Red wheat flour, 100% extraction&lt;/td>
&lt;td>90.6%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>125g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->diastatic barley malt&lt;sup id="fnref:2">&lt;a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->(sun-dried Chevallier)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>9.4%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>13g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>hot water (180-185°F)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>181%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>250g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>liquid yeast (WLP001 - White Labs, CA)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1.8%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2.5g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Step 1: gelatinize the flour&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Put the whole wheat flour in a bowl; add hot water in 2-3 increments, stirring constantly.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Step 2: saccharify the scald&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Add the malt at the end (to prevent malt enzymes from being destroyed) and mix again. Cover and hold at 150-155°F for 6 hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The scald becomes sweet/saccharified, since the diastatic malt contains amylase that converts starch into simple sugars. Saccharifying literally means &amp;ldquo;to convert into sugar.&amp;rdquo; Or, in more scientific words, saccharifying is the process of converting a sugar derivative or complex carbohydrate into a simple soluble fermentable sugar by hydrolysis.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-2/20230331_082732.jpg"
alt="The barm, after 6 hours of saccharification and before fermentation."/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>The barm, after 6 hours of saccharification and before fermentation.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Why scald the flour first?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In order for the scald (&amp;ldquo;mash&amp;rdquo; in brewing) to be successful, we need heat and water to gelatinize the starch granules, essentially opening up their inner depths to expose the starch chains.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>However, heat and water alone don&amp;rsquo;t break down starch into simpler sugars &amp;ndash; not on their own, anyway. In order to do that, we need enzymes. Malted barley, particularly pale (diastatic) malt, is packed with natural enzymes that can break down these long starch chains into much shorter fermentables that can be metabolized by yeasts.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>To the plant, starch serves as a reserve of energy that the embryo plant can use when it starts to germinate. In late summer to early fall, the seed falls off the stalk. If it immediately starts to grow after hitting the ground, it would grow too much before winter and not survive the cold. This also means that the seed comes off the stalk in a storage form known as starch, which is very hardy and doesn&amp;rsquo;t degrade nearly as quickly as sugar. So the seed will just sit in a field until the time is right for it to start growing. Then, when that time comes, many complex biological and chemical changes start to kick in, converting the starches into readily available sugars for the growing plant. Enzymes in the seed will activate, start degrading the cell walls, and break down the long chemical chains of starch into the short chains of maltose (a simple sugar). The growing plant can utilize this maltose until its stalk has poked above the surface of the ground, starting to produce its own sugar through photosynthesis.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Malting mimics this natural process, so we can activate those enzymes that will convert the starch into sweet, tasty maltose that yeast loves to eat.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Certain enzymes are produced during the malting process; the two major ones are α-amylase and β-amylase.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A-amylase basically liquefies starch and turns it into a carbohydrate stew. It also chops up the starch at 1-4 links. Every time it cuts the chain, a reducing end and a non-reducing end are formed on the chain. Β-amylase can work only on the non-reducing end. It will lop off 2 molecules of the carb stew and blend with one water molecule, producing maltose. B-amylase also can lop off 3 molecules of starch, mixing with one water molecule producing maltriose. Maltriose is the sugar that yeast use during lagering phase.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>After α-amylase and β-amylase can reduce the chain no further, α-limit and β-limit dextrins are formed. β-limit dextrin can chop the starch down to a 1-6 link. Once, the enzyme gets to a branch, they&amp;rsquo;re done. Enzymes such as dextrinase and maltase are de-branching enzymes, typically destroyed during the kilning of modern malts. There are a limited amount left in minimally modified pilsner malt. De-branching enzymes help α-amylase and β-amylase produce many non-reducing ends. The more the non-reducing ends, the more β-amylase has to work with &amp;ndash; and faster.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Brewers typically boil their wort after mashing to sanitize it and to boost hop utilization (among other things), which denatures all the enzymes. Since I don&amp;rsquo;t nuke the saccarified scald like brewers (leaving it a &amp;ldquo;raw ale&amp;rdquo;), I get to keep the valuable secondary enzymes in play for more starch conversion to take place.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Secondary enzymes, compared to their amylase cousins, aren&amp;rsquo;t very active under thermophilic conditions. However, they do become more active during mesophilic fermentation and give us a &amp;ldquo;secondary conversion&amp;rdquo; in beerspeak. This secondary conversion actually increases the amount of fermentable sugars by as much as 15%, which is a huge boost to plant efficiency.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Like a beer mash, there are many kinds of sugars in saccharified scald:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>fructose, glucose, and sucrose: ~30%&lt;/li>
&lt;li>maltose: ~45%, which, like trehalose, is made from 2 glucose molecules, but with a different bond between them.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>maltotriose: ~20%, which is 3 glucose molecules, with the exact same bond between them as in maltose.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>The increased concentration of sugar could lead to caramelization, which makes the beer less fermentable (among other things). Since I&amp;rsquo;m not after alcohol production, this is not a problem. In fact, the extra sugar might even enhance the flavor profile.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Again, I used &lt;a href="https://www.whitelabs.com/yeast-single?id=101&amp;amp;type=YEAST">WLP001 California ale yeast&lt;/a> in this barm. WLP001 has an attenuation rate of 73%-85%.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-1/20230321_143837.jpg"
alt="WLP001 California Ale Yeast"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>A homebrew pouch of WLP001 California Ale Yeast, from White Labs.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>In brewing, attenuation refers to the conversion of sugars into alcohol and carbon dioxide by the fermentation process; the greater the attenuation, the more sugar has been converted into alcohol. A more attenuated beer is drier and more alcoholic than a less attenuated beer made from the same wort. High-attenuating yeast indicates that the particular strain ferments more of the sugars available in a wort relative to other yeast strains. This results in a drier finish in the finished beer.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A 50% attenuation rate means that 50% of the sugars have been converted into alcohol and CO₂ by yeast. A 100% attenuation means all of the sugars have been consumed by yeast.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Beer fermented with normal brewer&amp;rsquo;s yeast will never have 100% attenuation. A 100% fermentable sugar solution will only attenuate to the level that the yeast can tolerate the alcohol or lack of nutrients; whereas in a wort that contains 30% non-fermentables; a yeast that can go to 80% attenuation will stop at 70% attenuation because there is nothing left to ferment. This is important because it can help predict the final gravity and alcohol content of a beer. A yeast with low attenuation will leave a beer with more sugar and more body than a yeast with high attenuation. This can also be very helpful when selecting a yeast strain for a recipe.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>You should let the yeast know what it is to ferment. It&amp;rsquo;s actually a living thing.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&amp;ndash; Yves Benoit, head brewmaster at Brouwerij De Brabandere&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Fermentability of a wort is based on much more than temperature of the mash. The composition of the grist (e.g. total diastatic power) can have a much bigger effect than temperature alone. Unfermentable sugars have the greatest impact on your attenuation than any other factors. You can turn a dry stout into a sweet one by adding just lactose. Usually, the more the non-fermentables in the mash (crystal malt, partially kilned malt, etc), the lower the attenuation. Manipulating temperatures is a tool for overcoming the limitations of the grist.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In &lt;a href="https://books.google.com/books/about/Brewing_with_Wheat.html?id=jc2QAwAAQBAJ">&lt;em>Brewing with Wheat&lt;/em>&lt;/a>, Stan Hieronymus mentions how brewers change their mash profile for each batch of grain, knowing that while it all may be wheat, the wheat from one particular farmer is different than the wheat from another. This is exactly like baking bread with different wheat varieties from different farms!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Step 3: inoculate with yeast&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Let the scald cool off gradually to ~75°F. Add &lt;strong>2.5g of WLP001&lt;/strong> (~100 drops); stir vigorously and mix thoroughly.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Ferment at &lt;strong>70°F-73°F&lt;/strong> (high end of WLP001&amp;rsquo;s recommended temperature range of 64°F-73°F) to bring out the yeast&amp;rsquo;s character. After &lt;strong>12 hours&lt;/strong>, the barm doubled in volume and started to fall and pull away from the sides of the bowl. It was ready.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-2/20230331_204415.jpg"
alt="WLP001 barm, after 12 hours of fermentation"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>WLP001 barm, after 12 hours of fermentation at 70°F-73°F.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Given the liquid yeast contains about 2.5 billion cells per mL and 2.5g has roughly 6.25 billion cells, the inoculation rate in the barm is about 16 million cells per gram.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Despite lower inoculation, I could tell the yeast was having much more fun in this saccharified scald loaded with nutrients than in the previous &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-1/">straight poolish&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Mr. J. Meikle was certainly spot on:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Parisian barm while fermenting behaves like a thin ferment made with distillers' yeast, sugar and a handful of flour, only the bells and gas bubbles are larger and brighter.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;h4 id="final-dough">final dough&lt;/h4>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Turkey Red wheat, 100% extraction&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>375g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>water&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>375g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>barm&lt;/td>
&lt;td>104%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>390.5g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sea salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>7.5g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>olive oil&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>20g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>The mixing process is the same as the &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-1/">straight poolish verison&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I let the dough ferment at &lt;strong>70-73°F&lt;/strong> for &lt;strong>8 hours&lt;/strong>, followed by another &lt;strong>14 hours&lt;/strong> at &lt;strong>60-63°F&lt;/strong>. The dough had nearly doubled in volume after 22 hours. That&amp;rsquo;s when I baked it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I just tipped the dough out onto a baking sheet; no shaping or slashing. I baked it at 350°F for 25 minutes.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-2/20230402_094542.jpg"
alt="WLP001 whole-wheat barm bread"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>WLP001 whole-wheat barm bread, baked.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Again, the bread smelled like buttery biscuits and toasted crackers during baking.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The bread felt much lighter in my hand than the &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-1/">poolish version&lt;/a>. The crumb turned out more like my usual sourdough &lt;em>pan de cristal&lt;/em> &amp;ndash; airy and open, with bigger, more irregular holes.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-2/20230402_095350.jpg"
alt="WLP001 whole-wheat barm bread"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>WLP001 whole-wheat barm bread, sliced.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Mr. J. Meikle was spot on again:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>The barm has the strength, without the &amp;ldquo;rampness,&amp;rdquo; of compound, and the mildness without the weakness of Virgin.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>The bread had a springy and chewy texture, and a nutty, slightly salty flavor that&amp;rsquo;s noticeably more complex than the &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-1/">straight poolish verison&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I tasted the same &lt;strong>clean, robust wheat flavor&lt;/strong> without a trace of tanginess, like eating Triscuit® Original whole wheat crackers (America&amp;rsquo;s favorite shredded wheat snacks), the opposite of sourdough breads.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I don&amp;rsquo;t think I&amp;rsquo;ve ever tasted a bread with such a dominating wheat flavor.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-2/20230402_110354.jpg"
alt="WLP001 whole-wheat barm bread"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>WLP001 whole-wheat barm bread, sliced.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Just like how WLP001 accentuates hop flavors in beers, I think the yeast accentuates wheat flavors in breads. The flavor of Turkey Red seems 5x-10x amplified in this WLP001 bread than in any of my sourdough breads.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The closest beer comparison I could think of is probably &lt;a href="https://www.anchorbrewing.com/blog/american-wheat-beers-heritage-and-history/">&lt;strong>American wheat beer&lt;/strong>&lt;/a>, something like &lt;a href="https://www.anchorbrewing.com/beer/summer_beer">Anchor Brewing&amp;rsquo;s Summer® Wheat&lt;/a>, the first American wheat beer brewed since Prohibition and released in the summer of 1984: medium-bodied, wheat-emphatic, clean and balanced; a smooth, crisp, and slightly bready mouthfeel.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-2/20230402_110548.jpg"
alt="WLP001 whole-wheat barm bread"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>WLP001 whole-wheat barm bread, sliced.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Adding 2% salt to the final dough was a good idea &amp;ndash; the extra salt opened up the taste buds.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The bread tasted great with a sharp cheddar and good mustard like Alstertor beer mustard, which IMO is the Charlize Theron of mustards: smooth, but not without an edge.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>There&amp;rsquo;s nothing like sitting down at the end of a day with a glass of your own fresh ale and a loaf of fresh homemade bread. The only thing to add might be homemade cheese or prosciutto!&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-2/20230402_112353.jpg"
alt="WLP001 whole-wheat barm bread"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>WLP001 whole-wheat barm bread, sliced.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>&lt;code>Note&lt;/code>:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I don&amp;rsquo;t think retarding beer yeast doughs at lower temperatures, as you would with sourdough breads, contributes much in terms of flavor or texture. It only makes scheduling easier.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Special thanks to White Labs, especially Erik Fowler in San Diego, CA and Bert Sheffield in Asheville, NC.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>How is this barm related to the adjective &lt;em>barmy&lt;/em>? When it first emerged in the language in the early 1500s, the adjective &lt;em>barmy&lt;/em> meant precisely that: full of froth, foam, or barm. But before long a figurative meaning had developed, so that by the early 17th century people who were just as excitably lively or as bubbly as a pint of beer&amp;rsquo;s foaming barm were being described in equivalent terms. From there, the more recent use of barmy to mean &amp;ldquo;unhinged&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;deranged&amp;rdquo;, or generally &amp;ldquo;not thinking straight&amp;rdquo; emerged &amp;ndash; the latter of which, at least, could always be blamed on consuming a bit too much barm.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>I malted a batch of heritage Chevallier barley at home myself and sun-dried them before grinding into a flour, to ensure the malt remained as pale as possible.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/section></content></item></channel></rss>