<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>diastatic barley malt on HERESY LEVAIN</title><link>/tags/diastatic-barley-malt/</link><description>Latest experiments in diastatic barley malt from HERESY LEVAIN</description><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2023 HERESY LEVAIN 🍞 CC BY-NC-SA 4.0</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 02 Apr 2023 22:55:42 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/diastatic-barley-malt/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>levure de bière #1.2: California ale yeast</title><link>/posts/byb-1-2/</link><pubDate>Sun, 02 Apr 2023 22:55:42 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/byb-1-2/</guid><description>A high-hydration whole-wheat bread leavened exclusively with WLP001 California ale yeast &lt;em>barm&lt;/em>. The crumb turned out much lighter and airier than the poolish version, more like sourdough breads. The taste was similarly clean and wheat-emphatic, without the slightest tang of acidity, reminiscent of Triscuit Original whole wheat crackers or Anchor Brewing&amp;rsquo;s Summer Wheat.</description><content>&lt;p>&lt;em>Beer = liquid bread. Want to stay updated on my &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/craft-beer-yeast">craft beer yeast bread-plays&lt;/a>? Subscribe to the &lt;a href="https://tinyletter.com/breadbuster">newsletter&lt;/a>!&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>As mentioned in my &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-1/">last breadpost&lt;/a>, &lt;strong>barm&lt;/strong> is simply a thick yeasty froth or scum formed on the top of a fermenting liquid, like beer or wine.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The original method of making yeast bread in Britain was a by-product of ale-making. When traditional ale is made, a yeasty froth appears on top of the fermenting liquid (the wort). This used to be scooped off, washed, and then added to bread dough as a leaven. Bread made this way is sweet, light, and fluffy, and the leavening yeast used to be called &amp;ldquo;barm&amp;rdquo;. Its unpredictability gives us the word &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->&amp;ldquo;barmy&amp;rdquo;&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Barm first appeared in written records before the 12th century. It came from Middle English &lt;em>berme&lt;/em>, which came from Old English &lt;em>beorma&lt;/em>; it&amp;rsquo;s akin to Middle Low German &lt;em>berm&lt;/em> (yeast), Latin &lt;em>fermentum&lt;/em> (yeast), &lt;em>fervēre&lt;/em> (to boil), and Old Irish &lt;em>berbaid&lt;/em> (he boils). The word has been in use more loosely since the 13th century in reference to the foam or &amp;ldquo;head&amp;rdquo; of a pint of beer.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Using barm to leaven bread appears to be an ancient method developed by Gaelic peoples in the mists of time (no wonder Scottish bakers were the last in Britain to ditch baking with barm), and was quite different from that used in Europe, i.e. leaven bread with a sourdough or leaven (called &amp;ldquo;levain&amp;rdquo; in French). When the Romans first conquered Gaul (modern-day France), they were astonished by the light sweet bread made by the Celtic inhabitants. Barm bread survived with the Celtic peoples in Britain, Scotland and Éire, but was not common in Europe &amp;ndash; in fact, it was even condemned during the Enlightenment as &amp;ldquo;unwholesome&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-2/20230402_111008.jpg"
alt="WLP001 whole-wheat barm bread"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>whole-wheat barm bread, leavened exclusively with White Labs' WLP001 California ale yeast.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>In England, noblemen&amp;rsquo;s bread &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Manchet">manchet&lt;/a>&amp;rdquo; was always made with barm, whereas the commoners' bread &amp;ldquo;maslin&amp;rdquo; was usually leavened with a sourdough. Barm bread survived until World War II &amp;ndash; and even later in northern England largely as &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Barm_cake">barm cakes&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In the 19th century, the barm process was refined and industrialized; &amp;ldquo;yeast&amp;rdquo; began to be manufactured on a large scale, and used worldwide as &lt;em>the&lt;/em> method to leaven bread.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Curiously, the old method of making a sponge, i.e. a thick batter of flour and water with the barm, was still used with the new industrially-produced yeast, and was re-introduced to Europe from Vienna where the first yeast factories were established. Viennese bakers who emigrated to France around 1840 initiated the production of Viennese breads and other luxury bakery products in Paris using such technique. This became popular in France as a &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href="https://bakerpedia.com/processes/poolish/">poolish&lt;/a>&amp;rdquo; (an Old English version of &amp;ldquo;Polish&amp;rdquo;, as this method was first developed in Poland); bakers switched from using combinations of yeast and sourdough (&lt;em>sur levain&lt;/em>) to yeast alone for making crusty bread such as baguettes at bakeshops.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-2/20230402_111040.jpg"
alt="WLP001 whole-wheat barm bread"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>whole-wheat barm bread, leavened exclusively with White Labs' WLP001 California ale yeast.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>At the beginning of the 20th century, barm was no longer universally held in high esteem.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A 1902 domestic science book, &lt;em>&lt;a href="https://chestofbooks.com/food/science/Handbook-Of-Household-Science/Yeasts-Part-2.html">Hand-Book Of Household Science&lt;/a>&lt;/em> by Juniata L. Shepperd, considered acidity in barm bread a defect:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>There is another variety of patent yeast known as &amp;ldquo;flour barm.&amp;rdquo; This is extensively used in Scotland. The chief peculiarity of bread from this is its decidedly acid taste, thought to be due principally to lactic acid. Much salt is used in making this bread, and it has not the flavor of what, in some other countries, is called the best bread.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>A decade later, James Grant wrote in &lt;em>&lt;a href="https://archive.org/stream/grantsbreadchem00granrich/grantsbreadchem00granrich_djvu.txt">The Chemistry Of Breadmaking&lt;/a>&lt;/em> (1912):&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Bread prepared by the aid of barms is generally of poor volume and colour, rather liable to be holey, with dull bloom and texture somewhat variable, but the flavour as a rule is good. Barms are suitable for working strong, harsh flours by long, slow processes.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Hmmmm. The artisanal, open-crumb, slightly tangy, naturally leavened bread &lt;em>en vogue&lt;/em> all over the US today was not beloved in Europe a century ago.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-2/20230402_111157.jpg"
alt="WLP001 whole-wheat barm bread"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>whole-wheat barm bread, leavened exclusively with White Labs' WLP001 California ale yeast.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Interestingly, the old barm method survived the invasions of Romans, Saxons and Normans. Which makes sense because it produced the sweetest, lightest bread in the right hands. Like other ancient breads, barm bread was highly digestible and nutritious because the ferments were never single strains like they are today, and included lactic acid bacteria which also gave the bread a marvelous flavor.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Barm bread has recently enjoyed some revival because it&amp;rsquo;s a characteristic ancient bread of Britain, a true heritage. Today some British bakers still add ale to bread dough to give it the ancient flavor, which sets the British bread culture apart from others. It&amp;rsquo;s a shame that the process was &lt;a href="https://sourdough.com/blog/enzyme-bread-tech">bastardized by industrialization&lt;/a> to produce modern unwholesome yeast breads.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="how-to-get-barm">how to get barm&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>So how do you get barm? There are several ways.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Option #1: You can always ask your neighborhood &lt;strong>craft brewers&lt;/strong> or &lt;strong>home-brewing friends&lt;/strong> for some spare barm. It can be an interesting educational process, as apparently an ancient law declares that the brewer is bound to accede to your request. Your first task, though, is to convince the brewer that you mean to create bread with the barm and not a rival beer!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Option #2: &lt;a href="http://www.danlepard.com/">Dan Lepard&lt;/a>, an Australian-British baking celeb, has a famous &lt;strong>shortcut for a quick barm&lt;/strong> in his book &lt;em>&lt;a href="https://www.thehandmadeloaf.com/">The Handmade Loaf&lt;/a>&lt;/em>, intended for people who don&amp;rsquo;t have malts and hops lying around the kitchen.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Basically, it involves gelatinizing 1 part of white flour with 5 parts of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brewing#Bottle_conditioning">bottle-conditioned&lt;/a> ale (heated to 158°F/70°C), letting it cool off to room temperature, and then inoculating with 0.4 part of leaven or yeast culture.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I haven&amp;rsquo;t tried his recipe, because there seems to be some weird contradiction. I bet a lot of people assume that the live yeast in the beer has something to do with making the bread rise. Nope, it doesn&amp;rsquo;t. Heating a fresh bottle of beer to &amp;gt;104°F (40°C) kills the live yeast in it, long before it reaches 158°F/70° where you&amp;rsquo;re supposed to whisk in the flour.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>You use bottle-conditioned beer for the same reasons you use freshly milled organic flour &amp;ndash; a bottle-conditioned beer has more flavor than one without. If you don&amp;rsquo;t understand these reasons, the recipe will still work.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I believe the purpose of heating the beer is to cook off some of the alcohol, which retards the action of yeast. Lepard was effectively using the beer as a flavoring, and then re-introducing yeasts via a leaven; however lovely the results may be, it&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em>not&lt;/em> a genuine barm bread. Lepard also says this is a perfect replica of the complex barm of the old times for the home bakers. Meh. I&amp;rsquo;m not satisfied with this method nor do I care for shortcuts. I want to make a barm from scratch.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Which leads me to option #3: &lt;strong>DIY from scratch&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-2/20230402_110840.jpg"
alt="WLP001 whole-wheat barm bread"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>whole-wheat barm bread, leavened exclusively with White Labs' WLP001 California ale yeast.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;h4 id="historic-barm">historic barm&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>William Jago&amp;rsquo;s 1911 classic, &lt;em>&lt;a href="https://archive.org/details/technologyofbrea00jagorich">The Technology of Bread-Making&lt;/a>&lt;/em>, gives three variations:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>compound barm (malt and hops);&lt;/li>
&lt;li>virgin barm (spontaneous fermentation with flour and water only); and&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Parisian barm (malt and flour).&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;Compound barm&amp;rdquo; is essentially unboiled wort, made with malt, hops and water, and then inoculated with an existing culture.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;Virgin barm&amp;rdquo;, containing only water and flour, differs from a sourdough starter in that it&amp;rsquo;s made with boiling water, i.e. the flour is gelatinized. Virgin barm should be left alone to ferment spontaneously, but even in 1911 bakers added &amp;ldquo;store&amp;rdquo; (an existing culture) to speed up the process.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;Parisian barm&amp;rdquo; includes malt again, together with scalded flour, but no hops. Virgin barm differed from Parisian only in being self-fermented.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;m interested in creating a barm that will increase the biodiversity of yeasts and maximize the aroma/flavor of the bread.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-2/20230402_112234.jpg"
alt="WLP001 whole-wheat barm bread"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>whole-wheat barm bread, leavened exclusively with White Labs' WLP001 California ale yeast.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;h4 id="19th-century-parisian-barm">19th-century Parisian barm&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>John Kirkland, in his 1927 book &lt;em>The Baker’s ABC&lt;/em>, wrote about barm:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;hellip;since bakers, or others for them, began to make a fermenting agent for themselves, about 1800, that has been described as bar, while the word yeast has been retained for the brewery product, as well for the more modern article sold in more solid form. Barm contains yeast cells, generally as a variety of species, as well as some of the liquor in which the yeast has been grown. Barms are of many kinds and all degrees of “strength”; that is, a particular lot may contain few or many yeast cells and much or little of the acids, peptones, alcohols, &amp;amp;c., which have resulted from earlier fermentations. Probably the earliest barm made, as distinguished from leavens &amp;ndash; was that from malt and hops as the baker in the first instance merely copied the brewer or the distiller.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This barm was known as compound or comp or patents. Some makers used a quantity of flour in the mixture, some did not. In Scotland, where barms were first made and where they continue in favour, the compound barm was displaced by a kind made with &lt;strong>scalded flour and malt&lt;/strong>. To this was given the name of &amp;ldquo;Parisian&amp;rdquo;, although no precise evidence to show that it was copied from the practice of Parisian bakers. Another sort which may contain a little malt , but may be all scalded and raw flour, is called “Virgin barm”.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>If there is such a thing as a &amp;ldquo;Parisian barm&amp;rdquo;, then I first learned this &amp;ldquo;scalded flour and malt&amp;rdquo; method from &lt;em>Russian&lt;/em> bakers, not Parisians.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Parisian barm was introduced from Paris to Scotland in the late 19th century. It&amp;rsquo;s essentially a scientific modification of the techniques of ancient Egypt and modern France.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>William Jago&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em>&lt;a href="https://archive.org/details/technologyofbrea00jagorich">The Technology of Bread-Making&lt;/a>&lt;/em>, mentioned above, does offer a recipe for &amp;ldquo;Parisian barm&amp;rdquo;, supplied by a Mr. J. Meikle, who was apparently a well-known baker and bread writer familiar with the Scottish baking trade. Meikle&amp;rsquo;s descriptions show an evolution of baking practice beginning with, and developing away from, beer-brewing techniques.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-2/1910-Parisian-barm.png"
alt="Meikle&amp;#39;s Parisian barm recipe"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Mr. J. Meikle&amp;rsquo;s Parisian barm recipe&lt;/p>&lt;p>Source: &lt;a href="https://archive.org/details/technologyofbrea00jagorich/page/238/mode/2up" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">The Technology of Bread-Making (1911) by William Jago&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>This is very similar to the &lt;em>opara&lt;/em> (yeasted scald-sponge) method I&amp;rsquo;ve always relied on to make complex Baltic rye breads.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>&lt;a href="https://www.gutenberg.org/files/53627/53627-h/53627-h.htm">The Bread and Biscuit Baker&amp;rsquo;s and Sugar-Boiler&amp;rsquo;s Assistant&lt;/a>&lt;/em> (1890) by Robert Wells gives a Parisian barm recipe using hops:&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-2/1890-Parisian-barm.png"
alt="Robert Wells&amp;#39; Parisian barm recipe"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Robert Wells' Parisian barm recipe&lt;/p>&lt;p>Source: &lt;a href="https://www.gutenberg.org/files/53627/53627-h/53627-h.htm" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">&lt;em>The Bread and Biscuit Baker&amp;rsquo;s and Sugar-Boiler&amp;rsquo;s Assistant&lt;/em> (1890)&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Why does Wells include hops in Parisian barm and Jago doesn&amp;rsquo;t? I speculate there might be a few reasons:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Barm made with hops is able to &amp;ldquo;overcome the power of foreign ferments longer than that made without hops, because the bitter of the hops is not suited to bacterial growth&amp;rdquo;, according to Shepperd&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em>&lt;a href="http://chestofbooks.com/food/science/Handbook-Of-Household-Science/Yeasts-Part-2.html%20">Hand-Book Of Household Science&lt;/a>&lt;/em> (1902). However, &amp;ldquo;one can use but little of a yeast made with hops without injuring the flavor of the bread, and a weak yeast acts so slowly as to cause disastrous results, it is better to make yeast oftener without hops, and use plenty of it in bread making.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Since barm without hops didn&amp;rsquo;t keep as well, maybe some bakers just continued using hops to prevent barm spoilage while others didn&amp;rsquo;t. Pasteurisation arrived in the late 1870s and fewer hops were needed as a preservative. It certainly shows that disputes over what is or isn&amp;rsquo;t a poolish, a sourdough, a barm, etc. predate internet bread-geek forums.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Hopstalgia, i.e. carryover from tradition or reverence for the old days, when barm used to be made from malt and hops as the baker copied the brewer/distiller. As mentioned above, one of the reasons that bakers moved away from beer yeast in the first place was because the hops made it unpleasantly bitter. The older generations who had grown up eating hoppy barm bread most likely developed an acquired taste and nostalgia for it. Compound barm (malt and hops), for example, was considered by many of the older bakers to be &amp;ldquo;&lt;em>the&lt;/em> barm for flavour in bread&amp;rdquo;, according to Jago&amp;rsquo;s 1911 &lt;a href="https://archive.org/details/technologyofbrea00jagorich">book&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;h4 id="my-21-century-barm">my 21-century barm&lt;/h4>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Turkey Red wheat flour, 100% extraction&lt;/td>
&lt;td>90.6%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>125g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->diastatic barley malt&lt;sup id="fnref:2">&lt;a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->(sun-dried Chevallier)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>9.4%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>13g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>hot water (180-185°F)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>181%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>250g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>liquid yeast (WLP001 - White Labs, CA)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1.8%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2.5g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Step 1: gelatinize the flour&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Put the whole wheat flour in a bowl; add hot water in 2-3 increments, stirring constantly.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Step 2: saccharify the scald&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Add the malt at the end (to prevent malt enzymes from being destroyed) and mix again. Cover and hold at 150-155°F for 6 hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The scald becomes sweet/saccharified, since the diastatic malt contains amylase that converts starch into simple sugars. Saccharifying literally means &amp;ldquo;to convert into sugar.&amp;rdquo; Or, in more scientific words, saccharifying is the process of converting a sugar derivative or complex carbohydrate into a simple soluble fermentable sugar by hydrolysis.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-2/20230331_082732.jpg"
alt="The barm, after 6 hours of saccharification and before fermentation."/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>The barm, after 6 hours of saccharification and before fermentation.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Why scald the flour first?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In order for the scald (&amp;ldquo;mash&amp;rdquo; in brewing) to be successful, we need heat and water to gelatinize the starch granules, essentially opening up their inner depths to expose the starch chains.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>However, heat and water alone don&amp;rsquo;t break down starch into simpler sugars &amp;ndash; not on their own, anyway. In order to do that, we need enzymes. Malted barley, particularly pale (diastatic) malt, is packed with natural enzymes that can break down these long starch chains into much shorter fermentables that can be metabolized by yeasts.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>To the plant, starch serves as a reserve of energy that the embryo plant can use when it starts to germinate. In late summer to early fall, the seed falls off the stalk. If it immediately starts to grow after hitting the ground, it would grow too much before winter and not survive the cold. This also means that the seed comes off the stalk in a storage form known as starch, which is very hardy and doesn&amp;rsquo;t degrade nearly as quickly as sugar. So the seed will just sit in a field until the time is right for it to start growing. Then, when that time comes, many complex biological and chemical changes start to kick in, converting the starches into readily available sugars for the growing plant. Enzymes in the seed will activate, start degrading the cell walls, and break down the long chemical chains of starch into the short chains of maltose (a simple sugar). The growing plant can utilize this maltose until its stalk has poked above the surface of the ground, starting to produce its own sugar through photosynthesis.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Malting mimics this natural process, so we can activate those enzymes that will convert the starch into sweet, tasty maltose that yeast loves to eat.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Certain enzymes are produced during the malting process; the two major ones are α-amylase and β-amylase.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A-amylase basically liquefies starch and turns it into a carbohydrate stew. It also chops up the starch at 1-4 links. Every time it cuts the chain, a reducing end and a non-reducing end are formed on the chain. Β-amylase can work only on the non-reducing end. It will lop off 2 molecules of the carb stew and blend with one water molecule, producing maltose. B-amylase also can lop off 3 molecules of starch, mixing with one water molecule producing maltriose. Maltriose is the sugar that yeast use during lagering phase.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>After α-amylase and β-amylase can reduce the chain no further, α-limit and β-limit dextrins are formed. β-limit dextrin can chop the starch down to a 1-6 link. Once, the enzyme gets to a branch, they&amp;rsquo;re done. Enzymes such as dextrinase and maltase are de-branching enzymes, typically destroyed during the kilning of modern malts. There are a limited amount left in minimally modified pilsner malt. De-branching enzymes help α-amylase and β-amylase produce many non-reducing ends. The more the non-reducing ends, the more β-amylase has to work with &amp;ndash; and faster.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Brewers typically boil their wort after mashing to sanitize it and to boost hop utilization (among other things), which denatures all the enzymes. Since I don&amp;rsquo;t nuke the saccarified scald like brewers (leaving it a &amp;ldquo;raw ale&amp;rdquo;), I get to keep the valuable secondary enzymes in play for more starch conversion to take place.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Secondary enzymes, compared to their amylase cousins, aren&amp;rsquo;t very active under thermophilic conditions. However, they do become more active during mesophilic fermentation and give us a &amp;ldquo;secondary conversion&amp;rdquo; in beerspeak. This secondary conversion actually increases the amount of fermentable sugars by as much as 15%, which is a huge boost to plant efficiency.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Like a beer mash, there are many kinds of sugars in saccharified scald:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>fructose, glucose, and sucrose: ~30%&lt;/li>
&lt;li>maltose: ~45%, which, like trehalose, is made from 2 glucose molecules, but with a different bond between them.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>maltotriose: ~20%, which is 3 glucose molecules, with the exact same bond between them as in maltose.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>The increased concentration of sugar could lead to caramelization, which makes the beer less fermentable (among other things). Since I&amp;rsquo;m not after alcohol production, this is not a problem. In fact, the extra sugar might even enhance the flavor profile.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Again, I used &lt;a href="https://www.whitelabs.com/yeast-single?id=101&amp;amp;type=YEAST">WLP001 California ale yeast&lt;/a> in this barm. WLP001 has an attenuation rate of 73%-85%.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-1/20230321_143837.jpg"
alt="WLP001 California Ale Yeast"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>A homebrew pouch of WLP001 California Ale Yeast, from White Labs.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>In brewing, attenuation refers to the conversion of sugars into alcohol and carbon dioxide by the fermentation process; the greater the attenuation, the more sugar has been converted into alcohol. A more attenuated beer is drier and more alcoholic than a less attenuated beer made from the same wort. High-attenuating yeast indicates that the particular strain ferments more of the sugars available in a wort relative to other yeast strains. This results in a drier finish in the finished beer.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A 50% attenuation rate means that 50% of the sugars have been converted into alcohol and CO₂ by yeast. A 100% attenuation means all of the sugars have been consumed by yeast.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Beer fermented with normal brewer&amp;rsquo;s yeast will never have 100% attenuation. A 100% fermentable sugar solution will only attenuate to the level that the yeast can tolerate the alcohol or lack of nutrients; whereas in a wort that contains 30% non-fermentables; a yeast that can go to 80% attenuation will stop at 70% attenuation because there is nothing left to ferment. This is important because it can help predict the final gravity and alcohol content of a beer. A yeast with low attenuation will leave a beer with more sugar and more body than a yeast with high attenuation. This can also be very helpful when selecting a yeast strain for a recipe.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>You should let the yeast know what it is to ferment. It&amp;rsquo;s actually a living thing.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&amp;ndash; Yves Benoit, head brewmaster at Brouwerij De Brabandere&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Fermentability of a wort is based on much more than temperature of the mash. The composition of the grist (e.g. total diastatic power) can have a much bigger effect than temperature alone. Unfermentable sugars have the greatest impact on your attenuation than any other factors. You can turn a dry stout into a sweet one by adding just lactose. Usually, the more the non-fermentables in the mash (crystal malt, partially kilned malt, etc), the lower the attenuation. Manipulating temperatures is a tool for overcoming the limitations of the grist.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In &lt;a href="https://books.google.com/books/about/Brewing_with_Wheat.html?id=jc2QAwAAQBAJ">&lt;em>Brewing with Wheat&lt;/em>&lt;/a>, Stan Hieronymus mentions how brewers change their mash profile for each batch of grain, knowing that while it all may be wheat, the wheat from one particular farmer is different than the wheat from another. This is exactly like baking bread with different wheat varieties from different farms!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Step 3: inoculate with yeast&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Let the scald cool off gradually to ~75°F. Add &lt;strong>2.5g of WLP001&lt;/strong> (~100 drops); stir vigorously and mix thoroughly.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Ferment at &lt;strong>70°F-73°F&lt;/strong> (high end of WLP001&amp;rsquo;s recommended temperature range of 64°F-73°F) to bring out the yeast&amp;rsquo;s character. After &lt;strong>12 hours&lt;/strong>, the barm doubled in volume and started to fall and pull away from the sides of the bowl. It was ready.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-2/20230331_204415.jpg"
alt="WLP001 barm, after 12 hours of fermentation"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>WLP001 barm, after 12 hours of fermentation at 70°F-73°F.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Given the liquid yeast contains about 2.5 billion cells per mL and 2.5g has roughly 6.25 billion cells, the inoculation rate in the barm is about 16 million cells per gram.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Despite lower inoculation, I could tell the yeast was having much more fun in this saccharified scald loaded with nutrients than in the previous &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-1/">straight poolish&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Mr. J. Meikle was certainly spot on:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Parisian barm while fermenting behaves like a thin ferment made with distillers' yeast, sugar and a handful of flour, only the bells and gas bubbles are larger and brighter.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;h4 id="final-dough">final dough&lt;/h4>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Turkey Red wheat, 100% extraction&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>375g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>water&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>375g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>barm&lt;/td>
&lt;td>104%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>390.5g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sea salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>7.5g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>olive oil&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>20g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>The mixing process is the same as the &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-1/">straight poolish verison&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I let the dough ferment at &lt;strong>70-73°F&lt;/strong> for &lt;strong>8 hours&lt;/strong>, followed by another &lt;strong>14 hours&lt;/strong> at &lt;strong>60-63°F&lt;/strong>. The dough had nearly doubled in volume after 22 hours. That&amp;rsquo;s when I baked it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I just tipped the dough out onto a baking sheet; no shaping or slashing. I baked it at 350°F for 25 minutes.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-2/20230402_094542.jpg"
alt="WLP001 whole-wheat barm bread"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>WLP001 whole-wheat barm bread, baked.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Again, the bread smelled like buttery biscuits and toasted crackers during baking.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The bread felt much lighter in my hand than the &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-1/">poolish version&lt;/a>. The crumb turned out more like my usual sourdough &lt;em>pan de cristal&lt;/em> &amp;ndash; airy and open, with bigger, more irregular holes.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-2/20230402_095350.jpg"
alt="WLP001 whole-wheat barm bread"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>WLP001 whole-wheat barm bread, sliced.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Mr. J. Meikle was spot on again:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>The barm has the strength, without the &amp;ldquo;rampness,&amp;rdquo; of compound, and the mildness without the weakness of Virgin.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>The bread had a springy and chewy texture, and a nutty, slightly salty flavor that&amp;rsquo;s noticeably more complex than the &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-1/">straight poolish verison&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I tasted the same &lt;strong>clean, robust wheat flavor&lt;/strong> without a trace of tanginess, like eating Triscuit® Original whole wheat crackers (America&amp;rsquo;s favorite shredded wheat snacks), the opposite of sourdough breads.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I don&amp;rsquo;t think I&amp;rsquo;ve ever tasted a bread with such a dominating wheat flavor.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-2/20230402_110354.jpg"
alt="WLP001 whole-wheat barm bread"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>WLP001 whole-wheat barm bread, sliced.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Just like how WLP001 accentuates hop flavors in beers, I think the yeast accentuates wheat flavors in breads. The flavor of Turkey Red seems 5x-10x amplified in this WLP001 bread than in any of my sourdough breads.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The closest beer comparison I could think of is probably &lt;a href="https://www.anchorbrewing.com/blog/american-wheat-beers-heritage-and-history/">&lt;strong>American wheat beer&lt;/strong>&lt;/a>, something like &lt;a href="https://www.anchorbrewing.com/beer/summer_beer">Anchor Brewing&amp;rsquo;s Summer® Wheat&lt;/a>, the first American wheat beer brewed since Prohibition and released in the summer of 1984: medium-bodied, wheat-emphatic, clean and balanced; a smooth, crisp, and slightly bready mouthfeel.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-2/20230402_110548.jpg"
alt="WLP001 whole-wheat barm bread"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>WLP001 whole-wheat barm bread, sliced.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Adding 2% salt to the final dough was a good idea &amp;ndash; the extra salt opened up the taste buds.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The bread tasted great with a sharp cheddar and good mustard like Alstertor beer mustard, which IMO is the Charlize Theron of mustards: smooth, but not without an edge.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>There&amp;rsquo;s nothing like sitting down at the end of a day with a glass of your own fresh ale and a loaf of fresh homemade bread. The only thing to add might be homemade cheese or prosciutto!&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-2/20230402_112353.jpg"
alt="WLP001 whole-wheat barm bread"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>WLP001 whole-wheat barm bread, sliced.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>&lt;code>Note&lt;/code>:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I don&amp;rsquo;t think retarding beer yeast doughs at lower temperatures, as you would with sourdough breads, contributes much in terms of flavor or texture. It only makes scheduling easier.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Special thanks to White Labs, especially Erik Fowler in San Diego, CA and Bert Sheffield in Asheville, NC.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>How is this barm related to the adjective &lt;em>barmy&lt;/em>? When it first emerged in the language in the early 1500s, the adjective &lt;em>barmy&lt;/em> meant precisely that: full of froth, foam, or barm. But before long a figurative meaning had developed, so that by the early 17th century people who were just as excitably lively or as bubbly as a pint of beer&amp;rsquo;s foaming barm were being described in equivalent terms. From there, the more recent use of barmy to mean &amp;ldquo;unhinged&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;deranged&amp;rdquo;, or generally &amp;ldquo;not thinking straight&amp;rdquo; emerged &amp;ndash; the latter of which, at least, could always be blamed on consuming a bit too much barm.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>I malted a batch of heritage Chevallier barley at home myself and sun-dried them before grinding into a flour, to ensure the malt remained as pale as possible.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/section></content></item></channel></rss>