<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>blue corn on HERESY LEVAIN</title><link>/tags/blue-corn/</link><description>Latest experiments in blue corn from HERESY LEVAIN</description><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2023 HERESY LEVAIN 🍞 CC BY-NC-SA 4.0</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 23 Apr 2023 20:04:07 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/blue-corn/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>levure de bière #4: corn-fused on East Coast</title><link>/posts/byb-4/</link><pubDate>Sun, 23 Apr 2023 20:04:07 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/byb-4/</guid><description>A tasty and uniquely blue-colored Midwestern corn bread that combines Kansas wheat, Illinois corn, and East Coast ale yeast. Earthy and toasty aroma, reminiscent of cornfields. Subtle nutty corn flavor with toasty sweetness.</description><content>&lt;p>&lt;em>Beer = liquid bread. Want to stay updated on my &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/craft-beer-yeast">craft beer yeast bread-plays&lt;/a>? Subscribe to the &lt;a href="https://tinyletter.com/breadbuster">newsletter&lt;/a>!&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>I spent a few days in New York City and did some things I had not done before.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I took a trip uptown to the &lt;a href="https://www.wholefoodsmarket.com/stores/harlem">125th Street Whole Foods&lt;/a>. I went there, because it was a nice change from Lower and Midtown Manhattan. It was an easy trip (right by the 2/3 train), and I liked having reasons to go to Harlem. That Whole Foods is an easy punch line &amp;ndash; widely dubbed &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href="https://nymag.com/intelligencer/2017/07/harlem-gentrification-whole-foods-vanishing-new-york.html">the ultimate gentrifier&lt;/a>.&amp;rdquo; But I feel like people who say that don&amp;rsquo;t actually go there, because it fits in the neighborhood pretty well. And I saw lots of Black Harlemites there.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Getting away from middle-class urban spaces was refreshing to me. I enjoyed going out to Flushing, Elmhurst, and Ridgewood. It&amp;rsquo;s a totally different world out there. I went to see some friends who live near Yankee Stadium, and we hit one of the Jamaican spots there. Honestly, I didn&amp;rsquo;t get out of Manhattan much until my second year living in NYC. Then I&amp;rsquo;d start getting off at every stop along the 7 train, discovering all the amazing cuisines I could find there: Asian, African, South American, Persian, Mediterranean, Balkan&amp;hellip;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I walked to FieldTrip (a restaurant chain by Chef JJ Johnson that highlights &amp;ldquo;freshly milled, heirloom rice grains&amp;rdquo;) on Malcolm X Boulevard. I got the shrimp bowl (with coconut sticky rice), and a rice crispy treat spiked with dragon fruit juice for dessert. Every cuisine is getting the fast-casual bowl treatment these days.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I went to the new Harlem location of Charles Pan-Fried Chicken, on Edgecombe Avenue, for Harlem&amp;rsquo;s best remaining soul food. There used to be a little sandwich shop here that had really good cheesesteaks with a special sauce. I think it was run by the Nation of Islam.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>On my final day, I met up with some friends at BierWax Queens, a hip-hop and vinyl-themed bar in Ridgewood, run by some DJ, and had an imperial stout on draft (Memory &amp;amp; Perception by Finback Brewery in Queens). Lastly, I stopped by Newyorktitlan, a small hole-in-the-wall Mexican brunch spot nestled in the shadow of the M train near Myrtle-Wyckoff in Bushwick, and had &lt;em>chilaquiles&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Why do people live in New York? There is no relationship between them. Except for an inner electricity which results from the simple fact of their being crowded together. A magical sensation of contiguity and attraction for an artificial centrality. This is what makes it a self-attracting universe, which there is no reason to leave. There is no human reason to be here, except for the sheer ecstasy of being crowded together.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&amp;ndash; Jean Baudrillard, &lt;em>Amérique&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;hr>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-4/20230422_203120.jpg"
alt="blue corn bread"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Midwest blue corn bread: Kansas wheat + Illinois corn + East Coast ale yeast&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Contrary to what most people think, I always associate corn with the East Coast of the United States. I was first introduced to corn tortillas and &lt;em>paste di meliga&lt;/em> (Italian cornmeal shortbread cookies) in New York City, and then grits in South Carolina.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In Old English, corn meant &amp;ldquo;grain&amp;rdquo; instead of maize, because the latter was native to America. Brewing farmhouse ale from maize in Europe was an impossibility, simply because maize didn&amp;rsquo;t grow here. In Orkney, ales brewed from grains are referred to as &amp;ldquo;corn ale.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In the New World, however, corn = maize. Corn defined drinking and bread culture during America&amp;rsquo;s Colonial Era as well as the years after the Revolutionary War. Pilgrims made &amp;ldquo;thirded bread&amp;rdquo; (or Boston brown bread) with equal quantities of rye, wheat, and corn. Slather some butter, and it was a complete meal.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The colony of Connecticut couldn&amp;rsquo;t sustain wheat production, which meant that &amp;ldquo;thirded bread&amp;rdquo; was not a cultural survivor in the Provision State, although it was popular in other New England colonies. Instead, rye &amp;lsquo;n&amp;rsquo; injun, a steamed bread made with just rye and cornmeal &amp;ndash; &lt;em>sans&lt;/em> the wheat &amp;ndash; survives in Connecticut to this day. It&amp;rsquo;s famously mentioned in Laura Ingalls Wilder&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em>Farmer Boy&lt;/em> as part of one of Mother Wilder&amp;rsquo;s delicious meals.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Many varieties of corn had their origin in the northeastern US. Cultivated into the early years of the 20th century, the varieties disappeared from the region almost overnight. Changing farm practices and the abandonment of the local gristmills led to the demise of New England&amp;rsquo;s traditional corn varieties, even as the same varieties were being cultivated and milled widely around the world, from Spain to Japan.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Corn is remarkable among the grains, because it&amp;rsquo;s used as food from the emergence of the flower buds to the time the kernels are mature. Even among the dry, mature kernels, there is a range of colors, textures, and flavors. No other grain provides such culinary elasticity.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>More than just a kitchen ingredient, the corn plant is an elegant organism. The cornfield itself provides more than just a crop of wholesome kernels.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-4/20230417_220211.jpg"
alt="Rovey blue corn"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Blue corn from Rovey Seed Co. (Farmersville, Illinois)&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Once viewed as a gift of the gods, corn has slipped under a cloud, a victim of modernity&amp;rsquo;s prodigal and detached ways. Today few people actively produce corn from seed to harvest, crack the dry corn kernels into small pieces for backyard chickens, grind it for bread, or nixtamalize it for hominy, tamales, tortillas, etc. Furthering that detachment: Over the last century or so, corn has been transformed from a wholegrain dietary staple into an industrial chemistry kit.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Most of the corn produced in the US is turned into alcohol, starch, oil, and numerous chemicals used widely in food processing; the by-products are used to fatten livestock. The kernels are treated with a strong acid and &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Corn_wet-milling">wet-milled&lt;/a>, which allows the corn refiner to separate the starches, proteins, fibers, and oils. We consume corn throughout the day in the form of meat, soft drinks, and processed foods, but only rarely as a whole grain. As early as 1954, the corn-refining industry estimated that 50% of Americans' diet was based on corn &amp;ndash; that percentage is probably a lot higher now. Grain corn has been bred and engineered in astounding quantities to provide certain chemical and energy qualities, yet the modern cultivars of the grain are barely suitable as human food. In fact, some genetically modified types of corn are not even approved for human consumption.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>I just had a chance to experiment with some non-GMO food-grade grain corns from Derek Rovey, the 3rd-generation owner of &lt;a href="http://www.roveyseed.com/">Rovey Seed Co.&lt;/a>, based in Farmersville, Illinois. Turns out the tortillas I enjoyed in New England a few years ago were made with Rovey&amp;rsquo;s corn; I didn&amp;rsquo;t realize it until now.&lt;/p>
&lt;div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
&lt;iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/4ZXIqfJez5o" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video">&lt;/iframe>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>Rovey&amp;rsquo;s corn kernels are good-sized and thoroughly cleaned; I guess they utilize some of the latest cleaning and sorting technology.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This variety of blue corn has slightly less protein, less starch, and more sugar than its white and red counterparts. Its deep purple-blue color comes from its rich anthonyacin content, the same health-promoting compound found in dark berries.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Blue corn just hits different, and this variety is no exception.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-4/20230417_220446.jpg"
alt="Rovey blue corn"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Blue corn from Rovey Seed Co. (Farmersville, Illinois)&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>First, I tossed a handful of the blue corn kernels on a popcorn popper just out of curiosity. I knew that dent corn has softer kernels (higher content of soft starch) than popcorn, and I just wanted to see how the kernels differ when heated.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Well, the blue corn kernels popped more than I expected. They didn&amp;rsquo;t fully explode into a white, fluffy substance like popcorn, but turned out brittle and concussively crunchy like CornNuts® Crunchy Corn Snacks!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>These bluish-brown &amp;ldquo;corn nuts&amp;rdquo; had a very interesting tortilla flavor, too. It&amp;rsquo;s like eating a super crunchy taco shell. Maybe thousands of years ago, in these very lands, corn was toasted in hot sand until the kernels popped?&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-4/20230418_192351.jpg"
alt="Rovey blue corn popped"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Rovey&amp;rsquo;s blue corn kernels, popped!&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>I also made a bread with milled blue corn and WLP008 East Coast ale yeast.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="saccharified-corn-porridge">Saccharified corn porridge&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>I intended to achieve 2 goals with the corn porridge:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>To heighten the flavor of corn in the final dough; and&lt;/li>
&lt;li>To provide some fermentable starch for amylase in the diastatic malt. Amylase breaks down starch (made up of long chains of water-insoluble glucose molecules) into simple sugars (branched but shorter chains of water-soluble glucose), which can be metabolized by the yeast.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>To make corn fermentable, the starch it contains in the endosperm must first be gelatinized (i.e. breaking down the intermolecular bonds of starch molecules).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Grain starch is composed of glucose molecules bound together in chains. These grain starch chains come in two types: amylose and amylopectin. Amylose is essentially a straight chain of glucose molecules, not too complicated, but it has the ability to form pretty dense starch granules, particularly in some varieties of corn. Amylopectin has a branched structure of glucose strands and, for many grains, makes up ~75% of the total starch content.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-4/starch-amylose-amylopectin.png"
alt="Different sources of starch"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Different sources of starch, and their respective percentages of amylose and amylopectin.&lt;/p>&lt;p>Source: &lt;a href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/332008553_Starch-based_films_Major_factors_affecting_their_properties" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">Thakur et al. (2019)&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Different starches require different temperatures to properly gelatinize. Conveniently, the gelatinization temperature for barley starch is in a similar range to the amylase enzyme activity optimum. However, for corn starch, the gelatinization temperature is significantly higher. Corn starch granules are typically small in size, polyhedral in shape, and have relatively low amylopectin contents. This makes water penetration into the granule difficult at lower temperatures.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-4/starch-gelatinization.png"
alt="Different starches gelatinize at different temperature"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Different starches gelatinize at different temperatures (°C)&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Therefore, commonly recommended corn starch gelatinization temperature range is 158-176°F for ~30 minutes. Since I want to be certain that gelatinization is complete, the simplest way to do this is to cook the corn in boiling water. After gelatinization is complete, the starch can then be converted to sugar by amylase.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>wholegrain blue corn (Rovey Seeds, Illinois)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>90%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>180g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->diastatic barley malt (wind-dried Chevallier)&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>20g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>boiling water&lt;/td>
&lt;td>144%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>252g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Process:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Mill the whole-kernel blue corn into a fine flour (slightly finer than cornmeal).&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Roast the corn flour in a dry skillet on the stovetop until fragrant. This helps to bring out the rich, deep aroma and flavor of corn.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Set the malt aside. Mix roasted corn flour with boiling water, until evenly combined. Simmer on the stovetop over low heat (185-195°F) for 30 minutes, stirring frequently. This will sufficiently gelatinize the corn starch.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Cool down to ~155°F, stir in the malt, and mix well. Cover and hold at 140-150°F for 12 hours. Saccharification takes place in this temperature range, i.e. amylase converts sugar derivatives or complex carbohydrates into simple soluble fermentable sugars.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>After 12 hours, cool off slowly to room temperature.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>The saccharified roasted corn porridge made from Rovey&amp;rsquo;s blue corn took on a beautiful dark blue color and intoxicating aroma &amp;ndash; reminiscent of fresh tortilla chips and popcorn at the same time! It tasted sweet like unbaked cookies.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Total: 452g (to be divided into 152g and 300g)&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-4/20230422_204035.jpg"
alt="blue corn bread"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Blue corn bread, crumbshot&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;h3 id="corn-barm-wlp008">Corn barm: WLP008&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Remove 152g of the saccharified corn porridge &amp;ndash; this will become the barm. Set aside the rest for the final dough.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>saccharified corn porridge&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>152g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>East Coast ale yeast (WLP008 - White Labs, CA)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1.5g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.whitelabs.com/yeast-single?id=108&amp;amp;type=YEAST">WLP008&lt;/a> East Coast ale yeast &amp;ldquo;possesses a similar neutral character of WLP001 California Ale Yeast® with slightly higher ester production.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This strain has a slightly lower attenuation (70%-75%) compared to &lt;a href="https://www.whitelabs.com/yeast-single?id=101&amp;amp;type=YEAST">WLP001&lt;/a> (73%-85%), which &amp;ldquo;leaves some mouthfeel and residual sweetness which balances hop bitterness.&amp;rdquo; Sounds perfect for a slightly sweetish corn bread!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The recommended temperature range for WLP008 is 68°-73°F. I fermented the barm (semi-aerobically) at 70-73°F for 14 hours. When ripe, the barm became very bubbly and porous, with a faint ethanol aroma.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Don&amp;rsquo;t go overboard with fermentation here &amp;ndash; you&amp;rsquo;re making a bread, not moonshine!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Total: 153.5g&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-4/20230422_213722.jpg"
alt="blue corn bread"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Blue corn bread, crumbshot&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;h3 id="final-dough">Final dough&lt;/h3>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Turkey Red wheat, 100% extraction&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>350g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>saccharified corn porridge&lt;/td>
&lt;td>85.7%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>300g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>corn barm&lt;/td>
&lt;td>43.9%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>153.5g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>water (bassinage)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>16%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>56g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1.1%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>4g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Kansas-grown Turkey Red wheat + Illinois-grown dent corn. How &lt;a href="https://www.buzzfeed.com/martyfcmly/how-midwestern-are-you-b7kpy2yh9w">much more Midwestern&lt;/a> can it get?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Add everything together and mix thoroughly. The dough will be sticky and delicate. Adjust hydration as necessary. Corn seems to have an endless appetite for water.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Cover with a breathable, damp towel. Ferment at 70-73°F for 4 hours; perform 4 rounds of coil-fold, 45 minutes apart.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Keep the dough at 68-63°F for another 14 hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Shape as desired.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Final proof: 2 hours at ~72°F.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Bake: 45 minutes at 350°F.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-4/20230422_202150.jpg"
alt="blue corn bread"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Blue corn bread, fresh out of the oven.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;h3 id="tasting">Tasting&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>This true Midwestern bread had a striking natural blue color, an incredibly tender texture, and deeply nutty flavor.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Aroma&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Earthy and subtly toasty, with faint ethanol; reminded me of walking through a cornfield.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Texture&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The crust was thin and firm, but not unyielding; it held up the crumb well. Very easy to bite through and evidently gum-friendly (great for grandparents and kids).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The crumb felt springy in between my fingers; not crumbly at all like a &lt;a href="https://sallysbakingaddiction.com/my-favorite-cornbread/">typical cornbread&lt;/a>. The corn added a little firmness to the crumb, but it was still very moist and tender, custardy and creamy. The slices held up well like as bookends in sandwiches.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-4/20230422_204116.jpg"
alt="blue corn bread"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Blue corn bread, crumbshot&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Flavor&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A mild tortilla chip flavor upfront, quickly developing into a mellow sweetness with a fruity undertone and a little hoppiness, and ending with a mouthwatering sensation. Clean taste and a nice balance between nutty corn flavors and toasty sweetness.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I guess switching from West Coast ale yeast to East Coast ale yeast increased the malty sweetness and fruity esters, along with other subtle yeast characteristics.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-4/20230422_204411.jpg"
alt="blue corn bread"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Blue corn bread, sliced.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Corn definitely has some special emotional pull. I&amp;rsquo;m besotted.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Corn&amp;rsquo;s marvelous color and high soft starch content gave me a dozen ideas&amp;hellip; Stay tuned!&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>🍻 Special thanks to&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Derek Rovey, &lt;a href="http://www.roveyseed.com/">Rovey Seed Co.&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Bert Sheffield &amp;amp; Erik Fowler, &lt;a href="https://www.whitelabs.com/">White Labs&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>Homemade, fully modified.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/section></content></item></channel></rss>