<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>high extraction on HERESY LEVAIN</title><link>/tags/high-extraction/</link><description>Latest experiments in high extraction from HERESY LEVAIN</description><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2023 HERESY LEVAIN 🍞 CC BY-NC-SA 4.0</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 13 Sep 2020 22:50:39 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/high-extraction/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>The Wheatwalker</title><link>/posts/the-wheatwalker/</link><pubDate>Sun, 13 Sep 2020 22:50:39 -0700</pubDate><guid>/posts/the-wheatwalker/</guid><description>My first foray into baking with heirloom wheat: an experimental open-crumb wheaty bread made with locally grown and milled Turkey Red, the OG American wheat.</description><content>&lt;p>I recently took a trip to CoMo (Columbia, MO) to visit Richard Kapp&amp;rsquo;s lovely farm and &lt;a href="https://www.centralmissourigrainsforfood.com/">mill&lt;/a>. The moment Richard told me he had local Turkey Red, I was hooked. I had no idea Turkey Red could be grown in central Missouri.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Richard shared a lot of stories about local agriculture: growing hard wheats in Missouri is more challenging than selling bicycles in Alaska, because of the climate, soil, distribution, uncompetitive commercial potential, dearth of local interests, etc. The University of Missouri is far less keen on hard wheat trials and researches than Kansas and Nebraska.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Richard also gave me a nice tour of his farm, and kindly offered me a sample of his freshly milled organic Turkey Red flour (85% extraction) to try. This batch of Turkey Red was grown by Paul Lehmann, an organic farmer in Fayette (~25 miles northwest of CoMo).&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="the-og-american-wheat">The OG American wheat&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>Turkey Red is a type of hard red winter wheat brought to Kansas by Mennonite immigrants from Russia, the part now known as Ukraine, in the late 1870s. It ended up becoming the primary wheat variety grown in the Midwest for the next ~70 years. It grew especially well in Kansas and, by the early 20th century, was planted in more than 75% of the fields. (Hard red winter wheat was widely grown in the Great Plains area with Kansas as the center, and became known as &amp;ldquo;Kansas wheat.&amp;quot;)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>After World War II, as industrial farming and the &amp;ldquo;Green Revolution&amp;rdquo; started taking hold, this heritage variety faded away. Wheat began to be hybridized for yield and depend on the application of fertilizers, herbicides, pesticides, etc. The increase in productivity, in many cases, come at the cost of flavor and nutrition.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>There is speculation that the changes made during hybridization altered the protein and gluten structure of the grain, which has made modern hybrid wheat more difficult to digest and is thought to be the cause of gluten-intolerence in many people.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Unlike modern high-yielding dwarf wheat varieties, Turkey Red grows very tall, creating lots of straw and biomass for the soil. It&amp;rsquo;s a landrace variety, i.e. it contains genetic diversity making it adaptable across bio-regions. Fortunately, Turkey Red seeds were saved and this heritage wheat is making a comeback in many parts of the Midwest. It&amp;rsquo;s one of the most popular revival wheats used by US bakers, treasured for its flavor and digestibility.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>There is actually a museum in Goessel, Kansas dedicated to the Mennonite farmers who brought over Turkey Red seeds from Russia in 1874.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="master-formula">Master formula&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>Total Turkey Red flour used: 450g (440g in the dough + 10g bran for dusting)&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>total weight&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>flour&lt;/td>
&lt;td>440g&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>water&lt;/td>
&lt;td>380g&lt;/td>
&lt;td>86%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>levain&lt;/td>
&lt;td>88g&lt;/td>
&lt;td>20%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>9g&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->spent grains&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->&lt;/td>
&lt;td>45g&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>raisins&lt;/td>
&lt;td>20g&lt;/td>
&lt;td>4.5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Dusting:&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>reserved bran&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Process:&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>process&lt;/th>
&lt;th>time&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>bran soaking&lt;/td>
&lt;td>12 hours (75°F)&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>autolyse&lt;/td>
&lt;td>6 hours (60°F)&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>bulk ferment&lt;/td>
&lt;td>14 hours (44°F)&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>final proof&lt;/td>
&lt;td>3 hours (75°F)&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>bake&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1 hour&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>I used extended bran soaking, high hydration, and retarded cold fermentation in this dough to help draw out the natural flavors of heritage wheat flours.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h4 id="day-1">Day 1&lt;/h4>
&lt;h5 id="10pm">10pm&lt;/h5>
&lt;p>Sift 450g of the 85% extraction Turkey Red flour into&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>400g flour (~75% extraction)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>50g bran &amp;amp; germ
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>40g: for hot soaker&lt;/li>
&lt;li>10g: for dusting later&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Even though the 85% extraction flour has already been sifted, it still contains a fair amount of the bran and germ which can&amp;rsquo;t be milled as finely as the starch and can stand in the way of gluten formation.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Still, you want to hang on to every bit of these, because they contain important nutrients as well as a nuanced flavor from the local terroir.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Make a scalded soaker:&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>bran &amp;amp; germ&lt;/td>
&lt;td>40g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>boiling water&lt;/td>
&lt;td>160g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Mix well and let sit, covered, at room temperature for 12-18 hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h4 id="day-2">Day 2&lt;/h4>
&lt;h5 id="1pm">1pm&lt;/h5>
&lt;p>Mix together:&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sifted ~75% extraction flour&lt;/td>
&lt;td>400g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>scalded soaker&lt;/td>
&lt;td>200g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>cold water (50°F)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>200g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Mix well and autolyze at 60°F for ~6 hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;h5 id="7pm">7pm&lt;/h5>
&lt;p>After ~6 hours of cool autolyse, mix the final dough.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Add 88g of stiff whole wheat levain (60% hydration). Slap &amp;amp; fold for 5-7 mins.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Add the salt and 20g of water (&lt;em>bassinage&lt;/em>), mix and squeeze for another 5-10 mins until completely absorbed. The dough is very tacky but should start to feel some strength by the end of this mixing.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Place the worked dough in a fridge (44°F) immediately. Cold bulk-ferment for the next 14 hours. Do 3 sets of stretch &amp;amp; fold, at 30 minutes apart, during the first 2 hours. My dough felt very extensible, although not very strong.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>At the 3-hour mark, laminate the dough with spent grains (not drained) à la German &lt;em>biertreberbrot&lt;/em> and chopped raisins.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>My dough almost passed the &amp;ldquo;windowpane&amp;rdquo; test!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>At the 4-hour mark, perform a coil-fold.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Remove 10g of the dough and put in an aliquot jar for easy measuring. Place the aliquot next to the dough in the same bowl, and return both to the fridge. Leave them undisturbed overnight.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h4 id="day-3">Day 3&lt;/h4>
&lt;h5 id="9am">9am&lt;/h5>
&lt;p>Remove the dough from fridge, and pre-shape via a loose coil-fold. Both the dough and the aliquot have risen a little bit overnight.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Rest for 45-60 minutes.&lt;/p>
&lt;h5 id="10am">10am&lt;/h5>
&lt;p>Shape the dough tightly and place in a proofing vessle. I put mine in a loaf pan lined with parchment paper.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Let the dough rest for 2-3 hours at room temperature, until the aliquot portion has risen nearly 100%. Mine took ~3 hours to get there.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;code>Note&lt;/code>: Watch the dough not the clock! Move at the dough&amp;rsquo;s pace.&lt;/p>
&lt;h5 id="1pm-1">1pm&lt;/h5>
&lt;p>Time to bake!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I did 15 minutes at 375F in the toaster oven, followed by another 35 minutes at 300F.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The dough had a pretty decent oven spring. It actually rose more than I expected and emitted some intoxicating wheat aroma!&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/the-wheatwalker/20200912201813b.jpg"
alt="85% extraction Turkey Red wheat bread"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>When the bread was done baking, it sounded hollow when I firmly thumped the bottom with my fingers.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/the-wheatwalker/20200912201815.jpg"
alt="85% extraction Turkey Red wheat bread"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Should&amp;rsquo;ve slashed a little deeper, huh?&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/the-wheatwalker/20200912201817b.jpg"
alt="85% extraction Turkey Red wheat bread"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Let the bread cool.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Size of the baked bread: 8&amp;rdquo; x 5&amp;quot; x 4&amp;quot;.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h4 id="day-4">Day 4&lt;/h4>
&lt;h5 id="3pm">3pm&lt;/h5>
&lt;p>After 24 hours of cooling and curing, came the moment of truth&amp;hellip;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The crunchy crust has softened overnight and is quite easy to cut into. The knife comes out mostly clean.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/the-wheatwalker/20200913201527c.jpg"
alt="85% extraction Turkey Red wheat bread"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The crumb is fairly open. No gaping holes, but a very nice texture. Moist, tender, pillowy, and springy. I&amp;rsquo;m surprised how light it is.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/the-wheatwalker/20200913201532a.jpg"
alt="85% extraction Turkey Red wheat bread"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The crumb surrounding the raisins tastes mildly tangy but flavorful &amp;ndash; almost like a small amount of caraway seeds and cinnamon has been added. Scattered raisins give you random bursts of sweetness.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The spent grains impart a subtle malty flavor and nutty crunch every now and then when you hit a berry. In case you are wondering, it does not taste like beer at all. You just get some extra fiber from the spent grains.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/the-wheatwalker/20200913201548c.jpg"
alt="85% extraction Turkey Red wheat bread"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The crust is thin, crisp, chewy and firm, and tastes much more flavorful (sweet, cinnamony notes).&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/the-wheatwalker/20200913201547e.jpg"
alt="85% extraction Turkey Red wheat bread"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The extended hydration of bran and long autolyse really helped with gluten development. The dough needed quite a bit of coaxing at the beginning, but gradually fell into place. A cool, long fermentation helped to develop a light texture and a complex flavor.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Overall, this is a wheaty loaf that doesn&amp;rsquo;t taste dense or earthy like other almost whole wheat loaves. It has a lingering flavor that is just incredible.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This Turkey Red from CoMo is absolutely delicious. The high-quality soil these grains are grown in and the freshness of the flour contribute a rich, unmistakable nuttiness and depth of flavor to the bread.&lt;/p>
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>The spent grains were a wet mush from a local craft brewery, consisting of 1/2 white wheat malt and 1/2 pilsner malt.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/section></content></item></channel></rss>