<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>poolish on HERESY LEVAIN</title><link>/tags/poolish/</link><description>Latest experiments in poolish from HERESY LEVAIN</description><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2023 HERESY LEVAIN 🍞 CC BY-NC-SA 4.0</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 30 Mar 2023 19:55:42 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/poolish/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>levure de bière #1.1: California ale yeast</title><link>/posts/byb-1-1/</link><pubDate>Thu, 30 Mar 2023 19:55:42 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/byb-1-1/</guid><description>A very high hydration &lt;em>pan de cristal&lt;/em> leavened exclusively with White Labs' WLP001 California Ale Yeast. A 48-hour whole-wheat &lt;em>poolish&lt;/em> was used in the final dough, which went through another 24 hours of fermentation. This bread had a very clean wheaty character and neutral aroma &amp;amp; flavor &amp;ndash; a perfect baseline for my upcoming experiments.</description><content>&lt;p>Happy Thirsty Thursday! I will be going on a &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/craft-beer-yeast">bread-baking adventure with craft beer yeasts&lt;/a> over the next few weeks/months. (You can stay updated on my experiments through a &lt;a href="https://tinyletter.com/breadbuster">newsletter&lt;/a>.)&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Just a glass of beer, a piece of dry bread &amp;ndash; and in one moment the brain is stronger, the mind is clearer and the will is firm!&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Fyodor Dostoyevsky, &lt;em>Crime and Punishment&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;m not a big drinker. I enjoy &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->craft beers and spirits&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --> every now and then, but I &lt;a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/02/07/dining/drinks/wine-millennials.html">don&amp;rsquo;t drink often enough&lt;/a> to even think about brewing them at home. While many people were driven to drink more during the Covid lockdown, I went the other way. I do have tanks of Russian &lt;em>&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kvass">kvass&lt;/a>&lt;/em> and Romanian &lt;em>&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bor%C8%99_(bran)">borș&lt;/a>&lt;/em> brewing in house all the time.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For some time now, I&amp;rsquo;ve been fascinated by the centuries-old relationship between beer and bread &amp;ndash; it&amp;rsquo;s absolutely gripping, and the more I learn, the more gripping it gets. Today, for instance, I was learning about the old, strong relationship in Europe between bakers and brewers. Ages ago, breweries and bakeries lived side-by-side harmoniously. Brewers happily went about their noble work &amp;ndash; mashing, sparging, and fermenting. One blessed by-product of the brewing process was a foam that formed frothily on top of the fermenting liquor. The dusty baker next door would welcome consignments of this malty foam &amp;ndash; known as &amp;ldquo;barm&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; and utilize the natural yeasts in it to leaven his dough. It made perfect sense, and as historical records have shown, ale and bread were the staple diet in the old days.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;As we brew, so we bake.&amp;rdquo; - an old adage&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Previously, I had thought that before commercial yeasts were developed, all bakers used sourdough to make their bread. Nope! Up until the 19th century, village bakers either depended on village brewers for their yeast (&amp;ldquo;barm&amp;rdquo;) in order to leaven their bread, or they literally brewed up their own &amp;ldquo;barm&amp;rdquo; for baking.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-1/20230330_132800.jpg"
alt="pan de cristal with WLP001 yeast poolish"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>pan de cristal&lt;/em> with WLP001 yeast poolish&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Andreas Krennmair&amp;rsquo;s book, &lt;em>Vienna Lager&lt;/em>, has an interesting take on how the relationship between brewers and bakers changed in the 19th century when brewers switched from ales to lagers:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Industrialisation had a profound effect on other breweries in and around Vienna: because of the quick success of Anton Dreher&amp;rsquo;s beer and brewing methods, all other breweries switched to bottom fermentation just within a few years. This rapid change had an unintended implication for another craft that had previously been reliant on breweries: baking. In the centuries before, bakers had been reliant on fresh beer yeast, which brewers always had available in abundance. When brewers started switching to bottom fermentation, the yeast given to bakers also changed its properties: &amp;hellip;the yeast suddenly contained hop bittering compounds and hop resins that turned these yeast darker and bitter-tasting, making it unsuitable for baking. &amp;hellip;so the Viennese baker&amp;rsquo;s guild announced in 1845 that they would award a prize to the person who could produce a leaven that was suitable to replace the much sought-after top-fermenting beer yeast.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Coincidentally, the 1800s were the golden age of the hop industry; hop acreage reached its peak in 1878.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>By the end of the century, yeast specifically cultivated for breadmaking had become commercially available in blocks, and later in dry, granulated forms. Slowly &amp;ndash; and sadly &amp;ndash; the close bond between breweries and bakeries faded away.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-1/20230330_132906.jpg"
alt="pan de cristal with WLP001 yeast poolish"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>pan de cristal&lt;/em> with WLP001 yeast poolish&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.toastale.com/">Toast Ale&lt;/a>, a London-based craft brewery, makes beer from waste bread. In the &lt;a href="https://www.willhawkes.net/blog/2023/3/20/march2023newsletter">March 2023 edition&lt;/a> of Will Hawkes&amp;rsquo;s newsletter &lt;em>London Beer City&lt;/em>, Toast&amp;rsquo;s founder talked about the company&amp;rsquo;s funding (some from Heineken), marketing strategy (&amp;ldquo;buyer personas&amp;rdquo;) and business model:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>While the impact of bread on the flavour of the beer is limited (typically, bread replaces 25 percent of the malted barley), I’ve always thought the implied message of Toast, that you can make great beer out of old bread, was a difficult one for the brewing industry. What happened to the ‘finest malt and hops’?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&amp;hellip;those who drink Toast’s beers are at ease with the idea of surplus bread being used to make it. In common with most people, I suspect, they don’t really care about malt and hops. They just want something nice to drink.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>The idea of making bread with breweries' by-products has intrigued me for a long time. I&amp;rsquo;ve baked and enjoyed &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/breadford-von-regrainton/">breads infused with brewer&amp;rsquo;s spent grains&lt;/a>, as well as ones leavened with &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/yeast-water/">wild yeasts captured from fruits&lt;/a>. But how about baking bread with brewer&amp;rsquo;s yeast?&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="bakers-yeast-vs-brewers-yeast">baker&amp;rsquo;s yeast vs. brewer&amp;rsquo;s yeast&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>In the mid-19th century, when bakers ditched breweries' barms &lt;em>en masse&lt;/em> and started looking for new sources of yeast, for a few years a new trade of &amp;ldquo;barm-brewers&amp;rdquo; sprang up who specialized in propagating yeast for bakers.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-1/1860-barm.png"
alt="a paper given to the Royal Scottish Society of Arts in 1860"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>A paper given to the Royal Scottish Society of Arts in 1860, describing the various modes of leavening bread.&lt;/p>&lt;p>Source: &lt;a href="https://books.google.ie/books?id=ueM0AAAAMAAJ&amp;amp;pg=PA235" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">Transactions of the Royal Scottish Society of Arts, Volume 5&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>This in turn was displaced by the introduction of compressed blocks of yeast known as &amp;ldquo;fresh yeast&amp;rdquo; today. As &lt;a href="https://dafteejit.com/2020/03/the-history-of-modern-baking-yeast/">Andreas Krennmair writes&lt;/a>, the process of making compressed yeast was invented by a brewer, who used brewer&amp;rsquo;s yeast. This has inspired Lars Marius Garshol to ponder, &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href="https://www.garshol.priv.no/blog/411.html">Does bread yeast exist?&lt;/a>&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In fact, most forms of brewer&amp;rsquo;s yeast and baker&amp;rsquo;s yeast currently on the market all come from the same species of yeast called &lt;em>&lt;code>Saccharomyces cerevisiae&lt;/code>&lt;/em>. The yeast derives its name from the Latinized Greek meaning &amp;ldquo;sugar fungus&amp;rdquo;, because it converts sugars into CO₂ and ethanol during aerobic fermentation &amp;ndash; which makes beer alcoholic and inflates a lump of dough into a fluffy loaf of bread.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>All &lt;em>S. cerevisiae&lt;/em> strains share a common natural history. Some, through artificial selection, are better adapted for certain processes, while others have more than one use.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Before the arrival of industrial yeasts, baker&amp;rsquo;s yeast used to be much more diverse, but what we call &amp;ldquo;bread yeast&amp;rdquo; today is simply particular strains of &lt;em>S. cerevisiae&lt;/em> monocultures that have been selected by yeast manufacturers primarily for their ability to rapidly metabolize wheat starch, produce large quantities of CO₂ while fermenting the dough, and make bread light. The quick-rising yeast now available in stores is an improved strain developed using modern genetic methods. Professional bakers use commercial yeasts that produce a fast and strong rise and a clean taste (less flavor and depth) in the finished loaf of bread.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Modern bread yeast manufacturers narrowly focus their yeast development on two issues:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>gas production.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>speed of rising.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>Variants are produced with these goals in mind, to suit different technical requirements of the baking industry.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For example, instant yeasts (aka. fast-rising, rapid-rise, quick-rise, and bread machine yeast), are manufactured to dissolve more quickly than active dry yeasts; they can be mixed directly into flour and other dry ingredients, without the need to &amp;ldquo;proof&amp;rdquo; the yeast in warm water first. Lesaffre, one of the world&amp;rsquo;s largest yeast producers, has formulated &lt;a href="https://lesaffre.ae/en/our-products/professional-products/saf-instant-gold-500g/">Saf-Instant® Gold dry yeast&lt;/a> specifically for sweet doughs (with &amp;gt;=5% sugar/weight of flour) like Hawaiian rolls and &lt;em>panettoni&lt;/em>, as well as &lt;a href="https://lesaffrebaking.com/product/saf-instant-red/">Saf-Instant® Red&lt;/a> that excels in sugarless doughs.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-1/20230330_132311.jpg"
alt="pan de cristal with WLP001 yeast poolish"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>pan de cristal&lt;/em> with WLP001 yeast poolish&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>A number of people claim that baker&amp;rsquo;s yeast brews good beers (since most bread yeasts are &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->phenolic&lt;sup id="fnref:2">&lt;a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A 2018 paper published in the &lt;em>Journal of the Institute of Brewing&lt;/em>, titled &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1002/jib.503">evaluation of &lt;em>Saccharomyces cerevisiae&lt;/em> strains isolated from non-brewing environments in beer production&lt;/a>&amp;rdquo;, tested 12 novel &lt;em>S. cerevisiae&lt;/em> strains isolated from grape must, bakery, wine, and apple stillage in the production of beer. The researchers found that&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>The most suitable strain for beer production, based on fermentative ability and volatile profile, was a baker&amp;rsquo;s yeast&amp;hellip;. Interestingly, some esters were above the sensory threshold.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Another example: The Finnish farmhouse ale &lt;em>sahti&lt;/em> is fermented with baking strains, rather than &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->brewing strains&lt;sup id="fnref:3">&lt;a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">3&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->, of &lt;em>S. cerevisiae&lt;/em>. A 2020 paper, titled &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1002/jib.608">sourdough derived strains of &lt;em>Saccharomyces cerevisiae&lt;/em> and their potential for farmhouse ale brewing&lt;/a>&amp;rdquo;, concludes&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>sourdough isolates of &lt;em>S. cerevisiae&lt;/em> are suitable for &lt;em>sahti&lt;/em> production, but could also be applied to other beer styles as a way to differentiate products.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>However, I haven&amp;rsquo;t heard the other way round, i.e. brewer&amp;rsquo;s yeast makes good bread.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Manufacturers of beer and wine yeasts all describe multiple varieties of yeasts, each producing a slightly differently flavored product. In the case of wine, some yeasts are tied to specific cultivars of grapes. The importance of yeast strains in producing different varieties of beer is illustrated by White Labs' assortment of beer yeasts:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.whitelabs.com/yeast-single?id=169&amp;amp;type=YEAST">WLP566&lt;/a> Belgian Saison II Ale Yeast: &amp;ldquo;a moderate phenol producer with clove-like flavor and aromatic notes present in the finished beer&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.whitelabs.com/yeast-single?id=174&amp;amp;type=YEAST">WLP590&lt;/a> French Saison Ale Yeast: &amp;ldquo;produces flavors and aromas of pear, apple and cracked pepper&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.whitelabs.com/yeast-single?id=267&amp;amp;type=YEAST">WLP077&lt;/a> Tropicale Yeast Blend: &amp;ldquo;a balance of tropical flavors and aromas, such as passionfruit, grapefruit, and mango&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Wouldn&amp;rsquo;t it be lovely to be able to make a bread that produces a &amp;ldquo;clove-like&amp;rdquo; aroma and flavor when it&amp;rsquo;s toasted? Or a loaf with a slight hint of smoky tomato that might make it ideal for &lt;em>bruschetta&lt;/em>?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>What if breads in a bakery might, for the first time, be differentiated by subtleties of aroma? Imagine a boule with a hint of plum and thyme under an overtone of apple &amp;ndash; next to a boule made with the same recipe but a different yeast and thus yielding a hazelnut aroma.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-1/20230330_132413.jpg"
alt="pan de cristal with WLP001 yeast poolish"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>pan de cristal&lt;/em> with WLP001 yeast poolish&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Beer is, after all, liquid bread. Like brewers, I&amp;rsquo;m constantly on the lookout for special flours and yeasts to make that unique, satisfying loaf.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I keep thinking about experimenting with combinations of different yeast strains in a dough to see how they might enhance a bread&amp;rsquo;s flavor and aroma. The yeast monoculture practice be damned.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>What does it take to make a good loaf of bread with brewer&amp;rsquo;s yeast? Is it possible in the modern era? I want to find out.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>There is a vast catalog of yeast strains used by brewers and wine makers that I want to experiment with, and it&amp;rsquo;s never been easier to collaborate with people over the internet.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="california-ale-yeast">California ale yeast&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>The first craft beer yeast I decided to experiment is &lt;a href="https://www.whitelabs.com/yeast-single?id=101&amp;amp;type=YEAST">WLP001&lt;/a> California Ale Yeast®, which is White Labs' OG yeast strain, first produced in 1995.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-1/20230321_143837.jpg"
alt="WLP001 California Ale Yeast"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>A homebrew pouch of WLP001 California Ale Yeast, from White Labs.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>This &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->&amp;ldquo;Chico&amp;rdquo;&lt;sup id="fnref:4">&lt;a href="#fn:4" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">4&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --> strain (named after the &lt;em>châteaux&lt;/em> of Sierra Nevada Brewing Company) is probably the most widely used beer strain on the West Coast, if not in the entire country. It&amp;rsquo;s a driving force behind IPA 2.0, aka. the yeast that launched 1,000 beers.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>WLP001 is famous for its clean flavors and hardy fermentations and is known for its use in hoppy beers. It accentuates hop flavors and aromas and attenuates well, even for high-gravity beers. A higher-than-average attenuation leads to drier beers as well as medium flocculation to leave a clean and crisp beer. With a healthy pitch and yeast, WLP001 is also quick at reabsorbing diacetyl.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>The yeast has a very beery aroma right out of the package.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A &amp;ldquo;clean-fermenting&amp;rdquo; strain with a neutral flavor and aroma profile (instead of a &amp;ldquo;fruity&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;estery&amp;rdquo; strain) would be an interesting baseline for comparisons with other yeasts.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Another reason for starting with WLP001 is that a clean fermenter showcases a brewer&amp;rsquo;s recipe formulation (e.g. choice of malts, hops, brewing temperatures, and fermentation temperatures) more than other strains. Since I&amp;rsquo;ve made &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/pan-de-cristal/">these kinds of breads&lt;/a> many times, it&amp;rsquo;d be fairly easy for me to tell how the ale yeast differs from sourdough.&lt;/p>
&lt;h5 id="wlp001-poolish">WLP001 poolish&lt;/h5>
&lt;p>Many researchers have reported that the dough fermentation by &lt;em>S. cerevisiae&lt;/em> promoted an increase in the contents of phenolic compounds due to the structural breakdown of cell wall, leading to the liberation of phenolic compounds and/or metabolization of phenolics by yeast.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>On the other hand, thermal processing may have negative effects on these bioactive compounds, likely caused by oxidation, isomerization, and interaction with wheat proteins.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>One technical challenge of baking with yeast is making the yeast&amp;rsquo;s distinct character shine through.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Maybe a poolish (a preferment with 25% of total flour) with super low yeast inoculation would help? A poolish particularly elevates the bread&amp;rsquo;s creamy, slightly nutty character and crisp, thin crust. (Yum.)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>So I made a loose preferment that used roughly equal parts of whole wheat flour and water by weight with a tiny bit of California ale yeast &amp;ndash; and no salt.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Turkey Red wheat flour, 100% extraction&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>125g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>water&lt;/td>
&lt;td>120%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>150g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>ale yeast (WLP001 - White Labs, CA)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2.5g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>I mixed the whole wheat flour and water together in a &lt;strong>shallow, wide-open bowl&lt;/strong>. I prefer it to tall, narrow fermenters because high hydrostatic pressure and CO₂ levels tend to inhibit ester formation.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-1/20230326_145734.jpg"
alt="WLP001 yeast poolish, before fermentation"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>WLP001 yeast poolish, before fermentation.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>I added ~100 drops of WLP001, which totaled ~2.5g. I whipped it vigorously into the mixture.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>White Labs' homebrew yeasts typically have a concentration of &amp;gt;=100 billion cells per 40 mL, i.e. 2.5 billion cells per mL. Assume 2.5g of the liquid yeast contains roughly 6.25 billion cells, the inoculation rate in the poolish is about 22-23 million cells per gram.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>These [West Coast] yeasts have a potential ester profile. If you play with fermentation temperature, you can really influence the character of the beer.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Richard Norgrove, Bear Republic Brewing Company (Healdsburg, California)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>WLP001 has a fermentation temperature range of 64°F-73°F. I loosely covered up the poolish (leaving an air gap) and let it ferment at the high side of the recommended temperatures (&lt;strong>70°F-73°F&lt;/strong>), in order to bring out the yeast&amp;rsquo;s character. I checked on it every few hours and gave it a stir to aerate the mixture.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-1/20230326_145753.jpg"
alt="WLP001 yeast poolish, before fermentation"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>WLP001 yeast poolish, before fermentation.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>I provided WLP001 all the time it needed to propagate, and let the poolish tell me when it was done. It ended up going for &lt;strong>48 hours&lt;/strong>. This was to ensure vigorous and complete fermentation before the poolish was mixed into the final dough.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-1/20230328_153644.jpg"
alt="WLP001 yeast poolish, after 48 hours of fermentation"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>WLP001 yeast poolish, after 48 hours of fermentation.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Clean strains usually ferment more slowly than fruitier strains and flocculate at a medium rate, remaining in suspension long enough to condition the beer properly.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>When ripe, the poolish doubled in volume. It was brimming with almost uniform micro-bubbles, instead of the bigger, more irregular bubbles you get with sourdough or bread yeast.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-1/20230328_153717.jpg"
alt="WLP001 yeast poolish, after 48 hours of fermentation"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>WLP001 yeast poolish, after 48 hours of fermentation.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Upon initial mixing, the mixture had a mild toasty wheat aroma from freshly milled Turkey Red wheat. The toasty wheat aroma was replaced by a slight yeasty twang after 12 hours, so I assume that&amp;rsquo;s when the yeast started working. After 48 hours, the yeasty aroma was completely gone. The smell was very clean &amp;ndash; maybe with a hint of fresh beer.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-1/20230328_153656.jpg"
alt="WLP001 yeast poolish, after 48 hours of fermentation"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>WLP001 yeast poolish, after 48 hours of fermentation.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>A quick search on home-brewing forums show that &lt;a href="https://www.homebrewtalk.com/threads/wlp001-peach-flavor.211921/">peach esters&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://www.homebrewtalk.com/threads/wlp001-flocculation-and-clearing.242072/">slow flocculation&lt;/a> seem to be the two major complaints people have with WLP001. Neither is a problem for my bread.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="final-dough">final dough&lt;/h4>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Turkey Red wheat, 80% extraction&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>375g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>water&lt;/td>
&lt;td>105%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>395g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>WLP001 poolish&lt;/td>
&lt;td>74%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>277.5g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sea salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>4g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>olive oil&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>20g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>I decided &lt;em>not&lt;/em> to use a levain (sourdough), in order to have a more clean aroma/flavor profile of the ale yeast. So, this dough was leavened purely by a poolish with WLP001.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-1/20230328_221805.jpg"
alt="WLP001 yeast poolish dough"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>WLP001 yeast poolish dough&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The process is similar to the &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/california-dreamin-2/">&lt;em>pan de San Joaquín&lt;/em>&lt;/a>:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Autolyze the flour at 70% hydration for 2 hours in the fridge.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Add the poolish. Mix until well incorporated.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Double hydration: Slowly drizzle in the remaining water, and &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zgz0oAhgwyg">Rubaud-mix&lt;/a> until thoroughly absorbed. Cover the dough and let it rest for 20 minutes at room temperature.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Mix in the salt. Let the dough rest for a few minutes.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Gently mix in the olive oil. Let the dough rest and relax for 30 minutes.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Bulk ferment the dough at &lt;strong>~73°F&lt;/strong> for &lt;strong>8 hours&lt;/strong>, performing a coil-fold every 45 minutes during the first 3 hours.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Transfer the dough to a cooler place &lt;strong>~65°F&lt;/strong> and leave (loosely covered) for another &lt;strong>16 hours&lt;/strong>.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Divide into 2 pieces. No shaping or slashing necessary. Bake as usual: 25-30 minutes at 350°F.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;h4 id="total">total&lt;/h4>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Turkey Red wheat, 80% extraction&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>500g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>H₂O&lt;/td>
&lt;td>109%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>545g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>liquid ale yeast (WLP001)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>0.5%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2.5g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sea salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>0.8%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>4g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>olive oil&lt;/td>
&lt;td>4%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>20g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;h4 id="tasting">tasting&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>The bread smelled like buttery biscuits and toasted crackers during baking.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-1/20230330_132240.jpg"
alt="pan de cristal with WLP001 yeast poolish"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>pan de cristal&lt;/em> with WLP001 yeast poolish, crumb shot&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The crumb had almost uniform micro-bubbles &amp;ndash; just like the poolish &amp;ndash; rather than the bigger, irregular air holes you get with sourdough or bread yeast.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-1/20230329_233127.jpg"
alt="pan de cristal with WLP001 yeast poolish"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>It had a very clean wheat flavor &amp;ndash; something I hadn&amp;rsquo;t noticed in a sourdough bread and it really stood out to me in this bread. It reminded me of eating Triscuits, with a slight hint of dankness.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I think this clean and neutral bread would be a good baseline for my upcoming craft beer yeast experiments.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-1/20230329_233251.jpg"
alt="pan de cristal with WLP001 yeast poolish"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The crust turned a beautiful mahogany color that I hadn&amp;rsquo;t seen before with sourdough breads.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-1/20230330_133023.jpg"
alt="pan de cristal with WLP001 yeast poolish"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>pan de cristal&lt;/em> with WLP001 yeast poolish, crust shot&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Overall, I would say the yeast struggled in this dough, probably because it had no nutrients. Which gives me &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/byb-1-2/">an interesting idea&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-1-1/20230330_132603.jpg"
alt="pan de cristal with WLP001 yeast poolish"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>pan de cristal&lt;/em> with WLP001 yeast poolish&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>&lt;em>This is my 1st &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/craft-beer-yeast">&lt;em>pain maison à la levure de bière&lt;/em>&lt;/a>. Special thanks to White Labs, especially Erik Fowler (Head of Education &amp;amp; Craft Hospitality) in San Diego, CA and Bert Sheffield (R&amp;amp;D Chef) in Asheville, NC.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>Tom Acitelli, author and journalist who writes about wine, beer and spirits, has written some interesting books about America&amp;rsquo;s craft brewing &amp;amp; distilling revolution: &lt;em>The Audacity of Hops: The History of America&amp;rsquo;s Craft Beer Revolution&lt;/em> (2013), &lt;em>American Wine: A Coming-of-Age Story&lt;/em> (2015), and &lt;em>Whiskey Business: How Small-Batch Distillers Are Transforming American Spirits&lt;/em> (2017).&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>A phenol is a hydroxylated aromatic ring, a compound with a 6-membered carbon ring bonded directly to a hydroxyl group (-OH). These are the same class of compounds used in some antiseptics, and some consumers describe their flavor and aroma as medicinal. The health benefits of phenolic acids are primarily due to their antioxidant properties, but these acids also show anti-ulcer, anti-diabetic, anti-cancer, anti-inflammatory, anti-aging, anti-microbial, cardioprotective, hepatoprotective and neuroprotective activities.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:3" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>Ale strains of &lt;em>S. cerevisiae&lt;/em> are &amp;ldquo;top-fermenting&amp;rdquo; (I prefer &amp;ldquo;top-harvesting&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;warmish-fermenting&amp;rdquo; for clearer communication) yeasts. They are relatively hydrophobic, such that upon flocculating or clumping together, they tend to connect to the CO₂ produced and float to the surface of the fermenter contents. As a result, brewers were able to collect the yeast and create more colonies for future beers. On the other hand, lagers are made with &lt;em>S. pastorianus&lt;/em> strains, which are &amp;ldquo;bottom-fermenting&amp;rdquo; (or &amp;ldquo;bottom-harvesting&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;cold-fermenting&amp;rdquo;, to be more specific) and widely thought to have originated from a natural hybridization event that occurred between a &lt;em>S. cerevisiae&lt;/em> strain and a non-&lt;em>S. cerevisiae&lt;/em> strain, probably a &lt;em>S. bayanus&lt;/em> strain. From this perspective, ales are considered closer to the ancient beer type than lagers.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:4" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;Chico&amp;rdquo; refers to Chico, California, the first location of Sierra Nevada Brewing Company&amp;rsquo;s OG taproom, where the strain is sourced. In 1979, two home brewers established the Sierra Nevada Brewing Company to expand their beloved hobby into a business. The pair&amp;rsquo;s first beer release was the famed Pale Ale, the beer that proved beers with an aggressively hopped backbone could be successful. Although labeled as a pale ale, it was really the &amp;ldquo;OG IPA&amp;rdquo; as it highlighted hops that no other beers had done before. Sierra Nevada brewers nicknamed this strain of yeast &amp;ldquo;Chico&amp;rdquo;, after the brewery&amp;rsquo;s hometown.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:4" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/section></content></item></channel></rss>