<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>montana craft malt on HERESY LEVAIN</title><link>/tags/montana-craft-malt/</link><description>Latest experiments in montana craft malt from HERESY LEVAIN</description><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2023 HERESY LEVAIN 🍞 CC BY-NC-SA 4.0</copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 08 May 2023 11:39:22 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/montana-craft-malt/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>levure de bière #5.1: thiol and error</title><link>/posts/byb-5-1/</link><pubDate>Mon, 08 May 2023 11:39:22 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/byb-5-1/</guid><description>My very first trip down the thiol rabbit hole. Split-batch bake: one recipe, two experimental thiol-forward breads. One loaf was inoculated with Berkeley Yeast&amp;rsquo;s London Tropics, the other with London Tropics + Thiol Boost. The breads turned out COMPLETELY different. POG bombs.</description><content>&lt;p>&lt;em>Beer = liquid bread. Want to stay updated on my &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/tags/craft-beer-yeast">craft beer yeast bread-plays&lt;/a>? Subscribe to the &lt;a href="https://tinyletter.com/breadbuster">newsletter&lt;/a>!&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p> &lt;/p>
&lt;p> ̶«̶ ̶̶̶ ̶ ̶ ̶̶̶ ̶«̶　🍞 🍻 🍞 🍻  ̶»̶ ̶̶̶ ̶ ̶ ̶̶̶ ̶»̶&lt;/p>
&lt;p> &lt;/p>
&lt;p>ICYMI, there has been a huge thiols-at-all-cost craze going on in the brewing world. Heavily hopped IPAs with novel tropical fruit aromas and flavors have been a massive growth category. Triple New England IPA has consistently topped Untappd&amp;rsquo;s list of highest-average rated beer styles, and 1/3 of Untappd&amp;rsquo;s 120 million check-ins in 2022 were some kind of IPA. (Which makes one wonder about Heineken&amp;rsquo;s new American debut, Heineken® Silver, brewed specifically to meet &lt;em>Americans' distaste for bitter beers&lt;/em>.)&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>In 2022, the top three beer styles for the highest number of overall Untappd check-ins were: American IPA, New England IPA and Imperial IPA (the style distinction between an American and a New England IPA is hard to define as almost all of the world’s top 50 highest rated American IPAs are hazy in appearance). &amp;hellip;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The IPAs of 2013 were so bright you could read that year’s best-of list through any of the beers. Sparkling and golden-amber in colour, they were simply American IPAs and didn’t need a West Coast prefix to make drinkers realise it’s not a hazy New England beer – the whole prospect of a cloudy yellow IPA was still a curiosity. Viewed from 2023, where almost all IPAs (and Pale Ales) are now at least a bit hazy, and many are totally opaque with a mouthfeel often described with adjectives like smooth, thick and juicy, those original West Coasters feel like a throwback. That clean clarity and crispness of flavour has gone sweet and squidgy, and it’s not just the IPAs.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Mark Dredge, &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href="https://www.beer52.com/ferment/article/1605/ten-years-that-changed-beer">Ten years that changed beer&lt;/a>&amp;rdquo;, Beer52&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Commercial breweries and home-brewers all over the world are injecting new products (e.g. Thiolized® yeasts and Phantasm® thiol powder), switching to fancy hops (e.g. Vic Secret™, Amarillo®, Mandarina Bavaria, Nelson Sauvin™, and Motueka™) and hop products (e.g. Cryo Hops®, Incognito®, Salvo™, and SubZero Hop Kief™), and trying new techniques (e.g. mash-hopping) to make &amp;ldquo;thiol bombs.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-1/phantasm-basqueland-2023-04-08.png"
alt="Basqueland Phantasm Crush"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Basqueland Phantasm Crush Hazy IPA, brewed with a whirlpool charge of Phantasm thiol powder and dry-hopped with Nelson Sauvin™, Citra®, and Citra® Cryo Hops®.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The results have been mixed. There are some success stories underneath the hype, but a number of brewers say it&amp;rsquo;s just a cranked-up odd flavor (mostly aroma) that may not even compliment the finished beer.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Evidently, tinkering with thiols takes a lot of &amp;ldquo;trial and error.&amp;rdquo; The wine industry has been researching and creating thiol-optimized strains since ~2004, nearly 20 years before the beer industry.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I wanted to go down the thiol rabbit and see what it was all about.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-1/Stone-phantasm.jpg"
alt="Stone Brewing Patio Magic"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Stone Brewing just released the experimental thiol-packed Patio Magic Double IPA in February 2023. It&amp;rsquo;s brewed with Phantasm thiol powder, as well as the experimental hop 843 developed by Hop Breeding Company. The 8.8% ABV India Pale Ale has amplified orange, berry, floral, and wood notes.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;h3 id="thiology">Thiology&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Over the last several decades, there have been endless studies on the hop plant and the enormous impact hops have had on craft brewing, particularly in America. New hop varieties have been &lt;a href="https://daily.sevenfifty.com/beer-hops-are-going-high-tech/">R&amp;amp;D&amp;rsquo;ed&lt;/a>, specifically focusing on the creation of compounds that humans perceive to impart bold tropical fruit aromas and flavors.&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="embed music-spotify">
&lt;iframe
style="border-radius:12px"
src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/episode/3wt0SOKLtPqdTaGM9FXNAV?utm_source=generator&amp;theme=0"
width="100%"
height="152
"
frameBorder="0"
allowfullscreen=""
allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture">&lt;/iframe>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>American hop varieties are characteristically fruity; they add aromas of citrus, pine, tropical fruit, black currant, sweat, and onion/garlic to beer, thanks to the aromatic compounds that originate in the hops' essential oil, which is comprised predominantly of mono- and sesqui-terpenes (volatile organic compounds that play crucial roles in human perception of table grape and wine flavors), some terpene alcohols, and a tiny bit of sulfur-containing &lt;strong>thiols&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Researchers have found that these biotransformative thiols are the main contributors to the highly sought-after tropical aromas, and thus may be giving certain hop varieties an edge over others. (Biotransformation just means the development of new aromas and flavors when yeast interacts with this &lt;em>smörgåsbord&lt;/em> of compounds.)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Thiols (also called mercaptans, with the general formula R-SH), are sulfur analogs of alcohols.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Three volatile thiol molecules responsible for tropical aromas in beer have been in the spotlight across the winemaking and brewing communities:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>3-mercaptohexanol (&lt;strong>3MH&lt;/strong>), which creates citrus aromas like grapefruit and gooseberry;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>3-mercaptohexyl acetate (&lt;strong>3MHA&lt;/strong>), which can come across as guava or passion fruit; and&lt;/li>
&lt;li>4-mercapto-4-methylpentan-2-one (&lt;strong>4MMP&lt;/strong>), which the nose recognizes as black current or wood aromas.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Instead of smelling sulfury like rotten eggs, these free, volatile thiols have tropical and fruity aromas.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As you can see, the first 2 molecules &amp;ndash; 3MH and its acetate ester, 3MHA &amp;ndash; are almost solely responsible for imparting strong tropical fruit aromas.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-1/what-are-thiols.png"
alt="An overview of thiols"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>An overview of thiols: structure, aroma profile, and threshold. The small concentrations make a ton of difference in human perceived aromas and flavors.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The thiol content in hops depends strongly on the variety, and can be influenced by harvest maturity, terroir, and other seasonal variables. Several of the most popular hops of the last decade, e.g. Cascade, Citra®, Simcoe®, Nelson Sauvin™, and Mosaic®, are found to contain&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>free thiols&lt;/strong>, which are aroma-active, volatile compounds such as 3MH, 3MHA and 4MMP that are soluble in beer; as well as&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>thiol precursors&lt;/strong>, which are &amp;ldquo;bound&amp;rdquo;, non-aroma-active, non-volatile compounds that can be liberated &amp;ndash; with the help of a specific enzyme &amp;ndash; from the amino acids they are bound to, and thus become free and aromatic.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>The presence of these thiol compounds, alongside the complex array of terpenes and other essential oils, seem to give these hop varieties an edge when creating fruit-forward beers such as American IPAs. Some of these hops are running out in places, probably due to this thiol craze (and supply chain disruptions).&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-1/hops-free-thiols.png"
alt="free thiols in hops"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Published data on free thiols in hops&lt;/p>&lt;p>Source: &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/files/CBC-Development-of-Thiols-and-Thiol-Precursors-in-Different-Hop-Varieties.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">Christina Schönberger and Laurent Dagan, Craft Brewers Conference 2020&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Most common thiol precursors, in their conjugated (glutathionylated or cysteinylated, often written as &lt;strong>Glut-3MH&lt;/strong> or &lt;strong>Cys-3MH&lt;/strong>) and therefore non-active forms, have been identified in multiple other plant raw materials as well, such as grapes (and musts), tannin, fruits, and malts.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Many plants naturally produce an odorless molecule (Glut-3MH) as a byproduct of glutathione metabolism. Some of this Glut-3MH is converted into a second, non-volatile molecule, Cys-3MH, through the activity of naturally occurring plant enzymes; then, another plant enzyme converts some of this Cys-3MH into the aroma-active thiol, 3MH.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-1/F2_pathway-01.png"
alt="Biosynthesis of 3MH in plants"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Biosynthesis of 3MH in plants (red arrows = enzymatic reactions)&lt;/p>&lt;p>Source: &lt;a href="https://berkeleyyeast.com/science-lesson/enhance-thiol-biotransformation-with-tropics/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">Berkeley Yeast&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Pure natural magic.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The efficiency of each step in this biosynthetic pathway varies dramatically across different plants.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In tropical fruits like guava and passion fruit, for example, the conversion of Glut-3MH &amp;ndash;&amp;gt; Cys-3MH &amp;ndash;&amp;gt; 3MH is very efficient, and these plants contain a high concentration of 3MH as a result. That&amp;rsquo;s why tropical fruits smell like tropical fruits &amp;ndash; they contain significant sources of volatile thiol compounds.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In barley malts and hops, however, the efficiency of these two reactions is obviously low (that&amp;rsquo;s why these two naturally don&amp;rsquo;t smell like tropical fruits). The enzymes that catalyze each conversion are inefficient, producing few 3MH molecules. Even in hops that are famous for tropical fruit characters, researchers have found that &amp;lt;=1% of the Glut-3MH is actually converted to 3MH.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Consequently, barley malts and hops contain a low concentration of free thiols like 3MH, but high concentrations of thiol precursors like Glut-3MH and Cys-3MH.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-1/thiol-precursors-malts-hops.png"
alt="Average percentages of thiol precursors in barley and hops"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Average percentages of thiol precursors in barley and hops&lt;/p>&lt;p>Source: &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/files/CBC-Development-of-Thiols-and-Thiol-Precursors-in-Different-Hop-Varieties.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">Laurent Dagan&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>That means, the abundance of thiol precursors found in hops and malts have the potential to be converted into volatile thiols during fermentation &amp;ndash; just think about how exciting it would be to figure out how to unlock it all! This, indeed, has recently become a subject of great interest &amp;ndash; or even obsession &amp;ndash; for brewers. The reason is simple: While these thiol precursor molecules are flavorless, it only takes 1-2 enzymatic reactions to biotransform them into aroma-active 3MH and unleash a tropical fruit nirvana.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>One of these yeast-encoded enzymes capable of converting flavorless precursor molecules into volatile thiols during &amp;ldquo;biotransformation&amp;rdquo; is &lt;strong>cysteine S-conjugate beta-lyase&lt;/strong> (&lt;strong>CSL&lt;/strong>), from the class of carbon-sulfur lyases. This enzyme can break the carbon-sulfur bond present in these odorless cysteinylated thiol precursors, releasing the highly aroma-active unconjugated form (polyfunctional/free thiols).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A number of companies have created various new products that focus on enhancing thiol biotransformation. There are currently two main approaches, and they often go hand in hand:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>increase the load of thiols in the mash, especially in the bound form (since thiol precursors are abundant in nature and non-volatile);&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>manipulate the enzymes to turbocharge the thiol biosynthesis process.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>I will look at some of the most popular products in each category.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="thiol-precursor-enhancers">Thiol precursor enhancers&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Outside of thiol precursor-laden hops like Calypso™, Cascade, Mittelfrüh, and Žatec (Saaz), one (overhyped) product that claims to enhance or elevate thiol precursors is Phantasm®, a powder made from New Zealand Marlborough Sauvignon Blanc grapes, which are said to be incredibly rich in both free thiols and Cys-3MH &amp;ndash; allegedly a much higher concentration of thiols than hops and malts.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-1/Phantasm-powder.jpg"
alt="Phantasm thiol powder"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Phantasm thiol powder, frequently touted as &amp;lsquo;the biggest modern-day game-changer for hop aroma.&amp;rsquo; Like new iPhones, this product has a super long waiting list and is hard to get.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Phantasm came from the owner of Garage Project, a brewery based in the Aro Valley of Wellington, New Zealand, near the Marlborough region, famous for producing exceptionally high-quality Sauvignon Blancs known for their intense tropical fruit aromas. New Zealand has been ground zero for thiol research as it pertains to the wine industry, with scientists working to better understand how to unlock thiols in Marlborough&amp;rsquo;s expressive Sauvignon Blanc grapes.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It turns out that after winemakers use those thiol-laden grape skins, they throw them away.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;Maybe one winemaker&amp;rsquo;s trash is another beermaker&amp;rsquo;s treasure.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Jos Ruffell, founder of Phantasm and owner of Garage Project&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Ruffell found a way to dehydrate and powderize those leftover Marlborough Sauvignon Blanc grape skins, making a thiol-rich product that brewers could use to enhance the aromas of their beers. A pretty clever business idea.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-1/garage-project-phantasm-2023-04-17.png"
alt="Garage Project Phantasm Hazy IPA"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Garage Project Phantasm Hazy IPA, transmogrified with Phantasm® thiol powder.&lt;/p>&lt;p>Source: &lt;a href="https://garageproject.co.nz/products/phantasm-hazy" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">Garage Project&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Ruffell brought Phantasm to market in late 2020, marketing it primarily as an aroma-enhancer in hazy IPAs. Stories of early successes by popular brewing companies, including Ruffell&amp;rsquo;s own Garage Project, went viral on the internet, and created instant, fervent demand that far exceeded supply.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet">&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr">Phantasm is an experimental product in extremely short supply out of New Zealand, derived from Sauvignon Blanc grape skins. We&amp;#39;re very honored to be one of the first few breweries in the world, and first in Canada with access to play with this super magical powder.&lt;/p>&amp;mdash; Kilter Brewing (@kilterbrewing) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/kilterbrewing/status/1371661768838107144?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">March 16, 2021&lt;/a>&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8">&lt;/script>
&lt;p>Unsurprisingly, Phantasm (both the name of that company and its flagship product) has taken the brewing world by storm. (I wonder how much of a role the scarce availability and perceived exclusivity have played in Phantasm&amp;rsquo;s stratospheric popularity.) Outside of the core four (hops, malt, yeast, and water), Phantasm® is the &amp;ldquo;hottest&amp;rdquo; brewing ingredient on the market today.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;Essentially, brewing with Phantasm is like an MSG addition for aroma.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Jos Ruffell, founder of Phantasm and owner of Garage Project&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>In December 2022, Phantasm (the company) held the inaugural Phantasm Cup, a new (annual) competition to find the best thiol-forward beer in North America, sponsored by Half Acre Brewing and Omega Yeast, in Chicago. The grand prize &amp;ndash; an all-expenses-paid trip to New Zealand during hop harvest &amp;ndash; went to Wise Man Brewing (Winston-Salem, North Carolina), which won for a New Zealand-hopped NEIPA incorporating the theme ingredient.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-1/Phantasm-Cup-Wiseman.png"
alt="Wiseman NEIPA won 2022 Phantasm Cup"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Be Your Future, Wise Man Brewing&amp;rsquo;s New England IPA collaboration with Protagonist Beer, won the inaugural Phantasm Cup in December 2022. This hazy IPA features Phantasm® powder to crank up thiols and maximize juicy, tropical fruit flavors. Mash-hopped with Saaz and double dry-hopped with Nelson Sauvin™, Rakau™, and Idaho 7®, this beer boasts a big fruity aroma, soft mouthfeel, and notes of ripe pineapple, dried mango, and white grape.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-1/Phantasm-Cup-Explorium.jpg"
alt="Explorium Fancy Italian Boater Pils"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Fancy Italian Boater Pils, The Explorium Brewpub&amp;rsquo;s collab with 608 Brewing Company, won 3rd place. The original dry-hopped lager (the Italian Pilsner) is given a South Pacific facelift, with Phantasm® powder; dry-hopped with Nelson Sauvin™ and Motueka™. This crisp lager pops with effervescent tropical fruit and finishes with lime, white grape, and berry. Phil Humphrey, 608 Brewing Company&amp;rsquo;s owner and head brewer, said, &amp;lsquo;If you love wine, you&amp;rsquo;re gonna love this beer.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p>&lt;p>Source: &lt;a href="https://z-upload.facebook.com/exploriumbrew/posts/3401842456740901" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">The Explorium Brewpub&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Other standout Phantasm-enriched beers include a trio of Phuture beers, brewed via 3-way collaboration among three San Diego breweries, each featuring Phantasm® but a different beer style and hop combination:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Pure Project Brewing: Phuture I (New England / Hazy IPA; 6.5% ABV)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Harland Brewing: Phuture II (New England / Hazy Double IPA; 8.0% ABV)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>North Park Beer Co.: Phuture III (New England / Hazy Triple IPA; 10% ABV)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Another California-based collaborative brew from Alvarado Street Brewery and Green Cheek Beer Co., a double-dry-hopped Imperial Hazy IPA with Phantasm®, Nelson Sauvin™, Riwaka™, and Citra®, named Thiology 101, also impressed. Notice the pattern?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Meanwhile, Ruffell continues to capitalize on the worldwide &amp;ldquo;thiol craze&amp;rdquo;, by working on thiol-packed blends of Phantasm® and hops. He&amp;rsquo;s collaborating with Yakima Chief Hops to develop an experimental blend of Phantasm® combined with Citra®, Mosaic® and Simcoe® Cryo hops, and teaming up with Freestyle Hops to create a &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href="https://www.freestylehops.com/hop-varieties/mega-motueka/">Mega Motueka&lt;/a>&amp;rdquo; blend of Phantasm® and Motueka™ hops.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Expansion of Phantasm&amp;rsquo;s operation is also on the table. In fact, a liquid version of Phantasm® is in the pipeline, which is shown during trials to be up to 40x as concentrated as the powder, and successful in contributing deepened aromas to finished beers.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-1/phantasm-liquid-motueka-2023-04-16.png"
alt="Basqueland Phantasm Crush"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>One Drop Brewing Co. Liquid Motueka, a 8.4% ABV single-hop DIPA. In this collaboration brew with Freestyle Hops and Phantasm, One Drop experiments with some juicy new hop products, such as 1) thiol-bumped Mega Motueka pellets, which consist of Phantasm® powder and late-harvested Motueka™ hops from Nelson, NZ; and 2) a liquid hop product from Freestyle called SubZero Hop Kief™, which is the oil distillate of Motueka™ hops achieved through a process that removes all of the vegetative green matter contained in hop pellets, leaving just the aromatic, sticky oils.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Some brewers use Phantasm® powder in tandem with hop varieties that already produce a solid base of thiol precursors, such as Citra® and Nelson Sauvin™, and add a thiolized yeast strain to coax the fullest range of tropical aromatics out of the brew.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;We just threw a bunch of shit in the beer and called it good.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Phil Humphrey, 608 Brewing Company&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.craftbrewingbusiness.com/news/weldwerks-explains-its-use-of-a-thiol-named-phantasm-and-other-beers-to-know-this-week/">Craft Brewing Business&lt;/a> recently asked Skip Schwartz, Innovation and Wood Cellar Lead at WeldWerks Brewing Co., about what it was like brewing with Phantasm:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Did Phantasm save costs by perhaps requiring less hops than usual to attain an even bigger flavor?&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Since this is our first time using this product, there is still a lot for us to learn and how best to use it. We are planning on trying at least a few more beers using Phantasm before we fully make any decisions. The bigger thing is that it does not change the flavor, just the aroma. Since Phantasm is a thiol, it works more on your orthonasal than it does on your taste buds, but you do notice more defined hop characteristics on your retronasal as well.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Like I said earlier, tinkering with thiols is a lot of &amp;ldquo;trial and error.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="thiolized-yeasts">Thiolized yeasts&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Having a glut of thiol precursors alone isn&amp;rsquo;t enough. The true trick is unlocking them.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Enter &amp;ldquo;thiolized&amp;rdquo; yeasts, which are capable of producing CSL during fermentation to free thiols from their precursors, allowing them to have a sensory impact on the end-product.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0740002011000141">IRC7&lt;/a> is the key gene at the center of current research, because it encodes a CSL enzyme. A &lt;a href="https://academic.oup.com/femsyr/article/15/5/fov034/2467698">research paper&lt;/a> found that &amp;ldquo;a full-length copy of IRC7 is absolutely required for the cleavage of both precursors.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Many brewing yeast strains naturally contain the IRC7 gene. However, most of the naturally occurring CSLs in brewing yeasts aren&amp;rsquo;t as active as CSLs from other species, e.g. the CSL of &lt;em>S. hominis&lt;/em>, a natural bacterium commonly found on human skin, is far more active and more specific in generating tropical aromas.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The ideal yeast strains for thiol biotransformation are those that are capable of &lt;em>both&lt;/em> fermentation and high CSL activity. Unfortunately, this combination is quite rare in the yeast world. Most traditional brewing yeasts have mutations in the IRC7 gene that deactivate the enzyme. Of those that do have a functional IRC7 gene, they are capable of only releasing 3MH from the Cys-3MH precursor, while leaving all of the Glut-3MH untapped.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Current methods used to develop new yeasts for efficiently catalyzing thiol biotransformation include&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>interspecifically crossing strains with naturally high IRC7 activity to achieve &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s00217-022-04132-6">hybrid vigor&lt;/a>&amp;quot;; and&lt;/li>
&lt;li>genetically modifying existing yeast strains to galvanize higher CSL activity.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>FWIW, lager yeast (&lt;em>Saccharomyces pastorianus&lt;/em>) is a natural hybrid between &lt;em>Saccharomyces cerevisiae&lt;/em> and the newly discovered &lt;em>Saccharomyces eubayanus&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It&amp;rsquo;s an exciting time for yeast lovers between bio-engineered yeasts and heirloom kveiks.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>A mention of GMO inevitably evokes the popular stigma of Monsanto Roundup Ready®. Indeed, GMO has become a politically charged and highly polarizing topic; GMO foods are widely considered bad and dangerous, so much so that the EU has basically banned GMO crops.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Like artificial intelligence (AI), genetic modification is a tool, which can be utilized to transform our society, for better or worse. A blanket rejection of all GM products seems silly. Learning more about the history and place of genetic engineering in our society helps to fully understand and perhaps form an informed opinion on this technology.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Saccharomyces cerevisiae&lt;/em> probably contains ~6,000 genes, and genetically modifying them to produce specific chemicals and pharmaceuticals has &lt;a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/24677744/">already been done&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In GMO yeasts, researchers essentially delete or add a targeted gene for a specific purpose, e.g. release certain esters, remove certain phenols, or enhance biotransformation potential. Also, a GMO yeast strain doesn&amp;rsquo;t require potentially dangerous pesticides and herbicides, like GMO seeds might. This distinction seems worth pointing out and keeping in mind.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;div class="embed music-spotify">
&lt;iframe
style="border-radius:12px"
src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/episode/0FVxpZvcQr4bHSCIXNTIpY?utm_source=generator&amp;theme=0"
width="100%"
height="152
"
frameBorder="0"
allowfullscreen=""
allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture">&lt;/iframe>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>To catalyze efficient conversion of bound thiols to free thiols, the enzymatic activity of CSL needs to be turbocharged during fermentation. So far, there are 2 ways to do that:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Activate or turn up the IRC7 gene within the yeast to (over)express CSL.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Add exogenous hyperactive CSL.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>Both can boost CSL enzyme activity during fermentation to elevated levels, to maximize the thiol biotransformation potential.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A handful of thiol-unlocking strains have shown up on the market, specifically developed to enhance the yeast&amp;rsquo;s ability to biotransform compounds found in malt and hops to unleash thiols. The process of making each strain is different, even though the final product is advertised as being comparable, if not the same.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>White Labs&lt;/strong>, which caught the rising yeast wave and has sold some iconic products for nearly three decades around the world, is a latecomer. It only recently released its first thiol-unlocking product, &lt;a href="https://www.whitelabs.com/yeast-single?id=267&amp;amp;type=YEAST">WLP077 Tropicale&lt;/a>, which is &lt;a href="https://www.whitelabs.com/news-update-detail?id=74">a non-GMO blend of previously available strains&lt;/a> that are specifically selected for high IRC7 enzyme activity. (I could be wrong, but I doubt this blend will live up to the thiol-releasing potential of the new GMO strains from other labs. This seems like White Labs' way of catching up to the other companies while keeping the non-GMO tag.)&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Escarpment Labs&lt;/strong> has bred &lt;a href="https://escarpmentlabs.com/products/thiol-libre">Thiol Libre&lt;/a> from strains naturally high in IRC7 activity. (I&amp;rsquo;ve heard that the yeast appears to have lost quite a bit of its English ale character during the hybridization, while also not overexpressing the IRC7 gene that produces the required CSL enzyme to unlock thiols.)&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Omega Yeast&lt;/strong> has taken the GMO route and used CRISPR-Cas9 to cisgenically insert activated IRC7 gene (OYL-402 Cosmic Punch™), or transgenically add skin bacteria-derived CSL gene (e.g. Helio Gazer™, Star Party™, and Lunar Crush™), to produce Thiolized® versions of its popular yeast strains.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Berkeley Yeast&lt;/strong>, a startup founded by UC Berkeley scientists and funded by NSF, NIH, and USDA, as well as venture capital, has taken the transgenic GMO approach to bio-engineer the &lt;a href="https://berkeleyyeast.com/available-yeast-strains/">Tropics™ series&lt;/a>, which likely produce the strongest thiol characters of the bunch, because they sourced the &lt;em>TnaA&lt;/em> gene (encoding a tryptophanase with strong CSL activity &amp;ndash; probably the most active CSL known to the natural world so far) from &lt;em>Citrobacter freundii&lt;/em>, a commensal bacterium found in water, soil, food, and the intestines of humans and animals. (&lt;a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1002/yea.1493">Research&lt;/a> has demonstrated that expression in yeast of a bacterial enzyme with CSL activity results in very high levels of thiol production.)&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>It seems yeast companies are drawing a line in the sand and deciding if they&amp;rsquo;re going to be GM or non-GM. The latter opens up the EU market.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Is yeast going to be the new hops? I think so.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="berkeley-yeast">Berkeley Yeast&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Since I always root for entrepreneurial endeavors, I&amp;rsquo;d like to devote some ink to &lt;a href="https://berkeleyyeast.com">Berkeley Yeast&lt;/a>. The 6-year-old startup (based in Oakland, California) has risen out of the ashes of GigaYeast, which ended operations in July 2021. (Berkeley Yeast offers a &lt;a href="https://berkeleyyeast.com/strains/vermont-tropics/">thiolized version&lt;/a> of GigaYeast Vermont IPA.)&lt;/p>
&lt;div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
&lt;iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/1ZXWtUdaKD8" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video">&lt;/iframe>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>Berkeley Yeast&amp;rsquo;s first prototype was a &lt;a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41467-018-03293-x#auth-Rachel_A_-Li">bio-engineered brewer&amp;rsquo;s yeast that makes terpenes&lt;/a> (linalool, geraniol, and citronellol), which produce hop-like citrus and floral flavors &amp;ndash; and make the &lt;a href="https://berkeleyyeast.com/strains/chico-superbloom/">yeast&lt;/a> a potential drop-in replacement for hops.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Hops are a key ingredient in beer, and they grow best in just a few places on earth. Most of the US hop crop is grown in Yakima Valley in the state of Washington, which benefits from the Cascade mountains' watershed and sunny, fairly dry climate. Hop production is resource-intensive and increasingly unsustainable.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Disrupting the hop industry inevitably invites pushback. After all, using hops is part of the tradition of brewing and nobody wants to phase out hops entirely. Complementing hops, on the other hand, and allowing brewers to obtain similar tropical aromas without using those highly-demanded thiol-loaded hops, would be a smarter move.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>And that&amp;rsquo;s precisely how Berkeley Yeast evolved &amp;ndash; from hop-disruptive to hop-complimentary.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Berkeley Yeast&amp;rsquo;s main thing, though, seems to be engineering &lt;a href="https://berkeleyyeast.com/science-lesson/diacetyl-free-strains-prevent-diacetyl-formation/">diacetyl-free strains&lt;/a> that keep diacetyl (a buttery-tasting compound that&amp;rsquo;s undesirable in many types of beer) low during fermentation and after packaging, by inserting a gene that encodes the alpha acetolactate decarboxylase (ALDC) enzyme into the yeast genome. An ordinary yeast naturally converts fermentable sugars into α-acetolactate (precursor to diacetyl) during fermentation. The ALDC enzyme consumes α-acetolactate as it&amp;rsquo;s produced, and converts it into acetoin (the end product of the pathway), thus bypassing diacetyl formation. This ensures beer will stay fresh and clean after it leaves the brewery.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>They also have a STA1- Sacch Trois, dubbed Alexandre Trois, that &lt;a href="https://berkeleyyeast.com/science-lesson/diastaticus-and-sta1/">has the STA1 gene deleted&lt;/a>, solving a big headache for breweries. (Middle finger to &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->White Labs &lt;a href="https://www.whitelabs.com/yeast-single?id=182&amp;amp;type=YEAST&amp;amp;style_type=5">WLP644&lt;/a>&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->?)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>CRISPR-Cas9 is one way to edit genomes. The technology took a big step forward in the US in 2016 when the Department of Agriculture decided it &lt;a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/nature.2016.19754">would not regulate a CRISPR-edited mushroom&lt;/a>, which was engineered to resist browning by targeting a family of genes.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Berkeley Yeast started GM trials with CRISPR, but now utilizes a different set of (open source) molecular scissors.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Compared to Omega&amp;rsquo;s top-selling Thiolized® series, Berkeley Yeast developed the Tropics™ in a different way, but the purpose is the same: to produce more of the hyperactive enzyme that unlocks thiols.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-1/Tropics_3MHA.png"
alt="3MH and 3MHA production in London Tropics"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Illustration of 3MH and 3MHA production in London Tropics.&lt;/p>&lt;p>Source: &lt;a href="https://berkeleyyeast.com/science-lesson/enhance-thiol-biotransformation-with-tropics/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">Berkeley Yeast&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Based on what I&amp;rsquo;ve gathered so far from research papers, podcasts, and various corners of the internet, my high-level understanding of how Berkeley&amp;rsquo;s Tropics™ strains work is &amp;ndash; it&amp;rsquo;s two-fold:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Precursors &amp;ndash;&amp;gt; 3MH: a CSL-encoding gene (&lt;em>TnaA&lt;/em>) is transgenically sourced from a commensal bacterium, &lt;em>Citrobacter freundii&lt;/em>, and inserted into a parent London ale yeast strain to turbocharge the CSL enzyme, which breaks the carbon-sulfur bond in these odorless cysteinylated thiol precursors, releasing non-active thiols into the free, volatile, aromatic form (3MH).&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>3MH &amp;ndash;&amp;gt; 3MHA: esters in &lt;em>Saccharomyces cerevisiae&lt;/em> are produced by the alcohol acyltransferase (AAT), another yeast-encoded enzyme. One or more of the &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->native AATs&lt;sup id="fnref:2">&lt;a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --> expressed in the Tropics™ strains is capable of acetylating 3MH to its acetate ester, 3MHA.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>Because human sensory threshold for 3MHA (aromas of guava and passionfruit) is &lt;em>waaaay&lt;/em> lower than for 3MH (citrus aromas like grapefruit and gooseberry), a single molecule of 3MHA is perceived to be as potent as at least a dozen molecules of 3MH. It&amp;rsquo;s the synergy of these two molecules that creates a tropical fruit nirvana. Voila!&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-1/20230429_140316.jpg"
alt="London Tropics"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>London Tropics from Berkeley Yeast&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;h3 id="pain-de-thiol">&lt;em>Pain de Thiol&lt;/em>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The best way to delve into thiols is to actually play with it, through hands-on &amp;ldquo;trial and error.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;code>TL;DR&lt;/code>: I made a simple wholegrain bread, with 38.5% barley malt flour and 61.5% whole wheat flour. I cooked up a big batch of the mash and split it into two equally. One was inoculated with Berkeley Yeast&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href="https://berkeleyyeast.com/strains/london-tropics/">&lt;strong>London Tropics&lt;/strong>&lt;/a>, the other with &lt;strong>London Tropics &lt;em>and&lt;/em> &lt;a href="https://berkeleyyeast.com/boost/thiol/">Thiol Boost&lt;/a>&lt;/strong>. Otherwise, these were exactly the same. (Equivalent of split-batch brewing; one recipe, two beers.)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;code>Spoiler&lt;/code>: The breads turned out COMPLETELY different. A tiny drop of Thiol Boost made a ton of difference. One had a crisp, assertive maltiness with a fruity undertone, the other had crazy fruit punch energy like a POG (passion fruit, orange, and guava) bomb.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Total ingredients&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Each loaf (~900g/2lbs baked):&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Turkey Red whole wheat flour&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100.00%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>400g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>barley malts, assorted&lt;/td>
&lt;td>62.50%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>250g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>tap water&lt;/td>
&lt;td>162.50%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>650g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sea salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1.00%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>4g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>London Tropics (Berkeley Yeast)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>0.725%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2.9g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>&lt;code>Only variable&lt;/code>: 0.5mL &lt;a href="https://berkeleyyeast.com/boost/thiol/">Thiol Boost&lt;/a>, which is a proprietary clear liquid that has been extracted from plants (not grapes, i.e. not a Phantasm® copycat) and purified to contain only the precursors to 3MH and 3MHA, to amplify POG (passion fruit, orange, and guava) flavors. All the other undesirable plant molecules, such as 4MMP which may come across as diesely and dank, are stripped away.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-1/20230428_162742.jpg"
alt="thiol boost"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Thiol Boost from Berkeley Yeast. The aroma of this clear liquid, out of the box, reminds me of colorful summer popsicles. The flavor transports me back to childhood days of eating popsicles on a hot summer day. 1 tiny drop (0.5mL) goes a loooong way.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>This is very much like brewing a beer, &lt;em>sans&lt;/em> hops. Instead, it relies on the gluten in wheat flour for structure.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The aroma and flavor produced by London Tropics were very, very noticeable throughout the process and in the baked bread; that one drop of Thiol Boost made a ton of difference.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The devil, as always, is in the details.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="1-all-barley-malt-mash">1. All-barley malt mash&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>Since thiol biotransformation begins with the precursor molecules (Glut-3MH and Cys-3MH), the amount of 3MH and 3MHA produced by thiolized yeast depends on the concentrations of these precursors in the grains used for baking.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As mentioned earlier, thiol precursors are not just in hops, but also &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/files/143_Dagan.pdf">largely abound in malts&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
&lt;iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Ob5Jxy2cKLs" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video">&lt;/iframe>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>Researchers' key findings:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Glut-3MH was the most abundant precursor across malts considered.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Roasting appears to considerably reduce the amount of precursors, since no precursors were found in the most roasted malt sample. In other words, un-kilned or lightly kilned malts are shown to contain more precursors than kilned ones.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Malts made from barley are all higher in thiol precursors than non-barley varieties. Barley malts exhibited the highest concentrations of Glut-3MH and Cys-3MH with levels ranging from 40-700 mg/kg and from 1-7 mg/kg, respectively, much higher than malted rice, sorghum or wheat.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-1/malt-thiol-precursors.png"
alt="thiol precursors in barley malts"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Thiol precursors identified in barley malts&lt;/p>&lt;p>Source: &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/files/143_Dagan.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">Roland et al.&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>TL;DR, if you want to create an overload of thiol precursors in the mash, stick with un-kilned or lightly-kilned barley malts.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For this mash, I used a total of 250g dry barley malts:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>unkilned: 20%&lt;/li>
&lt;li>lightly kilned: 56%&lt;/li>
&lt;li>others: 24%&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>%&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Bavarian Pilsner (Steffi - Montana Craft Malt)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>28%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>70g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Munich Light (Voyager - Montana Craft Malt)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>28%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>70g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sun-dried barley malt (Chevalier - homemade)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>20%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>50g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Melanoidin Gold (Genie - Montana Craft Malt)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>12%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>30g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Cara Ruby (Montana Craft Malt)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>12%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>30g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>tap water&lt;/td>
&lt;td>132%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>330g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-1/20230501_193959.jpg"
alt="craft barley malts from Montana Craft Malt"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>4 craft barley malts from Montana Craft Malt&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>I used a 5-step infusion mash to maximize the potential of endogenous enzymes. I did the whole thing on a kitchen stove top so I could easily apply direct heat when needed. It took 8 hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Finely grind all the malts into flour. Mix with water. Start at 95°F. Hold at 95-110°F for 30 minutes (acid rest).&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Gradually raise the temperature to ~130°F. Hold at 128-133°F for 30 minutes (protein rest; since most of the malts used here are well-modified and already contain higher levels of amino acids, the mash benefits from a protein rest closer to 133°F than 122°F, IMO).&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Gradually raise the temperature to ~145°F. Hold at 140-149°F for 4 hours (beta-amylase conversion).&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Gradually raise the temperature to ~158°F. Hold at 155-162°F for 2 hours (alpha-amylase conversion).&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Gradually raise the temperature to ~168°F. Hold at 168-170°F for 1 hour (dextrin conversion).&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>After 8 hours, the mash took on a darker brown color, and tasted incredibly malty and sweet, like a condensed wort. No fruity aroma or flavor whatsoever, as far as I could tell.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Total: 580g (to be divided into 2 equal portions)&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="2-thiolized-barms">2. Thiolized barms&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>I wanted to make 2 loaves of bread, one with London Tropics and Thiol Boost and the other with only London Tropics, to see how much of a sensory difference the booster would make.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>So I let the mash cool off to room temperature, and divided it into 2 equal portions, placed in 2 separate containers.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Berkeley Yeast&amp;rsquo;s recommended dosage for Thiol Boost is 200-400 mL/BBL of wort, which is 0.17%-0.34% of wort volume.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I added the liquid yeast to both mashes at the same time, and mixed it in thoroughly. One hour later, I added a drop of Berkeley Yeast&amp;rsquo;s liquid Thiol Boost to barm #2.&lt;/p>
&lt;h5 id="barm-1-control">Barm #1: control&lt;/h5>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>%&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>mash&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>290g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>thiolized yeast (London Tropics - Berkeley Yeast)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2.9g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Total: 292.9g&lt;/p>
&lt;h5 id="barm-2-thiol-boost">Barm #2: thiol boost+&lt;/h5>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>%&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>mash&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>290g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>thiolized yeast (London Tropics - Berkeley Yeast)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2.9g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>thiol boost (Berkeley Yeast)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>0.17%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>0.5mL&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Total: 294.3g&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I loosely covered both, and let them ferment at ambient temperatures (65-68°F) until the yeast told me it had done its job. And that ended up taking ~50 hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;h5 id="-observation-log-">📝 Observation log 📝&lt;/h5>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>After ~4 hours&lt;/strong>, tropical aromas started to manifest. Both barms smelled pungently fruity, with subtle differences.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Barm #1 (control) smelled like a pile of overripe guavas, bananas, and pineapples, with slight citrusy notes.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Barm #2 (thiol boost+) smelled about the same, but with more sweetness to it that reminded me of persimmons.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>The taste of both matched the aroma, too. Sweet and fruity; no off-flavors.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>After ~12 hours&lt;/strong>, the aromas evolved a bit.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Barm #1 (control): still smelled like overripe, sugar-laden tropical fruits (pawpaws, guavas, mangoes, bananas, and oranges); intensely sweet and chocolaty; a little boozy.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Barm #2 (thiol boost+): the difference from control became more noticeable &amp;ndash; wildly sweeter, fruitier, and boozier. The chocolaty sweet aromas became a lot stronger, almost overwhelming, like Tootsie Rolls next to tropical fruits that were too far gone. All of the aromas from control were present, but 10x amplified. The caramelly sugary and chocolaty aromas became so immensely dominant that the fruity aromas became less pronounced.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>The taste matured, too.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Barm #1 (control): the sweetness deepened, reminiscent of chocolate, caramel, and maybe artificial sweetener, with heavy doses of overripe tropical fruit flavors; a slight bitter aftertaste.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Barm #2 (thiol boost+): 50%-70% sweeter than control; stronger flavors of overripe fruits and alcohol, overpowering the chocolaty sweetness; less bitter aftertaste; didn&amp;rsquo;t taste as pleasant as it smelled anymore.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Still no sign of fermentation.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>After ~24 hours&lt;/strong>, some tiny bubbles finally started to show up.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Aromas:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Barm #1 (control): aromas of chocolate and caramel deepened further to smell more like Tootsie Rolls; citrus notes became more pronounced and pleasant (no more nauseatingly overripe fruits), inviting mental images of Tootsie Rolls on top of pineapples; boozy smell was gone.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Barm #2 (thiol boost+): less Tootsie Roll, more &lt;em>fresh&lt;/em> tropical fruits picked at peak ripeness; a little grassy note, evoking mental images of tropical fruit salad atop a freshly mowed lawn.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Taste:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Barm #1 (control): a bit sweeter and a lot fruitier; mildly chocolaty and caramely; tasted like Tootsie Rolls and overripe tropical fruits; still a boozy undertone; the bitter aftertaste mellowed out.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Barm #2 (thiol boost+): deeply Tootsie Roll; sweeter, fruitier, and more pleasant than earlier; a boozy undertone, reminiscent of vanilla-infused bourbon; the mild bitter aftertaste moved to the middle, right after the exorbitant sweetness.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>It seems biotransformation started (3-4 hours in) waaaay before any signs of fermentation showed up (~24 hours in).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>After ~48 hours&lt;/strong>, both barms were brimming with bubbles and nearly doubled in volume.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Aromas:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Barm #1 (control): about the same, with a clearer emphasis on Tootsie Rolls sweetness.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Barm #2 (thiol boost+): about the same.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Taste:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Barm #1 (control): sweeter, fruitier, and much more pleasant; loads of fresh, perfectly ripe guava and pineapple, with a slightly tart finish; the citrus flavor moved to the foreground and became much more pronounced.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Barm #2 (thiol boost+): intensely fruity; a wide range of tropical fruits like pineapple, guava, mango, passion fruit, etc.; a brighter and much more pleasant flavor profile on the palate; a grapefruit-like metallic aftertaste.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>I stirred both barms back down, and they came back up almost immediately.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-1/20230429_141522.jpg"
alt="thiolized barm"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>thiolized barm #2 (thiol boost+), ~48 hours after London Tropics inoculation&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;h4 id="3-final-dough">3. Final dough&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>I added the same ingredients to each barm to make the final dough.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Dough #1: control&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>%&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Turkey Red wheat flour, 100% extraction&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100.00%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>400g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>water&lt;/td>
&lt;td>80.00%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>320g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>barm #1&lt;/td>
&lt;td>73.23%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>292.9g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sea salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1.00%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>4g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Total: 1,016.9g&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Dough #2: thiol boost+&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>%&lt;/th>
&lt;th>weight&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Turkey Red wheat flour, 100% extraction&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100.00%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>400g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>water&lt;/td>
&lt;td>80.00%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>320g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>barm #2&lt;/td>
&lt;td>73.58%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>294.3g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>sea salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1.00%&lt;/td>
&lt;td>4g&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Total: 1,018.3g&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Process&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For both doughs, I did&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>autolyse: 30 minutes at ~64°F&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>bulk fermentation: 8 hours at ~70°F&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>final proof: 16 hours at ~64°F&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>bake: 45 minutes in total; 10 minutes @ 400°F and 35 minutes at 350°F.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>The pungent tropical fruit aromas persisted into the final dough, carried over to my hands during dough-mixing, and stayed for hours after.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>No tropical fragrance during baking, just typical bread crust aroma.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I let the baked breads rest for 12 hours before cutting.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="taste-test">Taste test&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>What emerges from the spectral mist?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A wholegrain bread, transmogrified through fermentation by Berkeley Yeast&amp;rsquo;s London Tropics, with the addition of Thiol Boost, naturally releasing an aromatic phantasmagoria of ripe tropical fruits.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-1/20230501_210859.jpg"
alt="pain de thiol #1"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>pain de thiol&lt;/em> #1: the control&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The aromas from the dough apparently persisted into the baked bread. Very little thermal degradation. Those who say beer yeasts lose their characters in breads are obviously not doing it right. LOL.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>To me, each bread tasted exactly like how it smelled, from barm to dough.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A panel of 3 taster (excluding me) donated their palates to this blind taste test. None of them was informed of the ingredients in the bread beforehand, only that it was not gluten-free.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I had so much fun watching the tasters' reactions. The panel&amp;rsquo;s combined description of these 2 breads:&lt;/p>
&lt;h5 id="bread-1">Bread #1&lt;/h5>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>aroma: massively sugary and chocolaty, with a fruity undertone, like some kind of fruit candy; one taster mentioned &amp;ldquo;caramel&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Tootsie Roll&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>flavor: mildly sweet; guava, passion fruit, and mango upfront, with a pineapple aftertaste and a little wheaty finish. All 3 tasters pointed out a weird artificial off-flavor, like artificially flavored water.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-1/20230501_213312.jpg"
alt="pain de thiol #1"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>pain de thiol&lt;/em> #1: the control&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-1/20230501_212311.jpg"
alt="pain de thiol #1"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>pain de thiol&lt;/em> #1, crumbshot&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;h5 id="bread-2">Bread #2&lt;/h5>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>aroma: immensely fruitier than bread #1; mainly overripe tropical fruits (ridiculous amounts of guava and passion fruit, with pineapple undertone); subtle chocolaty note (not as pronounced as in bread #1)&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>flavor: pungently sickeningly fruity and sweet, like &amp;ldquo;fruit leather rolled in whole wheat.&amp;rdquo; One taster described it as &amp;ldquo;off-putting&amp;rdquo;, one said it was &amp;ldquo;disgusting&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;nearly inedible&amp;rdquo;, and the third one immediately screamed &amp;ldquo;something is wrong with this!&amp;rdquo; and had to spit it out. They all noted artificiality was much more outstanding in this loaf. An overdone POG bomb.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-1/20230501_215723.jpg"
alt="pain de thiol #2"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>pain de thiol&lt;/em> #2: thiol boost+&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-1/20230501_214809.jpg"
alt="pain de thiol #2"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>pain de thiol&lt;/em> #2, crumbshot&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>All 3 tasters were able to tell these 2 breads apart, right away, despite identical crust and crumb textures. They unanimously preferred &lt;strong>bread #1 (the control)&lt;/strong> over bread #2 (thiol boost+), and said bread #1 was much more balanced and more pleasant to eat, comparatively. They enjoyed bread #1 as PB&amp;amp;J, but would not touch bread #2 again.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;h3 id="thoughts">Thoughts&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>It was a tremendously fun bread experiment. The flavors from London Tropics are unmistakable. Tropical fruit characters were on steroids in these 2 loaves of thiol-enriched bread, especially in the one with a drop of Thiol Boost added.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Tropics + Thiol Boost take fermentation and the end-product to an aroma blast of overripe exotic fruits, beyond realism. It transports you into a kind of infinity feeling. The fermentation goes through several stages, and you end up on a tropical island, touching down via &lt;a href="https://backtothefuture.fandom.com/wiki/Mr._Fusion">Mr. Fusion-powered DeLorean time machine&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Berkeley Yeast&amp;rsquo;s tests have shown that Tropics strains are capable of biotransforming unhopped beers. My experiment confirms it can biotransform an &amp;ldquo;unhopped&amp;rdquo; bread (aka. solid beer).&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="thiol-dominant----thiol-complimentary">thiol-dominant &amp;ndash;&amp;gt; thiol-complimentary?&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>The aromas/flavors that are reported to fade away using Phantasm® remain very heavily in the end-product using Tropics + Thiol Boost. This could be the game-changing combo, instead of Phantasm + Omega.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>These thiol-dominant breads turned out a bit too much (there&amp;rsquo;s apparently enough thiol precursors in the malts alone), so I think I&amp;rsquo;ll go light on thiols in the next experiment and make a thiol-complimentary bread, by&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>adding a lot of adjuncts in the mash starter (to decrease precursor load), or&lt;/li>
&lt;li>blending London Tropics with a traditional strain&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>to halve or even quarter thiol levels in the final bread.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As for Thiol Boost, I might have to dip a toothpick in it and swirl the toothpick around in the mash to add just the tiniest hint of the booster.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A lot of info on internet homebrewing forums seems to suggest the biggest benefit of thiolized yeasts is that it enhances the aroma experience of a beer more than the flavor. I consider flavor to be a combination of taste and aroma. A more pleasant aroma inevitably leads our brains to interpret the overall flavor as better. Some people say they can&amp;rsquo;t decidedly tell the difference between thiol-boosted beers and those without. Well, I bet they won&amp;rsquo;t fail to notice the difference between these 2 loaves of &amp;ldquo;thiol bombs.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="thiols-have-quirks-too">thiols have quirks, too&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>Neither the panel of tasters nor I detected any wine-like aromas/flavors at all from Berkeley&amp;rsquo;s London Tropics and Thiol Boost (despite that bread #2 was an overdone POG bomb), but some brewers have reported a weird &lt;strong>white wine-ish character&lt;/strong> in their Phantasm® and Omega Thiolized® brews that detracts from the beer.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Since the wine industry figured out thiols way ahead of the beer industry and have already done a staggering amount of research on thiols, some brewers say these thiols are mostly wine-like, wine-adjacent or wine-related flavors &amp;ndash; synonymous with New Zealand-type hops (e.g. Nelson Sauvin™ and Motueka™) or even some new age European hops (i.e. Hallertau Blanc and Mandarina Bavaria). They can be awesome in the proper context, but they&amp;rsquo;re hardly a cheat code or shortcut (although they might save you 20% on hops, which probably nets to nothing per unit dollar spent). When does a beer become a grape ale? Perhaps brewers should step back and bear in mind that there are many more dimensions to a good beer, outside just a juicy burst of tropical aromas.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;If you love wine, you&amp;rsquo;re gonna love this beer.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Phil Humphrey, 608 Brewing Company&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Now that almost every brewer is thiol-conscious, hopping every IPA with New Zealand-style hops or lupulin-enriched hop products, and boosting it with Phantasm powder, how are breweries going to &lt;strong>differentiate&lt;/strong> themselves?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>There seems be a ceiling for the thiols&amp;hellip; Once you get there, it&amp;rsquo;s just all the same. Human &lt;strong>sensory threshold gets so saturated&lt;/strong> that stimuli no longer elicit an increased response. More isn&amp;rsquo;t better.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>All of these thiols are produced by precursors found on the ingredients you put in. Some people have reported a &lt;strong>sulfury/diesely character&lt;/strong> in beers made with Phantasm and thiolized yeasts. Since the CSL expression is fairly non-specific (outside of its proclivity for cysteinylated substrates, as it can barely work on glutathionylated precursors), I&amp;rsquo;m guessing all types of bound sulfur-containing molecules are released by thiolized yeast, resulting in a sulfury aroma.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Thiols &lt;strong>dissipate rather quickly&lt;/strong> over time, since free thiols are so sensitive to oxygen. I left bread #2 on the kitchen countertop, cut-side down, for ~2 days, and ~80% of the tropical fruit aromas vanished. Free thiols are found to be &lt;a href="https://dial.uclouvain.be/pr/boreal/object/boreal:157890">almost entirely absent after 1 year&lt;/a> and as quickly as 6 months in some samples, likely due to their &amp;ldquo;high propensity to undergo oxidation, nucleophilic additions or substitutions.&amp;rdquo; Like life, thiols are fleeting. Best enjoy your thiolized brews while fresh.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="how-to-nuke-your-thiols">how to nuke your thiols&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>Berkeley Yeast&amp;rsquo;s Tropics strains obviously already express enzymes that convert Glut-3MH to Cys-3MH during fermentation. More isn&amp;rsquo;t better.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>With these powerful thiolized yeasts,&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>loading additional precursors (especially Cys-3MH) through Phantasm or mash-hopping may be unnecessary (in this case, mash-hopping is likely to produce astringent vegetal off-flavors);&lt;/li>
&lt;li>late addition, or double/triple dry-hopping, with modern fancy hops, is &lt;em>not&lt;/em> a must (&amp;ldquo;hop creep&amp;rdquo; aside, these may even counterproductively reduce the impact of thiols);&lt;/li>
&lt;li>IPAs (double, triple, cold, New England, West Coast, etc.) are &lt;em>not&lt;/em> the only &amp;ldquo;thiol bombs&amp;rdquo; one can make. (I personally think thiols make more sense in simple blondes, &lt;em>witbiers&lt;/em>, and lagers.)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>A tiny amount of hops (as whirlpool additions) goes a long way towards complementing the thiol character &amp;ndash; unless the goal is to pack as many hops as possible into the beer.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>To create unique, great-tasting breads/beers, you need to understand which bio-active compounds are present in the different ingredients you put in, how high their content is, how they affect aromas/flavors in the end-product, and how they change during the fermentation process and storage.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A while ago, Brülosophy did a &lt;a href="https://brulosophy.com/2023/02/20/exbeeriment-impact-phantasm-powder-has-on-a-hazy-ipa/#more-142752">trial&lt;/a> with thiolized yeast and Phantasm thiol powder, and the results were quintessentially &amp;ldquo;inconclusive.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Curiously, tasters in this xBmt were unable to reliably distinguish a Hazy IPA made with Phantasm powder from one made without it when both were fermented with thiolized yeast.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>In the trial, the author hopped the living crap out of the beer, which inevitably masks the flavor from the thiols and any benefit that the Phantasm thiol powder may bestow.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It seems to me that guys at Brülosophy often don&amp;rsquo;t really understand the value they are testing. For example, they did a pressure-fermentation test where the pressurized side was done at only 8 psi and transferred into an open keg &amp;ndash; basically nullifying the factors that make pressure-fermentation useful. They also did some direct comparisons of yeasts, using highly hopped beers. Of course, you won&amp;rsquo;t be able to tell US-05 from BRY-97 in a triple IPA. And then peeps on the internet just eat their stuff up too much and take it as the gospel truth that yeast choice doesn&amp;rsquo;t matter, rather than arrive at the correct conclusion &amp;ndash; one data point suggests that in hoppy ales, the yeast&amp;rsquo;s contribution to the flavor profile can be less perceptible.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Yeast matters. Just ask the Belgians.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/byb-5-1/20230501_211527.jpg"
alt="pain de thiol #1"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>&lt;em>pain de thiol&lt;/em> #1, crumbshot&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>🍻🍻🍻🍻&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Special thanks to &lt;a href="https://berkeleyyeast.com/">Berkeley Yeast&lt;/a>, especially Nick Harris and Jeremy Roop, for generously offering me the opportunity to do these fun thiol experiments and answering my questions.&lt;/p>
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>Research on the evolutionary history of STA1 has shown the gene was not present in the wild ancestor of brewing yeast (&lt;em>Saccharomyces cerevisiae&lt;/em>), but rather arose during the course of brewing &amp;ndash; formed by a mutation that fused two ancestral genes &amp;ndash; as an alternative evolutionary strategy for efficient utilization of sugars in brewer&amp;rsquo;s wort. The resulting diastatic strain (&amp;ldquo;STA1+&amp;rdquo;, i.e. &lt;em>Saccharomyces cerevisiae var. diastaticus&lt;/em>) is able to consume complex sugars like oligosaccharides from dextrins and starches, which has allowed the strain to outcompete its ancestor. The STA1+ strains mainly rely on the Sta1p glucoamylase to break down maltotriose (unlike Ale/Beer 1 strains), which means these STA1+ strains will ferment fast initially when it gorges on glucose and maltose, but slow down as it moves on to consume maltotriose, since it produces low levels of Sta1p (hence the slow finish to the fermentation). &lt;a href="https://www.whitelabs.com/yeast-single?id=182&amp;amp;type=YEAST&amp;amp;style_type=5">WLP644&lt;/a>, a Belgian strain, was originally thought to be &lt;em>Brettanomyces&lt;/em> due to its funky character (e.g. low flocculation, tropical fruit esters, ability to form a pellicle, etc), but through DNA sequencing it was later revealed to be &lt;em>Saccharomyces&lt;/em>. Maybe not &lt;em>Saccharomyces cerevisiae&lt;/em>, but genetically it doesn&amp;rsquo;t belong to &lt;em>Brettanomyces&lt;/em>. WLP644 is STA1+, but it&amp;rsquo;s among the strains with low diastatic ability, thanks to &lt;a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC6719335/">a 1162-bp deletion in the promoter of STA1&lt;/a>. Other closely related strains are the &amp;ldquo;Duvel&amp;rdquo; family (WLP570, WY1388, WB-06), which also tend to be slow fermenters. Diastaticus has been widely deemed a nasty contaminant in the brewing industry; cross-contamination often leads to unexpected over-attenuation, potentially exploding bottles or cans, and even &lt;a href="https://www.denverpost.com/2017/12/18/left-hand-brewing-milk-stout-nitro-damages/">lawsuits&lt;/a>.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>Based on Berkeley Yeast&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;science lesson&amp;rdquo; &lt;a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20230327014233/https://berkeleyyeast.com/science-lesson/enhance-thiol-biotransformation-with-tropics/">post&lt;/a> on thiol biotransformation, as well as a &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/files/fermentation-08-00370.pdf">research paper&lt;/a> co-authored by Berkeley Yeast&amp;rsquo;s scientists and published in &lt;em>Fermentation&lt;/em> (August 5, 2022) that paired CSL expression with expression of a heterologous AAT enzyme, I initially assumed that a heterologous AAT enzyme via an AAT-encoding gene (MpAAT1 or CATec3), transgenically sourced (from &lt;em>Malus pumila&lt;/em> or &lt;em>Escherichia coli&lt;/em>), was inserted into the Tropics strains as well, to acetylate 3MH to its acetate ester, 3MHA. Based on how pungent the guava and passion fruit aromas were in my London Tropics-leavened breads, I thought it odd that Tropics would have added ATT since the paper showed that the addition seemed to reduce the total concentrations of 3MH &amp;amp; 3MHA. Additionally, Berkeley Yeast&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20230127053700/https://berkeleyyeast.com/available-yeast-strains/">strain catalog webpage&lt;/a> says all Tropics strains produce the CSL; there was no mention of the AAT at all. I was confused, so I reached out to Nick Harris, co-founder of Berkeley Yeast, for clarification. Nick explained to me that &amp;ldquo;the only gene that was inserted during the engineering was the CSL&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;the addition of the AAT was into a strain that we have yet to commercialize.&amp;rdquo; Ah huh! So, whatever AATs present in the Tropics are native, not an exogenous addition. As for why Tropics produced more 3MHA, both in absolute and relative terms, than the strains possessing an additional AAT &amp;ndash; well, it still remains a mystery.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/section></content></item></channel></rss>