<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>arizona on HERESY LEVAIN</title><link>/tags/arizona/</link><description>Latest experiments in arizona from HERESY LEVAIN</description><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2023 HERESY LEVAIN 🍞 CC BY-NC-SA 4.0</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 30 Nov 2021 16:22:21 -0600</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/arizona/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Desert Dynamo</title><link>/posts/desert-dynamo/</link><pubDate>Tue, 30 Nov 2021 16:22:21 -0600</pubDate><guid>/posts/desert-dynamo/</guid><description>Desert Dynamo, an impossible bread made with 100% Sonora whole wheat flour.</description><content>&lt;p>I went camping at Patagonia Lake State Park in Arizona last week, and picked up a few bags of White Sonora wheat berries (from Ramona American Indian Farms, AZ).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>White Sonora is a soft &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/joeliath/">white&lt;/a> winter wheat (SWWW) that has been adapted to the southwestern US, specifically the semi-arid climates of the Sonoran Desert in California and Arizona. It&amp;rsquo;s a very old wheat, first brought to the American Southwest by Spanish missionaries in the 17th century. They made a stretchy dough that gradually evolved into the flour tortilla.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>With low gluten-forming potential, Sonora is considered an ideal flour for pastries rather than breads. Well&amp;hellip; Since I&amp;rsquo;m not a fan of cakes and desserts, what should I do with my Sonora?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Turns out you can make a tall and fluffy bread just fine, with 100% Sonora flour. I learned a lot from my &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/posts/orange-sunshine/">previous experiment with Warthog&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/desert-dynamo/202111291613.jpg"
alt="Desert Dynamo"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The bread has a lovely flavor and texture, which are further enhanced by adding ~1% &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->diastatic barley malt&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --> and a squeeze of &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->orange juice&lt;sup id="fnref:2">&lt;a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --> to the dough. Diastatic malt increases the conversion of starches to sugar, boosting the Maillard reaction of the crust. Ascorbic acid (vitamin C) in orange juice &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->tightens the gluten network&lt;sup id="fnref:3">&lt;a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">3&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --> and gives the bread &lt;a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150215091859/http://www.clausmeyer.dk/en/grupe___meyer_flour/bread_recipes.html">a better rise&lt;/a>. As a result, the crumb is more chewy, and the crust more caramelized.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>You may be wondering, why not work with a strong wheat, to begin with? Why would anyone want to learn how to work with weak wheat varieties?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>First of all, you get to enjoy the distinctive flavors of these weaker wheats: nutty, herbal, earthy, sweet, spicy, etc. Why wouldn&amp;rsquo;t a baker/foodie want to try all this variety?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>When you buy packaged bread flour, whole wheat flour, or generic hard wheat berries, you are usually buying a blend of strong wheats grown in god-knows-where and mixed to achieve consistent characteristics such as a protein content of 12%-15% and the ability to form a strong gluten network. In contrast, when you buy a specific variety of grain, you are getting an individual product with unique characteristics (which vary somewhat from harvest to harvest).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Secondly, I believe it&amp;rsquo;s important to preserve &lt;a href="https://thecounter.org/united-nations-fao-report-biodiversity-loss-simran-sethi/">crop biodiversity&lt;/a> and move away from large-scale industrial monocultures &amp;ndash; planting only a few strains of a single crop means that a new pest or virus could virtually wipe out an entire plant species. It&amp;rsquo;s time we give power back to the farmers who understand the land and know how to manage different varieties and species of plants. Biodiversity is critical to a robust food system, a prerequisite for food and nutrition security. Do I even need to mention the obvious benefit of delicious flavors?&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;There are may of us who cannot but feel dismal about the future of various cultures. Often it is hard not to agree that we are becoming culinary nitwits, dependent upon fast foods and mass kitchens and megavitamins for our basically rotten nourishment.&amp;rdquo; - M.F.K. Fisher&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Thirdly, protein percentage is not indicative of the wheat&amp;rsquo;s baking performance &amp;ndash; the correlation between protein levels and gluten strength isn&amp;rsquo;t strong. It&amp;rsquo;s entirely possible to have high protein levels with weak gluten (e.g. durum, einkorn). Similarly, bread wheats grown in the more humid areas often have weaker gluten as well. This isn&amp;rsquo;t a bad thing &amp;ndash; some people relish the softer crumb from weaker gluten.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It&amp;rsquo;s totally possible to make good bread with weak wheat, but it takes some adjustment. IMO, any baker who relies on high-gluten flour or added vital wheat gluten to produce good bread is a cheat. Being able to produce great breads from any type of wheat takes knowledge and skills.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/desert-dynamo/202111272048.jpg"
alt="Desert Dynamo"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>A &amp;lsquo;pane al formaggio&amp;rsquo; I made with 100% Sonora at a friend&amp;rsquo;s house in Arizona.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>So, how do you bake a bread with weak flour? The &lt;em>bassinage&lt;/em> technique is a tip. Adding natural enhancers like diastatic malt and &lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/files/bread-improver-malt-vitamin-c.pdf">ascorbid acid&lt;/a>, as mentioned earlier, is another. Here&amp;rsquo;s the &lt;a href="https://thebakingnetwork.com/protecting-gluten-in-a-weak-dough/">door&lt;/a> to the rabbit hole.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I ran the Sonora wheat berries through the mill several times to get the finest grind possible. Smaller particles help the gluten bond better.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I also bolted the flour to take out 10% of the coarsest bits, which I scalded and then fed to the levain. It was all added back in the final dough; the wholegrain integrity of the bread is never compromised.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Dough:&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>~90% extraction Sonora flour (Ramona Farms, AZ)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>bran levain&lt;/td>
&lt;td>40%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>water (65% in autolyse + 17% in &lt;em>bassinage&lt;/em>)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>82%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->fresh orange juice&lt;sup id="fnref:4">&lt;a href="#fn:4" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">4&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>flaxseeds, freshly ground&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>diastatic barley malt powder&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Add-ins:&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>fresh jalapeños, diced&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Colby cheese + jalapeño cheddar, grated (Arizona Farms)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>8%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>toasted millet&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Mix the flour with salt, malt and flaxseeds. Autolyze with cold orange juice and ~2/3 of the water for 20-30 minutes in the fridge. The gluten will develop more readily in a drier dough environment.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Add the levain and the remaining water (&lt;em>eau de bassinage&lt;/em>) gradually, and mix until thoroughly incorporated. Minimal handling is preferred.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Transfer the dough to a fridge right away and ferment for 24 hours. Do a coil-fold every 3-4 hours. Sprinkle the add-ins during the last couple of folds.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>After 24 hours of bulk fermentation, I shaped the dough into a log, put it in a sandwich loaf pan, and let it rise at room temperature for ~3 hours before baking.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/desert-dynamo/202111291601.jpg"
alt="Desert Dynamo"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The bread is light and creamy, spicy and sweet.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/desert-dynamo/202111291824.jpg"
alt="Desert Dynamo"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Desert Dynamo, an impossible bread made with 100% Sonora whole wheat flour.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>Simply put, diastatic malt is a grain which has been sprouted, dried and grounded into a powder. It contains active enzymes (diastase) that degrade starch to maltose, a simple sugar that yeasts love. You can easily make diastatic malt at home, with high-quality whole grains.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>According to several studies, orange has the highest vitamin C content of all citrus fruits.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:3" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://breadbuster.github.io/files/BreadChemistry_tcm18-163980.pdf">Bread Chemistry&lt;/a> explains: &amp;ldquo;Ascorbic acid is, of course, a reducing agent but, during dough mixing, the enzyme ascorbic acid oxidase, naturally present in flour, catalyses its conversion to its oxidising form, dehydroascorbic acid (DHAA). In a reaction catalysed by another flour enzyme, DHAA converts glutathione (GSH), a tripeptide naturally found in wheat flour, to its dimer (GSSG). GSH, but not GSSG, can form disulfide bonds – so removing GSH prevents it from disrupting the disulfide crosslinking that otherwise form between gluten proteins.&amp;rdquo;&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:4" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>Fresh orange juice contains a lot more biologically &lt;em>active&lt;/em> ascorbic acid than pasteurized orange juice.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:4" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/section></content></item></channel></rss>