<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>baronesse barley on HERESY LEVAIN</title><link>/tags/baronesse-barley/</link><description>Latest experiments in baronesse barley from HERESY LEVAIN</description><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2023 HERESY LEVAIN 🍞 CC BY-NC-SA 4.0</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2020 12:09:53 -0500</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/baronesse-barley/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Zombie Dust</title><link>/posts/zombie-dust/</link><pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2020 12:09:53 -0500</pubDate><guid>/posts/zombie-dust/</guid><description>This unapologetically flavorful bread, made with a shameless amount of old bread, will be your only respite after the zombie apocalypse.</description><content>&lt;p>Grains used to be widely grown in the northeastern US. In 1845, wheat was grown in every country of New York. There were even four acres of wheat grown in Manhattan.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>New Jersey was one of the &amp;ldquo;bread colonies,&amp;rdquo; where wheat was an important export crop for farmers.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>During Colonial times the wheat belt in New Jersey stretched from New York City to Philadelphia. By 1750 the New Jersey colony had progressed rapidly in milling, and much of the flour marketed in New York City came from the region around New Brunswick. In the first half of the 18th century the New Jersey flouring mills were considered as the best in the country.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Harry B. Weiss, &lt;em>The Early Grist and Flouring Mills of New Jersey&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>In his book, &lt;em>The Third Plate&lt;/em>, Chef Dan Barber mentions that there was one gristmill for every seven hundred Americans in 1840.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The remains of those mills can still be seen along the banks of the Garden State&amp;rsquo;s rivers and major streams. In gristmills, grains were ground between millstones, which crushed the entire kernel (bran, germ, and endosperm) into flour. Once ground, flour had a shelf life of about 1 week. You brought your wheat to the mill or you milled it yourself. Some of the bran and germ could be sifted out, but the volatile oils in the remaining bran and germ turn rancid quickly through exposure to oxygen, reducing the shelf life of stone-ground flour. The invention of the modern roller mill in the late 1800s enabled millers to strip the bran and germ from the endosperm during milling &amp;ndash; and, in the process, remove most of the nutrients and flavors. Flour changed from a locally produced, perishable food into a high-volume, shelf-stable commodity. Many local farmers and millers were unable to compete against large-scale highly-efficient grain operations in the Midwest. By 1955, only &lt;a href="https://morrisparks.net/index.php/parks/cooper-gristmill">one&lt;/a> flour mill remained in New Jersey.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Re-localization of food supply chains has been underway across the world, to promote food sovereignty. The economics of local grains could work. There is a farmer in Ontario who makes a living selling his hand-processed grains direct to consumers. Thor Oechsner, an organic grain farmer in New York, built a mill (Farmer Ground Flour) and a bakery (Wide Awake Bakery) to ensure markets for his grains. Regional hubs and distributors like GrowNYC Grains and The Northeast Grainshed have been pivotal in connecting growers with processors and bakers, and sparking a rise in demand for local grains.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>IMHO, the success of re-localizing grains and flours largely depends on the willingness of bakers to develop a sensory approach to baking, i.e. understand the differences in gluten content, water absorption and flavor in locally-grown grains and locally-milled flours, which lack the consistency that large industrial mills achieve by blending different varieties of wheat. By foregoing strict adherence to recipes, bakers are liberated from the expectation that flour must behave consistently, regardless of the origin, farming practices and conditions in which the grain is grown. They would be able to better accommodate variability in the way locally-grown grains perform during the making of breads and pastries.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>The white flour industrial complex so completely dominates the food landscape&amp;hellip;that to wish for anything substantially different seems, well, wishful and nostalgic.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Michael Pollan, &lt;em>Cooked&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>I have been working my way through Pyotr Kropotkin&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em>Conquest of Bread&lt;/em>. It&amp;rsquo;s hard to forget that bread shortages helped ignite the French Revolution and the Arab Spring. Kropotkin&amp;rsquo;s call for &amp;ldquo;well-being for all&amp;rdquo; has inspired me to think about how to repurpose old bread into new meals, essentially &amp;ldquo;paying it forward&amp;rdquo; so that nothing is wasted and someone could always have a loaf of bread.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>German bakers have long had a tradition of adding an old bread soaker to a new dough. It helps to eliminate waste, save on fresh flours, and add buckets of flavors. Pretty clever.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Before you wrinkle your nose and scream &amp;ldquo;ewwwwwww,&amp;rdquo; the old bread used here is not a green and fuzzy piece of ancient crust, or a 3-day-old slice of supermarket pap, but a drying piece of good (sourdough) bread, e.g. the end of a loaf.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Here is a delicious way to upcycle a good amount of old bread into a new loaf.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ingredient&lt;/th>
&lt;th>baker&amp;rsquo;s %&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>80% extraction wheat flour (Redeemer - Whitesfields Farm, MA)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>roasted barley tea&lt;/td>
&lt;td>105%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>whole wheat levain&lt;/td>
&lt;td>60%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>salt&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>old WW bread&lt;/td>
&lt;td>50%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>homemade beetroot purée&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>raw seed mix (for coating)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>10%&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>To make roasted barley tea, first you gotta roast the barley. Spread whole, from-the-field, unhulled barley in a single layer on a sheet pan and place in oven. (I used unhulled Baronesse barley from Joseph&amp;rsquo;s Grainery, WA. It was bred by &lt;a href="http://www.nordsaat.de/ueber-uns/historie/?L=1">Nordsaat&lt;/a> in Germany where they don&amp;rsquo;t care about feed grains as much as in the US.) Roast at 400°F for 15-20 mins, or until the grains take on a golden brown color and exude a popcorn-like aroma. Let cool and store in an air-tight container. Now you can brew some scrumptious tea by steeping roasted barley in hot water for ~12 hours. This cannot be reproduced with pearled or naked barley, since much of the flavor comes from the roasted toasty hull.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Steam or roast some chopped beets. Pulse the cooked beets with coconut milk in a blender until smooth and creamy. The beetroot purée will add extra flavors and delightful swirls to the bread.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Soak the chunks of stale bread (can be any type) in 25% of the total tea. (Depending on how dry your bread is, you may want to adjust the hydration accordingly.) Add half of the levain. Leave in a fridge overnight. Next day, mash up any remaining lumps so that it&amp;rsquo;s a thick and somewhat smooth paste.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Autolyze the freshly milled flour with the remaining tea for 2 hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Mix in the soaker, the rest of the levain, and salt, until thoroughly combined.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Rest 30 mins. Do a strong letter fold.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Rest another 30 mins rest. Laminate with beetroot purée to add extra flavors and colorful swirls to the bread.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Rest 60 mins. Perform a coil-fold.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Rest another 2 hours before shaping. Roll the dough in seeds. No need to toast the seeds, as they will be nicely toasted during baking and add amazing flavors to the bread.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>10 hours final proof in the fridge.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Let the dough warm up for a few hours before baking.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It rose like a beast in the oven.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/zombie-dust/202001241449.jpg"
alt="Zombie Dust"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>OMG!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Every slice is packed with extra flavor and crunch, thanks to the layer of caramelized seeds atop the crust. Reminds me a lot of Whole Foods' Seeduction bread.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This loaf is completely unapologetic in what it is &amp;ndash; a bold and aromatic bread that is made with a hefty amount of old bread.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Gossamer-like crumb texture.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/zombie-dust/202001241639.jpg"
alt="Zombie Dust"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The last 4 slices&amp;hellip;&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/zombie-dust/202001242205.jpg"
alt="Zombie Dust"/>&lt;figcaption class="right">&lt;p>Zombie Dust, an unapologetically flavorful bread, made with a shameless amount of old bread. It will be your only respite after the zombie apocalypse.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Few things are as ordinary as a loaf of bread, yet the process by which it is made is extraordinary &amp;ndash; and still something of a mystery even to those who study it or practice it every day. - Michael Pollan&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>A variation of this bread I made later, without seeds:&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/zombie-dust/variation/202001241320.jpg"
alt="Zombie Dust"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/zombie-dust/variation/202001241323.jpg"
alt="Zombie Dust"/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;figure>&lt;img loading="lazy"
src="https://breadbuster.github.io/img/zombie-dust/variation/202001241324.jpg"
alt="Zombie Dust"/>
&lt;/figure></content></item></channel></rss>